<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 11:20:32 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Combination of the House of the Opus Sectile with the House of the Opus Quadratum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_combination-of-the-house-of-the-opus-sectile-with-the-house-of-the-opus-quadratum_y.sun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_combination-of-the-house-of-the-opus-sectile-with-the-house-of-the-opus-quadratum_y.sun/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania (Pleiades)
Location AUGUSTORITUM - Limoges
Augustoritum (Pleiades)
Location Description The earliest traces of settlement in this area are at the oppidum of Villejoubert 25 kilometers east of the city. The Roman settlement of Limoges proper dates from about 15-10 B.C. and was named Augustoritum (Augustus’s ford) in honor of the emperor. It covered some 65 to 100 hectares and was laid out in a regular rectangular grid. The ancient wall dates from the end of the third century. The town took water from several sources, including the aqueduct of Aigoulène; there were drains for waste water disposal. There were several public fountains and baths, a theater, an arena, and temples. The city declined in the fourth century. Its Roman name was replaced by the Celtic name of the local people; and its regular street pattern, almost totally lost.
Garden Combination of the House of the Opus Sectile with the House of the Opus Quadratum
Keywords  pool mosaic  Garden Description In the first half of the second century, the combination of these two beautiful houses made for truly sumptuous quarters. The residence, opening off of a vast vestibule with a central pool, covered an area of 5500 square meters, the whole of the insula. In the first phase of the work, heating was installed in the two reception rooms. Enjoyment of the east garden [1] of around 500 square meters was enhanced by a double-asped, 1.2-meter-deep pool in its center. It disappeared in a fire between the third and fourth century. In a second phase of embellishment, not prior to the years 226-235, the luxury of the décor was heightened. The reception room [2] was paved with a rich carpet of geometric opus sectile framed by a border of white marble, while new marble plates suppressed the old. To room [3] was added a large apse to the north, also furnished with a luxurious pavement of opus sectile and ornamented with a mosaic on either a wall or perhaps a semidome. The semicircle of this apse was constructed at the expense of a service courtyard. This courtyard [4] was bordered on the east by a portico which sheltered under its roof a well with a monolithic puteal. All of this magnificence was destroyed by fire in the late third or early fourth century.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the Combination of House of the Opus Sectile with House of the Opus Quadratum.    Dates First Phase：first half of the second century
Second Phase：226-235 CE
Bibliography  J.P. Loustaud. Limoges antique, Travaux d’Archéologie Limousine, supplément 5, 2000, p. 198-202, plan p. 198. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 138203
TGN ID 7030318 7008410
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House 35, Insula VII-5</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-35-insula-vii-5_y.sun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-35-insula-vii-5_y.sun/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania (Pleiades)
Location AUGUSTORITUM - Limoges
Augustoritum (Pleiades)
Location Description The earliest traces of settlement in this area are at the oppidum of Villejoubert 25 kilometers east of the city. The Roman settlement of Limoges proper dates from about 15-10 B.C. and was named Augustoritum (Augustus’s ford) in honor of the emperor. It covered some 65 to 100 hectares and was laid out in a regular rectangular grid. The ancient wall dates from the end of the third century. The town took water from several sources, including the aqueduct of Aigoulène; there were drains for waste water disposal. There were several public fountains and baths, a theater, an arena, and temples. The city declined in the fourth century. Its Roman name was replaced by the Celtic name of the local people; and its regular street pattern, almost totally lost.
Garden House 35, Insula VII-5
Keywords  manhole fountain  Garden Description This house, north of the House of the Large Vestibule, knew two states. In the first, 80-150, a series of rooms formed a U around a court [1] crossed by an underground stream. The room [2] to the east was crossed by a channel covered with large flagstones. This channel, with two strips of waterproofing in hydraulic cement, fed a fountain whose base was found at point A on the plan. To the south, at point B, a manhole with a quadrangular rim led into the subterranean tunnel of the stream. The second state of the house dates from the third century. A large, 205 square-meter room was then created which encroached on the courtyard [1], which, however, kept its fountain and manhole.
Dates First state: 80-150 CE
Second state: 3rd c CE
Bibliography  J.P. Loustaud. Limoges antique, Travaux d’Archéologie Limousine, supplément 5, 2000, p. 230-232, plan p. 231. (with a bibliography of earlier works) (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 138203
TGN ID 7030318 7008410
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House in the Rue des Clairettes</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-in-the-rue-des-clairettes_y.sun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-in-the-rue-des-clairettes_y.sun/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania (Pleiades)
Location AUGUSTORITUM - Limoges
Augustoritum (Pleiades)
Location Description The earliest traces of settlement in this area are at the oppidum of Villejoubert 25 kilometers east of the city. The Roman settlement of Limoges proper dates from about 15-10 B.C. and was named Augustoritum (Augustus’s ford) in honor of the emperor. It covered some 65 to 100 hectares and was laid out in a regular rectangular grid. The ancient wall dates from the end of the third century. The town took water from several sources, including the aqueduct of Aigoulène; there were drains for waste water disposal. There were several public fountains and baths, a theater, an arena, and temples. The city declined in the fourth century. Its Roman name was replaced by the Celtic name of the local people; and its regular street pattern, almost totally lost.
Garden House in the Rue des Clairettes
Keywords  pool portico  Garden Description This house was discovered in the excavation of 1998 in the rue des Clairettes. Constructed in the first half of the second century, it dominated the street. Only the wing running east-west is known. A portico must have opened onto a large garden to the north [1]. In the axis of this garden was the central room [2] of the wing with 125 square meters. In the center of this room was a large square pool, several times remodeled. Originally it was paved with marble or limestone and fed by an underground vaulted tunnel that crossed the whole room. To the south opened another portico overlooking a terrace two meters below; the street which defined the southern border was on beyond.
Dates Constructed in the first half of the second century。
Excavation Dates 1998
Bibliography  J.P. Loustaud. Limoges antique, Travaux d’Archéologie Limousine, supplément 5, 2000, p. 208-209, plan p. 208. (with a bibliography of earlier works) (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 138203
TGN ID 7030318 7008410
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House in “Vigne de fer” street</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-in-vigne-de-fer-street_y.sun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-in-vigne-de-fer-street_y.sun/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania (Pleiades)
Location AUGUSTORITUM - Limoges
Augustoritum (Pleiades)
Location Description The earliest traces of settlement in this area are at the oppidum of Villejoubert 25 kilometers east of the city. The Roman settlement of Limoges proper dates from about 15-10 B.C. and was named Augustoritum (Augustus’s ford) in honor of the emperor. It covered some 65 to 100 hectares and was laid out in a regular rectangular grid. The ancient wall dates from the end of the third century. The town took water from several sources, including the aqueduct of Aigoulène; there were drains for waste water disposal. There were several public fountains and baths, a theater, an arena, and temples. The city declined in the fourth century. Its Roman name was replaced by the Celtic name of the local people; and its regular street pattern, almost totally lost.
Garden House in “Vigne de fer” street
Keywords  gallery  Garden Description This house at the corner of rue Vigne de fer and Boulevard Gambetta was discovered during salvage excavations in 1962. The garden [1] was exposed only for 6.1 by 9 meters, but its length is thought to have been more than 20 meters. A low wall, 60 centimeters high, with a rounded top bore the 4.45 meter high colonnade. The combination, which it was possible to reconstruct conceptually, had a coating painted red and black plinths accented with a fillet. The walls of the gallery were painted; rectangular red panels alternated with narrower, vertical black panels enhanced by wreaths and chains of foliage and fruits, cupids, masques, and birds. The lower register was a sequence of wild animals. The house was destroyed by fire.
Images   Fig. 2: House in Vigne de fer street   Excavation Dates 1962
Bibliography  J.P. Loustaud. Limoges antique, Travaux d’Archéologie Limousine, supplément 5, 2000, p. 202-205, plan p. 203 (with a bibliography of earlier works) (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 138203
TGN ID 7030318 7008410
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Five Mosaics</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-of-the-five-mosaics_y.sun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-of-the-five-mosaics_y.sun/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania (Pleiades)
Location AUGUSTORITUM - Limoges
Augustoritum (Pleiades)
Location Description The earliest traces of settlement in this area are at the oppidum of Villejoubert 25 kilometers east of the city. The Roman settlement of Limoges proper dates from about 15-10 B.C. and was named Augustoritum (Augustus’s ford) in honor of the emperor. It covered some 65 to 100 hectares and was laid out in a regular rectangular grid. The ancient wall dates from the end of the third century. The town took water from several sources, including the aqueduct of Aigoulène; there were drains for waste water disposal. There were several public fountains and baths, a theater, an arena, and temples. The city declined in the fourth century. Its Roman name was replaced by the Celtic name of the local people; and its regular street pattern, almost totally lost.
Garden House of the Five Mosaics
Keywords  mosaic  Garden Description Situated west of the forum, part of insula VI-5, this house had two successive stages. The first is called House of the Lion Emblema; the second, House with the OpusQuadratum. Each occupied about 2300 square meters.
The House of the Lion Emblema was organized around a central garden with peristyle [1] of 20 by 23 meters. The floor of the porticos is white concrete with calcite aggregates. The columns supporting the roof of the portico rest on a low wall covered by a coating painted red. To the north, in the axis of the garden, was the triclinium [2] (12.6 x 7.8 m) where were found two black-and-white carpet mosaics, with the emblema of the lion in the more northern one. South of the garden, it is worth noting, there was a bath. For no apparent reason, this beautiful house was destroyed and another, the House of the Opus Quadratum, was superimposed on the previous foundations, keeping practically the same plan. The garden with portico [1] of 440 square meters had in the northern part a foundation for a pool or perhaps for monumental stairs connecting the portico to the garden. The limestone columns were apparently Corinthean. The northern portico had a floor of opus signinum; the floors of the other galleries were bare. To the north, the reception room [3] was reduced in length to 9.8 by 7.8 meters, but flanked by symmetric rooms with larger mosaics than those of the preceeding phase. This room, lying in the axis of the possible pool or steps, was embellished by a luxurious paving with an opus quadratum motif made of marble rectangles. South of the garden, an important room [4] (12 meters on a side) serves as a vestibule for the main room and marks the end of this house, which was later connected to its neighbor In the center of the room was a pool with a rim and paving of white marble and a water jet in the center.
Bibliography  J.P. Loustaud. Limoges antique, Travaux d’Archéologie Limousine, supplément 5, 2000, p. 191-196, plans p. 191 and p. 194 (with bibliography of earlier works). (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 138203
TGN ID 7030318 7008410
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Large Vestibule</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-of-the-large-vestibule_y.sun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-of-the-large-vestibule_y.sun/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania (Pleiades)
Location AUGUSTORITUM - Limoges
Augustoritum (Pleiades)
Location Description The earliest traces of settlement in this area are at the oppidum of Villejoubert 25 kilometers east of the city. The Roman settlement of Limoges proper dates from about 15-10 B.C. and was named Augustoritum (Augustus’s ford) in honor of the emperor. It covered some 65 to 100 hectares and was laid out in a regular rectangular grid. The ancient wall dates from the end of the third century. The town took water from several sources, including the aqueduct of Aigoulène; there were drains for waste water disposal. There were several public fountains and baths, a theater, an arena, and temples. The city declined in the fourth century. Its Roman name was replaced by the Celtic name of the local people; and its regular street pattern, almost totally lost.
Garden House of the Large Vestibule
Keywords  porticos vestibule  Garden Description This house was discovered in the quarter of the multimedia library, northwest of the forum. It was part of insula VII-5, covered an area of 1600 square meters, and underwent two successive stages. In its first stage, it had a mural chimney which gave the house its name. Four wings for living surrounded a 200 square-meter interior court with a gallery [1], which was crossed by an underground stream. It was destroyed about A.D. 70-80 to make place for the House of the Large Vestibule, its second stage. The new house was generally over the level of the old. A large, 600 square meter garden [1], surrounded on four sides by porticos, formed the center of the house. To the north, in the central axis of the house is the 249 square meter vestibule which gives its name to the house. Two cubbyholes opening onto the northern portico fill the corners on either side of the vestibule.
Dates The first stage was destroyed about A.D. 70-80 to make place for the House of the Large Vestibule, its second stage.
Bibliography  J.P. Loustaud. Limoges antique, Travaux d’Archéologie Limousine, supplément 5, 2000, 2000, p. 205-208, plan p. 206 (with bibliography of earlier works). (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 138203
TGN ID 7030318 7008410
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Opus Sectile</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-of-the-opus-sectile_y.sun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-of-the-opus-sectile_y.sun/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania (Pleiades)
Location AUGUSTORITUM - Limoges
Augustoritum (Pleiades)
Location Description The earliest traces of settlement in this area are at the oppidum of Villejoubert 25 kilometers east of the city. The Roman settlement of Limoges proper dates from about 15-10 B.C. and was named Augustoritum (Augustus’s ford) in honor of the emperor. It covered some 65 to 100 hectares and was laid out in a regular rectangular grid. The ancient wall dates from the end of the third century. The town took water from several sources, including the aqueduct of Aigoulène; there were drains for waste water disposal. There were several public fountains and baths, a theater, an arena, and temples. The city declined in the fourth century. Its Roman name was replaced by the Celtic name of the local people; and its regular street pattern, almost totally lost.
Garden House of the Opus Sectile
Keywords  portico  Garden Description This house occupied part of insula VI-5, across the street to the west of the forum. Constructed a little after the middle of the first century, it filled a space of 2300 square meters and certainly had an upper story. It consists of a living wing to the north of a garden with porticos [1] of 560 square meters. The south portico has preserved traces of a low wall on which the columns rested ; its inside had a coating painted black. The quality of the main reception room centered on the garden [3] (10 x 5.65 m), one of the most important rooms, is hard to judge because of the modifications in the following stage connected with installation of a hypocaust. The second reception room to the east [2] is ornamented by coatings painted in the Pompeian third style.
Dates Constructed a little after the middle of the first century.
Excavation Dates Bibliography  J.P. Loustaud. Limoges antique, Travaux d’Archéologie Limousine, supplément 5, 2000, p. 196-8, plan p. 196. (with bibliography of earlier works). (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 138203
TGN ID 7030318 7008410
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Seventh of March (Nones de Mars)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-of-the-seventh-of-march-nones-de-mars_y.sun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-of-the-seventh-of-march-nones-de-mars_y.sun/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania (Pleiades)
Location AUGUSTORITUM - Limoges
Augustoritum (Pleiades)
Location Description The earliest traces of settlement in this area are at the oppidum of Villejoubert 25 kilometers east of the city. The Roman settlement of Limoges proper dates from about 15-10 B.C. and was named Augustoritum (Augustus’s ford) in honor of the emperor. It covered some 65 to 100 hectares and was laid out in a regular rectangular grid. The ancient wall dates from the end of the third century. The town took water from several sources, including the aqueduct of Aigoulène; there were drains for waste water disposal. There were several public fountains and baths, a theater, an arena, and temples. The city declined in the fourth century. Its Roman name was replaced by the Celtic name of the local people; and its regular street pattern, almost totally lost.
Garden House of the Seventh of March (Nones de Mars)
Keywords  pool  Garden Description Uncovered between 1982 and 1991, this vast residence south of the forum opens to the east onto the Cardo maximus. Constructed between A.D. 30 and 40 on a high artificial terrace, it occupies 3734 square meters, half of insula IV-6. Remodeled in the second or third century, it is sometimes considered a schola, but without certainty. Beyond a large atrium and a tablinum comes a first central peristyle [1] (25.1 x 20.8 m = 522 sq m) with Corinthian and Tuscan columns. In the middle is a rectangular pool 9.87 meters long fed from the town’s public aqueduct through a vaulted tunnel 52 meters long. A vast, T-shaped room for entertaining, the principal triclinium of the house, is centered on this peristyle, opening onto it through a large bay. On the further side, this room extends, along its whole length into the vast garden [4] (26 x 29 m). Embellished with triple Tuscan porticos in a U, it forms the second part of the house. The west portico provides access to a series of rooms which complete this vast residence.
Dates 20-30 CE
Excavation Dates 1982-1991
Bibliography  J.P. Loustaud. Limoges antique, Travaux d’Archéologie Limousine, supplément 5, 2000, p.179-91, plan p.181 (with bibliography of earlier works). (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 138203
TGN ID 7030318 7008410
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House with Aquatic Décor</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-with-aquatic-de%CC%81cor_y.sun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-with-aquatic-de%CC%81cor_y.sun/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania (Pleiades)
Location AUGUSTORITUM - Limoges
Augustoritum (Pleiades)
Location Description The earliest traces of settlement in this area are at the oppidum of Villejoubert 25 kilometers east of the city. The Roman settlement of Limoges proper dates from about 15-10 B.C. and was named Augustoritum (Augustus’s ford) in honor of the emperor. It covered some 65 to 100 hectares and was laid out in a regular rectangular grid. The ancient wall dates from the end of the third century. The town took water from several sources, including the aqueduct of Aigoulène; there were drains for waste water disposal. There were several public fountains and baths, a theater, an arena, and temples. The city declined in the fourth century. Its Roman name was replaced by the Celtic name of the local people; and its regular street pattern, almost totally lost.
Garden House with Aquatic Décor
Keywords  court planting  Garden Description Discovered during excavation of Boulevard Gambetta, this house, in its original stage, had a central room with a painted décor of dolphins and aquatic motifs. In a second stage, towards the middle of the second century, this room [1] was transformed into a light well. It was a court open to the sky, though somewhat protected by the projection of a roof. One band of the former floor was kept; all the rest was covered by hauled-in earth, perhaps for planting. In the northwest corner of the court were found two vats for crushing lime.
Dates The second stage towards the middle of the second century.
Bibliography  J.P. Loustaud. Limoges antique, Travaux d’Archéologie Limousine, supplément 5, 2000, p. 211, plan p. 211. (with a bibliography of earlier works) (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 138203
TGN ID 7030318 7008410
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The House of the Small Viridarium</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_the-house-of-the-small-viridarium_y.sun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_the-house-of-the-small-viridarium_y.sun/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania (Pleiades)
Location AUGUSTORITUM - Limoges
Augustoritum (Pleiades)
Location Description The earliest traces of settlement in this area are at the oppidum of Villejoubert 25 kilometers east of the city. The Roman settlement of Limoges proper dates from about 15-10 B.C. and was named Augustoritum (Augustus’s ford) in honor of the emperor. It covered some 65 to 100 hectares and was laid out in a regular rectangular grid. The ancient wall dates from the end of the third century. The town took water from several sources, including the aqueduct of Aigoulène; there were drains for waste water disposal. There were several public fountains and baths, a theater, an arena, and temples. The city declined in the fourth century. Its Roman name was replaced by the Celtic name of the local people; and its regular street pattern, almost totally lost.
Garden The House of the Small Viridarium
Keywords  brick  Garden Description Discovered in the course of a campaign of excavations in 1928, this house occupies part of insula VI-4 west of the forum. It had a central courtyard [1] with a peristyle of columns of brick. The garden, 11.5 meter long, occupied at least 90 square meters. Though incompletely explored, we know that it had in its center a vat for crushing lime and an area paved with reused marble plates with a molding.
Excavation Dates 1928
Bibliography  J.P. Loustaud. Limoges antique, Travaux d’Archéologie Limousine, supplément 5, 2000, p. 210, plan p. 210. (with a bibliography of earlier works) (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 138203
TGN ID 7030318 7008410
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>