<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>tablina on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/tablina/</link>
    <description>Recent content in tablina on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 07:38:05 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/tablina/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Atrium House</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_atrium/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 07:38:05 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_atrium/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Garden Atrium House (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords urban villas
villae urbanae
atrium houses
atriums
tablina
colonnades
peristyles (Roman courtyards)
apsed pools
piscinae
Garden Description West of the House of Dionysos stood the so-called &amp;ldquo;atrium house&amp;rdquo; which covered an area of 1400 sq. m. (Plan 1). It was built around the middle of the 1st century A.D.
Entering from the colonnaded street at the west, one passed through a room reconstructed as an atrium, continuing along a corridor around the tablinum, and arrived at a peristyle courtyard with a semicircular pool. This courtyard, approximately 10 x 13 m. in size, was almost certainly a garden (Plan 1, G). A ground level gutter ran around the edge of the unpaved courtyard. This part of the house remained unchanged until the destruction of the building in the 4th century.
Maps Plans   Plan 1: Plan of the so-called &amp;#39;atrium house&amp;#39; with an apsidal pool (P) in its garden courtyard (G). Adapted from Precht 1971, fig. 2. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Middle of the first century CE until the fourth century CE
Bibliography  G. Precht, &amp;ldquo;Die Ausgrabungen um den Kölner Dom. Vorbericht über die Untersuchungen,&amp;rdquo; Kölner Jahrbuch 12, 1971:55-56, fig. 2, pl. 7.2. (worldcat) H. Hellenkemper, &amp;ldquo;Architektur als Beitrag zur Geschichte der CCAA,&amp;rdquo; in H. Temporini, ed., Aufstieg und Niedergang der Römischen Welt II.4, Berlin, 1974, p. 810, figs. 20-21. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108751
TGN ID 7004446
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 09 July 2020
Related articles House of Dionysos (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>