<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>tablina on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/tablina/</link>
    <description>Recent content in tablina on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 19:24:07 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/tablina/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Epidius Fortunatus (I.iii.3)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_3/house_of_epidius_fortunatus_i.iii.3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 19:24:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_3/house_of_epidius_fortunatus_i.iii.3/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 3
Garden House of Epidius Fortunatus (I.iii.3)
Keywords  archaeological garden aqueducts basins (vessels) gutters (building drainage components) peristyles (columnades) podiums (building divisions) porticoes puteal tablina tufa  Garden Description On the right of the tablinum were ten steps that led to the peristyle garden (a). A portico enclosed the garden on the west, north and east sides. This was supported by ten columns and two engaged columns which were stuccoed brick painted red. The north, east, and west edges of the garden had a gutter. There were two cistern openings, according to Mau, one located in the northeast corner of the garden with a tufa puteal and the other in the corresponding corner of the portico. Water emptied at the northeast corner from the gutter into the cistern and into the street at the southeast and southwest corners. An aqueduct pipe came out of the first column, (counting from the south, on the west portico), and ran between the gutter and the portico. The pipe rose, supported from the second column on the west side, to spurt a jet of water in the gutter. Flanking the west and the north porticos, it disappeared going to the northwest. On the west side it was possible in two places to let water flow into the gutter by a widening of the pipe. The gutter had openings to the gardens at these two points to serve as watering outlets. There were keys before and after the widen pipe sections to control the flow of water. Two branches of this pipe entered a room (b) off the northwest corner of the peristyle where there was a basin.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2 : Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Scavi, pp. 70-71. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., pp.50-51.(worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 26. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 181-182. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 77. Pernice, p. 14. Warscher, “Codex.” photos nos. 4, 6-10a.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 27 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa Della Grata Metallica; Casa Dell’Atrio Tetra-Stilo (I.ii.28)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_28/casa_della_grata_metallica_i.ii.28/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 15:01:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_28/casa_della_grata_metallica_i.ii.28/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 28
Garden Casa Della Grata Metallica; Casa Dell’Atrio Tetra-Stilo (I.ii.28)
Keywords  altars (religious fixtures) archaeological garden cisterns (plumbing components) peristyles (columnades) podiums (building divisions) porticoes tables (support furniture) tablina triclinia tufa  Garden Description At the rear of the house there was a peristyle garden (a) with a portico along the east side and part of the south. The excavation took place in 1873-74. A low wall joined three stuccoed brick columns and two engaged ones which supported the portico. There was an entrance to the garden on the south side opposite the door from the tablinium (b) and another on the east opposite the kitchen door (c), which was closed later according to Mau. The columns were white above the height of the wall and red below. Water was carried to the cistern by a wide gutter on the south and east edges of the garden, and Mau found some evidence of aqueduct water. There was a masonry triclinium (l.medius, 5.30 m.; l.imus, 3.85 m.; l.summus, 2.70 m.) with a circular table (dia. of support, 0.70 m. ) built against the west wall. Inside of each couch there were four niches (0.19 m. wide). The last niche in the south couch was larger in size and separated from the other three by the mouth of the cistern. There was a small masonry podium on the north wall with steps for access. A round tufa altar was located opposite the lectus summus (Fig. 3).
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I.ii.28; 10.11.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation dates 1873-1874
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Descr., p. 48. (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), col. 60. Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 25. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 250-252. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 77. Soprano, p. 293, no. 2 and figs. 28.6 and 29. Viola, “Scavi” p. 14. (worldcat) Warscher, “Codex.” photo no. 54-57.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 27 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.ii.17 B</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_17/i.ii.17_b/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2020 15:01:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_17/i.ii.17_b/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 17
Garden I.ii.17 B
Keywords  archaeological garden atriums mural paintings (visual works) peristyles (columnades) pillars porticoes statues statuettes (free-standing sculpture) tablina  Garden Description The peristyle garden to the east of the atrium was excavated in 1873. It had a portico on the north and west supported by two pillars, one at the northwest corner and the other in the middle of the north side. A gutter sloped towards the southeast corner as it went around the east, north, and west edges of the garden. A shrine-like structure was built against the east wall with the marble veneered façade above the level of the floor of the niche. The niche contained a marble statuette of Venus, her left arm supported by a statuette (1.04 m. high; Mus Naz. inv. no. 109 608; Ruesch no. 1325). The wall behind the statue was painted to represent blue drapery and the ceiling had a shell-like fluting. Two small marble statuettes of toads (Mus. Nac. inv. no. 109 609, 109 610) found in the garden and probably the one of two doves (Mus. Naz. inv. no. 120 407) found in the tablinum decorated the flowerbeds. There was also a marble head of a man identified as Agrippa, found cemented in a cup (total height 0.285 m.; Mus. Nac. inv. no. 109 611; Reusch no. 1081). The marble statuette of Hercules wrapped in a lion skin (0.70 m. high; Mus. Nac. inv. no. 109 677) found in the atrium was probably a garden decoration. The large room on the north had a fine view of the garden and the east and south walls of the garden were decorated with garden paintings. These were separated by narrow panels with a painting of a candelabrum, according to Mau, and each painting featured a fence with an amphora upon it. Behind this there was a thicket with birds. On either side of the amphora there was an ibis, and a pheasant in the center. Fiorelli mentioned observing animals in the paintings. Jashemski notes that no trace of the paintings remained when she examined the site, and further, she has never seen a pheasant represented in any garden paintings. Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation dates 1873
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 22, no. 10. de Franciscis, Ritratto, p. 25 and figs. 10-11. (worldcat) Döhl, p.1. Dwyer, Pomp. Sculpture, pp. 124, 12. (worldcat) Fiorelli, Descr., p. 44. (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), cols. 46-47, 48, 55. Grimal, p. 445, no. 1.  Jashemski, Gardens, 1::124-125. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, pp. 23-24. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 313. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 233-235. Ibid. (1874), pp. 265-266. Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 265-266.  Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 76. Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “L’arte,” p. 6 and pl. 14 (Venus). Schefold, WandP, p. 10. (worldcat)  Sogliano, “Pitture,” p. 223, no. 691. (worldcat)  Sogliano, “Scavi,” p. 310. (worldcat) Viola, “Scavi” pp. 12 and 76, no. 1, p.77, nos. 5, 12, p.79, nos. 45, 46. (worldcat) Warscher, “Codex,” photo no. 32.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.ii.17 A</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_17/i.ii.17_a/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2020 15:00:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_17/i.ii.17_a/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 17
Garden I.ii.17 A
Keywords  archaeological garden mural paintings (visual works) piscinae tablina  Garden Description At the rear of the house was a very small garden entered from the tablinum. Excavated in 1872, much of the garden was occupied by two small raised pools, according to Mau. (Fig. 3) Attached to the west wall was a masonry pool 0.58 m. deep on the inside and 0.73 m. high on the outside. The other pool was to the south and there was a garden painting on the rear wall.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, *Scavi*, pl. 1; Niccolini, *Case*, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I.ii.17; 10.13.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation dates 1872
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Descr., p. 44. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 23. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 264-265. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. Gen.,” p. 76. Viola, “Scavi” p. 12. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 25 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Legionary Houses at Castra Vetera (Germania Inferior)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/castra_vetera/ger_inf_castra_vetera/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:57:44 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/castra_vetera/ger_inf_castra_vetera/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Province Description Location Castra Vetera
Castra Vetera (Pleiades)
Garden Legionary houses at Castra Vetera (Germania inferior)
Keywords  castra praetoriums atriums peristyles (Roman courtyards) tablina pedestals Pliny the Younger  Garden Description In the Neronian fort of the 5th and 15th legions near the civilian settlement of Colonia Ulpia Traiana were two vast buildings on either side of the headquarters building (principia). These were the residences, or praetoria, of the two legionary commanders. The western palatial complex was 76-77 m. in width and 97 m. in length (over 7400 sq. m.) (Plan 1). It was entered from the east through a vestibule and an atrium. The villa had several peristyle courtyards, including one long peristyle courtyard with apsidal ends which has been interpreted as a garden (G on plan). Between the atrium and the apsidal courtyard was a large room, possibly a tablinum or a dining room. This courtyard measured 18.80 x 83 m. and had an open area 10.80 m. wide, surrounded on all sides by a covered columned walkway, 3.50 m. in width.
The partially excavated eastern villa was 78.50 m. wide and 109 m. in length. It too had several peristyle courtyards and one long courtyard 19 x 74.60 m. in size. The open area between the covered walkways was 5.80 m. wide. In front of each of the columns surrounding the courtyard were buttress-like foundations which the excavator interpreted as possible bases for statues. The excavator referred to the long courtyards in these houses as &amp;ldquo;hippodrome gardens&amp;rdquo;, and compared them to known stadium or hippodrome gardens at Pliny&amp;rsquo;s Tuscan villa, on the Palatine in Rome (Domus Augustana) and at Hadrian&amp;rsquo;s villa at Tivoli. The comparison is unacceptable, however, since both ends of the courtyards in the legionary camp are apsidal, unlike a stadium or hippodrome which has one straight end. The long garden courtyards at Xanten may have had more in common with the long, apsidal gardens referred to by Pliny as gestatio in modum circi (Epist. 5.6.17). It can be considered reasonably certain that the courtyards in both legionary villas were not foreseen for races or athletic activities, but for gardens as an ideal place for promenades.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the western *praetorium* in the double legionary base with its long apsidal garden (G). Adapted from Lehner 1930, fig. 39. (Rights statement).   Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  H. Lehner, Vetera. Die Ergebnisse der Ausgrabungen des Bonner Provinzialmuseums bis 1929. Römisch-Germanische Forschungen 4, Berlin, 1930, pp. 52-60, figs. 38-41. worldcat  Pleiades ID 108867
TGN ID 7004944
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 25 July 2020
Related articles The Houses of Insula 7 in Colonia Ulpia Traiana</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Atrium House</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_atrium/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 07:38:05 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_atrium/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Garden Atrium House (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords  urban villas villae urbanae atrium houses atriums tablina colonnades peristyles (Roman courtyards) apsed pools piscinae  Garden Description West of the House of Dionysos stood the so-called &amp;ldquo;atrium house&amp;rdquo; which covered an area of 1400 sq. m. (Plan 1). It was built around the middle of the 1st century A.D.
Entering from the colonnaded street at the west, one passed through a room reconstructed as an atrium, continuing along a corridor around the tablinum, and arrived at a peristyle courtyard with a semicircular pool. This courtyard, approximately 10 x 13 m. in size, was almost certainly a garden (Plan 1, G). A ground level gutter ran around the edge of the unpaved courtyard. This part of the house remained unchanged until the destruction of the building in the 4th century.
Maps Plans   Plan 1: Plan of the so-called &amp;#39;atrium house&amp;#39; with an apsidal pool (P) in its garden courtyard (G). Adapted from Precht 1971, fig. 2. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Middle of the first century CE until the fourth century CE
Bibliography  G. Precht, &amp;ldquo;Die Ausgrabungen um den Kölner Dom. Vorbericht über die Untersuchungen,&amp;rdquo; Kölner Jahrbuch 12, 1971:55-56, fig. 2, pl. 7.2. (worldcat) H. Hellenkemper, &amp;ldquo;Architektur als Beitrag zur Geschichte der CCAA,&amp;rdquo; in H. Temporini, ed., Aufstieg und Niedergang der Römischen Welt II.4, Berlin, 1974, p. 810, figs. 20-21. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108751
TGN ID 7004446
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 09 July 2020
Related articles House of Dionysos (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>