<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Achaea on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/categories/achaea/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Achaea on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 08:54:29 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/categories/achaea/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Guest House 2</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/olympia/olympia_guest_house_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 08:54:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/olympia/olympia_guest_house_2/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands. The provincial capital was Corinth. Under Nero in the mid-1st century A.D. Epirus became a separate province, and in the mid-2nd century Thessaly was detached and added to the province of Macedonia. Under Roman domination many cities such as Athens, Sparta, Patras, and Corinth grew in size and prominence, the latter two partly owing to their importance as ports. After an initial decline in the number of rural sites in the early Empire, by the late Roman period the countryside was densely settled with farms and villas, due to changing landholding patterns and Roman improvements in agricultural and irrigation technology. The main exports from Achaea were wine, particularly from the northern Peloponnese, as well as olive oil and honey, linen and woollen textiles and marbles.
Location Olympia
Olympia (Pleiades)
Sublocation Garden Guest House II
Keywords  Archaeological peristyles (Roman courtyards)  Garden Description In the first third of the 3rd century A.D. another guest house, so-called Guest House II (B on plan), was built at Olympia, immediately east of and connected with Guest House I (see Fig. 3). Guest House II was almost certainly built to supplement Guest House I after alterations to the latter resulted in its loss of the peristyle courtyard and garden. Guest House II was built with a peristyle courtyard, and its design is very similar to the one in the earlier Guest House I. In the center of the courtyard was an unpaved, and possibly planted, rectangular island surrounded by a water channel (G on plan). Both guest houses were badly damaged in the late 3rd century and only partially used thereafter until their abandonment in the 4th century.
Plans   Fig. 3: Plan of Guest House I (A) and Guest House II (B) with their courtyard gardens (G). The garden in Guest House I was later paved over (C). Adapted from Mallwitz 1972, fig. 230.   Dates In the first third of the 3rd century A.D.
Bibliography  A. Mallwitz, Olympia und seine Bauten. Munich,1972, pp. 276-277, fig. 230. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 570531
TGN ID 7220732
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 27 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Guest House 1</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/olympia/olympia_guest_house_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 08:54:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/olympia/olympia_guest_house_1/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands. The provincial capital was Corinth. Under Nero in the mid-1st century A.D. Epirus became a separate province, and in the mid-2nd century Thessaly was detached and added to the province of Macedonia. Under Roman domination many cities such as Athens, Sparta, Patras, and Corinth grew in size and prominence, the latter two partly owing to their importance as ports. After an initial decline in the number of rural sites in the early Empire, by the late Roman period the countryside was densely settled with farms and villas, due to changing landholding patterns and Roman improvements in agricultural and irrigation technology. The main exports from Achaea were wine, particularly from the northern Peloponnese, as well as olive oil and honey, linen and woollen textiles and marbles.
Location Olympia
Olympia (Pleiades)
Sublocation Garden Guest House I
Keywords  Archaeological peristyles (Roman courtyards)  Garden Description A Roman guest house of the 2nd century A.D., so-called Guest House I, was erected southeast of the Roman Kladeos baths of ca. 100 A.D. (Fig. 3, A on plan). The guest house had a peristyle courtyard with a water-filled channel surrounding a rectangular island. The island may have been planted as a garden, since this area was not paved. Around 220/230 A.D. the guest house was altered. At this time, the building was given direct access through a corridor to the Kladeos baths. The peristyle courtyard of the guest house also was reduced in size and paved with terracotta slabs (C on plan), suggesting that the garden was no longer maintained.
Plans   Fig. 3: Plan of Guest House I (A) and Guest House II (B) with their courtyard gardens (G). The garden in Guest House I was later paved over (C). Adapted from Mallwitz 1972, fig. 230.   Dates A Roman guest house of the 2nd century A.D, Around 220/230 A.D. the guest house was altered
Bibliography  A. Mallwitz, Olympia und seine Bauten. Munich,1972, pp. 276-277, fig. 230. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 570531
TGN ID 7220732
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 27 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leonidaion</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/olympia/olympia_leonidaion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 08:54:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/olympia/olympia_leonidaion/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands. The provincial capital was Corinth. Under Nero in the mid-1st century A.D. Epirus became a separate province, and in the mid-2nd century Thessaly was detached and added to the province of Macedonia. Under Roman domination many cities such as Athens, Sparta, Patras, and Corinth grew in size and prominence, the latter two partly owing to their importance as ports. After an initial decline in the number of rural sites in the early Empire, by the late Roman period the countryside was densely settled with farms and villas, due to changing landholding patterns and Roman improvements in agricultural and irrigation technology. The main exports from Achaea were wine, particularly from the northern Peloponnese, as well as olive oil and honey, linen and woollen textiles and marbles.
Location Olympia
Olympia (Pleiades)
Sublocation Garden House of Nero
Keywords  Archaeological quatrefoils  Garden Description This building southwest of the temple of Zeus was the largest guest house in the sanctuary at Olympia. The original Leonidaion, a gift of Leonidas from Naxos, was built shortly after 338 B.C. with a central courtyard. In the 2nd century A.D. the building was remodeled, and this courtyard was transformed into a veritable water garden (Fig. 2). The garden consisted of an outer quatrefoil island surrounded by a water channel (stippled on plan), and in the middle of this island was another circular one around which ran a second water channel (stippled on plan). On the quatrefoil island were planting beds (b on plan) in the middle of the four sides and sculptures in each of the rounded corners. This island could be reached by a bridge spanning the outer channel on the north and south sides. The central circular island was not accessible by such bridges. During the earthquake in the late 3rd century, the building was badly damaged and not rebuilt in this form.
Plans   Fig. 2: Plan of the Leonidaion with its quatrefoil and circular gardens (white) and planting beds (b) surrounded by water channels (stippled) in the courtyard. Adapted from Mallwitz 1972, fig. 201.   Dates The original Leonidaion, a gift of Leonidas from Naxos, was built shortly after 338 B.C. In the 2nd century A.D. the building was remodeled
Bibliography  A. Mallwitz, Olympia und seine Bauten. Munich,1972, pp. 276-277, fig. 230. (worldcat) R. Tölle-Kastenbein, Antike Wasserkultur. Munich, 1990, p. 192. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 570531
TGN ID 7220732
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 27 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Nero</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/olympia/olympia_house_of_nero/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 08:53:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/olympia/olympia_house_of_nero/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands. The provincial capital was Corinth. Under Nero in the mid-1st century A.D. Epirus became a separate province, and in the mid-2nd century Thessaly was detached and added to the province of Macedonia. Under Roman domination many cities such as Athens, Sparta, Patras, and Corinth grew in size and prominence, the latter two partly owing to their importance as ports. After an initial decline in the number of rural sites in the early Empire, by the late Roman period the countryside was densely settled with farms and villas, due to changing landholding patterns and Roman improvements in agricultural and irrigation technology. The main exports from Achaea were wine, particularly from the northern Peloponnese, as well as olive oil and honey, linen and woollen textiles and marbles.
Location Olympia
Olympia (Pleiades)
Sublocation Garden House of Nero
Keywords  Archaeological peristyles (Roman courtyards) atriums  Garden Description This house was built at the time of, and possibly for, the emperor Nero, who, on several occasions in the mid-1st century A.D., performed personally in the games at Olympia. To enable the construction of the building just south of the stadium, the earlier east baths were demolished. The house had a peristyle courtyard (G on plan), measuring 14 x 17 m., that was reached after passing through the atrium in the west. In the courtyard was a distinctive decorative feature (Fig. 1). This consisted of a water channel one meter wide around the edges of the courtyard that could only be crossed by a bridge on each of the four sides. The lack of paving in the area encircled by the water channel suggests that the courtyard may have been planted. The building was partially torn down in the early 3rd century to make way for a Roman bathhouse.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the ‘House of Nero’ with its garden courtyard (G) and water channel (stippled). Adapted from Mallwitz 1972, fig. 167.   Dates This house was built at the time of, and possibly for, the emperor Nero, who, on several occasions in the mid-1st century A.D., performed personally in the games at Olympia.
Bibliography  A. Mallwitz, Olympia und seine Bauten. Munich,1972, pp. 276-277, fig. 230. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 570531
TGN ID 7220732
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 27 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sanctuary of Zeus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/olympia/olympia_sanctuary_of_zeus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 08:52:42 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/olympia/olympia_sanctuary_of_zeus/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands. The provincial capital was Corinth. Under Nero in the mid-1st century A.D. Epirus became a separate province, and in the mid-2nd century Thessaly was detached and added to the province of Macedonia. Under Roman domination many cities such as Athens, Sparta, Patras, and Corinth grew in size and prominence, the latter two partly owing to their importance as ports. After an initial decline in the number of rural sites in the early Empire, by the late Roman period the countryside was densely settled with farms and villas, due to changing landholding patterns and Roman improvements in agricultural and irrigation technology. The main exports from Achaea were wine, particularly from the northern Peloponnese, as well as olive oil and honey, linen and woollen textiles and marbles.
Location Olympia
Olympia (Pleiades)
Sublocation Garden Sanctuary of Zeus
Keywords Literary
Pausanias
orchards
Garden Description The extensive sanctuary at which Panhellenic athletic games took place, was situated on the Alpheus river in groves of trees of ancient date. In early Greek mythology, the semi-divine Herakles was said to have planted trees in the sacred precinct, called the Altis, at Olympia (Pindar, Olympian Odes 3.13-18, 23-26, 31-34). In the 2nd and 3rd centuries A.D., Roman visitors to the site could still see the groves of wild olives and plane trees (Pausanias 5.10.1, 5.13.1, 5.15.3; Philostratos, Imagines 2.6.1). In the Roman period, imperial patronage and the resuscitation of the games prompted the erection of several new buildings along the banks of the Kladeos river, in particular guest houses, for the many visitors and tourists.
Dates In the 2nd and 3rd centuries A.D., Roman visitors to the site could still see the groves of wild olives and plane trees
Bibliography Pleiades ID 570531
TGN ID 7220732
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 27 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sanctuary of Zeus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/nemea/nemea_sanctuary_of_zeus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 08:51:34 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/nemea/nemea_sanctuary_of_zeus/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands. The provincial capital was Corinth. Under Nero in the mid-1st century A.D. Epirus became a separate province, and in the mid-2nd century Thessaly was detached and added to the province of Macedonia. Under Roman domination many cities such as Athens, Sparta, Patras, and Corinth grew in size and prominence, the latter two partly owing to their importance as ports. After an initial decline in the number of rural sites in the early Empire, by the late Roman period the countryside was densely settled with farms and villas, due to changing landholding patterns and Roman improvements in agricultural and irrigation technology. The main exports from Achaea were wine, particularly from the northern Peloponnese, as well as olive oil and honey, linen and woolen textiles and marbles.
Location Nemea
Nemea (Pleiades)
Sublocation Garden Sanctuary of Zeus
Keywords  Literary Archaeological Pausanias orchards planting pits  Garden Description The grove of trees at the temple of Zeus is known through Pausanias’ description of it (2.15.2) and from archaeological excavations in the temple precinct. Excavations in the 1970s uncovered 23 planting pits cut out of the living rock on the south side of the temple (Fig.1, gray circles on plan). The pits were up to 2 m. in diameter and on average 65 cm. deep. Some of the tree pits were cut in relatively straight alignment with each other, but the overall impression is one of a rather loose arrangement. According to Pausanias, the trees were cypresses. This was confirmed by the excavators who found carbonised remains of cypress wood at the bottom of the planting pits. The archaeological context of the planting pits suggests that the trees were planted in the 5th or 4th century B.C., and indeed literary references of the late 5th century B.C. allude to them (Euripides, Hypsipyle, Prologue lines 99-104; preserved in a papyrus fragment of 2nd-3rd century A.D.). Trees were obviously still standing in the 2nd century A.D. when Pausanias visited Nemea.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the Sanctuary of Zeus at Nemea with rock-cut pits for trees (grey circles) between the temple and other sanctuary buildings. Adapted from Miller 1978, fig. 2.   Images   Nemea Zeus Temple and Grove Balloon Photo   Dates Trees were obviously still standing in the 2nd century A.D. when Pausanias visited Nemea.
Bibliography  S. G. Miller, “Excavations at Nemea 1976,” Hesperia 46,1977: 9-11; S. G. Miller, “Excavations at Nemea 1977,” Hesperia 47, 1978:65; (worldcat) D. E. Birge, L. H. Kraynak and S. G. Miller, Excavations at Nemea. Topographical and Architectural Studies. The Sacred Square, the Xenon and the Bath. Berkeley, 1992, pp. 85-96, figs. 1, 98-103. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 570504
TGN ID 7220732
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 27 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Victory Monument of Augustus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/nikopolis/nikopolis_victory_monument_of_augustus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 08:51:24 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/nikopolis/nikopolis_victory_monument_of_augustus/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands. The provincial capital was Corinth. Under Nero in the mid-1st century A.D. Epirus became a separate province, and in the mid-2nd century Thessaly was detached and added to the province of Macedonia. Under Roman domination many cities such as Athens, Sparta, Patras, and Corinth grew in size and prominence, the latter two partly owing to their importance as ports. After an initial decline in the number of rural sites in the early Empire, by the late Roman period the countryside was densely settled with farms and villas, due to changing landholding patterns and Roman improvements in agricultural and irrigation technology. The main exports from Achaea were wine, particularly from the northern Peloponnese, as well as olive oil and honey, linen and woollen textiles and marbles.
Location Nemea
Sublocation Garden Sanctuary of Zeus
Keywords  Literary Archaeological tropaeum (monument) orchards strabo pedestals altars (religious fixtures) friezes (ornamental areas) planting pits  Garden Description The tropaeum or monument celebrating the victory of Octavian over the joint forces of Anthony and Cleopatra in the sea battle of Actium is situated on the “Sacred Hill of Apollo,” north of the ancient city of Nikopolis. On this hill, according to ancient sources, Octavian camped during the crucial days before the battle of 31 B.C. (Dio Cassius 51.1.3; Suetonius 18.2, 96.2; Plutarch, Antonius 65.3; Philip of Salonica, Anthologia Palatina 6.236). At the foot of the hill lies the suburb of the city where the ruins of the stadium and gymnasium, and other buildings related to the Actian games are preserved. Strabo, writing during the reign of Augustus, describes the topography and vegetation: “Nikopolis is populous, and its numbers are increasing daily, since it has not only a considerable territory and the adornment taken from the spoils of the battle, but it also has in its suburb the thoroughly equipped sacred precinct, one part of it being in a sacred grove that contains a gymnasium and a stadium for the celebration of the quadrennial games, the other part lying above the grove on the hill that is sacred to Apollo” (7.7.6. translation: Murray and Petsas 1989). It is not clear from the above passage if the sacred grove of the precinct was a natural one, which existed before the erection of the monuments, or if it was part of the building program of Augustus, the founder of the city. Most probably the grove was contemporary with the construction of the stadium and the gymnasium, which occupied a considerable land space. In any case, the extensive work for the construction of the stadium and the gymnasium would have affected the existing landscape. The entire complex of the monument (Fig. 1) plays the role of both a victory monument and an open-air sanctuary dedicated to Mars, Neptune, and Apollo. It is built on two terraces. On the first terrace, a massive retaining wall of opus caementum, dressed with opus quasi-reticulatum, supports the pressure of the entire construction of the complex. Above it is the façade of the platform (the second retaining wall), the end walls of which return at right-angles into the hillside. The façade, facing south, preserves cuttings to hold the bronze rams (rostra) of the defeated fleet, while on its upper part were a number of large rectangular limestone blocks bearing a long dedicatory inscription in Latin to Mars and Neptune. On the top of this wall was a second, much broader terrace, along three sides of which stood a π-shaped portico, open to the south. The north wing of this portico marks the northern limit of the terrace, while its side wings run south up to the rear of the second retaining wall. The wings, which supported covered colonnades, created an inner courtyard 38x38 m. The area inside the courtyard framed by the porticos contained a monumental altar, probably dedicated to Apollo, and three pedestals, probably for over-life sized statues. Dio (51.1.3) mentions that the monument also constituted an εδος, an abode or throne of the god Apollo. The altar, preserved only to the foundation level, was decorated with elaborate marble reliefs in a Classicizing style that referred directly or metaphorically to the battle and the events that followed. The main scene of the friezes decorating the altar depicts the triumph of Augustus at Actium on August 29, 31 B.C. During the excavation of the upper terrace within the peristyle courtyard fragments of at least eighteen complete or partially restored ceramic planting pots were found (Fig. 11.1c). The average height of the pots is 14 cm., and all of them have a wide hole (2.5 to 5 cm.) in the bottom, made before firing. The size of these holes, larger than would have been needed for drainage, indicates that they were for the branches of a bush or shrub to be drawn through for air layering (for this method of propagating new plants see chapter 14). These wheel-made pots are either of ovoid or piriform shape with flaring rims; they always have, on the interior and sometimes on the exterior surface, grooves from the fingers of the potters. The clay of the pots is fine, powdery, not hard fired, ranging in color from pale brown to pale yellow, and the surfaces of the pots were covered in a yellowish brown to gray slip. The survival of the pots is a result of their placement inside the natural soil of the hill, which consisted of either gravel or yellowish clay. Much of the surface soil of the courtyard was washed away. The landscape design of the site is contemporary with the building of the monument. The pots were placed along the outer stylobates of the porticos at a distance of between 20 to 60 cm., from the stylobate. The planting of the courtyard towards the south, as it is evident from two planting pots, reached the rear of the podium. Perhaps other plants were placed near the pedestals and the altar of the monument, but for the moment this cannot be proven. The exact distance between the pots is impossible to calculate, but from the few instances where this was possible, we can conclude that the plants were placed very close to each other in front of the columns. The placement of the pots close together and near the stylobates would exclude the planting of large trees, which would cause damage to the porticos and cut off the view from the interior. No traces of the roots or the seeds of the plants that might have been in the pots have been found, but the plants used to decorate the most sacred area of the monument may have been laurels. The sacred laurel of Apollo is mentioned frequently in Greek and Latin literature. Besides its association with Apollo, in Roman life the laurel is connected with victory, victorious generals, and their triumphs. Octavian, on the occasion of his Actian triumph depicted on the marble frieze of the altar of the monument, stands on the currus triumphalis holding a laurel branch in his extended right hand and wearing a laurel wreath on his head. All the magistrates who accompany him in the triumph also wear laurel wreaths. The Roman Senate voted in 27 B.C. that a laurel tree should be placed on each side of the door of the House of Augustus on the Palatine, and a civic crown of oak leaves should be placed above the door. This was considered such an extraordinary honor that Augustus mentions it in his Res Gestae (34), and the laurel became his permanent emblem. Certainly, the plant of Apollo could not be absent from his Sacred Hill where Octavian erected the monument as an act of pietas to his patron god and to his divine supporters, Mars and Neptune.
Plans   Fig. 2: State plan of the monument. Courtesy of K. L. Zachos.   Images   Fig. 1: Provisional reconstruction of the monument, based on the evidence from the recent excavations. Drawing courtesy of K. L. Zachos.     Fig. 3: Clay planting pots. Photo courtesy of K. L. Zachos.   Dates Octavian camped during the crucial days before the battle of 31 B.C. the triumph of Augustus at Actium on August 29, 31 B.C. The Roman Senate voted in 27 B.C. that a laurel tree should be placed on each side of the door
Bibliography  W. M. Murray and Ph. M. Petsas, “Octavian’s campsite memorial for the Actian War,” Trans. Am. Phil Soc. 79, 1989:4; K. L. Zachos, Το Μνημείο του Οκταβιανού Αυγούστου στη Νικόπολη: Το Τρόπαιο της Ναυμαχίας του Ακτίου. Athens 2001; For interim reports see A. Philadelpheus, Archaeologiki Ephemeris 1913:235; A. Philadelpheus, Praktika 1913:85-91 and pls. 3-4; (worldcat) A. Philadelpheus, Praktika 1921:11-12, 44; (worldcat) K. L. Zachos, Archaeologikon Deltion, Chronika for 1995, 1996, 1997, 1998, 1999, 2000; K. L. Zachos, “Excavations at the Actian Tropaeum at Nikopolis. A preliminary report,” in J. Isager, ed., Foundation and destruction. Nikopolis and northwestern Greece. Monograph 3, Danish Institute. Athens, 2001, pp. 29-41; (worldcat) K. L. Zachos, “The tropaeum of the sea-battle of Actium at Nikopolis: interim report,” JRA 16, 2003: 65-92.(worldcat)  Pleiades ID TGN ID 7011016
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 27 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shrine of the Fates</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/titane/titane_shrine_of_the_fates/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 12:42:56 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/titane/titane_shrine_of_the_fates/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands. The provincial capital was Corinth. Under Nero in the mid-1st century A.D. Epirus became a separate province, and in the mid-2nd century Thessaly was detached and added to the province of Macedonia. Under Roman domination many cities such as Athens, Sparta, Patras, and Corinth grew in size and prominence, the latter two partly owing to their importance as ports. After an initial decline in the number of rural sites in the early Empire, by the late Roman period the countryside was densely settled with farms and villas, due to changing landholding patterns and Roman improvements in agricultural and irrigation technology. The main exports from Achaea were wine, particularly from the northern Peloponnese, as well as olive oil and honey, linen and woollen textiles and marbles.
Location Titane
Titane (Pleiades)
Sublocation located above the acropolis
Garden Sanctuary of Ganemede or Hebe
Keywords  Literary Pausanias orchards  Garden Description n the narrow road to Titane near Corinth was a grove of holm oaks and a shrine of the Fates which Pausanias visited in the 2nd century A.D. (2.11.4). According to Pausanias, the grove was said to be particularly old. Part of the religious ritual at the site was the annual sacrifice of pregnant ewes on the open-air altar and the offering of a libation made of a mixture of milk, honey and flowers.
Plans Dates Pausanias visited in the 2nd century A.D.
Bibliography Pleiades ID 570741
TGN ID Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sanctuary of Demeter and Persephone</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/sikyon/sikyon_sanctuary_of_demeter_and_persephone/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 12:42:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/sikyon/sikyon_sanctuary_of_demeter_and_persephone/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands. The provincial capital was Corinth. Under Nero in the mid-1st century A.D. Epirus became a separate province, and in the mid-2nd century Thessaly was detached and added to the province of Macedonia. Under Roman domination many cities such as Athens, Sparta, Patras, and Corinth grew in size and prominence, the latter two partly owing to their importance as ports. After an initial decline in the number of rural sites in the early Empire, by the late Roman period the countryside was densely settled with farms and villas, due to changing landholding patterns and Roman improvements in agricultural and irrigation technology. The main exports from Achaea were wine, particularly from the northern Peloponnese, as well as olive oil and honey, linen and woollen textiles and marbles.
Location Sikyon
Peloponnese (Pleiades)
Sublocation located above the acropolis
Garden Sanctuary of Ganemede or Hebe
Keywords  Literary Pausanias orchards  Garden Description Pausanias gave directions on how to reach the grove called Pyraia, located near the city of Sikyon (2.11.3). He did not reveal what kind of trees grew here, but the grove was sacred to Demeter and Persephone. In it both men and women held religious festivals, but in separate locations. Statues of Demeter and Persephone, as well as Dionysos, were still standing in a chamber of the sanctuary when Pausanias visited the site in the 2nd century A.D.
Plans Dates Pausanias [In the time of Pausanias]
Bibliography Pleiades ID 570577
TGN ID 7002741
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sanctuary of Ganymede or Hebe</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/phigalia/phigalia_sanctuary_of_ganymede_or_hebe/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 12:41:58 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/phigalia/phigalia_sanctuary_of_ganymede_or_hebe/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands. The provincial capital was Corinth. Under Nero in the mid-1st century A.D. Epirus became a separate province, and in the mid-2nd century Thessaly was detached and added to the province of Macedonia. Under Roman domination many cities such as Athens, Sparta, Patras, and Corinth grew in size and prominence, the latter two partly owing to their importance as ports. After an initial decline in the number of rural sites in the early Empire, by the late Roman period the countryside was densely settled with farms and villas, due to changing landholding patterns and Roman improvements in agricultural and irrigation technology. The main exports from Achaea were wine, particularly from the northern Peloponnese, as well as olive oil and honey, linen and woollen textiles and marbles.
Location Phigalia
Arcadia (Pleiades)
Sublocation located above the acropolis
Garden Sanctuary of Ganemede or Hebe
Keywords  Literary Pausanias orchards  Garden Description The only indication that there was a garden at this sanctuary is a literary reference to a grove of cypress trees. According to Pausanias (2.13.3), this ancient sanctuary in the northeastern Peloponnese was located above the acropolis. The grove associated with the goddess Ganymede or Hebe was still in existence when Pausanias travelled to Phlious. In honour of the goddess, a number of prisoners were pardoned every year, the fetters of those set free being hung on the trees in the grove.
Plans Dates Pausanias [In the time of Pausanias]
Bibliography Pleiades ID 570102
TGN ID 5004240
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sanctuary of Mysian Demeter</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/pallene/pallene_sanctuary_of_mysian_demeter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 12:41:28 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/pallene/pallene_sanctuary_of_mysian_demeter/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands. The provincial capital was Corinth. Under Nero in the mid-1st century A.D. Epirus became a separate province, and in the mid-2nd century Thessaly was detached and added to the province of Macedonia. Under Roman domination many cities such as Athens, Sparta, Patras, and Corinth grew in size and prominence, the latter two partly owing to their importance as ports. After an initial decline in the number of rural sites in the early Empire, by the late Roman period the countryside was densely settled with farms and villas, due to changing landholding patterns and Roman improvements in agricultural and irrigation technology. The main exports from Achaea were wine, particularly from the northern Peloponnese, as well as olive oil and honey, linen and woollen textiles and marbles.
Location Pallene
Pallene (Pleiades)
Sublocation Garden Sanctuary of Poseidon
Keywords  Literary Pausanias orchards natural spring  Garden Description Pausanias described a grove of all kinds of trees with a natural spring sacred to Demeter near Pallene in the Argolid (7.27.9-10). According to legend, the sanctuary was established by an Argive, Mysios. An annual festival of Demeter took place here for the duration of seven days. On the third day of that festival, the sacred rites were celebrated exclusively by female devotees.
Plans Dates Pausanias [In the time of Pausanias]
Bibliography Pleiades ID 580051
TGN ID 7002739
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Onchestos Sanctuary of Poseidon Onchestios</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/onchestos/onchestos_sanctuary_of_poseidon_onchestios/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 12:40:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/onchestos/onchestos_sanctuary_of_poseidon_onchestios/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands. The provincial capital was Corinth. Under Nero in the mid-1st century A.D. Epirus became a separate province, and in the mid-2nd century Thessaly was detached and added to the province of Macedonia. Under Roman domination many cities such as Athens, Sparta, Patras, and Corinth grew in size and prominence, the latter two partly owing to their importance as ports. After an initial decline in the number of rural sites in the early Empire, by the late Roman period the countryside was densely settled with farms and villas, due to changing landholding patterns and Roman improvements in agricultural and irrigation technology. The main exports from Achaea were wine, particularly from the northern Peloponnese, as well as olive oil and honey, linen and woollen textiles and marbles.
Location Onchestos
Onchestos (Pleiades)
Sublocation Garden Sanctuary of Poseidon Onchestios
Keywords  Literary Pausanias orchards shrine  Garden Description According to Pausanias, the ancient city of Onchestos in Boeotia lay in ruins by the time he visited the site in the 2nd century A.D., but the shrine and statue of Poseidon Onchestios and the sacred grove survived (9.26.5). This, he says, was the grove that Homer praised in his poetry (Iliad 2.506; see also Homeric Hymn to Apollo 229-238). Perhaps the trees that Pausanias saw were not quite as old as he thought, since Strabo, writing over a hundred years earlier, described the site as treeless and the temple empty (9.2.33). Replanting in the sanctuary might account for the presence of the trees seen later by Pausanias.
Plans Dates He [Pausanias] visited the site in the 2nd century A.D.
Bibliography Pleiades ID 540984
TGN ID 7002683
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sanctuary of Zeus Philios</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/megalopolis/megalopolis_sanctuary_of_zeus_philios/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 12:30:28 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/megalopolis/megalopolis_sanctuary_of_zeus_philios/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands. The provincial capital was Corinth. Under Nero in the mid-1st century A.D. Epirus became a separate province, and in the mid-2nd century Thessaly was detached and added to the province of Macedonia. Under Roman domination many cities such as Athens, Sparta, Patras, and Corinth grew in size and prominence, the latter two partly owing to their importance as ports. After an initial decline in the number of rural sites in the early Empire, by the late Roman period the countryside was densely settled with farms and villas, due to changing landholding patterns and Roman improvements in agricultural and irrigation technology. The main exports from Achaea were wine, particularly from the northern Peloponnese, as well as olive oil and honey, linen and woollen textiles and marbles.
Location Megalopolis
Megalopolis (Pleiades)
Sublocation The Agora of Megalopolis
Garden Sanctuary of Zeus Philios
Keywords  Literary Pausanias orchards religious image  Garden Description Pausanias mentioned a small grove of trees in the sanctuary of Zeus Philios that was in close proximity to the agora in Megalopolis (8.31.4-5). The grove was enclosed within a boundary wall. In the precinct were images of the goddesses Demeter and Kore. This grove almost certainly had been in existence since pre-Roman times, but it still flourished in the 2nd century A.D. when Pausanias visited the site.
Plans Dates it still flourished in the 2nd century A.D. when Pausanias visited the site.
Bibliography Pleiades ID 540898
TGN ID 7010920
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sanctuary of Apollo and the Nymphs</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/kyrtones/kyrtones_sanctuary_of_apollo_and_the_nymphs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 12:25:33 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/kyrtones/kyrtones_sanctuary_of_apollo_and_the_nymphs/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands. The provincial capital was Corinth. Under Nero in the mid-1st century A.D. Epirus became a separate province, and in the mid-2nd century Thessaly was detached and added to the province of Macedonia. Under Roman domination many cities such as Athens, Sparta, Patras, and Corinth grew in size and prominence, the latter two partly owing to their importance as ports. After an initial decline in the number of rural sites in the early Empire, by the late Roman period the countryside was densely settled with farms and villas, due to changing landholding patterns and Roman improvements in agricultural and irrigation technology. The main exports from Achaea were wine, particularly from the northern Peloponnese, as well as olive oil and honey, linen and woollen textiles and marbles.
Location Krytones
Kyrtones (Pleiades)
Sublocation Garden Sanctuary of Apollo and the Nymphs
Keywords  Literary Pausanias orchards  Garden Description A grove and shrine of Apollo in the mountain-top town of Kyrtones in Boeotia was visited by Pausanias in the 2nd century A.D. (9.24.4). There was also a natural spring at the site, next to which was a sanctuary of the Nymphs and a small grove of fruit-bearing trees.
Plans Dates Bibliography Pleiades ID 540898
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sanctuary of Poseidon</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/isthmia/isthmia_sanctuary_of_poseidon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 10:54:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/isthmia/isthmia_sanctuary_of_poseidon/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands. The provincial capital was Corinth. Under Nero in the mid-1st century A.D. Epirus became a separate province, and in the mid-2nd century Thessaly was detached and added to the province of Macedonia. Under Roman domination many cities such as Athens, Sparta, Patras, and Corinth grew in size and prominence, the latter two partly owing to their importance as ports. After an initial decline in the number of rural sites in the early Empire, by the late Roman period the countryside was densely settled with farms and villas, due to changing landholding patterns and Roman improvements in agricultural and irrigation technology. The main exports from Achaea were wine, particularly from the northern Peloponnese, as well as olive oil and honey, linen and woollen textiles and marbles.
Location Isthmia
Isthmia (Pleiades)
Sublocation Garden Sanctuary of Poseidon
Keywords  Literary Pausanias orchards Strabo  Garden Description We know of a grove of trees in the precinct of the temple of Poseidon, thanks to Pausanias’ and Strabo’s descriptions of it in the early 1st and the later 2nd century A.D. (Strabo 8.6.22; Pausanias 2.1.7). According to Pausanias, on one side of the precinct stood statues of athletes who had been victorious in the Isthmian games, and opposite them was a row of pine trees. The fact that these trees stood in a row suggests that they were intentionally planted.
Plans Dates Bibliography Pleiades ID 570316
TGN ID 5004291
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sanctuary of Hyernetho</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/epidauros/epidauros_sanctuary_of_hyernetho/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 10:46:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/epidauros/epidauros_sanctuary_of_hyernetho/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands. The provincial capital was Corinth. Under Nero in the mid-1st century A.D. Epirus became a separate province, and in the mid-2nd century Thessaly was detached and added to the province of Macedonia. Under Roman domination many cities such as Athens, Sparta, Patras, and Corinth grew in size and prominence, the latter two partly owing to their importance as ports. After an initial decline in the number of rural sites in the early Empire, by the late Roman period the countryside was densely settled with farms and villas, due to changing landholding patterns and Roman improvements in agricultural and irrigation technology. The main exports from Achaea were wine, particularly from the northern Peloponnese, as well as olive oil and honey, linen and woollen textiles and marbles.
Location Epidauros
Epidauros (Pleiades)
Sublocation Garden Sanctuary of Hyernetho
Keywords  Literary Pausanias orchards  Garden Description According to local legend, the Argive maiden, Hyrnetho, died in an ancestral struggle and was buried on this site (Pausanias, 2.28.6-7). The sanctuary lay in the midst of a grove of wild olive trees. Established law, even in Roman times, forbade anyone to remove broken branches of these olives or any other trees in the grove.
Plans Dates Bibliography Pleiades ID Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden and Cistern of Gallatis, Son of Pythion</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/chaeronea/chaeronea_tomb_garden_and_cistern_of_gallatis_son_of_pythion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 10:33:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/chaeronea/chaeronea_tomb_garden_and_cistern_of_gallatis_son_of_pythion/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands. The provincial capital was Corinth. Under Nero in the mid-1st century A.D. Epirus became a separate province, and in the mid-2nd century Thessaly was detached and added to the province of Macedonia. Under Roman domination many cities such as Athens, Sparta, Patras, and Corinth grew in size and prominence, the latter two partly owing to their importance as ports. After an initial decline in the number of rural sites in the early Empire, by the late Roman period the countryside was densely settled with farms and villas, due to changing landholding patterns and Roman improvements in agricultural and irrigation technology. The main exports from Achaea were wine, particularly from the northern Peloponnese, as well as olive oil and honey, linen and woollen textiles and marbles.
Location Chaeronea
Chaeronea (Pleiades)
Sublocation Garden Tomb Garden and Cistern of Gallatis, Son of Pythion
Keywords  Inscription funerary buildings  Garden Description An inscription found near Chaeronea and known only from a transcription records the dedication by Gallatis, the son of Pythion, probably some time during the first or second century, of a funerary monument to himself, his wife, his children, and whomever his children wish, “with the cistern and garden” (sÊn t“ fr°[ati] ka‹ kÆpƒ). The freedom Gallatis grants to his children to dispose of the property as they wish is unusual, but cisterns (as at the tomb gardens of Lictoria Chaerusa at Capena [CROSS-REFXXX] and of P. Sullius Zoticus [Cross-refXXX; cf. also CIL 6.29961 = XXX] at Rome) and wells (as at the tomb garden of Claudia Semne [Cross-ref XXX; cf. CIL 6.29959] at Rome), are sometimes mentioned explicitly, and ready sources of water, even when not specified, must often have been provided along with the gardens they supplied in such funerary dispositions.
Plans Dates probably some time during the first or second century
Bibliography  IG VII, 3453; J. Kubińska, Les monuments funéraires dans les inscriptions grecques de l’Asie Mineure. Warsaw, 1968, pp. 146-47. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 540701
TGN ID 7010731
Contributor Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Altar of the Twelve Gods</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/athens/athens_altar_of_the_twelve_gods/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 10:20:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/athens/athens_altar_of_the_twelve_gods/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands. The provincial capital was Corinth. Under Nero in the mid-1st century A.D. Epirus became a separate province, and in the mid-2nd century Thessaly was detached and added to the province of Macedonia. Under Roman domination many cities such as Athens, Sparta, Patras, and Corinth grew in size and prominence, the latter two partly owing to their importance as ports. After an initial decline in the number of rural sites in the early Empire, by the late Roman period the countryside was densely settled with farms and villas, due to changing landholding patterns and Roman improvements in agricultural and irrigation technology. The main exports from Achaea were wine, particularly from the northern Peloponnese, as well as olive oil and honey, linen and woollen textiles and marbles.
Location Athens
Athens (Pleiades)
Sublocation Athenian Agora (Pleiades)
Garden Altar of the Twelve Gods
Keywords  Literary Archaeological grove (orchards) Statius  Garden Description A ‘grove’ of olive and laurel trees surrounding the Altar of the Twelve Gods in the Athenian Agora is mentioned in the late 1st century A.D. by the Roman writer Statius in his epic poem Thebaid (12.481-496). Excavations conducted there indeed revealed the remains of the planting pits of trees, although there appears to have been a very limited number of only three or four pits.
Plans Dates Mentioned in the late 1st century A.D.
Bibliography  M. Crosby, “The Altar of the Twelve Gods in Athens,” in Commemorative Studies in Honor of T. Leslie Shear. Hesperia Suppl. 8. Princeton, 1949, pp. 82-103, pl. 12.1; J. (worldcat) McKendrick Camp, The Athenian Agora. Excavations in the heart of Classical Athens. London, 1986, pp. 40-42, figs. 23-24.(worldcat)  Pleiades ID 807514119
TGN ID 5004159
Contributor Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa of Herodes Atticus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/eua/villa_of_herodes_atticus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 14:24:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/eua/villa_of_herodes_atticus/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands. The provincial capital was Corinth. Under Nero in the mid-1st century A.D. Epirus became a separate province, and in the mid-2nd century Thessaly was detached and added to the province of Macedonia. Under Roman domination many cities such as Athens, Sparta, Patras, and Corinth grew in size and prominence, the latter two partly owing to their importance as ports. After an initial decline in the number of rural sites in the early Empire, by the late Roman period the countryside was densely settled with farms and villas, due to changing landholding patterns and Roman improvements in agricultural and irrigation technology. The main exports from Achaea were wine, particularly from the northern Peloponnese, as well as olive oil and honey, linen and woollen textiles and marbles.
Location Eua
Eua (Pleiades)
Garden Villa of Herodes Atticus
Keywords  Archaeological mosaics (visual works) Serapeum Antinoön  Garden Description A large (20,000 sq. m.) villa on a small hill near the ancient site of Eua has been systematically excavated since the 1980s. Most of the discoveries, however, remain unpublished. Because the earliest remains date to the Flavian period and an inscription mentions the name Hipparchus, father of Herodes Atticus (103-171 A.D.), it is likely that this was family property inherited by Herodes and transformed by him into one of the most luxurious Roman estates in Greece. At the center of the plan was a large garden defined on three sides (north, south, and east) by porticoes paved in mosaics representing various mythological scenes in a continuous sequence (850 sq. m.). The numerous statues placed in the garden, representing divinities, historical characters, athletes, and philosophers, were part of a decorative program in which the sculptural and mosaic themes were linked. For example, in the north portico, in front of a mosaic depicting Menelaos holding Patroclos’ body, fragments of a statuary group representing the same subject were found (“Pasquino” type). In the south portico, a sculpture of Achilles and Penthesilea (copy of a second century B.C. original from Pergamon) was found in front of a mosaic with the same subject. Other mosaic subjects are the hunt of Aeneas and Dido, the Horai and Charites, the labors of Heracles, and cupids making wine.The eastern part of the villa had a nymphaeum and an exedra, containing six statues depicting girls, one of which dates to the fifth century B.C. The villa also had a Serapeum and an Antinoön. After the death of Herodes the villa probably became imperial property. A phase dating to the Tetrarchy is attested, and during the time of Constantine a mosaic, depicting the Circus Maximus, was added. The villa was destroyed by an earthquake in A.D. 400 A.D. and by the invasions of the Goths.
Dates From the 2nd century CE until 400 CE
Bibliography G. Ieranò, “I tesori di un intellettuale,” Archeo 6, 2001:48-53; G. Spyropoulos, Drei Meisterwerke der griechischen Plastik aus der Villa des Herodes Atticus zu Eva/Loukou. (worldcat)Frankfurt-am-Main, 2001.
Pleiades ID 570241
Contributor Annalisa Marzano (ORCID: 0000-0002-6485-9143)
Publication date 20 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gardens of Epicurus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/athens/athens_gardens_of_epicurus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 11:34:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/athens/athens_gardens_of_epicurus/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands. The provincial capital was Corinth. Under Nero in the mid-1st century A.D. Epirus became a separate province, and in the mid-2nd century Thessaly was detached and added to the province of Macedonia. Under Roman domination many cities such as Athens, Sparta, Patras, and Corinth grew in size and prominence, the latter two partly owing to their importance as ports. After an initial decline in the number of rural sites in the early Empire, by the late Roman period the countryside was densely settled with farms and villas, due to changing landholding patterns and Roman improvements in agricultural and irrigation technology. The main exports from Achaea were wine, particularly from the northern Peloponnese, as well as olive oil and honey, linen and woollen textiles and marbles.
Location Athens
Athens (Pleiades)
Garden The Gardens of Epicurus
Keywords  Literary Gymnasium  Garden Description In the 4th century B.C., the schools and gardens of the philosophers Plato, Aristotle, Theophrastos and Epicurus were built in the vicinity of the gymnasia in the suburbs of Athens. Like the gymnasia, these schools were held in especially high esteem by members of the wealthy, educated class of Roman society who eagerly absorbed Greek culture and often completed their education in Athens. It is difficult to say in exactly what condition these schools were at this time, but the memory of them in their prime was still vivid. The educational institutions of Athens were maintained until the emperor Justinian decreed that the schools be closed in 529 A.D.
Many dialogues and descriptions of private villas of Roman aristocrats reveal that parts of their estates were landscaped and designed to evoke Greek gymnasia and schools, where, in theory at least, hours could be spent discoursing and philosophizing. Parts of the villas, such as those of Cicero and the emperor Hadrian, were occasionally named ‘Academy’ and &amp;ldquo;Lykeion&amp;rdquo; after the gymnasia and schools of Athens.
Cicero set the scene in De finibus 5.1.3 for a group of men in the Academy near the gardens of Epicurus in 79 B.C., and he mentioned the garden of Plato in the same suburb (De finibus 5.1.2). Roman statues of Epicurus and the Epicurean philosopher Colotes found outside the Dipylon gate on the road to the Academy may reflect some rebuilding prompted by Hadrian in the school of Epicurus located here. Heliodoros (Aethiopica 1.16.5), writing in the 3rd century A.D., mentioned a gathering of men near the garden of Epicurus.
Maps Plans Images Dates Bibliography  E. Vanderpool, “The museum and garden of the peripatetics,” ArchEphemeris, 1953-1954, pt. 2: 126-28. M. Carroll-Spillecke, “The gardens of Greece from Homeric to Roman times,” Journal of Garden History 12.2, 1992: 91.  Pleiades ID 579885
TGN ID 5004159
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 20 July 2020
Related articles </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Circus of Roman Corinth</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/corinth/corinth_circus/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 09:50:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/corinth/corinth_circus/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands.
The provincial capital was Corinth. Under Nero in the mid-1st century A.D. Epirus became a separate province, and in the mid-2nd century Thessaly was detached and added to the province of Macedonia. Under Roman domination many cities such as Athens, Sparta, Patras, and Corinth grew in size and prominence, the latter two partly owing to their importance as ports. After an initial decline in the number of rural sites in the early Empire, by the late Roman period the countryside was densely settled with farms and villas, due to changing landholding patterns and Roman improvements in agricultural and irrigation technology. The main exports from Achaea were wine, particularly from the northern Peloponnese, as well as olive oil and honey, linen and woollen textiles and marbles.
Location Corinth
Corinth (Pleiades)
Garden The Circus of Roman Corinth
Keywords  Archaeological circus spinae amphorae mosaic  Garden Description The circus of Roman Corinth was excavated in 1967-1968 in the so-called Gymnasium area to the north of the city. The eastern curved meta, a portion of the spina (a total of 19 meters in length; Max. W. 4.49 m.), and a series of hard-packed racecourse floors were recovered, along with a fragmentary marble cone that was part of a turning post (meta). Lead curse tablets, typical finds in circuses, were found close to the meta. It appears that the circus was planned as an integral component of the Caesarian design of the city after 44 B.C. and constructed during the mid- to late-Augustan period. There are renovation phases in the late 1st century and 6th century A.D. This circus was probably the site of the equestrian contests of the Corinthian Caesarea festival and, at times, of the Panhellenic Isthmian Games.
In the spina and meta excavators found three large pits cut into the bedrock, spaced roughly 6 m. apart, center to center, and placed just south of the central axis of the structure(s) (pit 1: (in meta) Diam. 1.65 m.; Depth 0.88 m.; pit 2: (in spina) Diam. 1.65 m.; Depth 0.79 m.; pit 3 (in spina): Diam. 1.45 m.; Depth 0.80 m., Fig. 1) There is no indication of hydraulic cement within the pits or in the spina area. The pits can be dated to the original construction phase of the circus from the mid- to late-Augustan period. Later, in the 5th century A.D., the pits were filled in. Based on the similarities of the diameter and depth of these pits to those for cypresses at nearby Nemea, it is very likely that these are also planting pits for trees. If so, the planting pit in the meta would be evidence for a tree in the same location where the marble cone has been restored in a later phase (Fig. 2). Shallow channels cut into the bedrock lead toward the pits from different directions. No terracotta or lead water pipes were found, and there is no evidence for the water supply system, suggesting that these channels may have been simply for directing rainwater into the planting pits.
A transport/storage amphora, broken into several fragments and with the neck and foot cut off, was found inside one of the pits (pit 2, Fig. 3). This amphora was almost certainly reused as a planting pot and is further evidence that the meta and spina were planted. The amphora is a North Italian Dressel 6 or Spanish Dressel 7-11 type, with dates ranging from the 1st century A.D. to first half of the 2nd century A.D. Thus, the planting pot may not belong to the earliest phase of the circus. Fragments of marble sculpture were found in the fill above the spina, including a large egg-shaped object that may be part of a lap-counting device, a colossal hand, the fragmentary head and arm of a youth, the left leg of an athlete with palm tree support, as well as a lifesized terracotta comic mask. The presence of these fragments suggests the possibility that the spina/meta area was also decorated with sculptures amidst the garden plantings.
The so-called “hippodrome garden” type (see … add cross-references to Domus Flavia on the Palatine Hill in Rome, “Stadium-Garden” at Hadrian’s Villa at Tivoli, the Villa of the Little Circus at Silin, Jericho, Pliny’s Tuscan villa, and Domitian’s villa above Lake Albano) must have been inspired in some way by Greek hippodromes and/or by Roman circuses with planted areas with sculptural and possibly architectural decoration in the central area and probably around the circumference of the elongated racecourse. It must be pointed out, however, that no Greek hippodrome has ever been excavated, although new excavations at the Sanctuary of Zeus on Mt. Lykaion in Arcadia, Greece may be able to shed some light for the first time on a Classical period hippodrome structure and its possible garden features (http://lykaionexcavation.org). In addition, although trees appear in circus scenes illustrating the spina and meta of the Circus Maximus in Rome on 3rd – 4th century A.D. mosaics, e.g., the Barcelona mosaic, as well as on coins, e.g., coin of Philip I, and on sarcophagus reliefs, such as the Vatican sarcophagus (Humphrey, Roman Circuses, pp. 235-236, figs. 56, 119; p. 127, fig. 56; pp. 196-203, fig. 99-101) and the possibility of plantings has been proposed in the spinae of Roman circuses (e.g., by Humphrey, Roman Circuses, p. 38 for the circus at Leptis Magna), no specific archaeological evidence has been recorded until the publication of this circus at Corinth.
Plans   Fig. 1: Actual State Plan of the Roman circus, with planting pits labeled. From D. G. Romano, “Roman Circus,” p. 589, fig. 3. Plan courtesy of the author.   Images   Fig 2. Reconstruction drawing of the Roman circus with hypothetical cypress trees planted in the spina and meta. Drawing by David Pacifico for the Corinth Computer Project.     Fig. 3: Fragmentary amphora found in pit 2 in the spina of the Roman circus. Photograph courtesy of James Wiseman.   Dates Bibliography BIBLIOGRAPHY: D. G. Romano, “A Roman Circus in Corinth,” Hesperia (worldcat) 74, 2005:585-611; J. H. Humphrey, Roman Circuses: Arenas for Chariot Racing. (worldcat) Berkeley,1986.
Pleiades ID 570182
TGN ID 7010734
Contributor David Gilman Romano (ORCID: 0000-0001-5764-6652)
Publication date 16 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sanctuary of Artemis</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/aulis/aulis_sanctuary_of_artemis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 09:50:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/aulis/aulis_sanctuary_of_artemis/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands.
The provincial capital was Corinth. Under Nero in the mid-1st century A.D. Epirus became a separate province, and in the mid-2nd century Thessaly was detached and added to the province of Macedonia. Under Roman domination many cities such as Athens, Sparta, Patras, and Corinth grew in size and prominence, the latter two partly owing to their importance as ports. After an initial decline in the number of rural sites in the early Empire, by the late Roman period the countryside was densely settled with farms and villas, due to changing landholding patterns and Roman improvements in agricultural and irrigation technology. The main exports from Achaea were wine, particularly from the northern Peloponnese, as well as olive oil and honey, linen and woollen textiles and marbles.
Location Aulis
Aulis (Pleiades)
Garden Sancturary of Artemis
Keywords  Literary grove (sacred grove) Pausanias  Garden Description The shrine of Artemis at Aulis in Boeotia was visited by Pausanias (9.19.6-8). The Greeks in Homer’s Iliad had sacrificed to Artemis in Aulis in hope for favorable winds to carry them from Greek shores to Troy (Iliad 2.305-310). The late 5th century Athenian playwright, Euripides, made reference to the grove of Artemis in his Iphigenia in Aulis (185-186, 1543-1549). Here in the 2nd century A.D. Pausanias noted white stone statues (presumably marble) of Artemis and saw palm trees growing in the sanctuary. According to him, the fruit was not all edible, as it was in Palestine, but he remarked that the fruit ripened better than the dates in Ionia.
Dates Bibliography Pleiades ID Aulis (Pleiades)
TGN ID 5004252
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 16 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Temple of Hephaistos</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/athens/athens_temple_of_hephaistos/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 09:49:38 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/athens/athens_temple_of_hephaistos/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands.
The provincial capital was Corinth. Under Nero in the mid-1st century A.D. Epirus became a separate province, and in the mid-2nd century Thessaly was detached and added to the province of Macedonia. Under Roman domination many cities such as Athens, Sparta, Patras, and Corinth grew in size and prominence, the latter two partly owing to their importance as ports. After an initial decline in the number of rural sites in the early Empire, by the late Roman period the countryside was densely settled with farms and villas, due to changing landholding patterns and Roman improvements in agricultural and irrigation technology. The main exports from Achaea were wine, particularly from the northern Peloponnese, as well as olive oil and honey, linen and woollen textiles and marbles.
Location Athens
Athens (Pleiades)
Sublocation Athenian Agora (Pleiades)
Garden Temple of Hephaistos
Keywords  Archaeological planting pots (horticultural containers)  Garden Description On the western edge of the Athenian Agora on Kolonos hill was the temple of Hephaistos, built in the second half of the 5th century B.C. Excavations in 1937 around the temple revealed numerous square planting pits cut into the living rock in the 3rd century B.C. and again in the 1st century B.C. (Fig. 1). Rock-cut planting pits were preserved in four rows on the south, with isolated examples of such pits on the north and west sides (G on plan). The excavator cogently argued for rows of plantings to the north, south and west of the temple. The lack of planting pits on the north and west sides can be explained by the fact that the rocky hill upon which the temple was built fell away sharply on the north and west, requiring levelling layers above the natural rock. Into these deposits trees or shrubs were planted, leaving no trace of planting pits in the rock below. On the steeper southern side, however, the rock slope had to be shaved off, necessitating the cutting of planting pits into the rock. Possibly more than 60 such pits were arranged in rows parallel to the temple in the 3rd century; two rows on the north and south sides, and one row on the west side. After the Roman destruction of many Athenian buildings by Sulla in 86 B.C., at least the south side was replanted and two more rows of pits dug, resulting in four rows of trees or shrubs on this side. In many of the pits was a terracotta planting pot in ashy soil at a depth of ca. 50 cm. These planting pots, possibly containing laurel and pomegranate shrubs, had drainage and root holes in the bottom. The lack of maintenance of the irrigation pipes leading to the garden caused the plantings to wither and die by the second half of the 1st century A.D. The garden has been replanted with myrtle bushes and pomegranate trees.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the Temple of Hephaistos and its temple grove (G) with surviving rows of planting pits (open squares). Adapted from Thompson 1937, fig. 1.   Dates 3rd century BCE to the 3rd century CE
Bibliography D.B. Thompson, “The Garden of Hephaistos”, Hesperia 6, 1937:396-425; M. Carroll-Spillecke, “The gardens of Greece from Homeric to Roman times,” Journal of Garden History (worldcat) 12.2, 1992:90, figs. 10-11.
Pleiades ID 807514119
807514119
TGN ID 5004159
Contributor ORCID Publication date 16 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hadrians Library</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/athens/athens_hadrians_library/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 09:48:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/athens/athens_hadrians_library/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands. The provincial capital was Corinth. Under Nero in the mid-1st century A.D. Epirus became a separate province, and in the mid-2nd century Thessaly was detached and added to the province of Macedonia. Under Roman domination many cities such as Athens, Sparta, Patras, and Corinth grew in size and prominence, the latter two partly owing to their importance as ports. After an initial decline in the number of rural sites in the early Empire, by the late Roman period the countryside was densely settled with farms and villas, due to changing landholding patterns and Roman improvements in agricultural and irrigation technology. The main exports from Achaea were wine, particularly from the northern Peloponnese, as well as olive oil and honey, linen and woollen textiles and marbles.
Location Athens
Athens (Pleiades)
Garden Hadrian&amp;rsquo;s Library
Keywords  Literary Archaeological piscinae peristyles (Roman courtyards) Gymnasium Pausanias colonnades  Garden Description The most monumental building dedicated to education and intellectual pursuits in Athens was the so-called Library of Hadrian (Fig. 1). It consisted of four columned halls with exedrae at regular intervals on the north and south sides, and a library room flanked by lecture halls on the east.
In the center of the building was a large open peristyle courtyard with a long pool (stippled on plan). The courtyard has been reconstructed as a garden (G on plan) in which students and scholars could stroll, and there were almost certainly statues in this area. One is reminded of Vitruvius’ recommendation to plant the open areas between the colonnades of buildings with greenery which he believed improved the air and made walks in this environment healthy for body and mind (5.9.5). The building bears a strong resemblance typologically, and very likely thematically, to the late Hellenistic/early Roman gymnasium outside the city in the Academy. Pausanias, our literary source for Hadrian’s building projects in Athens, referred to the library as a splendid building with 100 columns, adorned with statues and paintings (1.18.9).
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the Library of Hadrian with its courtyard garden (G) and apsidal pool (stippled). Adapted from Travlos 1971, fig. 316.   Dates Bibliography J. Travlos, Bildlexikon zur Topographie des antiken Athen. (worldcat) Tübingen, 1971, pp. 244-252, figs. 316-318; D. Willers, Hadrians panhellenisches Programm. Archäologische Beiträge zur Neugestaltung Athens durch Hadrian.(worldcat) Basel, 1990, pp. 14-21, figs. 1-2, pl. 1.3.
Pleiades ID 579885
TGN ID 5004159
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 16 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gymnasia and Groves</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/athens/athens_gymnasia_and_groves/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 09:47:21 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/athens/athens_gymnasia_and_groves/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands. The provincial capital was Corinth. Under Nero in the mid-1st century A.D. Epirus became a separate province, and in the mid-2nd century Thessaly was detached and added to the province of Macedonia. Under Roman domination many cities such as Athens, Sparta, Patras, and Corinth grew in size and prominence, the latter two partly owing to their importance as ports. After an initial decline in the number of rural sites in the early Empire, by the late Roman period the countryside was densely settled with farms and villas, due to changing landholding patterns and Roman improvements in agricultural and irrigation technology. The main exports from Achaea were wine, particularly from the northern Peloponnese, as well as olive oil and honey, linen and woollen textiles and marbles.
Location Athens
Athens (Pleiades)
Garden Gymnasia and Groves
Keywords  Literary Archaeological palaestrae Gymnasium  Garden Description The three most famous gymnasia in Athens, situated outside the city in naturally well-watered and shady sanctuaries of pre-Classical date, were those in the suburbs. In the Academy, was a shrine of the hero Hekademos; the Lykeion, had a sanctuary of Apollo; and a cult site of Herakles was located in Kynosarges. The gymnasia in these suburbs were especially revered in Roman times as prestigious educational centers. They included running tracks and other sports grounds for physical training, rooms for literary instruction and baths spread out over a large area and loosely added to in the course of time. In each of the three areas foundation walls of a building enclosing a palaestra, or sports ground, of the 4th century B.C. have been excavated. Roman building activity in the Athenian suburbs is confirmed by Pausanius (1.18.9). According to him, Hadrian had a gymnasium named after him outside the walls of Athens near the Ilissos River in Kynosarges, although it is unclear whether he actually had a new gymnasium built here in the 2nd century A.D. or if he merely refurbished the old one. Roman honorific inscriptions and baths erected on the sites of the three suburban gymnasia indicate that they were kept up and modernized well after the Classical period. Ancient literary references to the plane, elm, poplar, and olive trees in the Academy are numerous. Excavations in the suburb of Academy have shown that a new gymnasium was built there in the late Hellenistic/early Roman period. This gymnasium consisted of a central courtyard enclosed by porticoes on all four sides. The northern wing of the building complex contained rooms which were probably used as libraries and for lectures, while the south, west and east wings appear to have had a row of desks, of which only the stone bases remain, running down the middle of each corridors. The courtyard itself may have been used as a palaestra for training, although by this period Greek education focused less on physical training than on lectures, debates, and literary study (Fig. 1). The courtyard had a pool in the center (P on plan) and a podium for statues (S on plan), possibly of the Muses, at the northern end, both of which certainly would have restricted any space for athletics. No paving in the courtyard could be found, and it possible that it was planted in some way, perhaps with shade trees (G on plan).
Plans   Dates Bibliography J. Travlos, Bildlexikon zur Topographie des antiken Athen, (worldcat) Tübingen, 1971, pp. 42-51, 180F, 181L, 340-341, 345-347, 579, figs. 59-62; M. Carroll-Spillecke, Κήπος. Der antike griechische Garten. (worldcat) Wohnen in der klassischen Polis 3, Munich, 1989, pp. 28-29; W. Hoepfner, “Platon’s Akademie. Eine neue Interpretation der Ruinen,” in W. Hoepfner, ed., Antike Bibliotheken, (worldcat) Mainz, 2002, pp. 56-62.
Pleiades ID 579885
TGN ID 7001393
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 16 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban Houses Near the Areopagus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/athens/athens_urban_houses_near_the_areopagus/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 09:46:56 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/athens/athens_urban_houses_near_the_areopagus/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands. The provincial capital was Corinth. Under Nero in the mid-1st century A.D. Epirus became a separate province, and in the mid-2nd century Thessaly was detached and added to the province of Macedonia. Under Roman domination many cities such as Athens, Sparta, Patras, and Corinth grew in size and prominence, the latter two partly owing to their importance as ports. After an initial decline in the number of rural sites in the early Empire, by the late Roman period the countryside was densely settled with farms and villas, due to changing landholding patterns and Roman improvements in agricultural and irrigation technology. The main exports from Achaea were wine, particularly from the northern Peloponnese, as well as olive oil and honey, linen and woollen textiles and marbles.
Location Athens
Athens (Pleiades)
Sublocation Areopagus (Pleiades)
Garden Urban Houses near Areopagus
Keywords  Archaeological piscinae peristyles (Roman courtyards)  Garden Description Several Roman houses in Athens make use of the remains of Classical and Hellenistic buildings, and, as far as we can tell, these houses generally had courtyards paved with marble chips, pebbles or tile set in mortar, rather than with gardens. One house on the north-west slope of the Areopagus, however, was of early Roman date and might have had a garden, since the surface of its peristyle courtyard was unpaved (Fig. 1). In the center of this courtyard was a rectangular water basin with apsidal ends, and in the southwest corner was a well. Another only partially excavated house of the mid-4th century A.D., built into the northern slope of the Areopagus, had a small courtyard (3.20 x 3.90 m.) paved with blue and white marble slabs surrounded by a masonry flower bed 50 cm. wide (Fig. 2; f on plan). Around this ran a shallow marble-paved basin (c on plan) which was supplied with water by a fountain on the south eastern side of the courtyard. Water flowed from the basin through a lead pipe in the middle of each side of the courtyard into the planter beds.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of an early Roman house with its possible garden courtyard and apsidal pool near the Areopagus. Adapted from Thompson and Wycherley 1972, p. 185, fig. 46.   Images   Fig. 2: Paved courtyard with its flowerbeds (f) and surrounding water channel (c) in a late Roman house near the Areopagus. Adapted from Frantz 1988, pl.25a.   Dates Bibliography A. Frantz, Late Antiquity: A.D. 267-700. The Athenian Agora XXIV. (worldcat) Princeton, 1988, pp. 36-37, pls. 24a, 25a; H. A. Thompson and R. E. Wycherley, The Agora of Athens. The History, Shape and Uses of an ancient City Center. The Athenian Agora XIV. (worldcat) Princeton, 1972, p. 185, fig. 46.
Pleiades ID 969121823
TGN ID 7001393
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 16 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Palace of the Giants</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/athens/athens_palace_of_the_giants/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 09:46:53 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/athens/athens_palace_of_the_giants/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands. The provincial capital was Corinth. Under Nero in the mid-1st century A.D. Epirus became a separate province, and in the mid-2nd century Thessaly was detached and added to the province of Macedonia. Under Roman domination many cities such as Athens, Sparta, Patras, and Corinth grew in size and prominence, the latter two partly owing to their importance as ports. After an initial decline in the number of rural sites in the early Empire, by the late Roman period the countryside was densely settled with farms and villas, due to changing landholding patterns and Roman improvements in agricultural and irrigation technology. The main exports from Achaea were wine, particularly from the northern Peloponnese, as well as olive oil and honey, linen and woollen textiles and marbles.
Location Athens
Athens (Pleiades)
Sublocation Athenian Agora (Pleiades)
Garden Palace of the Giants
Keywords  Archaeological Gymnasion (Gymnasium)  Garden Description A large complex of the early 5th century A.D. in the southern part of the Agora on the site of the earlier Odeon of Agrippa generally has been interpreted as a late Roman gymnasion (“Gymnasion of the Giants”). Homer Thompson, however, more recently proposed that the building might have been an official residence maintained by the Imperial court with suitable temporary accommodations for high-ranking government officials (Fig. 1). He suggested that the great northern courtyard may have met ceremonial needs as a reception area, while the other parts of the building served as quarters for guests, including bedrooms and baths. The northern courtyard (29 x 38 m.) was adorned with a row of statues stretching the length of the court. These included a figure of Epicurus, the great Classical philosopher who had a school and garden in the suburb of Academy in the 4th century B.C. Plantings in this setting would not be out of place thematically, but without any evidence for them, this must remain speculation.
It is possible that a garden might have been present in one of the inner courtyards of the building, especially since the complex was directly supplied by sufficient water from a late Roman aqueduct. The smallest of the courtyards (7 x 7 m.), the southeast court, was paved with terracotta tiles and cannot, therefore, have been planted, but the central courtyard seems not to have been paved (G on plan). The building stood on a plot of land of irregular shape that was enclosed within a boundary wall. This has been reconstructed as an informal garden area (G on plan), although no traces of plantings have survived. The complex was abandoned by ca. 530 A.D.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the so-called “Palace of the Giants” (shown cross-hatched in grey) in the Agora, with possible gardens (G). The dotted lines indicate the outlines of the earlier Odeon of Agrippa and other older buildings beneath the “Palace.” Adapted from Camp 1986, p. 200, fig. 166.   Dates Bibliography H. A. Thompson and R. E. Wycherley, The Agora of Athens. The History, Shape and Uses of an ancient City Center. The Athenian Agora XIV. (worldcat) Princeton, 1972, pp. 211-213; J. McKendrick Camp, The Athenian Agora. Excavations in the heart of Classical Athens. London, (worldcat) 1986, p. 200, figs. 166-167; H. Thompson in A. Frantz, Late Antiquity: A.D. 267-700. The Athenian Agora XXIV. (worldcat) Princeton, 1988, pp. 95-116, pls. 54-55.
Pleiades ID 807514119
TGN ID 5004159
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 16 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Temple Grove (Aegina)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/aegina/aegina_temple_grove/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 09:45:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/aegina/aegina_temple_grove/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands.
The provincial capital was Corinth. Under Nero in the mid-1st century A.D. Epirus became a separate province, and in the mid-2nd century Thessaly was detached and added to the province of Macedonia. Under Roman domination many cities such as Athens, Sparta, Patras, and Corinth grew in size and prominence, the latter two partly owing to their importance as ports. After an initial decline in the number of rural sites in the early Empire, by the late Roman period the countryside was densely settled with farms and villas, due to changing landholding patterns and Roman improvements in agricultural and irrigation technology. The main exports from Achaea were wine, particularly from the northern Peloponnese, as well as olive oil and honey, linen and woolen textiles and marbles.
Location Aegina
Aegina (Perseus)
Garden Temple Grove
Keywords  Literary grove (sacred grove) Pausanias Pindar  Garden Description Evidence for a temple grove on Aegina exists only in a literary reference. Pausanias (2.29.6) wrote that the shrine of Aiakos was surrounded by a grove of olive trees. Pausanias says that it had been there since ancient times, and a reference in 464 B.C. to the grove in Pindar’s Olympian Odes (13.109) confirms that it was much older. This sanctuary was located in a prominent spot in the harbor town and was enclosed within a wall built of white stone. At the time of Pausanias’ travels in Greece in the 2nd century A.D., the temple grove was still to be seen.
Dates Much older than 464 BCE, lasting until after the 2nd century CE
Bibliography Pleiades ID 579844
TGN ID 7011087
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 16 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>