<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>aedicula on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/aedicula/</link>
    <description>Recent content in aedicula on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 15:25:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/aedicula/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>II.1.3-7</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_i.md/ii.1.3-7/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 15:25:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_i.md/ii.1.3-7/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region II
Insula Insula VIII
Keywords  cauponae amphorae (storage vessels)  House House of Aemilius Primio and Aemiluis Saturninus
Garden Small garden to the rear of a caupona
Garden Description Behind the shop were the living quarters with a garden to the rear. The wall to the west was topped with the broken amphoras as it was shared with the adjacent garden of I.i.1-13.
Bibliography W. F. Jashemski, 1993, Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius. Volume 2, Appendices, p.75. (worldcat)
Pleiades ID 456321707
TGN ID 7004658
Excavation Dates Unspecified
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 19 February 2021</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>II.viii.6</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_viii/ii.viii.6/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_viii/ii.viii.6/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region II
Insula Insula VIII
Keywords  aedicula lararia strigillation triclinia dolium [lapilli] [sarculum] [dolabella]  Garden Description A large aedicula lararium on the east wall and a large triclinium (l. medius, 4.40 m.; l. imus 4.00; l. summus 3.80 m.; table between couches 1.00 x 1.67m.) were found in the large area attached to this humble house when excavation was started in 1953-1954. Human remains were uncovered with five gold coins, two gold rings, a strigil and seven medical instruments close to the -triclinium. Next to the shrine two terra-cotta votive offerings, a slender female winged figure (0.155 m. high; Pompeii inv. no. 10569) and a small draped figure with considerable red paint surviving on the drapery(figure (0.165 m. high; Pompeii inv. no. 10150) were found as well as a marble statuette of Hercules (ca. 0.57 high without base; Pompeii inv. no. 10138). South of the triclinium a doghouse had been built by mounting half of a dolium (0.70 x 0.50m.) on a masonry base 0.15 m. high. Further finds included a large terra-cotta funnel, but the function of this area could not be determined. Excavation by Jashemski in 1971-1972 revealed what appears to be a large commercial flower garden. Where the lapilli remained until the 1970s, the undamaged soil contours and root and stake cavities were well preserved. Circular watering depressions remained in one bed that held a small plant. Balloon photographs showed complicated bed arrangements and a path coming from the outside area to the middle of the garden where a left turn led to the triclinium and altar in front of the lararium. Fig.63, 17.7.73, Fig. 64, 8.33.73, Fig. 65, 21A.13.73 An extensive system of rain water collection and distribution had been built. Roof run off was collected in a large dolium on each side of the door and in a nearby pool. Additional water could be brought from outside sources and poured through an amphora tip in the east end of the north wall to fill a dolium imbedded in the northeast corner of the garden. The natural slope of the land was from north to south and the irrigation layout took advantage of this fact. When the dolium in the northeast corner overflowed the water ran down a channel along the east wall watering young trees planted in the channel until it fell into a second half dolium buried in the soil. This process would be repeated the length of the east wall and continued along the south wall. There were channels along the north and west walls and dividing all the beds in the interior of the garden. Fig. 66, 23.23.74, Fig. 67, 21.31.73, Fig. 68, 18.10.73 Eleven large tree root cavities were counted with dimensions of 30 cm. or more at ground level. One grew near the southwest corner of the shrine, three along the walls and seven scattered about the garden. Another huge, partially destroyed cavity about 2 m. could have been an olive tree that grew to the west of the cistern. Many other smaller tree root cavities were found, and carbonized cherries (Prunus cerasus L.) that were found here would identify at least some of these. Along the walls with the tree root cavities were terra-cotta pots similar to those found in the House of the Ship Europa. There were well preserved vine root cavities and post cavities for the pergola over the triclinium. Most of the garden cavities that remained were for the stakes that supported the frames for the shade structures for young bedding plants. Parallel to the west wall, 3.30m. away from it, a row of posts formed either a shed or an arbor with roofing support holes in the wall above. Two ancient gardening tools, a sarculum and a dolabella were found in the garden along with bones, teeth, perfume bottle fragments, and fragments of terra-cotta unguent containers. The house to this garden contained a large number of glass perfume bottles. The assessment of pollen and spores found here are shown in Jashemski, Gardens, 1:282-284 and in Tables F-H. Fig. 69, 21.15.73, Fig. 70, 7.33.73, Fig. 71, 11.8.73, Fig. 72, 11.31.71, Fig. 73, 21.30.72, Fig. 74, 11.20.74
Plans   Fig. 62, Plan of Region II, insula viii   Images   Fig.63, 17.7.73 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 64, 8.33.73 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 65, 21A.13.73 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 66, 23.23.74 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 67, 21.31.73 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 68, 18.10.73 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 69, 21.15.73 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 70, 7.33.73 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 71, 11.8.73 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 72, 11.31.71 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 73, 21.30.72 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 74, 11.20.74 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)   Pleiades ID 456321707
TGN ID 7004658
Excavation Dates 1953-1954, 1971-1972
Bibliography  Jashemski, The Garden of Hercules at Pompeii (II.viii.6): The Discovery of a Commercial Flower Garden, American Journal of Archaeology, 83 (1979) (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.I, p.279-288 and figs. 421-435 (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, pp.94-95 (worldcat) Meyer, p.432  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 10 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa del Mobilio Carbonizzato</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tiffany_fong2/casa_del_mobilio_carbonizzato/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tiffany_fong2/casa_del_mobilio_carbonizzato/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Insula V
House 5
Garden Casa del Mobilio Carbonizzato
Keywords  fauces aedicula opus signinum aedicula lararium [lararium]  Garden Description 549.V.5. Visible from the fauces, this little courtyard (a) had an elaborate aedicula shrine which was excavated in 1932-1933. A low double wall with a gutter bordered the courtyard on the west and north sides with a cistern opening located in the center of the west edge of garden. Four small flower beds on the sides and a circular bed in the center had raised borders to retain the water for the plants within, and the remainder of the courtyard was paved in opus signinum. Jashemski commented that the garden had been restored with eleven such small planting beds. The east wall had traces of an animal painting on a blue background by the aedicula lararium. A deer was painted on the right side and several more indistinct animal forms were noted over the lararium. At the south end of this wall there were traces of leaves and a lattice fence suggesting a garden painting may have been located here.
Plans   Plan of Casa dell’Ara Laterizia     Plan of Casa dell’Ara Laterizia   Images   Illustration of Casa dell’Ara Laterizia     Illustration of Casa dell’Ara Laterizia   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1932-1933
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 370-371 Maiuri, Herculaneum,p. 44 Maiuri, Ercolano, pp.260-261 and fig. 203 (plan) on p. 256.  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa dello Scheletro</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/tiffany_fong/casa_dello_scheletro/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/tiffany_fong/casa_dello_scheletro/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Garden Casa dello Scheletro
##Jashemski Catalogue 536.III.3.
Keywords  aedicules tympanum pergola amorino  Garden Description The small light well of this house had once been occupied by a pool. By the time of the eruption it had been filled with soil and converted to a small garden (a). During this change an aedicula was built on a high podium against the back wall, decorated with mosaic and shells, and garden paintings were added to the light well walls. The walls on the east and south had panels framed on the top and sides with a wide red band and a smaller black one inside. The south wall had panels on both sides of the mosaic aedicule, and of all the panels, the left panel of the south wall was the best preserved, although the GARDENS OF THE ROMAN EMPIREITALIA2center third is missing. In this panel the lattice fence is evident and a tympanumis suspended form the center of the top. This panel also has traces of what could have been a trellised pergola just to the left of the aedicula. The garden in the background is filled with densely planted bushes and a bird is perched on a branch on either edge of the panel. A masonry base was uncovered in the pool which had at one time supported a fountain jet or statuette. The excavation was begun in 1830-1831, resumed in 1869-1871, and completed in 1927. The niche of the aedecula shrine was decorated with a cluster of acanthus leaves with a female face in the center. A small roof was set in the wall to protect the painting and above this was a marble relief of an amorino flying to the left carrying a filled money purse. An iron grate was built over the top of this light well to prevent intruders from gaining access from the neighbor’s roofs. To the north was an apsed room which gained light and air from this area.
Plans   Herculaneum 536.III.3.Casa dello Scheletro   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1830-1831; 1869-1871; 1927
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, pp. 369-370 (worldcat) Maiuri, Herculaneum, pp. 35-36 (worldcat) Idem, Ercolano, pp. 51, 272-274 and fig. 213 (plan) on p. 266; Sear, Roman wall and vault mosaics no. 26, pp. 66-67, calls the shrine a fountain.(worldcat)  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa dello Scheletro</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tiffany_fong/casa_dello_scheletro/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tiffany_fong/casa_dello_scheletro/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Insula III
House 3
Garden Casa dello Scheletro
Keywords  aedicules tympanum pergola amorino  Garden Description The small light well of this house had once been occupied by a pool. By the time of the eruption it had been filled with soil and converted to a small garden (a). During this change an aedicula was built on a high podium against the back wall, decorated with mosaic and shells, and garden paintings were added to the light well walls. The walls on the east and south had panels framed on the top and sides with a wide red band and a smaller black one inside. The south wall had panels on both sides of the mosaic aedicule, and of all the panels, the left panel of the south wall was the best preserved, although the GARDENS OF THE ROMAN EMPIREITALIA2center third is missing. In this panel the lattice fence is evident and a tympanumis suspended form the center of the top. This panel also has traces of what could have been a trellised pergola just to the left of the aedicula. The garden in the background is filled with densely planted bushes and a bird is perched on a branch on either edge of the panel. A masonry base was uncovered in the pool which had at one time supported a fountain jet or statuette. The excavation was begun in 1830-1831, resumed in 1869-1871, and completed in 1927. The niche of the aedecula shrine was decorated with a cluster of acanthus leaves with a female face in the center. A small roof was set in the wall to protect the painting and above this was a marble relief of an amorino flying to the left carrying a filled money purse. An iron grate was built over the top of this light well to prevent intruders from gaining access from the neighbor’s roofs. To the north was an apsed room which gained light and air from this area.
Plans   Plan of Casa dello Scheletro   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1830-1831; 1869-1871; 1927
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, pp. 369-370 (worldcat) Maiuri, Herculaneum, pp. 35-36 (worldcat) Maiuri, Ercolano, pp. 51, 272-274 and fig. 213 (plan) on p. 266;(worldcat) Sear, Roman wall and vault mosaics no. 26, pp. 66-67, calls the shrine a fountain.(worldcat)  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>