<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/beneharnum_lescar_pyr%C3%A9n%C3%A9es-atlantiques/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2020 11:20:32 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/beneharnum_lescar_pyr%C3%A9n%C3%A9es-atlantiques/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa Saint-Michel</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/beneharnum_lescar_pyr%C3%A9n%C3%A9es-atlantiques/beneharnum-lescar-pyre%CC%81ne%CC%81es-atlantiques_villa-saint-michel_y.sun/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/beneharnum_lescar_pyr%C3%A9n%C3%A9es-atlantiques/beneharnum-lescar-pyre%CC%81ne%CC%81es-atlantiques_villa-saint-michel_y.sun/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_Aquitania Gallia_Aquitania (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location BENEHARNUM Lescar
Bene(h)arnum (Pleiades)
Location Description Today, Lescar is a small suburb of Pau, about ten kilometers to the northwest. In Roman times, however, it was the site of Beneharnum, a major city of Aquitania that gave its name to the Bearn region. Its center was at the edge of the high bluff rising above the valley of the Gave de Pau, a site now marked by the Romanesque church of Saint Julien. There are numerous Roman remains in the area, and the Office de Tourisme has organized a 5.5 kilometer, self-guided loop tour of them, including the site of the Villa Saint-Michel, about 200 meters south of Avenue Carrérot, on the east side of the chemin de Ferré. The site, however, is privately owned. Part of the villa was destroyed in building the owner&amp;rsquo;s house; the rest has been reburied and is under a lawn. A beautiful geometric mosaic and some artifacts, including a scythe blade, may be seen at the museum, which is in front of the west façade of Saint Julien..
Garden Villa Saint-Michel
Keywords  galleries (upper level spaces) mosaic  Garden Description From a high terrace about a kilometer east of the ancient Beneharnum, the residents of this suburban villa covering some 2000 square meters could look out over the valley of the Gave de Pau and on to the majestic, sharply outlined peaks of the Pyrenees on the horizon. Discovered in 1886, it was excavated by M. Bats and J. Seigne in 1968-70. The first phase of the construction was probably around the middle of the first century and included a courtyard.
A remodeling occurred around 100 – 150. The main entrance was from the north by a semicircular peristyle with 12 columns and a diameter of 18 meters. The carpet mosaic of the gallery depicted this colonnade projected upon the floor and with a garland of foliage suspended between each support.
The center of the villa was organized around a rectangular peristyle (33 x 26 m). Both the galleries and the central part were covered with mosaics, but in the southeast corner a floor of pebbles surrounded a masonry mass interpreted by Bats and Seigne as possibly a structure to hold planters. A gallery 45 meters long ran along the south façade of the villa and offered a splendid panorama over the valley of the Gave de Pau and on to the Pyrenees beyond.
Plans   Fig. 1: Villa Saint-Michel.    Dates Discovered in 1886, it was excavated by M. Bats and J. Seigne in 1968-70.
Bibliography  M. Bats and J. Seigne. La villa gallo-romaine de Saint-Michel à Lescar (Beneharnum), Bull. de la Société des Sciences, Lettres et Arts de Pau (Pau), 7, 1972, p. 19-66 ; G. Fabre, CAG, 64, 1994, n°203 ; Demeures, p. 363-365, plans p. 100.  Pleiades ID 981505 246237
TGN ID 300004031 300240727
Contributor Clopper Almon
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>