<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>graffiti on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/graffiti/</link>
    <description>Recent content in graffiti on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2020 12:44:41 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/graffiti/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>I.ii.6</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_6/i.ii.6/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2020 12:44:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_6/i.ii.6/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 6
Garden I.ii.6
Keywords  archaeological garden atriums graffiti (casual notations) gutters (building drainage components) inscription peristyles (columnades) piscinae porticoes puteal  Garden Description The west portico of the small peristyle garden at the rear of the house was entered through two doors directly from the atrium. The garden was enclosed on four sides by a portico supported by eight stuccoed brick columns. On the foreside, the two first columns on the left had a larger intercolumniation corresponding to the wide opening opposite the atrium. Between these columns stood a terra-cotta puteal covered with white stucco. A gutter around the edges of the garden was shown in the plan. The round pool in the center of the garden no longer exists, and only stumps of the columns remain today. One of the graffiti on the walls of the portico noted that on November 17 Puteolana gave birth to three males and two females (XV K(alendas) NOV(embres) PVTEOLANA PEPERIT MASCL(os) III FEMEL[as] II) (CIL IV.3890). Perhaps they were either piglets or puppies. Pigs were more common in ancient cities than is commonly realized.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Descr., p. 39. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, 1: 104-105 (for the graffito). (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 21. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 199. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. Gen.,” p. 76. Pernice, p. 18. Viola, “Scavi,” p 11. (worldcat) Warscher, “Codex.”  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 24 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>