<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>fountain on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/fountain/</link>
    <description>Recent content in fountain on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 11:20:32 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/fountain/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>House 35, Insula VII-5</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-35-insula-vii-5_y.sun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-35-insula-vii-5_y.sun/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania (Pleiades)
Location AUGUSTORITUM - Limoges
Augustoritum (Pleiades)
Location Description The earliest traces of settlement in this area are at the oppidum of Villejoubert 25 kilometers east of the city. The Roman settlement of Limoges proper dates from about 15-10 B.C. and was named Augustoritum (Augustus’s ford) in honor of the emperor. It covered some 65 to 100 hectares and was laid out in a regular rectangular grid. The ancient wall dates from the end of the third century. The town took water from several sources, including the aqueduct of Aigoulène; there were drains for waste water disposal. There were several public fountains and baths, a theater, an arena, and temples. The city declined in the fourth century. Its Roman name was replaced by the Celtic name of the local people; and its regular street pattern, almost totally lost.
Garden House 35, Insula VII-5
Keywords  manhole fountain  Garden Description This house, north of the House of the Large Vestibule, knew two states. In the first, 80-150, a series of rooms formed a U around a court [1] crossed by an underground stream. The room [2] to the east was crossed by a channel covered with large flagstones. This channel, with two strips of waterproofing in hydraulic cement, fed a fountain whose base was found at point A on the plan. To the south, at point B, a manhole with a quadrangular rim led into the subterranean tunnel of the stream. The second state of the house dates from the third century. A large, 205 square-meter room was then created which encroached on the courtyard [1], which, however, kept its fountain and manhole.
Dates First state: 80-150 CE
Second state: 3rd c CE
Bibliography  J.P. Loustaud. Limoges antique, Travaux d’Archéologie Limousine, supplément 5, 2000, p. 230-232, plan p. 231. (with a bibliography of earlier works) (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 138203
TGN ID 7030318 7008410
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>