<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/latimer/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/latimer/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Latimer</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/latimer/latimer_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/latimer/latimer_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Latimer
Latimer (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Latimer
Keywords archaeological garden
barrier walls
fences (site elements)
flower gardens
orchards
rural villas
vegetable gardens
villae rusticae
Garden Description Excavations at this country house in Buckinghamshire have produced evidence for gardens adjacent to the main residence in its latest phase dating to the beginning of the 4th century (Fig. 1). The house at the west is of the winged corridor type, fronted by a large courtyard bisected by a paved central drive with a banked edge. Between the outer courtyard wall and the house were areas used for gardening (G in Fig. 1). Just inside the outer yard wall on the south side of the drive traces of at least six bedding trenches cut into the natural subsoil and running parallel to each other were followed for at least 5 meters (b in Fig. 1). These have been interpreted by the excavator as the remains of vegetable gardens (Fig. 2). He also attributed a number of stake holes in this area to small fences bounding the vegetable gardens, and suggested the possibility of an orchard on the northern side of the drive as well as a formal flower garden nearer to the house between the projecting wings, for which there is no concrete archaeological evidence. Finally a small pit just inside the courtyard gateway may represent a pit dug to take one of a pair of trees flanking the entrance.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the residential building (A) with excavated bedding trenches (b) in its garden courtyard (G). Adapted from Branigan 1971, fig. 20.(Rights statement)   Images   Fig. 2: Reconstruction of the house and garden. Courtesy of K. Branigan.   Dates Evidence for gardens dating to the beginning of 4th century
Bibliography  K. Branigan, Latimer. Belgic, Roman, Dark Age and Early Modern Farm, Bristol, 1971, pp. 85-86, 184, figs. 14, 20 (worldcat) R.J. Zeepvat, “Roman Gardens in Britain,” in: A.E. Brown, ed., Garden Archaeology. Council for British Archaeology Research Report 78, London, 1991, p. 56, fig. 5.3. (worldcat)  Periodo ID Pleiades ID 79555
TGN ID 1029792
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 11 July 2020
Related articles </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>