<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nennig on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/categories/nennig/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Nennig on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/categories/nennig/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/nennig-villa-rural/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/nennig-villa-rural/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location NENNIG (Germany)
NENNIG (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa
Keywords  peristyle corridors bath building  Garden Description The villa of this rural estate of the third century and its grounds are the only parts of the complex which have been investigated (Fig. 1). The farm lay about 40 km. south of Trier on a gentle slope above the Moselle river. The villa is of the winged corridor type with a facade of over 45 meters in length, taking up an area of 4200 square meters. In the villa were two peristyle courtyards, but both were paved with slabs of red sandstone rather than having been laid out as gardens.
Parks were laid out on the grounds of the villa. A peristyle corridor 250 meters in length and 8.80 meters in width led from the villa to the bath building on the southwest, although it was not directly connected to either building. From the open-sided corridor one could enjoy the view of the almost certainly landscaped grounds, and of the terrain sloping down to the river. It is assumed that there was another peristyle corridor on the northeast. A grotto on the grounds of the villa belonged to the park.
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  P. Steiner, Die römische Villa von Nennig, Saarbrücken, 1955. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/1073267042) H. Mylius, &amp;ldquo;Die Rekonstruktion der römischen Villen von Nennig und Fliessem,&amp;rdquo; Bonner Jahrbuch 129, 1924:110-120, fig. 1, pls. 4-5. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/1075378207)  Pleiades ID 109198
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 12 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/veirherrenborn-rural-villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/veirherrenborn-rural-villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location VEIRHERRENBORN (Germany)
VEIRHERRENBORN (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa
Keywords  courtyard paddock  Garden Description The house stood in the middle of a farm complex 75 meters wide and 120 meters long. It dates to the early second century. The house (A on the plan, Fig. 1) is of the winged corridor type, measuring 19.30 x 22.40 meters.
On the west and east, in front of and behind the house, were open courtyards enclosed by a wall. The western courtyard has been interpreted as a garden (G on plan); the eastern one may have been a paddock.
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  H. Cüppers, ed., Die Römer in Rheinland-Pfalz, Stuttgart, 1990, p. 653, fig. 594. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/924024101)  Pleiades ID 109198
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 12 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
