<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>peristyle on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/peristyle/</link>
    <description>Recent content in peristyle on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 12:00:02 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/peristyle/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Park Area Adjacent to the Great Palaestra and the Amphitheater</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/park_area_adjacent_to_the_great_palaestra_and_the_amphitheater/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/park_area_adjacent_to_the_great_palaestra_and_the_amphitheater/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region II
Keywords  peristyles palaestra  Garden Description Park-like areas were located between the Great Palaestra and the Amphitheater and to the north. Here booths were set up under trees or awnings and a carnival atmosphere existed as depicted in a painting (Mus. Naz. inv. no. 112 222) found in the peristyle of house I.iii. 23. Two huge root cavities were found in front of the palaestra by Maiuri, although only one was recorded in his plan, and six trees grew in a row on the north side of the palaestra.
Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.I, pp. 13-14, 161-162 (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, pp. 91-92 (worldcat) Maiuri, Notizie degli scavi di antichità, p.194 (worldcat)  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 10 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Venus Marina; Casa Della Venere in Conchiglia (II.iii.3)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/region_ii_2/insula_iii/house_3/ii.iii.3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/region_ii_2/insula_iii/house_3/ii.iii.3/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region II
House Casa della Venere in conchiglia; House of Venus Marina(II.iii.3)
Garden Peristyle Garden
Keywords  architectural paintings villa peristyles (Roman courtyards)  Garden Description Redecorating had been just completed to this site at the time of the eruption and here was found the best preserved garden paintings in Pompeii. Nine stuccoed columns, gold below, fluted white above, supported a portico on the west, north and part of the east sides of this peristyle garden (a) at the rear of the house. A gutter ran along the portico at the edge of the garden. Fig. 9, 50.35.64 Garden paintings decorated the outside walls of the sitting room (diaeta) (b), the small room (c) extending into the garden on the east, and the little room in the southeast corner of the garden. The long rear wall was in full view of the grand triclinium and so the paintings here were the focal point of the garden. Yellow bands separate the wall into three panels and a golden lattice fence on a black background extends across the base. On the left panel a poorly rendered statue of Mars stands on a pedestal in front of the fence. The garden painting behind this is painted on a blue background with an ivy garland framing the top and sides. The left side of the panel shows an oleander with pink blossoms, a myrtle with white blossoms and a heron (Ardea cinerea L.) standing on the fence. Then comes a slender and tall tree-like bush with a large yellow bird, perhaps an oriole, perched within, followed by another oleander in bloom, a pine with a song thrush (Turdus philomelos C.L.Brehm) eating a berry and another bird flying overhead. There is an oleander behind the statue of Mars, to the right a myrtle, a tall slender tree with yellow fruit, more oleanders, and another heron standing in front of an unidentified plant. Three more birds are painted, one hanging upside down like a titmouse to reach some berries (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, figs., 1, 103, 204, on pp. ii, 64 and 129). There is a mask at the center of the top (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, figs. 1, 101 and 204 on pp. ii, 62 and 129). Fig. 10, 18.36.59 Venus is featured on the large central panel floating on a seashell and accompanied by two amorini, one of which is riding a dolphin (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, figs. 101 and 203 on pp. 62 and 128). A narrow brown band runs around the side and top of this panel which dominates the garden. The right side panel is similar to the left one with a blue background, ivy garlands, and a mask in the center at the top (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, fig. 102 on p. 63). The images counted from the left are as follows; a myrtle bush with white flowers and a large bird above it, a clump of ivy in front of this with white flowers, then a tall slender oleander in bloom and another large bird perched on it, next a myrtle with a heron in front standing on the fence, a plant with fern-like foliage and finally a rosebush in bloom. The center of the panel features a basin-shaped, footed fountain on a pedestal in front of the fence. Water is spouting from the center and a bird is perched drinking on the left side rim with a pigeon on the opposing rim. Far into the background behind the fountain is a tree with graceful branches. A myrtle and an oleander with a gray shrike perched on it are painted to the right of the fountain along with another heron walking on the fence, a tall slender apple tree with yellow fruit, and a myrtle with a clump of ivy in front. Inserted into the border of the right panel is a small niche lararium decorated with green plants. Fig.11, 17.19.59, Fig. 12, 50.26.64, Fig. 13, 54.3.64 The outside walls of the small room which extends into the southeast corner of the garden are golden yellow with a red-brown border. The top had an ivy garland, the center caught up with a shield on the south wall and with a helmet on the east. The south wall painting features a two handled, footed egg-shaped fountain standing on a pedestal in front of the fence. It is decorated with three standing figures in high relief, and has a water jet in the center. Directly behind the fountain in back of the fence are a tall slender bush in bloom and a rose bush in flower to the left. There is a bird perching in this bush and a song thrush flying to the right towards a low shrub-like tree with fruit (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, fig. 104 on p. 65). The east wall painting is located to the left of the door with the main feature being a graceful two-handled crater fountain standing on a rectangular pedestal in front of the lattice fence (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, fig. 104 on p. 64). Behind the jetting fountain and the fence is a pine tree (Pinus sp.) with a large wood pigeon (Columba palumbus L.) perched on the top and a large bird flying towards the tree from either side. Low bushes fill the background. A soft green background is used in the garden paintings on the outside walls of the sitting room and the adjacent small room projecting into the garden on the east. The lattice fence is painted along the base and the panel is outlined with bands of red-brown. A bird perches on the right side of a footed, bowl-shaped, square rimmed fountain in the only portion of the south wall painting that remains. Fig. 14, 51.35.64 The fountain stands behind the lattice fence in the center of the panel and to the left just above are some yellow-orange flowers, difficult to identify, with oleanders and some other badly damaged flowers in the background. Daisies are painted to the left of the fountain and part of a tall bush with a little bird survived on the right edge of the panel. A belvedere window that looks out into the garden from the sitting room interrupts two of the panels on the east wall. Both panels have lost the top portion while little remains of the left panel. All that can be discerned here is a footed, bowl-shaped fountain with a bird on the right rim standing behind the fence in a garden of unidentified plants. On the right side panel an elaborate bowl-shaped fountain spouts water behind the fence with two birds perched on the rim, a brown bird on the left and a lighter colored one on the right. The garden behind the fence has a small tree with apple-like fruits on the left and a pomegranate tree directly behind the fountain. To the right is a myrtle in bloom and them one more tall bush (Jashemski, Gardens¸vol. 1, fig. 106 on p. 66). In the foreground are several roses and an ivy mound to the left of the fountain and what could have been another ivy bush to the right. Fig. 15, 22.15.66
Plans   garden paintings detail 1.     garden paintings detail - bird and plant.     overview garden paintings 1.     overview garden paintings 2.     overview garden paintings 3.     painting remains.     painting of garden.   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography   Jashemski, Wilhelmina F, The Gardens of Pompeii, Herculaneum, and the Villas Destroyed by Vesuvius, New Rochelle: Aristide D. Caratzas, 1979. Print , 1:63-66, 128-129 and fig. 1 on p. ii, figs. 101-106 on pp. 62-66, figs. 203 and 204 on pp. 128, 129; worldcat
  Jashemski, Wilhelmina F, and Stanley A. Jashemski, The Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the Villas Destroyed by Vesuvius. New Rochelle, NY: Caratzas, 1993. Print. pp. 84, 330-331worldcat
  Maiuri, Pompei, Roma: Roma, 1986. Print. p. 83-84worldcat
  Maiuri, Rome Painting,, pp. 7, 125;worldcat
  Michel, Dorothea, Pompejanische Gartenmalereien, Mainz am Rhein: P. von Zabern, 1978. Print. pp. 7, 125; worldcat
  Orr, David G.Roman Domestic Religion: A Study of the Roman Household Deities and Their Shrines at Pompeii and Herculaneum, Ann Arbor, Mich: UMI, 1999. Print.pp. 399-400;worldcat
  Schefold, Karl.Wände Pompejis: Topographisches Verzeichnis Der Bildmotive. Berlin: Gruyter, Walter de, &amp;amp; Co, 1957. Print. worldcat
  Pleiades ID 425769173
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 2 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Narrow garden in the house of Messius Ampliatus (II.ii.4)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/region_ii_2/insula_ii/house_4/ii.ii.4b/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/region_ii_2/insula_ii/house_4/ii.ii.4b/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region II
House House of Messius Ampliatus(II.ii.4))
Garden Narrow garden in the house of Messius Ampliatus (II.ii.4)
Keywords  villa courtyards  Garden Description B. The east portico gave access to the narrow garden (b) to the back of the house.
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography   Jashemski, Wilhelmina F, ‘The Garden of Hercules at Pompeii’ (II.viii.6): The Discovery of a Commercial Flower Garden.,American Journal of Archaeology, vol. 83, no. 4, 1979, pp. 403–411. [link](https://www.jstor.org/stable/504139. Accessed 2 Dec. 2020.)
  Spinazzola, Vittorio, and Salvatore Aurigemma, Pompei Alla Luce Degli Scavi Nuovi Di Via Dell&amp;rsquo;abbondanza (anni 1910-1923), Roma: Libreria dello Stato, 1953. Print. map after p. 376 where this garden is labeled hortus.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 433204
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 4 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Peristyle garden in house of Julia Felix (II.iv.a).</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/region_ii_2/insula_iv/house/ii.iv.a/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/region_ii_2/insula_iv/house/ii.iv.a/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region II
House House of Julia Felix
Garden Peristyle garden in house of Julia Felix
Keywords  jet d&amp;rsquo;eau peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes statuettes (free-standing sculpture) triclinia  Garden Description A. Three separate gardens were located in this property. It occupies the entire insula and is one of the largest properties in the city. It was originally excavated in 1755-1757, stripped of its works of art and re-buried. In 1951-1952 it was re-excavated and restored but not published. Sixteen elegantly carved slender marble pillars support a portico which borders the peristyle garden (a) on the west.Fig.18, 5.29.59, Fig. 19, 5.32.50, Fig. 20, 5.25.59 An alcove (b) housed a summer triclinium (l. medius, 4.00 m.; l. imus and summus 3.00 m.) with marble faced couches that looked through the portico into the garden. Between the couches a niche supplied water that ran down small marble steps to a hole at the bottom. The water re-surfaced as a jet in the middle of the trilinium. A vine covered arbor stretched along the south and east side of the garden and beyond it in bays on the east wall were raised planting beds, alternating semicircular and square. These were covered with pumice and decorated with a band of Egyptian blue around the sides and top, the middle bay having four bands of Egyptian blue. The room (c) to the south of the triclinium had a garden representation (0.185 x 0.42 m.) on the north part of the west wall on the red middle zone. Four fish ponds connected to form a long channel down the center of the garden. The little marble bridges that crossed the channel and covered alcoves at the bottom of the pools provided shelter for the fish and eels. A number of statuettes were found during the two excavations of this site. More recently the pieces that were found are as follows: A marble satyr (0.475 m. preserved height; Pompeii inv. no. 8856) located at the north end of the pool, a seated terra-cotta figure of Pittacus of Mitylene (0.65 m. high; Pompeii inv. no. 2181-4) found at the edge of the pool, a small marble fountain statuette of a sea crab in a shell (0.19 m. wide; Pompeii inv. no. 1073/54). During the earlier excavation some of the items found were as follows: a satyr child (0.46 m. high; Muz. Naz. inv. no. 6108), a nude youth holding grapes in his right hand and a goose in his left (0.76 m. high; Muz. Naz. inv. no. 6342), a faun(Muz. Naz. inv. no. 6343), an old man covered with a cloth (0.49 m. high), a bird with a lizard in its beak (0.32 m. high), a marble mask of a smiling youth on a small column (0.54 m. high), and a marble relief (0.36m. long x 0.11 m. high) of an old man seated of a bench, perhaps this was a pinax. The heads of twelve marble herms, (one woman, one old man, three bearded men) were reported by PAH, but the post of only one is mentioned and only the feet of the thirteenth herm was found. A terra-cotta group of Caritas Romana was found in many pieces as well as multiple fragments of other terra-cotta statuettes which had been in the eleven niches in the peristyle portico. Chambalu believed the herms stood between these niches.
Plans   view form the portico     detail of the jet.     portico and garden   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography   Annali Dell&amp;rsquo;instituto Di Correspondenza Archeologica, 1830, p.50 worldcat
  Bonucci, Carlo.Pompei Descritta Da Carlo Bonucc, p.219 worldcat
  Bragantini, Irene. Pitture E Pavimenti Di Pompei. Roma: Ministero per i beni culturali e ambientali, Istituto centrale per il catalogo e la documentazione, 1981. Print.1:238 worldcat
  Chambalu,Die weiderverschüttete Besitzung der Julia Felix beim Amphitheater in Pompeji, Pp, 1895. Print. pp. 14-15 and plan of Weber (1757) after p. 20 worldcat
  Della Corte, Notizie degli scavi antichita (1958), p. 125, no. 238 (Pittakos inscription);worldcat
  Dwyer, Eugene J. Pompeian Oscilla Collections: (pls. 80-130) Mainz: Verlag Philipp von Zabern, 1981. Print. p. 279, no. 81worldcat
  F. Rakob, *Ein Grottentriklinium in Pompeji,*RM (1964), pp. 182-194;worldcat
  H. Döhl, Plastik aus Pompeji , tesi di libera d tingen 1976, pp. 8-10
  Idem, Pompeii (Novara), p. 111 worldcat
  Idem, Pomp. Sculpture, pp. 67, 128, and figs. 197, 212;
  Jashemski, Wilhelmina F, The Gardens of Pompeii, Herculaneum, and the Villas Destroyed by Vesuvius, New Rochelle: Aristide D. Caratzas, 1979. Print , 1:48, 110 and figs. 81 on p. 47, 82 on p. 48, 83 (marble statue at north end of pool), 84 (Pittacus), and 85 (sea-crab in shell) on p. 49; worldcat
  Jashemski, Wilhelmina F, and Stanley A. Jashemski, The Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the Villas Destroyed by Vesuvius. New Rochelle, NY: Caratzas, 1993. Print. pp. 86-88, 396worldcat
  Kapossy, Balázs. Brunnenfiguren Der Hellenistischen Und Römischen Zeit. Zürich, 1969. Print. pp 46, 50 worldcat
  Lorenz, Thuri. Galerien Von Griechischen Philosophen Und Dichterbildnissen Bei Den Römern. Mainz: Verlag Ph. von Zabern, 1965. Print. p. 39worldcat
  Maiuri, I giardini, Le Vie d’Italia, no.9 Sept 1961, p. 1139; worldcat
  Maiuri, Statuette fittilli di Pittaco di Mitilene, Archeologia Classica 4 (1952): 55-59; worldcat
  Maiuri, Pompei ed Ercolano:Fra case ed abitanti, pp. 74-75; worldcat
  Pompeianarum Antiquitatum Historia, vol. 1 pt. 1, pp. 13, 15, 16, 18, 19, 21, 28, 29, 30, 31, 34, 37, 39 (Apr. 13, 1755-Mar. 6, 1756);Ibid., vol. 1 pt. 2, pp. 98, 101; worlcat
  Richter, Greek Portraits, 3:34 and fig. 134; worlcat
  Richter, Portraits of the Greeks, 1:89a; worlcat
  Rohden, Hermann. Die Terracotten Von Pompeji. Stuttgart, 1880. Print. pp. 24, 47-48, 53, 57, 62 and plates 35.3, 36, 41.4, 47; worldcat
  Salsa Prina Ricotti, The Importance of Water in Roman Open Air Tricliniums, in Ancient Roman Villa Gardens, Dumbarton Oaks Colloquium on the History of Landscape Architecture, no. 10, Dumbarton Oaks, 1987, pp. 172-173; worlcat
  Sear, Frank B. Roman Wall and Vault Mosaics. Heidelberg: F.H. Kerle, 1977. Print. p.94 worlcat
  Zahn, Wilhelm.Die Schönsten Ornamente Und Merkwürdigsten Gemälde Aus Pompeji, Herkulanum Und Stabiae vol2.pl.100 (plan)worldcat
  Pleiades ID 955554415
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 2 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Peristyle garden in house of Messius Ampliatus (II.ii.4) </title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/region_ii_2/insula_ii/house_4/ii.ii.4a/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/region_ii_2/insula_ii/house_4/ii.ii.4a/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region II
House House of Messius Ampliatus(II.ii.4))
Garden Peristyle garden in house of Messius Ampliatus (II.ii.4)
Keywords  villa courtyards  Garden Description A. The portico which bordered the peristyle garden (a) on the north and east side was accessed from the entrance hall. This site had been extensively damaged prior to excavation.
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography   Della, Corte M, Case Ed Abitanti Di Pompei, Pompei-scavi: M. Della Corte, 1954. Print. worldcat
  Jashemski, Wilhelmina F, ‘The Garden of Hercules at Pompeii’ (II.viii.6): The Discovery of a Commercial Flower Garden.,American Journal of Archaeology, vol. 83, no. 4, 1979, pp. 403–411. [link](https://www.jstor.org/stable/504139. Accessed 2 Dec. 2020.)
  Pleiades ID 634179974
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 2 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Swimming pool in house of Julia Felix (II.iv.b).</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/region_ii_2/insula_iv/house/ii.iv.b/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/region_ii_2/insula_iv/house/ii.iv.b/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region II
House House of Julia Felix
Garden Swimming pool in house of Julia Felix
Keywords  peristyles (Roman courtyards) swimming pools  Garden Description B. An outdoor swimming pool (8.50 x 4.50 m.; 1.50 m. deep) was located in the garden area (d) in the northeast part of the insula. There were steps into the pool on the north and south sides, and an entrance (8) into the area from the side street. Fig.21, 6.8.59
Plans   swimming pool   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Jashemski, Wilhelmina F, and Stanley A. Jashemski, The Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the Villas Destroyed by Vesuvius. New Rochelle, NY: Caratzas, 1993. Print. pp. 84 worldcat  Pleiades ID 955554415
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 2 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Terrace House 2</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/shamika_ghate/7._ephesos_terrace_house/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/shamika_ghate/7._ephesos_terrace_house/</guid>
      <description>Province Asia Asia (Pleiades)
Province description The region of what is now modern Turkey became a part of the Roman Empire in 133 B.C. when king Attalos III of Pergamum bequeathed his kingdom to the Roman people. The province included the heartland of the Pergamene kingdom as well as the territories of Mysia, Lydia, Ionia, Caria, western Phrygia and the eastern Aegean islands. Under Augustus in 27 B.C. Asia was declared a senatorial province and the governance of a proconsul. The capital of the province was Ephesos, although Pergamon may have fulfilled this role initially. Under Diocletian (284-305 A.D.) the province was subdivided into smaller administrative units: Hellespontus, Asia, Lydia, Caria, Phrygia I and Phrygia II. Due to its excellent harbors on the west coast and its many navigable rivers, Asia’s water-borne trade with the rest of the Mediterranean flourished. In the second century A.D. Asia experienced great prosperity, to which the growth and architectural aggrandizement of many of its cities attest. In the area of Kibyra, bordering the regions of Lycia, Caria, Phrygia and Pisidia, numerous inscriptions refer to the large imperial estates of Roman families. Woolen textiles, marble, and timber constituted a significant part of the commodities exported from the province.
While the Romans might have looked to the Greeks for inspiration in philosophy, architecture, sculpture, and the fine arts, the non-Greek peoples of the eastern Mediterranean are their inspiration for luxury, fine-living, and the status conferred by displays of individual wealth (Athenaeus Deip. XV.690). Asia was a center for such splendor, first in the kingdoms of Lydia, Phrygia, and Lycia, and then continued by the Persian satraps, and later the Hellenistic kings. The Persian paradeisos is particularly well-attested in literature referencing Asia. That these gardens are known primarily from Roman-period literary sources indicates their continuing influence. For example, long after the gold of Lydia’s Pactolus River had disappeared, Lydia remained a literary topos, not only for copious wealth, but for a life of luxury set in a landscape of natural abundance. Athenaeus (Deipnosophistae 12.515d-f) wrote in the second century A.D. that
&amp;ldquo;The Lydians in their luxury planned parks and made them like gardens and so kept in the shade. For they thought it more dainty not to have the sun’s rays touch them at all…&amp;rdquo;
Other districts of Asia captured the Roman imagination: Pliny the Elder writes of an ancient plane tree (Sycamorus orientalis) in Lycia with a girth of sufficient circumference to house a grotto in its hollow trunk, ornamented with pumice and moss with provisions for 18 people to dine there (Pliny HN 12.9).
The paradeisoi of the Persian satraps are of particular influence on the introduction of horti and gardens of Rome. The paradeisos, from the Persian, paira daeza, or “enclosed place,” is a term that had evolved by the Hellenistic period to mean a large enclosed park with luxurious gardens as well as orchards, collections of trees, crops, and hunting areas (see Sardis below). It was at Sardis that the Greek Lysander visited Cyrus the Younger, a visit recorded by Clearchus and retold by Xenophon. It is an essential moment in garden history recounted for the Romans by Cicero, De Senectute. 17.59. These paradeisoi, in the sense of luxurious orchards, are said by the Romans to have been brought to Greece by Kimon (Aristot. apud Plut. Cim. 10; comp. Cic. de Off. 2.18Plutarch), and were adopted by Hellenistic kings throughout Greece and southern Italy during the late Hellenistic period. The hunting parks at Daskyleion and Celenae are also vividly described by Xenophon (See Anabasis 1.2.7, 2.4.14 and Oeconomicus 4.13). Xenophon also describes how paradeisoi were occupied or cut down by armies during the fourth and third centuries BC. Appreciation for these parks apparently continued, and Seleucus of Syria took over the royal paradeisos at Sardis (Plutarch, Demetrios 50.6). Years of instability followed, so it is difficult to know what the Romans themselves thought of paradeisoi in Asia in the second and first centuries B.C. Notable examples of paradeisoi, in some form, may have been visible to Romans visiting Asia, as well. For example, the Mausoleum at Halicarnassus is now thought by its excavators to have been set in a grove or park.
Thus, the paradeisos, the alsos, the gymnasium, and the quadriporticus are not forms the Romans suddenly “discovered.” They had had a long influence and were integrated into the Hellenistic architectural forms of the Italic landscape. In the second century B.C., however, when the Roman generals began to define themselves as rulers of an empire, they turned directly to the palaces and paradeisoi of the Hellenistic monarchs to establish their power, to display spoils of war, and to create the luxurious setting for life in Rome. They further adapted the evolving quadriporticus form for display to the public Despite the importance of Asia Minor in the history of the Roman landscape, archaeological evidence is scant. The excavators contacted for this essay indicated that parks, gardens, and other planted areas have yet to become a subject of research design for the region and finds appear to be few—primarily inscriptions and wall paintings. Most of the smaller domestic courtyards—often the most manageable to investigate - are paved. The larger palaestrae, gymnasia, and enclosed open spaces have not been investigated for landscape architectural and planting features, although recently an important campaign of work in the South Agora at Aphrodisias is setting an important precedent (see below). This catalog includes areas with dirt and incomplete paved surfaces, and notes sites where the excavators have some level of optimism about fruitful future study. The subject of designed landscapes, gardens, and planted areas in Asia Minor awaits archaeological investigation.
Location EPHESOS (Efes, Turkey) (Pleiades)
Location Description Remains of gardens have yet to be discovered in this city, but an appreciation for garden culture is seen in the Terrace Houses, dating to the second and third centuries A.D., where wall paintings not only depict gardens, but use garden images to create the illustionistic experience of being in the space of garden.
House Terrace House 2
Keywords  courtyard dado peristyle (Roman courtyards) medallion (ornament areas) putto  House Description The most striking remains are in Terrace House 2, in Room 20 (Residence 4), excavated by H. Vetters between 1967-1983. Here, in a space originally designed as a courtyard, the walls are decorated with an elaborate garden scene. Much of the painting is covered by a later painting of marble panels, but on the north and west walls the garden scene has been partially revealed (Figs. 1 and 2). The viewer within the room looks out past a real marble dado on top of which is an illusionistic marble fence with an unusual egg and dart design along the top. Beyond is a garden scene, similar to those seen in Pompeii or the famous garden scene of Livia at Prima Porta. The scene is filled with luxuriant foliage, out of which apple trees rise up against the blue sky bearing apples or quinces. A bird flies over a young juniper or cypress. The illusion of the garden continues without a break around the corners. It allows the viewers to feel present in a garden, while knowing they are in a room looking out at it. The later painting completely destroys both the illusion and any recollection that the space had formerly been an open courtyard.
In the central peristyle of Residence 2 of Terrace House 2, Vetters uncovered a late Imperial mosaic of Dionysius and Ariadne in a niche. The peristyle itself is a paved courtyard, but the mosaic offers the viewer a rich view of a paradisiacal vineyard. A lunette features a mosaic of two peacocks holding a garland over a basket or urn of grapes and fruits, with white geese to each side standing on a green lawn with roses and lilies (Fig. 3). The ceiling of the niche features Dionysias and Ariadne in a central medallion set into a panel of blue, against which is arrayed a vine laden with grapes and doves (Fig. 4). In the upper corner, the vine emerges from the ground, and along the base of the wall, a winged putto leads two harnessed leopards or panthers. The opposite side is not preserved.
Just off the peristyle in Room 17, the walls feature a variety of birds, individually portrayed on white backgrounds either sitting on branches or standing among small plants. In Room 24, the landscape themes continue with a painting of stags in woodland, apparently being chased by a putto. Only a small fragment remains. In Room 14, mythological scenes of Achilles and Skyros (west wall) and Achilles and Priam (south wall) are set in a landscape of rocks and trees (Fig. 6). Bird and plant themes are represented through this house.
Maps Plans   Plan of Ephesos terrace house 2   Images   Garden painting in the North-West corner of the peristyle     Detail of the garden painting in the North-West corner of the peristyle, Photo by N. Blanc     Painting as discovered on the west wall of the terrace house 2     Painting as discovered on the North wall of the terrace house 2   Dates 1st-3rd c. CE
Bibliography  Forschungen in Ephesos Vol. VIII/1, Figs. 207-219 (worldcat) Forschungen in Ephesos Vol. VIII/2 Figs. 109-130 (worldcat) W. Jobst, Romische Mosaiken aus Ephesos I: Die Hanghauser des Embolos,Vienna, 1977 (worldcat) C. Kearns, “Visual representations of gardens: diachronic perspectives on the art of landscape,” In ed. K. Gleason, Cultural History of Gardens, London. 2013. pp. 164-165. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 599612
TGN ID 7002358
Contributor Kathryn Gleason (ORCID: 0000-0001-6260-8378)
Publication date 22 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa dell’Atrio Corontio</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tiffany_fong2/casa_dellatrio_corontio/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tiffany_fong2/casa_dellatrio_corontio/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Insula V
House 30
Garden Casa dell’Atrio Corontio
Keywords  [impluvium] [atrium] [peristyle] [viridarium]   Garden Description 552.V.30. A shallow cruciform-shaped impluvium was the central feature in the rectangular atrium of this house excavated in 1933-1934. The atrium gave the impression of a peristyle garden by way of the fountain centered in the impluvium, the plantings on either side and three tuffa columns on either side, fluted white stucco on the top and painted red at the base. These were connected by a low wall with plantings on the top creating a lush green atmosphere to the total effect. This arrangement was the result of the aqueduct supplying an abundance of water and reducing the demand on the cistern, which was found in the northeast corner of the garden, and the ancient well incorporated into the low wall. This house was noted by Maiuri as an elegant example of the transformation of the impluvium basin into a fountain and viridarium.
Plans   Plan of Casa A Graticcio   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1933-1934
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.1, fig. 90 on p. 52 Maiuri,Herculaneum,p. 51 Idem, Ercolano, pp.51, 263-264 and fig. 209 (plan) on p. 261  -
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>