<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2020 21:26:02 -2400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Gilded Stones</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_gilded_stones/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2020 21:26:02 -2400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_gilded_stones/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location saint-roman-en-gal
saint-roman-en-gal (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House of the Ocean Gods
Sublocation Description The northern end of this vast house is just west of the House of Five Mosaics and in the same insula. From the Passage des Grands Entrepôts along this northern limit, it runs over 100 meters southward to the “Voie I” along the south side of the archaeological site. The eastern edge is about 230 meters west of the Rhone. No less than five names have been given to the houses occupying part or all of the site. The following table of these names with approximate dates may help the reader keep them straight. The final house runs just over 100 meters from south to north. The first two houses covered only about the first 66 meters from the south, up to the noticeable kink in the north-south lines. The third house in the above list, the House of the Large Peristyle, was limited to the area north of this kink. The fourth house combined these two, while the last rebuilt the whole area keeping only the outline and a few walls. We describe the houses in chronological order. All plans for these houses are from La maison des dieux ocean, Equipe archèologique departmentale de Saint-Romain-en-Gal, published by Aglas, 1996.
House House of Gilded Stones
Keywords  peristyles (Roman courtyards) courtyards columns (architectural elements) fountains mosaics (visual works) porticoes  House Description  The living space was organized in U on three side of a garden with peristyle. An entrance on the south formed part of a porch [1] which led to the large vestibule [8] (8.5 x 6.4 m) which opened directly onto the peristyle [23]. From the stratigraphy of the soil it is not possible to know whether this peristyle court was planted or whether it was tamped earth. This courtyard (15.7 x 11.4 m) with an open area of 230 square meters is surrounded on all four sides by porticoes 2.5 meters wide. The columns have disappeared. A column with a phallus-formed top formed a fountain that was perhaps part of the décor of the peristyle; the column rested on a socle pierced by a channel for a conduit of lead which continued through the center of the column. A rectangular pool (7 x 3 m) with a semicircular apse of 2.5 meter diameter, perhaps ornamented by a fountain, occupied the northern half of the central area of the peristyle court. A lead pipe coming from the baths supplied water. The drain cut diagonally across the southern half of the courtyard and continued to the wall along the east side of the house, where it turned and ran parallel to this wall down to the channeled stream on the other side of the street to the south of the house.. On the west were rooms with concrete floors, perhaps bedrooms, except for the central room of the wing [16] (5 x 4.2 m) with a somewhat elevated floor in opus signinum. On the axis of the pool, to the north, was the most spacious room [20] (60 square m) which served as a triclinium; its presumed mosaic is totally lost. Room [18], with a mosaic floor, could have been a summer dinning room in connection with this garden, especially because of its position to the north. Further to the north, at the back of the lot, the house had a large garden [25] of 276 square meters with a portico [24] along the south side, 18.6 meters in length and 3 meters wide, with a floor of pounded earth. Below this portico lay a garden of 276 square meters, which one entered no doubt by steps. Study of the soil has not been able to determine how the place was planted. Was it a pleasure garden or a kitchen garden?
Plans   Plan of House of the Gilded Stones   Dates A.D. 20 – A.D. 60
Bibliography   Laroche, H. Savay-Guerraz, E. Chantriaux et al. Guides Archéologiques De La France. Saint-Romain-en-Gal: Conseil général du Rhône, Equipe archéologique de Saint-Romain-en-Gal, 1984, P. 46-57worldcat
  Maison 1996, t.II, p. 364-383
  Delaval, Eric, and Hugues Savay-Guerraz. La Maison Des Dieux Océan: (ier Siècle Avant J.-C. _ Iie Siècle Après J.-C.). Saint-Romain-en-Gal: AGLAS, 1996.worldcat
  Desbat, Armand. La Maison Des Dieux Océan À Saint-Romain-En-Gal (rhône). Paris: CNRS éditions, 1994, P. 86-132worldcat
  Prisset, Jean-Luc, Laurence Brissaud, and Odile Leblanc. Evolution Urbaine À Saint-Romain En-Gal: La Rue Du Commerce Et La Maison Aux Cinq Mosaïques. Paris: CNRS éd, 1994, P. 1-133. worldcat
  Gros, Pierre. L&amp;rsquo;architecture Romaine Du Début Du Iiie Siècle Av. J.-C. À La Fin Du Haut-Empire: 2 Maisons, Palais, Villas Et Tombeaux Paris: Picard, 2001, p. 160-162.worldcat
  Bouet, Alain, and Isabel Figueiral. Les Thermes Privés Et Publics En Gaule Narbonnaise. Rome: École française de Rome, 2003, P. 269-271, fig 189.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 5004109
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Cistern</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_the_cistern/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2020 21:26:02 -2400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_the_cistern/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location saint-roman-en-gal
saint-roman-en-gal (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House of the Ocean Gods
Sublocation Description The northern end of this vast house is just west of the House of Five Mosaics and in the same insula. From the Passage des Grands Entrepôts along this northern limit, it runs over 100 meters southward to the “Voie I” along the south side of the archaeological site. The eastern edge is about 230 meters west of the Rhone. No less than five names have been given to the houses occupying part or all of the site. The following table of these names with approximate dates may help the reader keep them straight. The final house runs just over 100 meters from south to north. The first two houses covered only about the first 66 meters from the south, up to the noticeable kink in the north-south lines. The third house in the above list, the House of the Large Peristyle, was limited to the area north of this kink. The fourth house combined these two, while the last rebuilt the whole area keeping only the outline and a few walls. We describe the houses in chronological order. All plans for these houses are from La maison des dieux ocean, Equipe archèologique departmentale de Saint-Romain-en-Gal, published by Aglas, 1996.
House House with the Cistern
Keywords  porticoes courtyards  House Description This house was exposed during a programmed excavation from 1981 to 1985. It occupies a plot of 1338 square meters facing Voie I, on which it opens through an entrance in the center of its façade. This phase, called the House with the Cistern, was constructed in the last years of the Augustan period on the site of an earlier building, itself Augustan and probably also a dwelling. It was occupied 20 to 25 years before being remodeled. In its unusual quadrilateral shape, no two sides were parallel, but the west and south sides were perpendicular, and the interior walls ran parallel to one or the other of them. The average width (in the east-west direction) was 24 meters and average length 66 meters. The construction was organized around three sides of the courtyard [12] (10 x 8 m); it may have been planted or may have had a simple earthen floor. To the north, a second open space, a court or a garden [17] (roughly 27 x 15 m) took up a third of the lot. A cylindrical structure [16] three meters in diameter, interpreted as a cistern, occupies an extension off the southeast corner. Nearly all of the floors are of pounded earth. Numerous areas of painted plaster have been discovered in the thirteen rooms that ring three sides of the courtyard [12]. However, the quality of the construction remained ordinary. Plans Dates B.C. 20 - A.D. 20
Bibliography   Laroche, H. Savay-Guerraz, E. Chantriaux et al. Guides Archéologiques De La France. Saint-Romain-en-Gal: Conseil général du Rhône, Equipe archéologique de Saint-Romain-en-Gal, 1984, P. 46-57worldcat
  Maison 1996, t.II, p. 364-383
  Delaval, Eric, and Hugues Savay-Guerraz. La Maison Des Dieux Océan: (ier Siècle Avant J.-C. _ Iie Siècle Après J.-C.). Saint-Romain-en-Gal: AGLAS, 1996.worldcat
  Desbat, Armand. La Maison Des Dieux Océan À Saint-Romain-En-Gal (rhône). Paris: CNRS éditions, 1994, P. 86-132worldcat
  Prisset, Jean-Luc, Laurence Brissaud, and Odile Leblanc. Evolution Urbaine À Saint-Romain En-Gal: La Rue Du Commerce Et La Maison Aux Cinq Mosaïques. Paris: CNRS éd, 1994, P. 1-133. worldcat
  Gros, Pierre. L&amp;rsquo;architecture Romaine Du Début Du Iiie Siècle Av. J.-C. À La Fin Du Haut-Empire: 2 Maisons, Palais, Villas Et Tombeaux Paris: Picard, 2001, p. 160-162.worldcat
  Bouet, Alain, and Isabel Figueiral. Les Thermes Privés Et Publics En Gaule Narbonnaise. Rome: École française de Rome, 2003, P. 269-271, fig 189.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 5004109
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Large Peristyle</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_the_large_peristyle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2020 21:26:02 -2400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_the_large_peristyle/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location saint-roman-en-gal
saint-roman-en-gal (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House of the Ocean Gods
Sublocation Description The northern end of this vast house is just west of the House of Five Mosaics and in the same insula. From the Passage des Grands Entrepôts along this northern limit, it runs over 100 meters southward to the “Voie I” along the south side of the archaeological site. The eastern edge is about 230 meters west of the Rhone. No less than five names have been given to the houses occupying part or all of the site. The following table of these names with approximate dates may help the reader keep them straight. The final house runs just over 100 meters from south to north. The first two houses covered only about the first 66 meters from the south, up to the noticeable kink in the north-south lines. The third house in the above list, the House of the Large Peristyle, was limited to the area north of this kink. The fourth house combined these two, while the last rebuilt the whole area keeping only the outline and a few walls. We describe the houses in chronological order. All plans for these houses are from La maison des dieux ocean, Equipe archèologique departmentale de Saint-Romain-en-Gal, published by Aglas, 1996.
Garden House of the Large Peristyle
Keywords  peristyles (columnades) colonnades peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes  Garden Description  Only its eastern end has been uncovered, and of the rooms for living &amp;ndash; presumably to the west – very little is known. What is known is a large peristyle of unusual form with a center certainly planted as a garden. The long axis of the peristyle ran almost due north to make an angle of about 80 degrees with the street along the north and with the axis of the living areas of the house to the west. The form of the peristyle (32.5 x 18 m with porticoes 3.7 meters wide) would have been a fairly normal, slightly trapezoidal “rectangle” with the south side missing were it not that more than half of the west side was also missing. The colonnade on that side ran straight into a wall, presumably of the neighbor’s house, which jutted out into the southwest corner of our owner’s elegant peristyle courtyard and garden. In the northern part of the courtyard, the presence of a U-shaped channel pool seems well attested but is not shown on the plan.
Plans   house of the large peristyle   Dates A.D. 20-A.D 60
Bibliography   Laroche, H. Savay-Guerraz, E. Chantriaux et al. Guides Archéologiques De La France. Saint-Romain-en-Gal: Conseil général du Rhône, Equipe archéologique de Saint-Romain-en-Gal, 1984, P. 46-57worldcat
  Maison 1996, t.II, p. 364-383
  Delaval, Eric, and Hugues Savay-Guerraz. La Maison Des Dieux Océan: (ier Siècle Avant J.-C. _ Iie Siècle Après J.-C.). Saint-Romain-en-Gal: AGLAS, 1996.worldcat
  Desbat, Armand. La Maison Des Dieux Océan À Saint-Romain-En-Gal (rhône). Paris: CNRS éditions, 1994, P. 86-132worldcat
  Prisset, Jean-Luc, Laurence Brissaud, and Odile Leblanc. Evolution Urbaine À Saint-Romain En-Gal: La Rue Du Commerce Et La Maison Aux Cinq Mosaïques. Paris: CNRS éd, 1994, P. 1-133. worldcat
  Gros, Pierre. L&amp;rsquo;architecture Romaine Du Début Du Iiie Siècle Av. J.-C. À La Fin Du Haut-Empire: 2 Maisons, Palais, Villas Et Tombeaux Paris: Picard, 2001, p. 160-162.worldcat
  Bouet, Alain, and Isabel Figueiral. Les Thermes Privés Et Publics En Gaule Narbonnaise. Rome: École française de Rome, 2003, P. 269-271, fig 189.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 5004109
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Ocean Gods</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_the_ocean_gods/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2020 21:26:02 -2400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_the_ocean_gods/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location saint-roman-en-gal
saint-roman-en-gal (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House of the Ocean Gods
Sublocation Description The northern end of this vast house is just west of the House of Five Mosaics and in the same insula. From the Passage des Grands Entrepôts along this northern limit, it runs over 100 meters southward to the “Voie I” along the south side of the archaeological site. The eastern edge is about 230 meters west of the Rhone. No less than five names have been given to the houses occupying part or all of the site. The following table of these names with approximate dates may help the reader keep them straight. The final house runs just over 100 meters from south to north. The first two houses covered only about the first 66 meters from the south, up to the noticeable kink in the north-south lines. The third house in the above list, the House of the Large Peristyle, was limited to the area north of this kink. The fourth house combined these two, while the last rebuilt the whole area keeping only the outline and a few walls. We describe the houses in chronological order. All plans for these houses are from La maison des dieux ocean, Equipe archèologique departmentale de Saint-Romain-en-Gal, published by Aglas, 1996.
Garden House of the Ocean Gods
Keywords  porticoes  Garden Description A century passed before further major modifications. Then the eight columns of the vestibule on the south were removed, and the mosaic floor with the heads of the ocean gods in the four corners (which gives its name to the house) was installed there. In the middle was of the vestibule was a circular pool (diameter 2.5 m) with water jets. North of the first peristyle garden, a huge room [14] was created connecting the first peristyle to the second. In the following peristyle [19], the U-shaped pool with the water jets was eliminated, though the rectangular pool (6.30 x 2.50 m), lined with white marble at the south end of the peristyle was kept. Its bottom was 40 centimeters below the level of the floor of the south portico. Several ovoid horticultural pots (oleae perforatae) in common pale earth ceramic were found against the north wall of this pool. The rest of the north end of the house remained unchanged. It should be added that the area [29] west of large room [30] may have been a third garden.
Plans Dates A.D. 185-A.D 247
Bibliography   Laroche, H. Savay-Guerraz, E. Chantriaux et al. Guides Archéologiques De La France. Saint-Romain-en-Gal: Conseil général du Rhône, Equipe archéologique de Saint-Romain-en-Gal, 1984, P. 46-57worldcat
  Maison 1996, t.II, p. 364-383
  Delaval, Eric, and Hugues Savay-Guerraz. La Maison Des Dieux Océan: (ier Siècle Avant J.-C. _ Iie Siècle Après J.-C.). Saint-Romain-en-Gal: AGLAS, 1996.worldcat
  Desbat, Armand. La Maison Des Dieux Océan À Saint-Romain-En-Gal (rhône). Paris: CNRS éditions, 1994, P. 86-132worldcat
  Prisset, Jean-Luc, Laurence Brissaud, and Odile Leblanc. Evolution Urbaine À Saint-Romain En-Gal: La Rue Du Commerce Et La Maison Aux Cinq Mosaïques. Paris: CNRS éd, 1994, P. 1-133. worldcat
  Gros, Pierre. L&amp;rsquo;architecture Romaine Du Début Du Iiie Siècle Av. J.-C. À La Fin Du Haut-Empire: 2 Maisons, Palais, Villas Et Tombeaux Paris: Picard, 2001, p. 160-162.worldcat
  Bouet, Alain, and Isabel Figueiral. Les Thermes Privés Et Publics En Gaule Narbonnaise. Rome: École française de Rome, 2003, P. 269-271, fig 189.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 5004109
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Vestibule with Columns</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_vestibule_with_columns/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2020 21:26:02 -2400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_vestibule_with_columns/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location saint-roman-en-gal
saint-roman-en-gal (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House of the Ocean Gods
Sublocation Description The northern end of this vast house is just west of the House of Five Mosaics and in the same insula. From the Passage des Grands Entrepôts along this northern limit, it runs over 100 meters southward to the “Voie I” along the south side of the archaeological site. The eastern edge is about 230 meters west of the Rhone. No less than five names have been given to the houses occupying part or all of the site. The following table of these names with approximate dates may help the reader keep them straight. The final house runs just over 100 meters from south to north. The first two houses covered only about the first 66 meters from the south, up to the noticeable kink in the north-south lines. The third house in the above list, the House of the Large Peristyle, was limited to the area north of this kink. The fourth house combined these two, while the last rebuilt the whole area keeping only the outline and a few walls. We describe the houses in chronological order. All plans for these houses are from La maison des dieux ocean, Equipe archèologique departmentale de Saint-Romain-en-Gal, published by Aglas, 1996.
House House of Vestibule with Columns
Keywords  porticoes vestibules colonnades columns (architectural elements) fountains triclinia mosaics (visual works) reception rooms  House Description  In phase I, the house had the L-shape due to the combination of the two previous houses. The main entrance was from the south, past a portico façade, and into a vestibule (12.9 x 11.9 m) that had a double colonnade. A square pool (4 x 4 m) with a water jet occupied its center. To the east and west, the vestibule was framed by rooms and shops. Beyond the vestibule, one came to the first garden [13]. It had a peristyle on four sides (13.5 x 12 m) with an open area of 167 square meters, porticoes 3 meters wide, and columns 3.3 meters high. A rectangular pool (3.5 x18 m) on the axis covered the central third of the garden. A masonry base of a fountain, statue or other ornament was found in the west part of the garden. North of the peristyle, in the center of the main building, was one of the main reception rooms of the house, on the axis of the pool. This triclinium (7.7 x 6.3 m) apparently had a mosaic that has been lost. The surrounding rooms are of small dimensions except for [15], a second reception area. Farther north, a portico [20] opens onto an esplanade [19] which makes the transition from one of the former houses to the other. The level of this free space was 1.4 meters above that of the garden ahead; stairs to the left and right led down. This second large garden (35 x 30 m), open towards the south, is surrounded on the other three sides by a peristyle with porticoes 3.7 meters wide. A channel pool 1.5 meters wide runs around the three sides of the peristyle. It has been proposed to see in room [25] (54 m2) a cold-weather dining room. The west gallery of the portico opened through three doors to the rooms of the building to the northwest. The space [28], with a pounded earth floor may have been intended as another reception room that was not finished. Beyond the corridor [31] there may have been more open space.
Phase III, from around the end of the first century, carried the ideas of Phase II into the first or southern peristyle garden. The pool in the center was converted into space for planting while a U-shaped channel pull was run around the east, south and west sides, while a wider, separate, rectangular pool ran along the north side. The south side had an apse projecting into the garden.
Plans NEW WAY ↓↓  plan of House of Vestibule with Columns   Dates A.D. 60 -A.D. 185
Bibliography   Laroche, H. Savay-Guerraz, E. Chantriaux et al. Guides Archéologiques De La France. Saint-Romain-en-Gal: Conseil général du Rhône, Equipe archéologique de Saint-Romain-en-Gal, 1984, P. 46-57worldcat
  Maison 1996, t.II, p. 364-383
  Delaval, Eric, and Hugues Savay-Guerraz. La Maison Des Dieux Océan: (ier Siècle Avant J.-C. _ Iie Siècle Après J.-C.). Saint-Romain-en-Gal: AGLAS, 1996.worldcat
  Desbat, Armand. La Maison Des Dieux Océan À Saint-Romain-En-Gal (rhône). Paris: CNRS éditions, 1994, P. 86-132worldcat
  Prisset, Jean-Luc, Laurence Brissaud, and Odile Leblanc. Evolution Urbaine À Saint-Romain En-Gal: La Rue Du Commerce Et La Maison Aux Cinq Mosaïques. Paris: CNRS éd, 1994, P. 1-133. worldcat
  Gros, Pierre. L&amp;rsquo;architecture Romaine Du Début Du Iiie Siècle Av. J.-C. À La Fin Du Haut-Empire: 2 Maisons, Palais, Villas Et Tombeaux Paris: Picard, 2001, p. 160-162.worldcat
  Bouet, Alain, and Isabel Figueiral. Les Thermes Privés Et Publics En Gaule Narbonnaise. Rome: École française de Rome, 2003, P. 269-271, fig 189.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 5004109
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>La Plaine, House A under the High School</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_b_under_the_high_school/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2020 21:26:02 -2400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_b_under_the_high_school/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location saint-roman-en-gal
saint-roman-en-gal (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House B under the High School
Sublocation Description Garden La Plaine, House B under the High School
Keywords Garden Description Plans   Plan of La Plaine, House B under the High School   Dates Bibliography   Maison 1996, t. II,, p. 362-363
  Lancha, Janine. Recueil General Des Mosaïques De La Gaule: Iii. Paris: CNRS, 1981, P. 302-307.worldcat
  M. Leglay, Informations archéologiques, in Gallia, 29, 2, 1971, P. 424-425.worldcat
  M. Leglay, “Les jardins à Vienne,” in Seventh Dumbarton Oaks Colloquium on the History of Landscape Architecture, Ancient Roman Gardens, Washington, 1981, P. 57-58.worldcat
  Bouet, Alain, and Isabel Figueiral. Les Thermes Privés Et Publics En Gaule Narbonnaise. Rome: École française de Rome, 2003, P. 275-277, Fig. 195.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 5004109
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>La Plaine, House A under the High School</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/la_plaine_house_a_under_the_high_school/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2020 21:26:02 -2400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/la_plaine_house_a_under_the_high_school/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location saint-roman-en-gal
saint-roman-en-gal (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation La Plaine, House A under the High School
Sublocation Description House La Plaine, House A under the High School
Keywords  domus peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes courtyards reception rooms  House Description This vast domus (120 x 60 m) presumably had its principal, monumental entry on the south side, along the Street of the Port. The south peristyle [6] (approximately 13.7 x 9.3 m) was surrounded by four porticoes with floors of terrazzo signinum. Three of them were 2 meters wide; the fourth, on the north, was 3 meters wide and gave access to the principal room [17].
The courtyard of this peristyle was certainly used as a garden. It had a rectangular pool (8.2 x 6.5 m) and within this pool, at the northern end, a semicircular pool. On the axis of the pool, the reception room [17] (11 x 10 m) served also as a transition to the second peristyle [33] with an open area (about 29.3 x 41.3 m) no doubt planted as a garden. The three-meter wide galleries of the porticoes gave access to a whole series of large rooms, one of which [39] had an apse on the outside, west wall. In the center of the garden was placed a first pool of 3 by 5 meters. To the south, a long, narrow second pool in front of room [17] has been only partially excavated. Along the north side of the courtyard was a rectangle (28.2 x 3.4 m) of water with an unusual apse in the center of its south side in the shape of a brace or accolade. In this apse was found a lead pipe. Against this apse was another pool, a square 5.8 meters on a side. The revetment of all of the pools in this northern peristyle was of marble.
In the northern wing of the house, a square reception room [53], 5.8 meters on a side, was centered on the axis of the garden. No mosaic was found in it, but the few remaining fragments of the pavement indicate that it was mainly of marble plaques.
Plans   Plan of La Plaine, House A under the High School   Dates Bibliography   Maison 1996, t. II,, p. 358-361
  Lancha, Janine. Recueil General Des Mosaïques De La Gaule: Iii. Paris: CNRS, 1981, P. 302-307.worldcat
  M. Leglay, Informations archéologiques, in Gallia, 29, 2, 1971, P. 57-58.worldcat
  M. Leglay, “Les jardins à Vienne,” in Seventh Dumbarton Oaks Colloquium on the History of Landscape Architecture, Ancient Roman Gardens, Washington, 1981, P. 57-58.worldcat
  Bouet, Alain, and Isabel Figueiral. Les Thermes Privés Et Publics En Gaule Narbonnaise. Rome: École française de Rome, 2003, P. 275-277, Fig. 195.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 5004109
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Columns</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_the_columns/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2020 23:06:02 -2400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_the_columns/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location saint-roman-en-gal
saint-roman-en-gal (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House of the Columns
House House of the Columns
Keywords  peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes reception rooms apsed pools fountains triclinia nymphaea (garden structures)  House Description The house had a linear plan starting from a garden on the south, then on the north side of the garden, a façade gallery, then several rooms, and finally a peristyle on the north. It went through three phases with the changes concentrated on the south garden. In the first phase, this garden [13] (23.5 x 11.5 m) was bordered on the north by a portico [12] 2.5 meters wide. In the garden, adjacent to this portico and directly in front of the principal reception room [8] was a rectangular pool (7.5 x 4 m) with an apse in the center of the south side. It probably had a fountain.
In the second phase, this south garden was reduced by the addition of two lateral porticoes (2.5 m wide) on its east and west sides. In keeping with the local fashion of the time, it was given a U-shaped rill or channel pool running around the outer rim of the garden. A 1.5 meter apse on the north side is slightly off the axis of the reception room [9]. In the center of the garden was a little square pool (1.5 m on a side) with an apse on the north. It was surrounded by benches in a U to form a masonry summer triclinium facing north. On the south side of the benches was a nymphaeum of three niches, a central semicircular one and a rectangular one to either side. At present, a water jet has been put in the middle of each of them. The final phase lasted about fifty years, beginning in the first half of the third century. The south garden was enlarged by the suppression of the east portico. The U-shaped channel pool lost its lateral arms, so that it became a simple rectangle (18 x 1.5 m) and it was made shallower. The apse, in practically the same place, was off-center to the west. The garden kept its summer triclinium and nympheum.
Plans   Fig. 1 Plan of House of the columns_phase1     Fig. 2 Plan of House of the columns_phase2     Fig. 3 Plan of House of the columns_phase2   Dates Bibliography   Maison 1996, t. II,, p. 309-401
  Guide Du Site Saint-Romain-En-Ga. Paris: Réunion des musées nationaux, 1999, P. 36-39.worldcat
  Gros, Pierre. L&amp;rsquo;architecture Romaine Du Début Du Iiie Siècle Av. J.-C. À La Fin Du Haut-Empire: 2 Maisons, Palais, Villas Et Tombeaux Paris: Picard, 2001, p. 189.worldcat
  Recherches Archéologiques a Saint-Romain-En-Gal (1988 - 1990). Vienne, 1992, P. 45-83.worldcat
  Bouet, Alain, and Isabel Figueiral. Les Thermes Privés Et Publics En Gaule Narbonnaise. Rome: École française de Rome, 2003, P. 271-275, fig. 194.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 5004109
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House with the Five Mosaics</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_with_the_five_mosaics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2020 23:06:02 -2400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_with_the_five_mosaics/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location saint-roman-en-gal
saint-roman-en-gal (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House with the Five Mosaics
House House with the Five Mosaics
Keywords  porticoes courtyards peristyles (Roman courtyards) opus signinum opus sectile (visual works) mosaics (visual works) triclinia  House Description Phase I: This phase is sometimes called the “House with the Off-Center Pool.” It occupied an area of 481 square meters with a usable covered surface of 213 square meters. Constructed after 138, it was built in part on the site and foundations of a commercial building going back to the middle of the first century. It was used only twenty to thirty years. It had an elongated, somewhat trapezoidal plan with two groups of rooms, one to the north and one to the south of a peristyle [5]. Most of the walls in short, east-west direction, were not perpendicular to the walls in the long, north-south direction. One entered the house by a modest doorway 1.8 meters wide into a little vestibule [1] which then led directly to the east portico of the courtyard, where presumably a garden grew. The principal room [7] (6.1 x 11.5 m) was on the south of the peristyle (8.5 x 11.5 m), where the gallery was wider and the roof presumably higher than on the other sides. This reception room had a good view of the rectangular pool along the south side of the garden. This 70-centimenter-deep pool (8.35 x 1.8 m) was lined in opus signinum.
Phase II: This phase (called the House of the Five Mosaics by those who call the first phase the House of the Off-center Pool), dates from the end of the second century, probably from 160 - 180. Although more luxurious than the first phase, it nevertheless kept the plan of the original. The covered area was enlarged to 293 square meters; but the garden, though reduced, remained central. The entrance [1] was shifted towards the south and got a more monumental gate 4.25 meter wide. In the southern wing, the main interior walls were rotated from their eastern end to be perpendicular to the north-south walls, with the result that the covered area was enlarged at the expense of the garden, which was reduced to 10-by-8 meters. It was bordered on the north and east by 1.5-meter-wide galleries, while the gallery to the south, though only 1.3 meters wide, had a floor of opus sectile. The east portico [2] became the only way to get from one of groups of rooms to the other. The garden received a U-shaped rill pool lined with white marble; the branches were of different length and less than a meter wide. The space left free at the end of the northern branch of the pool was the only access to the central part of the garden. In the two corners of the pool were found socles for some decorative elements, perhaps statues or fountains. Some parts of valves were found in the overflow from the pool. In the south wing, a large room [8] (7.5 x 7.0 m) opened onto the axis of the garden. With a mosaic of the xenia type, it apparently served as the triclinium. To the east, at the south end of the eastern gallery, was a smaller reception room for visitors [7] (4.0 x 4.5 m). The almost square (5 x 5 m) room [12] at the west end of the northern wing may have been, in the opinion of the excavators, a more familial, every-day triclinium. The house was occupied into the third century, but must have been abandoned, like the rest of the quarter, in the middle of that century.
Plans   Plan of house with five mosaics   Dates Bibliography   Lancha, Janine. Recueil General Des Mosaïques De La Gaule: Iii. Paris: CNRS, 1981, P. 259-286.worldcat
  Guides Archéologiques De La France. Saint-Romain-en-Gal: Conseil général du Rhône, Equipe archéologique de Saint-Romain-en-Gal, 1984, P. 57-58worldcat
  Lancha, Janine. Les Mosaïques De Vienne. Lyon: Presses universitaires de Lyon, 1990, P. 61-75.worldcat
  Recherches Archéologiques a Saint-Romain-En-Gal (1988 - 1990). Vienne, 1992, P. 86-132.worldcat
  Prisset, Jean-Luc, Laurence Brissaud, and Odile Leblanc. Evolution Urbaine À Saint-Romain En-Gal: La Rue Du Commerce Et La Maison Aux Cinq Mosaïques. Paris: CNRS éd, 1994, P. 1-133. worldcat
  Maison 1996, t. II,, p. 384-387
  Guide Du Site Saint-Romain-En-Ga. Paris: Réunion des musées nationaux, 1999, P. 64-69.worldcat
  Gros, Pierre. L&amp;rsquo;architecture Romaine Du Début Du Iiie Siècle Av. J.-C. À La Fin Du Haut-Empire: 2 Maisons, Palais, Villas Et Tombeaux Paris: Picard, 2001, p. 161-162.worldcat
  Bouet, Alain, and Isabel Figueiral. Les Thermes Privés Et Publics En Gaule Narbonnaise. Rome: École française de Rome, 2003, P. 269-271.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 5004109
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House with the Painted Portico</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_with_the_painted_portico/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2020 23:06:02 -2400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_with_the_painted_portico/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location saint-roman-en-gal
saint-roman-en-gal (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House with the Painted Portico
House House with the Painted Portico
Keywords  porticoes courtyards columns (architectural elements) apsed pools  House Description This house was destroyed to build the market and lies under it, but it is partly visible through glass plates in the floor. It was occupied approximately from 60 to 140. The lot covered 947 square meters and has two façade porticoes, one on the rue du Commerce and one on Voie III. The house was arranged around a central trapezoidal courtyard [1] (roughly 7,50 x 6,50 m) which may have been a garden. There were porticoes on only the north and east sides [2 and 3]. They had pounded earth floors; their black and green painted columns give the house its name. A one-meter wide channel pool ran around the north, east and south sides. Later, this pool was made shallower and its bottom covered with a concrete containing calcite crystals. A rectangular pool (5 x 2 m) with an axial apse of 1 meter closed the U-shaped channel pool on the west. A single cutting pot was found during the excavation.
Plans   Plan of house with the painted portico   Dates Bibliography   Maison 1996, t. II,, p. 392-393
  Guide Du Site Saint-Romain-En-Ga. Paris: Réunion des musées nationaux, 1999, P. 52-53.worldcat
  Recherches Archéologiques a Saint-Romain-En-Gal (1988 - 1990). Vienne, 1992, P. 45-83.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 5004109
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Sucellus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_sucellus/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 00:31:02 -0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_sucellus/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location saint-roman-en-gal
saint-roman-en-gal (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House of Sucellus
House House of Sucellus
Keywords  domus  House Description On leaving the House of the Lion from its northwest corner, following the rue du Rhône west for 35 meters and turning north on the rue des Thermes for 100 meters, one comes to the area now occupied by two structures, the House of Sucellus to the west and the Edifice with Pillars (Edifice aux piliers) to the east. Originally, the whole area was one house, called the House of the Fishpond (Maison au Vivier), which went through two phases. The space was then completely rearranged in a phase known as the House of the Large Gallery (Maison de la Grande Gallery), which was then transformed to its final state: the House of Sucellus to the west and the Edifice with Pillars to the east. The area was unearthed during a programmed excavation in 1990 and was found well preserved. The total surface area is about 2400 square meters.
Plans   Plan of House of Sucellus   Dates It was completely uncovered in 1987 so that its lines might be respected in the building above it, and then covered over to protect it during construction.
Bibliography   Maison 1996, t. II,, p. 406-411
  Gros, Pierre. L&amp;rsquo;architecture Romaine Du Début Du Iiie Siècle Av. J.-C. À La Fin Du Haut-Empire: 2 Maisons, Palais, Villas Et Tombeaux Paris: Picard, 2001, p. 189-190.worldcat
  Guide Du Site Saint-Romain-En-Ga. Paris: Réunion des musées nationaux, 1999, P. 30,33.worldcat
  Recherches Archéologiques a Saint-Romain-En-Gal (1988 - 1990). Vienne, 1992, P. 45-83.worldcat
  Bouet, Alain, and Isabel Figueiral. Les Thermes Privés Et Publics En Gaule Narbonnaise. Rome: École française de Rome, 2003, P. 271-275, fig.194.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 5004109
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Fishpond</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_the_fishpond/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 00:31:02 -0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_the_fishpond/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location saint-roman-en-gal
saint-roman-en-gal (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House of the Fishpond
Garden House of the Fishpond
Keywords  domus  Garden Description In the course of the second century, some two meters of fill was added to the garden to bring it up to the same level as the rest of the house. The use of the space was completely inverted. Rooms were built on the filled-in garden, and the former house was torn down to become a garden. This new house continued to occupy the whole insula. No plan is available for this house, but the new eastern part would be practically completely preserved in the next house. To the east now extended the new garden, which may possibly have preserved three branches of the channel-pool of the earlier house.
Plans   house of the fishpond   Dates Bibliography   Maison 1996, t. II,, p. 406-411
  Gros, Pierre. L&amp;rsquo;architecture Romaine Du Début Du Iiie Siècle Av. J.-C. À La Fin Du Haut-Empire: 2 Maisons, Palais, Villas Et Tombeaux Paris: Picard, 2001, p. 189-190.worldcat
  Guide Du Site Saint-Romain-En-Ga. Paris: Réunion des musées nationaux, 1999, P. 30,33.worldcat
  Recherches Archéologiques a Saint-Romain-En-Gal (1988 - 1990). Vienne, 1992, P. 45-83.worldcat
  Bouet, Alain, and Isabel Figueiral. Les Thermes Privés Et Publics En Gaule Narbonnaise. Rome: École française de Rome, 2003, P. 271-275, fig.194.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 5004109
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The House of the Lion</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/the_house_of_the_lion/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 00:06:02 -0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/the_house_of_the_lion/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location saint-roman-en-gal
saint-roman-en-gal (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation The House of the Lion
House The House of the Lion
Keywords  domus mosaics (visual works) courtyards peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes  House Description This house is today, as when it was built, only a few meters back from the right bank of the Rhone. It is now under the museum. It was completely uncovered in 1987 so that its lines might be respected in the building above it, and then covered over to protect it during construction. The museum sits above it on pilings so that at some future time the house can again be unearthed. It was built in the second century, covered a surface of more than 2500 square meters, and was occupied 100 to 150 years before being destroyed by the river. The name comes from a mosaic of a lion found in room [10] and now in the museum. The insula is separated into two parts by an east-west wall. It is difficult to determine whether the structures on either side are two halves of the same house or two different houses. However, the northern part was composed mainly of reception areas and lacked service rooms, so the assumption that it was somehow one house seems plausible.
Plans   Plan of the house of the lion   Dates It was completely uncovered in 1987 so that its lines might be respected in the building above it, and then covered over to protect it during construction.
Bibliography   Gros, Pierre. L&amp;rsquo;architecture Romaine Du Début Du Iiie Siècle Av. J.-C. À La Fin Du Haut-Empire: 2 Maisons, Palais, Villas Et Tombeaux Paris: Picard, 2001, p. 189-190.worldcat
  Recherches Archéologiques À Saint-Romain-En-Gal, 1988-1990. Vienne: Société des amis de Vienne, 1992, P.78,81.worldcat
  Bouet, Alain, and Isabel Figueiral. Les Thermes Privés Et Publics En Gaule Narbonnaise. Rome: École française de Rome, 2003, p.259-263, fig. 182-183.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 5004109
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>