<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_v/house_2/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2020 15:25:07 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_v/house_2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>I.v.2</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_v/house_2/i.v.2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2020 15:25:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_v/house_2/i.v.2/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula V
House House 2
Garden I.v.2
Keywords  archaeological garden kitchen gardens peristyles (columnades) pomerium  Garden Description B. The south half of the insula was also excavated in 1873-74. It was accessed from the back door in the peristyle garden of the tannery by descending six steps. This was a large open area (b) that had been cleared of previous structures. Formerly there had been five doors in the south wall leading to the pomerium but these were closed up. This area could have been used as a kitchen garden as suggested by Tatiana Warscher or for drying leather as suggested by Viola.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula v, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 8, p. 33; Viola, *Scavi*, pl. 1; Niccolini, *Case*, vol. 3, “*Topografia*,” pl. 10 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1873-1874
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Desc., p. 452. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 33. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), p. 275. Niccolini, Case, vol. 4, “Nuovi scavi, 1874-1882,” p. 2. Sogliano, GiorSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), cols. 10, 49, excavation finished in 1874. Viola, “Scavi” p. 15. Warscher, “Codex.&amp;rdquo;  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 03 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Officina Coriarioum of M. Vesonius Primus (I.v.2)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_v/house_2/officina_coriarioum_of_m._vesonius_primus/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 18:12:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_v/house_2/officina_coriarioum_of_m._vesonius_primus/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula V
House House 2
Garden Officina Coriarioum of M. Vesonius Primus (I.v.2)
Keywords  archaeological garden mosaics (visual works) opus signinum peristyles (Roman courtyards) pillars porticoes tables (support furniture) triclinia  Garden Description A. This tannery was excavated in 1873-1874. The peristyle courtyard had a portico to the north and east supported by brick pillars which had been most likely been built when the original house was converted to a tannery. Against the west wall there was a masonry triclinium (l.medius 4.99 m.; l.summus and l.imus 4.96 m.; table, 1.78 x 0.93 m.). The top of the triclinium table held the famous mosaic of a skull (0.45 x 0.50 m. Mus. Naz. inv. no. 109 982;; Reusch no. 163). The mosaic representing the Epicurian philosophy features a large skull over a butterfly on a wheel representing the soul and time. On either side of the skull are the possessions of both the rich and poor with a plumb line hanging over the skull indicating the equalizing power of death.The northeastern part of the courtyard was a rectangle, the north side of which was formed by the three first intercolumniations counting from the northeast corner of the north portico, and the east side by the first two intercolumniations counting from the same corner. This area was paved with opus signinum. The little area around the triclinium between the paved area and the west wall was believed to be a garden according to Mau.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula v, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 8, p. 33; Viola, *Scavi*, pl. 1; Niccolini, *Case*, vol. 3, “*Topografia*,” pl. 10 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1873-1874
Bibliography  Brendel, “Untersuchungen zur Allegorie des pompejanischen Totenkopfmosaiks,” RM (1934), pp 157-179. Fiorelli, Desc., p. 452. (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), col. 93. Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, fig. 268 on p. 181 and p. 198. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 33. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 272-275. Mau-Kelsey, pp. 398-399. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 48 (mosaic). Niccolini, Case, vol. 4, “Nuovi scavi, 1874-1882,” p. 1. Sogliano, GiorSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), cols. 9-10 and pl. 2. Soprano, p. 294, no. 3. Viola, “Scavi” p. 15. Warscher, “Codex,” photo no. 32.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 03 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>