<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>peristyles on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/peristyles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in peristyles on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 12:00:02 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/peristyles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Grotto of catullus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/sirmio/grotto_of_catullus/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/sirmio/grotto_of_catullus/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Sirmio
Sirmio (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region X
Garden House of Grotto of Aatullus
Keywords  insulae cryptoportici vestibules piscinae peristyles (columnades) porticoes bathhouses (water recreation structures) atriums ditches water supply systems water baths gutters (building drainage components) drains loam basins (vessels) statues cisterns (plumbing components) terrazzo water wells orchards presence chambers fences (site elements) exedrae (site elements) garden pavilions reception rooms terrazzo  Garden Description Sirmio is known from a citation in Catullus’ XXXI° poem (paene insularum, Sirmio, insularumque ocelle &amp;hellip;) and in later road itineraries as a staging post (Sermione mansio) along the road between Verona and Brixia (Brescia), which passed to the south of the peninsula, forming part of the erritory of Verona. In several areas along this ancient coastline remains have been brought to light of large and sumptuous villas built on the coast, in large coves or high places, with beautiful panoramas.The remains of a villa, called by fifteenth-century visitors to the site “Grotte di Catullo”, after Verona’s poet Catullus, are situated at the northern tip of the Sirmione peninsula, on the southern bank of the Benacus(Lake Garda), the largest of the pre-alpine lakes (Fig.1). As one of the most interesting examples of Roman residential architecture in northern Italy, this villa deserves the designation of villa maritima, as other similar examples along the Campanium-Latium coast.The villa covers an area of around 20,000 square meters distributed on three terraces, which ascend the slope of the hill on a series of substructures. The building has a rectangular plan (167.5 x 105 meters), with two foreparts; on the S side at the main entrance and on the N side at the tip of the peninsula, towards which the villa faced, so as to be surrounded by the lake on three sides (Fig. 2).On the evidence of recent studies, the villa is dated to the Augustan-Tiberian period (end of the first century B.C. –start of the first century A.D.): it was constructed after the destruction of an earlier building, the existence of which has been documented in a small archaeological excavation beneath the floor of one of the rooms on the southern side of the villa. Modifications to the building, in particular the creation of the large baths area, date to the end of the first –second century A.D. The destruction of the villa came quickly, with all probability around the 3rd century: at that time the functioning of the villa seems to have stopped and no later maintenance or building interventions have been identified; a differing situation as regards the other villas in the lake Garda area, which had a continued life, with phases of great importance, up to the first half of the fifth century.The building, constructed as a whole and with axial and symmetrical criteria, is characterized by long terraces on the eastern, western and northern sides: these connect directly with the large terrace on the northern forepart, which was shaded by a veiled covering, as demonstrated by the characteristic elements which supported the posts found in this area. By the side of the terraces were long porticoes: the western one built over a double-nave cryptoporticus, which acted as a substructure, the eastern for the main part built directly on the natural bedrock. The residential rooms were distributed in the northern and southern areas, the western part of the latter being occupied by the baths complex (Fig. 3-4).While the substructures are well-preserved, the residential floor, situated on the higher level, has been subject to greater destruction over the course of the centuries, due to the systematic robbing of building materials, already started in ancient times, the collapse of part of the wall on the eastern side along the hill-side, and in the agricultural use of the land, presently occupied by a vast olive grove (Fig. 5). The villa has been excavated on several occasions from the start of the 19th century and subsequently backfilled, so that the plan and hypotheses for the reconstruction for a large part of the residential level, which has not been the object of new research in recent years, are based on the notes and drawings of the 19th century, not always reliable. Other excavations were conducted between 1941 and 1965; research aimed at defining the chronology of the building and resolving problems in the plan of several rooms in the southern area were undertaken between 1984 and 1994.The events endured by the structure render difficult and at times impossible, at present, to hypothesize the functions and characteristics of many of the residential rooms, as also with the various open spaces present within the building. Undoubtedly, other than the large peristyle (C), which occupied the central area of the building, other open spaces, now buried (courtyards or gardens), were to be found along the central N-S axis. In the southern part there was an open space (N), situated between the western part of the villa, destined as the baths complex, and the eastern part containing the living rooms. In this case, according to the interpretation of the director of the first excavations and more recently, the area functioned as a courtyard giving access and light to the rooms on its E, S and W sides. A wall divided the courtyard from the S side of the peristyle, to which direct access was possible by one or more entrances. Another hypothesis suggests that access between the two courtyards was not axial but by a side corridor, while a wall with windows would have permitted a view of the internal garden.Of the other open space (O), situated to the N, there is uncertainty as to its function. One can hypothesize, on the basis of the 19th century plans, an open space with porticoes on all four sides: perhaps another small peristyle. An element which would confirm its use as a courtyard or garden is the presence of a stone-built rainwater drain, still present in the 19th century and illustrated by Orti Manara in his publication on Sirmione. Some parts of this drain have been re-used in the walls of the Early Medieval church of San Salvatore in Sirmione. There are no precise indications for external gardens and it is only possible to hypothesize the natural setting in which the villa was situated. However it must be stated that artificial terraces had been made on the eastern side of the building, or more precisely the areas which corresponded to the N-E and S-E corners, formed by the two foreparts of the villa. In the first (H) the bedrock has been cut to a depth of around 4 meters to create a large terrace, which occupied the whole area as far as the drop in level towards the lake (Fig.6). It is interesting that the second artificial terrace (I), of more limited extension, at around 10 meters below the residential level of the villa and reached by a flight of steps, was still known in the 19th century, by ancient tradition and without apparent justification, as “the garden.”The large central open space (C), beginning from the 19th century, was identified as a courtyard-viridarium. It is formed by an area of around 4000 square meters, equivalent to about one fifth of the whole area of the villa (Fig.7). Both the 19th century excavations and more recent trenches have failed to locate the presence of structures or floors, and it is therefore possible to hypothesize that the area functioned as a garden, probably surrounded on all four sides by porticoes as indicated in the 19th century plans and supported by recent research.The present land use, with many trees, and the thin soil cover in respect to the original ground surface, no longer permit the acquisition of data to allow a more precise reconstruction of the ancient garden, its internal sub-divisions, the types of vegetation, the possible ornamentation. On the S side of the peristyle is located a large perfectly preserved underground cistern (66), of a length corresponding to the width of the peristyle (42.60 x 2.40 meters). It is covered by a herringbone floor in small bricks, 6 meters wide and around 50 meters long (fig.8). Rainwater, collected in this part of the building, flowed into the cistern through a series of lead fistulae which entered the S-E and S-W corners, as is demonstrated by holes in the floor created by the robbing of the lead pipes, of which fortunately a small part is still preserved in the S-W corner, where it enters the cistern. The floor of the cistern has a slope of 7-8% from S to N: on the northern side four channels collected rain water and allowed it to flow in an organized manner towards the garden, with a slope of 6% (fig.9). The channel was formed in the initial part by a prolongation of the herringbone brick floor, which with its tapering form towards the external area helped the entry of rainwater into the channel, which flowed beneath the ancient ground surface (Fig. 10). The channels, lined with hydraulic mortar, were excavated in the bedrock, which outcropped on the eastern side and were covered with thin stone slabs. On the opposite side they were constructed in the earth and only their lower parts are preserved, the covering and the ancient floor shaving been robbed. Given the slope of the channels, their conformation and number, it is to be excluded that they had the sole function of draining the rainwater from the brick floor, and it may be hypothesized that they also served the function of directing to the garden the water which was extracted from the cistern, perhaps for irrigation.Water was drawn from the cistern by one or more wells: in the 19th century a well-curb, which was said to have come from the area of cistern, was still preserved in Sirmione. By the side of the cut which housed one of the well-curbs, two square holes had been cut into the floor in ancient times. It is hypothesized that they held the posts for the structure supporting the ropes and vessel used to extract water from the cistern (girgillus).There are no other elements to help describe the form of the large peristyle. Two pieces which may have formed part of the decoration of the garden are composed of sculptural fragments: a head dating to the second century A.D., found in the soil inside the cistern (66), and a sundial, presently lost, but fortunately represented by a drawing. Given the location, the head must have come from the peristyle, and can be hypothesized as belonging to the statue of a Dioscuros (fig. 11). In Greek marble, it is broken at the level of the chin. The head is covered by a pilos, from which issue locks of hair, curling on the forehead and sides of the face.There are no useful clues to help reconstruct the vegetation, which may have been present in and around the villa.The climate of Lake Garda is sub-Mediterranean, determined by the notably large mass of water which tends to maintain a constant temperature, much milder than the rest of the cisalpine area. The cultivation of olives already existed in Roman times, as documented by botanical evidence from recent excavations at Sirmione and the strong spread of the plant both in the locality and the whole area around Lake Garda in the Early Medieval period. In the same manner grapes were probably also cultivated, indirectly represented by an inscription found near Sirmione (fig. 12). Probably also common in the Roman period were the native species, shrubs such as oleander and rosemary and trees such as cypress, bay, ash and several species of oak, documented in the last two examples by botanic remains found at Sirmione, recently analyzed by the Archaeobiological Laboratory of the Civic Museums of Como.
Plans {&amp;lt; figure src=&amp;rdquo;../images/sirmio-2.png&amp;rdquo; alt=&amp;quot;Fig. 2: Plan of House of Grotto of Catullus.&amp;rdquo; title=&amp;quot;Fig. 2: Plan of House of Grotto of Catullus&amp;rdquo; &amp;gt;}}
  Fig. 3: Plan of the residential rooms     Fig. 5: Aerial view of vast olive grove     Fig. 7: Aerial view of courtyard-viridarium     Fig. 11: statue of a Dioscuros     Fig. 12: Figure of Plant fossils   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1801
Bibliography  G.G. Orti Manara, La penisola di Sirmione sul lago di Garda, Verona 1856.(worldcat) N. Degrassi, Le Grotte di Catullo, Taranto 1956. (worldcat) M. MirabellaRoberti, La villa romana di Sirmione, Milano 1958, pp.157-162.(worldcat) T.P.Wiseman, Le Grotte di Catullo. Una villa romana e i suoi proprietari, Brescia 1990. (worldcat) E. Roffia, Sirmione, le “grotte di Catullo”, in Ville romane sul lago di Garda, a cura di E.Roffia, Brescia 1997, pp.141-169. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 870993210
TGN ID 7005771
Contributor Tom Elliott (https://pleiades.stoa.org/author/thomase)
Publication date 15 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb garden of A. Coelius C. f.</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/patavium/tomb_garden_of_a.-coelius_c.-f./</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/patavium/tomb_garden_of_a.-coelius_c.-f./</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Patavium
Patavium (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region X
Garden Tomb garden of A. Coelius C. f.
Keywords  tombs epitaphs stelae mausoleums  Garden Description A broken marble slab immured in the cathedral at Padua since the seventeenth century records the epitaph of A. Coelius C. f., who some time in the first or second century dedicated to the divine spirits (Dis Manibus) and to himself in perpetuity a garden that had once, it seems, belonged to an Arius (hortum… Arianum). Whether it had always been a tomb garden or was only then being converted to a funerary use is uncertain.
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date unspecified
Bibliography  CIL 5.2935  Pleiades ID 393473
TGN ID 77003085
Contributor Brady Kiesling (https://pleiades.stoa.org/author/bkiesling)
Publication date 15 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb garden of A. Coelius C. f.</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/region_x/patavium/tomb_garden_of_a_coelius_c_f/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/region_x/patavium/tomb_garden_of_a_coelius_c_f/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Patavium
Patavium (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region X
Garden Tomb garden of A. Coelius C. f.
Keywords  tombs epitaphs stelae mausoleums  Garden Description A broken marble slab immured in the cathedral at Padua since the seventeenth century records the epitaph of A. Coelius C. f., who some time in the first or second century dedicated to the divine spirits (Dis Manibus) and to himself in perpetuity a garden that had once, it seems, belonged to an Arius (hortum… Arianum). Whether it had always been a tomb garden or was only then being converted to a funerary use is uncertain.
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date unspecified
Bibliography  CIL 5.2935  Pleiades ID 393473
TGN ID 77003085
Contributor Brady Kiesling (https://pleiades.stoa.org/author/bkiesling)
Publication date 15 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of L. Ogius Patroclus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/altinum/tomb_garden_of_l.-ogius_patroclus/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/altinum/tomb_garden_of_l.-ogius_patroclus/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location ALTINUM
ALTINUM (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region X
Garden Tomb Garden of L. Ogius Patroclus
Keywords  tombs epitaphs stelae grove (sacred grove) vegetable gardens  Garden Description A marble slab reported at Altinum in the sixteenth century and now in Venice records, above a depiction of an axe, a plumb-line, and a tree with birds, the epitaph of L. Ogius Patroclus, who some time (probably) in the late first or second century, “following the tradition of dutiful respect maintained by the corporation of firemen, donated while still living the gardens with building adjoining the tomb, so that from their revenue roses and food would be supplied generously for his patron and, eventually, for himself” (secutus pietatem col(legii) cent(onariorum) hortos cum aedificio huic sepult(urae) {a} iunctos vivos donavit, ut ex reditu eor(um) largius rosae et esce patrono suo et quandoque sibi ponerentur). The pairing of roses for the dead and food for the living (rosae et escae) was common in Roman funerary celebrations at the grave site, which perhaps suggests that mixed planting of flowers and vegetables was common in Roman tomb gardens as well (cf. ILS 6711, 8371).
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 16th century
Bibliography  CIL 5.2176 ILS 8369  Pleiades ID 197110
TGN ID 4000603
Contributor Sean Gillies (https://pleiades.stoa.org/author/sgillies)
Publication date 15 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb garden of T. Vettius Hermes</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ix/vardagate/tomb_garden_of_t.-vettius_hermes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ix/vardagate/tomb_garden_of_t.-vettius_hermes/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Vardagate
Vardagate (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region IX
Garden Tomb garden of T. Vettius Hermes
Keywords  tombs epitaphs stelae  Garden Description A marble stele now in a church at Grazzano records the epitaph of T. Vettius Hermes, a freedman ointment dealer (seplasiarius). After a gnomic sentiment about chthonic birthand reunion (mater genuit materq(ue) recepiit), Hermes goes on to declare that “these gardens, as great and excellent as they are, (will) serve my ashes, for I shall appoint caretakers to dine on the proceeds from them on my birthday and on the day of roses, in perpetuity” (hi horti ita uti o(ptimi) m(aximi)/que sunt cineribus seruite(!) meis nam curatores substituam uti uescantur ex horum hortorum reditu natale meo et per rosam in perpetuo).
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date unspecified
Bibliography  CIL5.7454, cf. p. 7454 ILS8342  Pleiades ID 383809
TGN ID unspecified
Contributor Sean Gillies (https://pleiades.stoa.org/author/sgillies)
Publication date 15 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa at Pola&#34;</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/barbariga/villa_at_pola/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/barbariga/villa_at_pola/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location BARBARIGA
BARBARIGA (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region X
Garden Villa at Pola
Keywords  mosaics (visual works) cryptoportici gutters (building drainage components) podiums (building divisions) peristyles (columnades) porticoes tesserae villae urbanae reception rooms atrium houses mural paintings (visual works) presence chambers  Garden Description This large maritime villa consisted of two parts, labeled “summer villa” and “winter villa”. The “summer” quarters unfold around a U-shaped peristyle, open on the sea-side, with central garden measuring 31.8 x 26.2 m. (fig. 2: 4). No traces of a pool or fountain were found in the center of the garden. The portico, 2.40 m wide, had a mosaic floor in black tesserae with a white border. Many rooms looked into the peristyle, with the main one probably being a triclinium (Fig. 1). On the two opposite corners of this side of the courtyard were also service rooms: Room 6 was the kitchen, 15 maybe a storeroom (many amphorae were recovered, but the room had a mosaic floor). Of the rooms around the peristyle, Room 31 was the most lavishly decorated. The back wall presented a semicircular niche with a statue-base, the floor had an elaborate polychrome mosaic, and the walls were covered with marble slabs. South of the “summer villa” was a long cryptoportico, flanking a garden, no longer preserved, but known from nineteenth century archival documents. The villa was built in the first century A.D. and, at least in part, was used down to the sixth century A.D.
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1801
Bibliography  M. De Franceschini, 1998, Le ville romane della X regio: Venetia et Histria. Catalogo e carta archeologica dell’insediamento romano nel territorio, dall’età repubblicana al tardo impero, Roma.(worldcat)  Pleiades ID 870993210
TGN ID 7005771
Contributor Tom Elliott (https://pleiades.stoa.org/author/thomase)
Publication date 15 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa of the Bath</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/tergeste/villa_of_the_bath/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/tergeste/villa_of_the_bath/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Tergeste
Tergeste (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region X
Garden Villa of the Bath
Keywords  archaeological garden cisterns (plumbing components) gutters (building drainage components) villae urbanae peristyles (columnades) porticoes bathhouses (water recreation structures) water baths courtyards atrium houses corridors  Garden Description Remains discovered in 1888 revealed a large semicircular garden (Fig. 1: c) enclosed by a portico (b), into which opened a series of rooms (d to p). A corridor (a) connected this garden to a bath quarter that boasted a nymphaeum (t) and a panoramic view onto the sea. A similar semicircular portico and garden was in the villa of Anguillara Sabatia, but the radial disposition of the rooms of the ‘Villa della Terma’s’ pars urbana is unusual, revealing a desire to lend each room a view onto the garden. The preservation of this villa is poor because for centuries it was scavenged for building material. Dated material ranges from the first century B.C. (brick stamps) to the early fifth century A.D. (coins). It is possible that these remains were part of the nearby “Villa della Statua.”
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1888
Bibliography  M. De Franceschini, 1998, Le ville romane della X regio: Venetia et Histria. Catalogo e carta archeologica dell’insediamento romano nel territorio, dall’età repubblicana al tardo impero, Roma.(worldcat)  Pleiades ID 187578
TGN ID 7005539
Contributor Brady Kiesling
Publication date 15 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa of the Statue (I.iii.23)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/tergeste/villa_of_the_statue/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/tergeste/villa_of_the_statue/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Tergeste
Tergeste (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region X
Garden Villa of the Statue
Keywords  archaeological garden cisterns (plumbing components) gutters (building drainage components) mural paintings (visual works) peristyles (columnades) porticoes mosaic pergolas bathhouses (water recreation structures) water baths atrium houses atriums nymphaea (garden structures) tesserae ceramic tile opus sectile (visual works) opus signinum garden pavilions [apsed triclinium] [archaeological garden]  Garden Description A villa dating from the first century B.C. to at least the time of Marcus Aurelius was discovered near the modern via Miramare in Barcola. It overlooked the sea to the west and had a portico at the south (Fig. 1: B), with rooms opening onto it. The main nucleus of the villa unfolded around a rectangular garden surrounded by porticoes on all four sides (the long sides measure 24.5 m.; the short ones 15.2; Fig. 1: U). A rectangular brick pool with a black mosaic pavement was in the north-east portion of the garden (Fig. 1: a). It pre-dates the portico, since it was partly destroyed by the paving of the north-east portico. A terminus post quem for the construction of the portico was determined by a coin of Nero, found inside the pool.
During nineteenth century excavations, fragments of two superimposed wall paintings were recovered in Room C. The outer layer is not well enough preserved to identify any subject, but the preserved fragments beneath show branches and leaves with colored backgrounds of light blue, red, yellow and white. It is, therefore, possible that this cycle of painting depicted a garden, echoing the view of the real plantings visible through the doorway.
North of the peristyle was the bath quarter (Fig. 1: G, H, I, M, P), but it is not completely clear how the two parts of the villa were connected. In a partially excavated Tuscan type atrium (G) with an impluvium, several fragments of a marble torso were recovered, possible from a copy of the Polykleitan Doryphoros or Diadumenos. On the west side of the villa facing the sea was a porticoed garden (Z) and large semicircular exedra (24 m in diameter). Under the mosaic floor of this exedra are traces of an earlier room (Fig. 1: a) with a mosaic floor. On axis with the center of the exedra and garden was a triclinium (6.2 x 12 m) with a black-and-white mosaic floor. Another exedra (7.5 x 15 m), with a black-and-white mosaic floor, had large windows looking to the sea, and beside it a staircase leading to the water’s edge and to a dock.
Dates 100 B.C.
Excavation Date 19th century
Bibliography  M. De Franceschini, 1998, Le ville romane della X regio: Venetia et Histria. Catalogo e carta archeologica dell’insediamento romano nel territorio, dall’età repubblicana al tardo impero, Roma.(worldcat)  Pleiades ID 187578
TGN ID 7005539
Contributor Brady Kiesling
Publication date 15 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>II.ix.6.B</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_ix/ii.ix.6b/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_ix/ii.ix.6b/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region II
Insula Insula IX
Keywords  peristyles porticoes pilasters puteals lararia opus signinum doliums  Garden Description B. This vineyard section of the property was excavated in 1984 by Dr. De Caro. A small peristyle garden (b) was enclosed on the east and south by a three column portico with a pilaster on the southwest corner. A low wall joined the pilaster and the west column on the south side with a terra-cotta puteal incorporated into it. The north and east sides of the garden had a gutter. The south part of this vineyard had a small house with a garden painting on the west wall. The excavators found the painting to be badly damaged but a section showing a lattice fence 0.68 m. high with leaves and flowers behind remained on the right two-thirds of the building. All of the painting above the fence had been lost. A huge lararium was built against the north portion of the wall which partially covered the image of a Frejus type statuette of Venus 0.87 m. high. An entrance from the east portico¬ led directly to the vineyard which had been in production at the time of the eruption. At the front of the house on the west end a treading floor for the grapes had been built. The floor was raised, enclosed by a low wall 18 cm. high, and paved with opus signinum. The juice would run into a pair of dolium buried in the soil at the east edge of the floor. Fig. 81, 16.11.70, Fig. 82, 7.14.71; Fig. 83, 7.16.71; Fig. 84, 7.28.71; Fig. 85, 9.25.71, Fig. 86, 9.26.71, Fig. 87, 49.10.64, Fig. 88, 54.20.64.
Plans   Fig. 75, Plan of Region II, insula ix   Images   Fig. 81, 16.11.70 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 82, 7.14.71 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 83, 7.16.71 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 84, 7.28.71 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 85, 9.25.71 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 86, 9.26.71 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 87, 49.10.64 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 88, 54.20.64. (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)   Pleiades ID 456321707
TGN ID 7004658
Excavation Dates 1984
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, pp. 97-98, 333 (worldcat)  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 10 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb garden of T. Vettius Hermes (I.iii.23)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_xi/vardagate/tomb_garden_of_t.-vettius_hermes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_xi/vardagate/tomb_garden_of_t.-vettius_hermes/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Vardagate
Vardagate (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region IX
Garden Tomb garden of T. Vettius Hermes
Keywords  tombs epitaphs stelae  Garden Description A marble stele now in a church at Grazzano records the epitaph of T. Vettius Hermes, a freedman ointment dealer (seplasiarius). After a gnomic sentiment about chthonic birthand reunion (mater genuit materq(ue) recepiit), Hermes goes on to declare that “these gardens, as great and excellent as they are, (will) serve my ashes, for I shall appoint caretakers to dine on the proceeds from them on my birthday and on the day of roses, in perpetuity” (hi horti ita uti o(ptimi) m(aximi)/que sunt cineribus seruite(!) meis nam curatores substituam uti uescantur ex horum hortorum reditu natale meo et per rosam in perpetuo).
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date unspecified
Bibliography  CIL5.7454, cf. p. 7454 ILS8342  Pleiades ID 383809
TGN ID unspecified
Contributor Sean Gillies (https://pleiades.stoa.org/author/sgillies)
Publication date 25 Oct 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Funerary Grove of Q. Cervonius Chryseros</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/aquileia/funerary_grove_of_q.-cervonius_chryseros/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/aquileia/funerary_grove_of_q.-cervonius_chryseros/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Aquileia
Aquileia (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region X
Garden Funerary Grove of Q. Cervonius Chryseros
Keywords  tombs stelae grove (sacred grove) altars (religious fixtures)  Garden Description A small inscribed altar of (probably) the Julio-Claudian era found by Mommsen among the stones of Aquileia and now lost records on its left and right sides dedications to Dis Pater and (H)era respectively and, on its front, the name of the dedicant, a consul’s aide (acc(ensus) co(n)s(ularis)) and local sevir at Florentia, Q. Cervonius Chryseros, who built “the grove, the enclosure wall, the altars, the mound (? molem), and the seats” (lucum, maceriem, aras, molem, [s]edilia). The dedication to Dis Pater suggests a funerary context, which leads Chioffi to identify the molis as a tomb monument of some ill-defined type (perhaps an irregular mound?). A Roman soldier serving in lower Germany at Carvium (Herwen) was buried by his two heirs ad molem, “near (or at) the mound” (AE 1939, 130). The same Chryseros perhaps appears as the owner of a slave, Fausta, who in fulfillment of a vow dedicated another monument to Dis Pater at Aquileia (CIL 5.35*).
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date unspecified
Bibliography  G. B. Brusin, Inscriptiones Aquileiae, Udine 1991-1993, no. 192.(worldcat) S. Panciera, Libitina e dintorni : Libitina e i luci sepolcrali, Rome 2004, nn. 17-31. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 187290
TGN ID 7005553
Contributor Sean Gillies (https://pleiades.stoa.org/author/sgillies)
Publication date 15 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>562.Insula or. I.2-3(B)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/insula_or._i/house_2-3/insula_or._i.2-3_b/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/insula_or._i/house_2-3/insula_or._i.2-3_b/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Insula Insula Orientalis I
House House 2-3
Garden B
Keywords  atrium peristyles stuccoing  Garden Description B. From the atrium the peristyle on the lower level was reached by way of a steeply sloping corridor. Stuccoed brick columns and a low wall 0.50 m. high enclosed the central area (b) and a large gutter collected water from the edges and conducted it to the cistern. A rectangular pool ca. 2.60 x 5.00 m. with the inside painted blue was located in the center of this area. At the rear of the pool an area paved with bipedales (tiles two feet long) covered the cellars below with an opening 1.70 x 2.20 to provide light. Jashemski noted that the paved and planted areas were reconstructed with a lattice fence between them, although she did not know of any evidence to support this interpretation.
Plans   Plan of the new excavations of Herculaneum (Maiuri, Herculaneum)     Herculaneum - insula orientalis I. 1-3-b   Images   Herculaneum - insula orientalis I. 2.3-2 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Maiuri, Herculaneum, pp.66-67 (worldcat) Maiuri, Ercolano, p. 353 (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, 1:50-51 and fig. 89 on p. 51 (worldcat)  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 20 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>563.Insula or. I.2-3(C)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/insula_or._i/house_2-3/insula_or._i.2-3_c/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/insula_or._i/house_2-3/insula_or._i.2-3_c/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Insula Insula Orientalis I
House House 2-3
Garden C
Keywords  peristyles  Garden Description C. There are five rooms south of the peristyle and on a lower level beyond them is another garden (c).
Plans   Plan of the new excavations of Herculaneum (Maiuri, Herculaneum)     Herculaneum - insula orientalis I. 1-3-c   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Maiuri, Ercolano, p. 353 (worldcat)  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 20 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Insula or. II</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/insula_or._ii/insula_or._ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/insula_or._ii/insula_or._ii/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Insula Insula Orientalis II
Garden Garden (a)
Keywords  peristyles porticos  Garden Description Directly south of the Great Palaestra there is a peristyle garden (a) enclosed by a portico. A pool with a low wall surrounding it is located in the center of this garden.
Plans   Plan of the new excavations of Herculaneum (Maiuri, Herculaneum)     Herculaneum - Garden (a) south of the Great Palaestra   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography Not applicable
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 20 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa D’Argo</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/tiffany_fong/casa_dargo/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/tiffany_fong/casa_dargo/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Garden Casa D’Argo
##Jashemski Catalogue 533.II.2. 534.II.2.
Keywords  cisterns (plumbing components) triclinium peristyles porticoes gutters (building drainage components)  Garden Description 533.II.2. A. The earliest excavations of Herculaneum were done with underground tunnels. Several of these crossed this site and were discovered sixty three years later when further excavation of this patrician house was conducted in1828-1835. Eight brick columns and one engaged column stood on each of the long sides of the portico that bounded the large peristyle garden (a) on the east, north, and west sides. The north side was supported by four more columns and at the two front corners there was a pillar with an engaged column on each side. In the center of the north side two smaller pillars with one engaged column each framed a garden view from the triclinium. All the supporting members were coated with fine stucco. Gutters ringing the garden conveyed rain water to the cistern.
534.II.2. B. A second peristyle garden was located to the west of the first, but has only been partially excavated. It has stuccoed columns and pillars joined by a wall 0.4 m. high painted with plants and flowers.
Plans   Casa D’Argo   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1828-1835
Bibliography  A.C. BdI (1835),p. 130 (worldcat) Bonucci, BdI (1830), p.121 (worldcat) Bonucci, Le due Sicilie: Ercolano, fig. 11 (plan) and p. 37 (worldcat) Breton,Pompeia p. 519 (worldcat) Maiuri, Herculaneum, p. 24 (worldcat) Idem,Ercolano, pp. 367-368 and fig. 293 (plan) on p. 362 (worldcat) Niccolini,Real museo borbonico, vol. 7, fig. 59 (plan), description by Bechi, pp. 19-21 (worldcat)     Ruggiero, Ercolano, pp. 541-545 (contains the detailed reports of Bonucci)(worldcat)     -      Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa D’Argo</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tiffany_fong/casa_dargo/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tiffany_fong/casa_dargo/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Insula II
House 2
Garden Casa D’Argo
Keywords  cisterns (plumbing components) triclinium peristyles porticoes gutters (building drainage components)  Garden Description 533.II.2. A. The earliest excavations of Herculaneum were done with underground tunnels. Several of these crossed this site and were discovered sixty three years later when further excavation of this patrician house was conducted in1828-1835. Eight brick columns and one engaged column stood on each of the long sides of the portico that bounded the large peristyle garden (a) on the east, north, and west sides. The north side was supported by four more columns and at the two front corners there was a pillar with an engaged column on each side. In the center of the north side two smaller pillars with one engaged column each framed a garden view from the triclinium. All the supporting members were coated with fine stucco. Gutters ringing the garden conveyed rain water to the cistern.
534.II.2. B. A second peristyle garden was located to the west of the first, but has only been partially excavated. It has stuccoed columns and pillars joined by a wall 0.4 m. high painted with plants and flowers.
Plans   Plan of Casa D’Argo   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1828-1835
Bibliography -BdI (1835),p. 130 (worldcat) -BdI (1830), p.121 (worldcat)
 Bonucci, Le due Sicilie: Ercolano, fig. 11 (plan) and p. 37 (worldcat) Breton,Pompeia p. 519 (worldcat) Maiuri, Herculaneum, p. 24 (worldcat) Maiuri,Ercolano, pp. 367-368 and fig. 293 (plan) on p. 362 (worldcat) Niccolini,Real museo borbonico, vol. 7, fig. 59 (plan), description by Bechi, pp. 19-21 (worldcat)     Ruggiero, Ercolano, pp. 541-545 (contains the detailed reports of Bonucci)(worldcat)     -      Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Eisenstadt</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/eisenstadt/eisenstadt_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 09:31:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/eisenstadt/eisenstadt_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Pannonia
Location Eisenstadt
Eisenstadt (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Eisenstadt
Keywords  altars (religious fixtures) archaeological garden atriums peristyles (Roman courtyards) podiums (building divisions) porticoes villae rusticae  Garden Description The residence of this villa rustica was entered on the southeast by a portico (Fig. 1). After passing through a room interpreted as the atrium, one arrived in the open courtyard which had a peristyle on three sides (G on plan). On the northern edge of the courtyard was a podium (P on plan) near which votive altars to Diana and Silvanus were found, both gods of the woods and suitable subjects for a garden. This corner of the courtyard, thus, seems to have had religious character. In the middle of the courtyard was a square foundation, measuring 1.80 x 1.80 m., possibly the remains of a base for some kind of figure. The villa rustica was established in the early 2nd century and occupied probably until the 4th century.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the rural villa with a peristyle courtyard (G) and a podium (P) for sculpture. Adapted from Thomas 1964, fig. 73. (Rights statement.)   Dates Early 2nd century - 4th century
Bibliography  E.B. Thomas, Römische Villen in Pannonien, Budapest, 1964, pp. 137-151, fig. 73. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 197425
TGN ID 7003056
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban House or Schola in Aquincum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/aquincum/aquincum_urban_house_or_schola/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jul 2020 16:44:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/aquincum/aquincum_urban_house_or_schola/</guid>
      <description>Province Pannonia
Province Description Location Aquincum
Aquincum (Pleiades)
Location Description This town on the Danube river acquired the rank of municipium under Hadrian in 124 A.D. In the year 194 it was granted colonial status.
Garden Urban House or Schola in Aquincum
Keywords  archaeological garden bathhouses (water recreation structures) fountains peristyles (Roman courtyards) piscinae statues statuettes (free-standing sculpture)  Garden Description Very few houses of Mediterranean type have been discovered, and only one can be said with certainty to have had a garden (Fig. 1, G in Fig. 1). The peristyle courtyard was a prominent feature of this house of irregular plan and substantial size near the southern city wall. The house dates to the 3rd century, and it is thought to have been a clubhouse or schola for young men (collegium iuventutis), complete with a bath suite. In the middle of the courtyard, framed on four sides by a low wall supporting columns, was a square masonry pool (Fig. 2). In the center of the pool was a fountain consisting of a small marble satyr standing on a column of the same material. This decorative element and the unpaved ground strongly suggest the existence of a garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of a building with a peristyle garden courtyard (G) and a pool in its center. Adapted from Polenz and Póczy 1986, fig. 47.(Rights statement.)   Images   Fig. 2: The excavated courtyard building with its peristyle garden. Photo courtesy of M. Carroll.)   Dates 3rd century
Bibliography  A. Mócsy, Pannonia and Upper Moesia. A History of the Middle Danube Provinces of the Roman Empire, London, 1974, p. 166, pl. 16b. (worldcat) H. Polenz and K. Póczy, Das römische Budapest. Neue Ausgrabungen und Funde in Aquincum, Münster, 1986, p. 124, fig. 47, pl. 10. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 1971301
TGN ID 8713146
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Structures under the Collège Lumière in Vesontio</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vesontio/vesontio_structures_under_the_colle%CC%80ge_lumie%CC%80re/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 09:48:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vesontio/vesontio_structures_under_the_colle%CC%80ge_lumie%CC%80re/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Vesontio
Vesontio (Pleiades)
Location Description The defensibility offered by this unique geography made Caesar hasten to occupy Vesontio in 58 BC. The town came to have all the usual Roman structures– forum, baths, aqueduct, and amphitheater (on the other side of the Doubs, to the northwest.) But the most visible remnant is the Porte Noire (Black Gate) [3], a triumphal arch built by Marcus Aurelius at the southeastern end of the cardo maximus, today Grande Rue and still the center of city life.
Archaeology in a downtown area is always a matter of seizing opportunities as they are presented by new construction, remembering and recording what was found, and coming back years later to complete the picture. A good example of this process is at our second site, [2] on the map. In 1973, the Neptune Mosaic was discovered in rue de Lorraine, one of the largest floor decorations in all Gaul. The extent of the mosaic under nearby buildings made full excavation impossible. More than thirty years later, in 2004, construction of a gymnasium for the Collège Lumière (a middle school) gave archaeologists access to much more of the site, about 3000 square meters, for a salvage excavation. As expected, the continuation of the Neptune mosaic was found; moreover, three other mosaics of high quality, along with columns, sculpted blocks, peristyles, and monumental pools came to light. The results of this excavation have not been published; we are grateful to the excavators for sharing their preliminary results.
Garden Structures under the Collège Lumière in Vesontio
Keywords  colonnades kraters mosaics (visual works) opus signinum peristyles (Roman courtyards) piscinae porticoes reception rooms rinceaux terrazzo  Garden Description The results of the 2004 excavation at the Collège Lumière are still under study and the data are therefore still partial. This zone, close to the river and the artisinal quarter has, in the past, yielded most of the mosaics recorded for Besançon. The ancient structures discovered on 3000 square meters relate to a Gallo-Roman urbanization extending from the Augustan period to the third century and superimposed on a rather dense Gallic occupation of the first century BC. Two phases of construction from the late Augustan period up through the end of the first century, have thus far not permitted the confirmation of the possible presence of a garden. On the other, later constructions dating from the beginning and last third of the second century are rich in peristyles with open space suitable for a garden.
At the beginning of the second century, in a third phase, a structure of large dimension (at least 2500 m2) but undetermined purpose was built on fill and leveling of the abandoned earlier buildings. It will simplify descriptions to let “north” denote the direction that is actually northeast, the direction towards the river. In these terms, large rooms (the largest reaching 126 sq. m.) and corridors were bordered on the south by an open area, possibly a garden, with porticos on at least the north and west sides, and by one peristyle to the west and by another to the east. The walls of the porticos around these peristyles were decorated with painted plaster. The west peristyle (at least 22 x 20 m) is the most complete. Only one wall, the east wall of the west peristyle, is common to these second century structures and the preceding ones of first century. It may thus represent a property line. Originally, it opened over a large threshold between the largest of the rooms and the western peristyle. It was subsequently first reduced and then completely closed.
The fourth phase, a remodeling at the end of the second century, is the best preserved, but its purpose remains unclear. It has yielded a series of elements that allow us to follow the architectural reasoning of the builders. It kept the basic plan of the third state: a peristyle to the east, one to the west, and a large garden to the south. The rooms, however, are considerably rearranged. Three grand reception rooms (of 200, 85, and 65 m2 ) with floors decorated with luxurious mosaics are organized in a very regular fashion in relation to the two peristyles and garden by corridors or galleries. The floors of these numerous spaces of circulation were a terrazzo in an opus signinum matrix, except for the gallery of garden, which had a mosaic.
The largest of the rooms, decorated by the Neptune mosaic, opened on its north side through a colonnade onto the south of the east peristyle and through another colonnade on the opposite side to the garden on the south. The spacing of the columns was the same (4.6 m) on both colonnades. The excavated part of the east peristyle showed that it was 22.3 meters wide; if it was square, it would have had an area of about 500 square meters. Another large room decorated with the rinceaux mosaic (so called for the bands of scrolled foliage) also opens onto the east peristyle. The gallery that borders the garden was widened into the garden in front of the Neptune room; against the wall of this extension there was a pool at least 1.5 meters wide and probably about 13 meters long. Several paving stones of the bottom have survived. The last room, the one with the Medusa mosaic, would seem to have opened onto the garden. The garden was about .95 meters lower than the house and was reached by descending four steps. The north portico of the west peristyle was enlarged in this final phase; the interval between columns reached 6.7 meters. The presence of the closed wall that may have been a property line obliges us to ask Did this west peristyle really belong to the structure to the east or was it part of a different edifice that may have extended to the west outside the limits of the excavation?
A fragment of a little ornamental stone krater was found in the material that filled the east peristyle after its abandonment. From late antiquity is the foundation of a pool or cistern of about 3.5 by 2.5 meters. Its stones have been removed, and only the opus signinum mortar bearing the imprint of the stones has been found. This structure pierced through all the archaeological levels and into the natural earth.
Plans Images not available (?)  Fig. 1: Plan of the domus, now under the Collège Lumière.  Dates Gardens: Beginning and last third of second century
Excavation Dates 2004
Bibliography  C. Gaston and C. Munier “Une luxueuse domus de la find du IIe siècle à Besançon, college Lumière (Doubs, F)&amp;rdquo;&amp;rdquo; in Premières Journées archéologiques frontalières de l&amp;rsquo;Arc jurassien: Mandeure, sa campagne et ses relations d&amp;rsquo;Avenches à Luxeuil et d&amp;rsquo;Augst à Besançon. Ed, Cécile Bélet-Gonda, Presses Univ. Franche-Comté (2007), 103-112.  Pleiades ID 177657
TGN ID 7008356
Contributor Claudine Monier (ORCID: N/A)
Christophe Gaston (ORCID: https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6865-5108)
Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 20 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House in the Rue du Palais de Justice in Vesontio</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vesontio/vesontio_house_in_the_rue_du_palais_de_justice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2020 16:58:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vesontio/vesontio_house_in_the_rue_du_palais_de_justice/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Vesontio
Vesontio (Pleiades)
Location Description The defensibility offered by this unique geography made Caesar hasten to occupy Vesontio in 58 BC. The town came to have all the usual Roman structures– forum, baths, aqueduct, and amphitheater (on the other side of the Doubs, to the northwest.) But the most visible remnant is the Porte Noire (Black Gate) [3], a triumphal arch built by Marcus Aurelius at the southeastern end of the cardo maximus, today Grande Rue and still the center of city life.
Archaeology in a downtown area is always a matter of seizing opportunities as they are presented by new construction, remembering and recording what was found, and coming back years later to complete the picture. A good example of this process is at our second site, [2] on the map. In 1973, the Neptune Mosaic was discovered in rue de Lorraine, one of the largest floor decorations in all Gaul. The extent of the mosaic under nearby buildings made full excavation impossible. More than thirty years later, in 2004, construction of a gymnasium for the Collège Lumière (a middle school) gave archaeologists access to much more of the site, about 3000 square meters, for a salvage excavation. As expected, the continuation of the Neptune mosaic was found; moreover, three other mosaics of high quality, along with columns, sculpted blocks, peristyles, and monumental pools came to light. The results of this excavation have not been published; we are grateful to the excavators for sharing their preliminary results.
Garden House in the Rue du Palais de Justice in Vesontio
Keywords archaeological garden \
 domus fountains hypocausts mosaics (visual works) opus sectile (visual works) opus signinum oeci peristyles (columnades) piscinae porticoes terrazzo water wells  Garden Description In 2000-2001, at the time of construction a new judiciary facility, an area of 2000 square meters was excavated at the center of this loop. The results are in large part unpublished. On land that had been occupied since the end of the second century BC, two houses of perishable materials were built in the eastern part of the site in the beginning of the first century AD. They were abandoned at the beginning of the Flavian epoch, and replaced by two imposing domus that lasted up to the middle of the third century. They stood on opposite sides of a property line wall (tinted in purple in Fig. 1) that was parallel to a cardo running in a northwest-to-southeast direction some hundred meters away. The two houses had slightly different orientations. The eastern house doubtless opened onto a southwest-northeast street passing 50 meters beyond the eastern limit of the excavation but partially brought to light in 1989-90 during excavations when a new parking facility was being built for the city hall. In this house, two independent structures (oecus) (tinted pink in the figure) with floors once decorated with mosaics since disappeared are wrapped about and connected by a portico (yellow tint) of complex plan with galleries 3 meters wide and opening onto an open space (green tint) covering 110 square meters. The counterpart of this portico is in part visible on the other side of the larger room. An incompletely known peristyle borders this oecus to the east (on the lower right edge of the plan). Its gallery was decorated with a terrazzo floor of opus signinum with accents of crustae, thin stone slices of which an opus sectile is made. In this phase, the north domus had a peristyle of 75 square meters with galleries on three sides. To the west (lower left corner of the plan), there was a large open space of nearly 500 square meters, which may have been a garden. At its west end, the wall of an incomplete building ran by a well and a masonry square 2.16 meters on a side which may have been the base of a shrine or monument. These structures were aligned with the property line wall. There was as yet no pool.
In the second half of the second century, the “garden” was restructured. The building on the west side was abandoned, the shrine or monument was kept, and a large pool put in at the eastern end supported against the wall of a terrace supporting the house to the east and consequently having the same orientation. This rectangular pool (21.2 x 3.5 m) had on the garden side a semicircular apse 6.9 meters in diameter. As part of the same architectural ensemble, a portico formed the retro-scene of the pool. Its opus signinum floor was 80 centimeters above the surface of the pool. Another, wider portico ran along the north side of the area. A shim-shaped gap existed between it and the property-line wall because of the difference in orientation. The monumental character of the pool and the north portico suggests that this garden may have been independent of both houses and was possibly a public space or belonged to a house further west, outside the limits of excavation.
At the beginning of the third century, the two domus were transformed. In particular, polychrome mosaics were installed in the east house and rooms with hypocausts in the north house. The little shrine or monument at the western end of the garden was eliminated, but the pool was reconstructed without alteration. The paving stones that had been in a pool were in part removed and used to build a 3.8 x 2.9 meter platform which served as the base, presumably, of a quadrangular fountain in the north house in an open space which replaced the peristyle, which was then destroyed.
Images Images not available (?) FIGURES:
 Fig. 1: Houses at the Palais de Justice Fig. 2: Axonometric representation  Dates Beginning of the Flavian epoch - middle of the third century
Excavation Dates 2000-2001
Bibliography  C. Gaston, “Un bassin monumental et une fontaine dans les fouille du Palais de Justice de Besancon,” Revue Archéologique de l&amp;rsquo;Est, t. 52, 2003, p.417-428. Christophe Gaston: “Données récentes sur l&amp;rsquo;achitecture antique à Besançon,” Archéopages/Inrap. No. 8, Nov. 2002, p. 28-35. Laurent Vaxelaire, Philippe Barral, “Besançon: de l’oppidum à la ville romaine” in La naissance de la ville dans l’Antiquité, M. Reddé et al. ed., Paris, 2003, p. 254-256.  Pleiades ID 177657
TGN ID 7008356
Contributor Claudine Monier (ORCID: N/A)
Christophe Gaston (ORCID: https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6865-5108)
Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 19 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Bad Kreuznach</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/bad_kreuznach/bad_kreuznach_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 12:39:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/bad_kreuznach/bad_kreuznach_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Bad Kreuznach
Bad Kreuznach (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Bad Kreuznach
Keywords  apsed triclinium colonnades cryptoportici fountains gutters (building drainage components) lararia mosaics (visual works) peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes villae rusticae  Garden Description This villa, almost 6000 square meters in size, gives eloquent testimony to the wealth and status of the owner of the rural estate. The estate was built in the second half of the 2nd century and occupied until its destruction around 275.
The three-storied villa with more than 50 rooms on the ground floor alone, many decorated with mosaics and imported marble revetment, was centered on a colonnaded garden courtyard (G in Fig. 1). Many of the sandstone columns from the peristyle, as well as fragments of sculpture from the garden, were found in the courtyard. The house was built into a hill, and the courtyard was terraced on two levels. Around the edges of the garden was a ground level gutter. From the apsed triclinium on the south, with a mosaic floor and a marble fountain in the middle, there was an excellent view of the garden.
At the northeast of the villa was a garden (G in Fig. 1) with a lararium. On the southwest there was a garden (G in Fig. 1) with a fountain. The northern facade had a cryptoporticus below and a porticoed corridor on the story above. The service area of the villa rustica lay in front of the villa to the north.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the rural villa with gardens (G) in the central courtyard and in the corners of the house. Plan adapted from Cüppers 1990, fig. 204.(Rights statement)   Dates Second half of 2nd century - around 275
Bibliography  G. Rupprecht, &amp;ldquo;Die Kreuznacher Mosaikbodenvilla. Kurzbericht (Stand: April 1977),&amp;rdquo; Saalburg Jahrbuch 34, 1977:78-87. G. Rupprecht, &amp;ldquo;Leben auf dem Land,&amp;rdquo; Archäologie in Deutschland 4, 1986: 36-39. (worldcat) Heinz Cüppers, Die Römer in Rheinland-Pfalz, Stuttgart, 1990, pp.321-323, fig. 204. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981525
TGN ID 7012371
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 15 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House in Insula 16 in Aventicum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_house_in_insula_16/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 10:24:03 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_house_in_insula_16/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Aventicum
Aventicum (Pleiades)
Location Description The town was established in the Augustan period as the civitas capital of the Helvetii. At this time the orthogonal street grid was laid out. Most probably in AD 71, it became Colonia Pia Flavia Constans Emerita Helvetiorum Foederata. The town was destroyed or badly damaged around AD 260, and it was progressively abandoned thereafter.
Garden House in Insula 16 in Aventicum
Keywords  colonnades insulae peristyles (Roman courtyards)  Garden Description In Insula 16 East, northeast of the forum, were small shops and houses belonging to three different owners. These were demolished when the town was promoted to the status of colonia by Vespasian. The new house occupied the whole insula and was entered on the northeast.
In the middle of the insula was a large peristyle courtyard which may have been planted (G in Fig. 1). In the southwestern part of the building complex taverns and shops opened onto the colonnaded street.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the house with a possible peristyle garden (G) in Insula 16. Adapted from McKay 1986, fig. 186.   Dates AD 71
Bibliography  H. Bögli and D. Weidmann, &amp;ldquo;Nouvelles recherches à Aventicum,&amp;rdquo; Archäologie der Schweiz 2, 1978:71-72, fig. 2.(worldcat) A. G. McKay, Houses, Villas and Palaces in the Roman World, London, 1975, pp. 202-203, fig. 186. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 177495
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 15 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House in Insula 13 in Aventicum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_house_in_insula_13/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 10:06:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_house_in_insula_13/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Aventicum
Aventicum (Pleiades)
Location Description The town was established in the Augustan period as the civitas capital of the Helvetii. At this time the orthogonal street grid was laid out. Most probably in AD 71, it became Colonia Pia Flavia Constans Emerita Helvetiorum Foederata. The town was destroyed or badly damaged around AD 260, and it was progressively abandoned thereafter.
Garden House in Insula 13 in Aventicum
Keywords  archaeological garden bathhouses (water recreation structures) corridors fountains garden pavilions gutters (building drainage components) insulae peristyles (Roman courtyards) piscinae reception rooms  Garden Description Recent excavations in Insula 13 on the northwestern edge of the town have uncovered the remains of two large and luxurious houses separated from each other by a narrow corridor. They date to the late 1st century and were occupied until the middle of the 3rd century. Both buildings had a length of 60 meters, spanning the length of the insula. The eastern house included a private bath suite and an apsed reception room on the southwest.
The most remarkable feature of the building was a T-shaped garden courtyard (G in Fig. 1) surrounded by a peristyle on all sides (Fig. 1). A ground line gutter ran around the edge of the courtyard. In the southern part of the garden was a large pool paved with limestone slabs and measuring 6 x 12 meters On the northern edge of the pool was a rectangular fountain. To the north of this was a square structure measuring 5.40 x 5.40 meters which may have been a garden pavilion.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of a courtyard house in Insula 13 with a peristyle garden (G) and pool (grey). Plan adapted from Carroll 2001, fig. 20. (Rights statement)   Dates Houses: Late 1st century - Middle of 3rd century
Bibliography  J. Morel, &amp;ldquo;Chronique archéologique 1993,&amp;rdquo; Bull. de l&amp;rsquo;Association Pro Aventico 35, 1993: 19-21, figs. 8, 11. J. Morel, “L’habitat,” in : A. Hochuli-Gysel, ed., Avenches, capitale des Helvètes, Archéologie Suisse 24.1, 2001: 45-46, figs. 58, 60. (worldcat) M. Carroll, Romans, Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 55, fig. 20. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 177495
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 15 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Palatial House in Insula 7 in Aventicum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_palatial_house_in_insula_7/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 14:48:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_palatial_house_in_insula_7/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Aventicum
Aventicum (Pleiades)
Location Description The town was established in the Augustan period as the civitas capital of the Helvetii. At this time the orthogonal street grid was laid out. Most probably in AD 71, it became Colonia Pia Flavia Constans Emerita Helvetiorum Foederata. The town was destroyed or badly damaged around AD 260, and it was progressively abandoned thereafter.
Garden Palatial House in Insula 7 in Aventicum
Keywords  archaeological garden axial plan bathhouses (water recreation structures) drains exedrae (site elements) mosaics (visual works) palaces peristyles (Roman courtyards) piscinae presence chambers  Garden Description The remains of a palatial house (Palais de Derrière la Tour) were recently uncovered in excavations on the western edge of the city in an area characterized by luxurious domestic dwellings (Fig. 1). The house in its final state, from the Severan period to the middle of the 3rd century, had a peristyle courtyard measuring 42 x 69 meters. North of the courtyard was a reception room 12 x 18 meters in plan with a mosaic floor.
The courtyard was on two levels, divided on the north by a terrace wall with two small exedrae, possibly pools. An axially arranged central pathway between the reception room on the north and an apsed triclinium on the south further divided the courtyard into an eastern and a western half. Steps led up to the triclinium and to the northern wing of the house. A ground level gutter ran around the courtyard, and a covered drain crossed it beneath the central path. It can reasonably be assumed that the courtyard was designed as a garden (G in Fig. 1) with garden elements such as the path and the exedral pools. With the addition on the northeast of another wing terminating in a bath complex, the building ultimately had a length of around 200 meters. The excavators believe that the building in its latest phase had official character.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the courtyard house or palace on the western fringe of Insula 7, with a garden courtyard (G) with two small apsidal pools on one side. Plan adapted from Morel 1995, fig. 4. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Severnan Period - Middle of 3rd century
Bibliography  J. Morel, “Avenches VD, Derrière la Tour et insula 7 : Fouilles 1989/1990,” Annuaire de la Société Suisse de Préhistoire et d’Archéologie 74, 1991: 214-220, fig. 2. (worldcat) J. Morel, “Avenches, Palais de Derrière la Tour,” Bull. de l’Association Pro Aventico 37, 1995: 206-209, fig. 4.(worldcat) J. Morel, “L’habitat,” in : A. Hochuli-Gysel, ed., Avenches, capitale des Helvètes, Archéologie Suisse 24.1 2001: 47-49, fig. 62.(worldcat)  Pleiades ID 177495
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 14 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House in Insula 30 in Augusta Raurica</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ausgusta_raurica/augusta_raurica_house_in_insula_30/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 10:02:05 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ausgusta_raurica/augusta_raurica_house_in_insula_30/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Augusta Raurica
Augusta Raurica (Pleiades)
Location Description The town on the Rhine River possessed colonial status since the late 1st century BC. The street grid, as well as many public and residential buildings, are well known from excavations.
Garden House in Insula 30 in Augusta Raurica
Keywords  colonnades corridors insulae peristyles (Roman courtyards) triclinia vestibules water wells  Garden Description Insula 30, east of the central baths, was taken up by a single house built around 200 AD. This replaced several earlier structures on the site. The insula, including the street colonnades, had an overall area of ca. 48 x 60 meters.
The house had a peristyle courtyard of rectangular shape which was surrounded on three sides by a low wall supporting stone columns. The courtyard was unpaved and almost certainly planted (G in Fig. 1). Entering the house from the east, one passed through a vestibule before arriving in the peristyle corridor around the courtyard. The courtyard wall, enclosing an area 14 x 23.50 meters in size, was fronted by a water channel. There was a well in the north. From the triclinium to the west of the courtyard, one had a view directly into the courtyard.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of a house in Insula 30 with a garden courtyard (G). Plan adapted from Laur-Belart 1988, fig. 126. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Insula: 200 A.D.
Bibliography  R. Laur-Belart, Führer durch Augusta Raurica, 5th Ed., Basel, 1988, pp. 134-136, fig. 126. (worldcat) M. Carroll, Romans, Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 55, fig. 20. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 177494
TGN ID 7017586
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 14 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House in Insula 1 and 2 in Augusta Raurica</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ausgusta_raurica/augusta_raurica_house_in_insula_1_and_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 17:34:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ausgusta_raurica/augusta_raurica_house_in_insula_1_and_2/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Augusta Raurica
Augusta Raurica (Pleiades)
Location Description The town on the Rhine River possessed colonial status since the late 1st century BC. The street grid, as well as many public and residential buildings, are well known from excavations.
Garden House in Insula 1 and 2 in Augusta Raurica
Keywords archaeological garden \
 insulae peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes terrace gardens  Garden Description This house, built on sloping terrain on the northern edge of the city around AD 150, was enlarged twenty years later to incorporate at least two certain gardens (Fig. 1). It bordered north and south on streets and was flanked on the east and west by other houses. In this last phase after ca. 170, the house covered an area of about 2000 square meters. In the center of the building was an irregular peristyle courtyard, at the north end of which was a private bath complex.
East of the house was a long rectangular area open to the sky and divided into plots by a wall. In the northernmost plot a layer of humic soil 20-40 centimeters thick was excavated that the excavators interpret as evidence for a garden (G on plan).
The northern part of the house facing the street included an open terrace which may have been built up on demolished walls of the earlier house. Humus-rich soil in the terrace area may indicate that it was planted (G in Fig. 1). Immediately south of the terrace was a portico that offered a splendid view of the valley.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Augusta Raurica., House in insula 1 and 2. Adapted from Hufschidt.(Rights statement)   Images Dates House: AD 150 - ca. 170
Bibliography  P.-A. Schwarz, „Die Nordmauer und die Überreste der Innenbebauung der spätrömischen Befestigung auf Kastelen in Augusta Rauricorum. Vorbericht über die Grabung 1991.51,“ Jahresberichte aus Augst und Kaiseraugst 13, 1992: 47-76. (worldcat) T. Hufschmid, Kastelen 3. Die jüngeren Steinbauten in den Insulae 1 und 2 von Augusta Raurica. Forschungen in Augst 23, Augst, 1996. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 177494
TGN ID 7017586
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 14 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Large Building North of Forum in Arae Flaviae</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/arae_flaviae/arae_flaviae_large_building_north_of_forum/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 11:07:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/arae_flaviae/arae_flaviae_large_building_north_of_forum/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Arae Flaviae
Arae Flaviae (Pleiades)
Location Description This town on the Neckar river was granted municipal status around 84 AD or slightly later. In modern terms, it lies about halfway between Zurich and Stuttgart.
Garden Large Building north of Forum in Arae Flaviae
Keywords  archaeological garden colonnades corridors peristyles (Roman courtyards) vestibules  Garden Description This building ca. 95 meters in width consisted of several units built at different times. These may represent more than one house, or they may be parts of one large house. The southern part of the complex, entered from the colonnaded street on the west, had a vestibule or corridor leading into a peristyle courtyard. This may have been planted, although the excavators could find no clear evidence of this. Beyond the peristyle to the east was a series of rooms, including one large room presumably with representative character, and an open area interpreted as a courtyard or garden (G in Fig. 1). The complex was built at the earliest during the reign of Trajan, but additions and alterations followed throughout the 2nd and perhaps the 3rd century.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of a house north of the forum with a peristyle courtyard and open areas to the east, possibly both planted as gardens (G). Adapted from Sommer 1992, Beilage 1.2. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Complex built at the earliest during the reign of Trajan.
Bibliography  C. S. Sommer, &amp;ldquo;Municipium Arae Flaviae. Militärisches und ziviles Zentrum im rechtsrheinischen Obergermanien,&amp;rdquo; Bericht der Römisch-Germanischen Kommission 73, 1992: 301-302, Beilage 1.2.  Pleiades ID 118572
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 13 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Legionary Houses at Castra Vetera (Germania Inferior)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/castra_vetera/ger_inf_castra_vetera/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:57:44 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/castra_vetera/ger_inf_castra_vetera/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Province Description Location Castra Vetera
Castra Vetera (Pleiades)
Garden Legionary houses at Castra Vetera (Germania inferior)
Keywords  castra praetoriums atriums peristyles (Roman courtyards) tablina pedestals Pliny the Younger  Garden Description In the Neronian fort of the 5th and 15th legions near the civilian settlement of Colonia Ulpia Traiana were two vast buildings on either side of the headquarters building (principia). These were the residences, or praetoria, of the two legionary commanders. The western palatial complex was 76-77 m. in width and 97 m. in length (over 7400 sq. m.) (Plan 1). It was entered from the east through a vestibule and an atrium. The villa had several peristyle courtyards, including one long peristyle courtyard with apsidal ends which has been interpreted as a garden (G on plan). Between the atrium and the apsidal courtyard was a large room, possibly a tablinum or a dining room. This courtyard measured 18.80 x 83 m. and had an open area 10.80 m. wide, surrounded on all sides by a covered columned walkway, 3.50 m. in width.
The partially excavated eastern villa was 78.50 m. wide and 109 m. in length. It too had several peristyle courtyards and one long courtyard 19 x 74.60 m. in size. The open area between the covered walkways was 5.80 m. wide. In front of each of the columns surrounding the courtyard were buttress-like foundations which the excavator interpreted as possible bases for statues. The excavator referred to the long courtyards in these houses as &amp;ldquo;hippodrome gardens&amp;rdquo;, and compared them to known stadium or hippodrome gardens at Pliny&amp;rsquo;s Tuscan villa, on the Palatine in Rome (Domus Augustana) and at Hadrian&amp;rsquo;s villa at Tivoli. The comparison is unacceptable, however, since both ends of the courtyards in the legionary camp are apsidal, unlike a stadium or hippodrome which has one straight end. The long garden courtyards at Xanten may have had more in common with the long, apsidal gardens referred to by Pliny as gestatio in modum circi (Epist. 5.6.17). It can be considered reasonably certain that the courtyards in both legionary villas were not foreseen for races or athletic activities, but for gardens as an ideal place for promenades.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the western *praetorium* in the double legionary base with its long apsidal garden (G). Adapted from Lehner 1930, fig. 39. (Rights statement).     Caption below the image. (RIGHTS STATEMENT)   Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  H. Lehner, Vetera. Die Ergebnisse der Ausgrabungen des Bonner Provinzialmuseums bis 1929. Römisch-Germanische Forschungen 4, Berlin, 1930, pp. 52-60, figs. 38-41. worldcat  Pleiades ID 108867
TGN ID 7004944
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 25 July 2020
Related articles The Houses of Insula 7 in Colonia Ulpia Traiana</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban House on Lungenstrasse</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_lungenstrasse/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:53:55 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_lungenstrasse/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Garden Urban house on Lungenstrasse (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords  peristyles (Roman courtyards) mural paintings (visual works)  Garden Description In the second half of the 1st century A.D. a large peristyle house was constructed on the western fringe of the city, built on the remains of abandoned pottery kilns. The peristyle courtyard of the house was at least 13 x 21 m. in size, but the structural remains were badly damaged when a temple complex was erected on the site around the middle of the 2nd century Neither the complete ground plan nor the extent of the building could be determined.
In the leveled remains of the 1st century house were fragments of painted wall plaster, including fragments of scenes depicting gardens (Image 1). These show trees against a sky-blue background. It is uncertain which rooms of the house were decorated in this way.
Maps Images   Fragments of garden paintings from the peristyle courtyard house on Lungengasse (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium). Photo courtesy of M. Carroll.   Dates mid-first to mid-second century CE
Bibliography None
Pleiades ID 108751
TGN ID 7004446
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 13 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban House on Wolfsstrasse</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_wolfsstrasse/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:52:13 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_wolfsstrasse/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Garden Urban house on Wolfsstrasse (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords  urban villas villae urbanae colonnades peristyles (Roman courtyards) mural paintings (visual works)  Garden Description Only a fraction of this house in the immediate vicinity of the House on Gertrudenstraße was excavated. Enough was salvaged, however, to be able to recognize that the house was of the peristyle type (Plan 1). The house was built after the middle of the 1st century A.D. By the mid-4th century the building was ruinous and the stones of most of the walls were robbed for reuse elsewhere.
The peristyle courtyard was ca. 7 m. wide and 11.30 m. long. Both faces of the wall surrounding it were plastered and painted red. Presumably the wall was several courses high, much like a balustrade, with columns on top. There was a doorway or monumental entrance, 3.50 m. wide, to the courtyard at the southeast. The corridor around the garden was 3.10 m. wide and had a beaten earth floor resurfaced more than once. Most of the original earth in the courtyard had been disturbed or removed in post-Roman times, but there was clearly no sign of a paved surface or beaten earth floors that had been trodden in the courtyard, so that one might postulate the existence of loose garden soil here during the occupation of the house (G on Plan 1). In the northern part of the courtyard was a deep, circular shaft which may have been a well (W on Plan 1), the stone courses of which had been robbed out.
Maps Plans   Plan 1: Plan of the partially excavated courtyard house with a possible garden (G) containing a well (W) on Wolfsstraße. Adapted from Carroll-Spillecke 1997, fig. 7. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Middle of the first century CE until the fourth century CE
Bibliography  M. Carroll-Spillecke, “Ausgrabungen in einem römischen Wohnviertel in der Wolfsstraße/Richmodstraße in Köln,” Kölner Jahrbuch 30 (1997): 415-31. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108751
TGN ID 7004446
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 12 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban House on Gertrudenstrasse</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_gertrudenstrasse/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:51:27 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_gertrudenstrasse/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Garden Urban house on Gertrudenstrasse (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords  urban villas villae urbanae peristyles (Roman courtyards) apsed pools piscinae  Garden Description This Mediterranean-type house just inside the western city wall had a peristyle courtyard ca. 9 x 14 m. in size, in the middle of which was a pool (3 x 8 m.) with apsidal ends (P on Plan 1).
The courtyard was unpaved, and the presence of a source of water suggests that it was designed as a garden (G on Plan 1). Although the house was only partially excavated, evidence for several rebuildings from the second half of the 1st to the 4th century was retrieved. The peristyle courtyard was retained throughout, indicating the importance attached to the garden by generations of owners.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the partially preserved house with a peristyle courtyard garden (G) and pool (P) on Gertrudenstraße. Adapted from Thomas 1993, fig. 3. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Middle of the first century CE until the fourth century CE
Bibliography  R. Thomas, Römische Wandmalerei in Köln, Mainz, 1993, pp. 321-327, figs. 138-39. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108751
TGN ID 7004446
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 12 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Atrium House</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_atrium/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 07:38:05 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_atrium/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Garden Atrium House (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords  urban villas villae urbanae atrium houses atriums tablina colonnades peristyles (Roman courtyards) apsed pools piscinae  Garden Description West of the House of Dionysos stood the so-called &amp;ldquo;atrium house&amp;rdquo; which covered an area of 1400 sq. m. (Plan 1). It was built around the middle of the 1st century A.D.
Entering from the colonnaded street at the west, one passed through a room reconstructed as an atrium, continuing along a corridor around the tablinum, and arrived at a peristyle courtyard with a semicircular pool. This courtyard, approximately 10 x 13 m. in size, was almost certainly a garden (Plan 1, G). A ground level gutter ran around the edge of the unpaved courtyard. This part of the house remained unchanged until the destruction of the building in the 4th century.
Maps Plans   Plan 1: Plan of the so-called &amp;#39;atrium house&amp;#39; with an apsidal pool (P) in its garden courtyard (G). Adapted from Precht 1971, fig. 2. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Middle of the first century CE until the fourth century CE
Bibliography  G. Precht, &amp;ldquo;Die Ausgrabungen um den Kölner Dom. Vorbericht über die Untersuchungen,&amp;rdquo; Kölner Jahrbuch 12, 1971:55-56, fig. 2, pl. 7.2. (worldcat) H. Hellenkemper, &amp;ldquo;Architektur als Beitrag zur Geschichte der CCAA,&amp;rdquo; in H. Temporini, ed., Aufstieg und Niedergang der Römischen Welt II.4, Berlin, 1974, p. 810, figs. 20-21. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108751
TGN ID 7004446
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 09 July 2020
Related articles House of Dionysos (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Dionyius</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_dionysius/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 20:22:59 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_dionysius/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Garden House of Dionysius (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords  urban villas villae urbanae triclinia insulae peristyles (Roman courtyards) apsed pools axial plan piscinae  Garden Description The largest urban villa excavated thus far in Cologne is the House of Dionysos (3400 sq. m.), named after the early 3rd century mosaic floor decorated with Dionysiac motifs in the triclinium (Image 1??). The house occupies part of an insula in the northeastern corner of the city, bordered on the south by a street leading to the harbor.
The original house, erected after A.D. 50, was rebuilt under Vespasian and included a peristyle garden courtyard measuring 23 x 27 m. (G on Plan 1). The garden was surrounded on three sides by a peristyle, 3.35 m. in width. A ground level gutter ran around the edge of the garden. At this time, a masonry pool with a paved floor occupied a position in the eastern part of the garden. A piece of lead pipe and a bronze opening were found associated with the pool. This was later replaced in the second half of the 2nd century by an apsed pool (4.20 x 5.40 m.) in the western half of the garden which drained into the gutter at the west. The pool was axially arranged between the entrance to the house on the east and the dining room on the west, from which a view through a wide doorway onto the garden was afforded. The triclinium was unheated, leading the excavator to interpret it as a summer triclinium. The connection with the garden would, in this case, be quite understandable. An axial planting pattern in the garden with a path leading from the entrance of the house to the pool is possible. There is, however, no evidence for the planting pattern or the type of vegetation in this garden. The house was inhabited until the 4th century.
Maps   CAPTION   Plans   Plan 1: Plan of the House of Dionysos, built around a central courtyard garden (G) with a pool (grey). Plan adapted from Fremersdorf 1956, fig. 27. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Reign of Vespasian until the end of the fourth century CE
Bibliography  F. Fremersdorf, Das römische Haus mit dem Dionysosmosaik vor dem Südportal des Kölner Doms, Berlin, 1956. (worldcat) M. Carroll, Romans, Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 55, fig. 20. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108751
TGN ID 7004446
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>