<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>peristyles on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/peristyles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in peristyles on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/peristyles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa D’Argo</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/herculaneum/tiffany-fong/casa_dargo/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/herculaneum/tiffany-fong/casa_dargo/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Garden Casa D’Argo
##Jashemski Catalogue 533.II.2. 534.II.2.
Keywords  cisterns (plumbing components) triclinium peristyles porticoes gutters (building drainage components)  Garden Description 533.II.2. A. The earliest excavations of Herculaneum were done with underground tunnels. Several of these crossed this site and were discovered sixty three years later when further excavation of this patrician house was conducted in1828-1835. Eight brick columns and one engaged column stood on each of the long sides of the portico that bounded the large peristyle garden (a) on the east, north, and west sides. The north side was supported by four more columns and at the two front corners there was a pillar with an engaged column on each side. In the center of the north side two smaller pillars with one engaged column each framed a garden view from the triclinium. All the supporting members were coated with fine stucco. Gutters ringing the garden conveyed rain water to the cistern.
534.II.2. B. A second peristyle garden was located to the west of the first, but has only been partially excavated. It has stuccoed columns and pillars joined by a wall 0.4 m. high painted with plants and flowers.
Plans   Casa D’Argo   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1828-1835
Bibliography  A.C. BdI (1835),p. 130 (worldcat) Bonucci, BdI (1830), p.121 (worldcat) Bonucci, Le due Sicilie: Ercolano, fig. 11 (plan) and p. 37 (worldcat) Breton,Pompeia p. 519 (worldcat) Maiuri, Herculaneum, p. 24 (worldcat) Idem,Ercolano, pp. 367-368 and fig. 293 (plan) on p. 362 (worldcat) Niccolini,Real museo borbonico, vol. 7, fig. 59 (plan), description by Bechi, pp. 19-21 (worldcat)     Ruggiero, Ercolano, pp. 541-545 (contains the detailed reports of Bonucci)(worldcat)     -      Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.iii.25 B</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_25/i.iii.25_b/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 17:22:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_25/i.iii.25_b/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 25
Garden I.iii.25 B
Keywords  peristyles (columnades) viridarium  Garden Description The viridarium (b) lay across the entire width of the house to the rear. The west (rear) of the peristyle garden (a) was completely open to the viridarium.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 75. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., p. 58.(worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 28. (worldcat) Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 78. Trendelenberg, BdI(1871), p. 172. Warscher, “Codex.”  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 29 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.iii.25 A</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_25/i.iii.25_a/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 17:22:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_25/i.iii.25_a/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 25
Garden I.iii.25 A
Keywords  archaeological garden peristyles (columnades) porticoes statues statuettes (free-standing sculpture) triclinia  Garden Description This house had an irregular plan and a small peristyle garden (a) enclosed on three sides by a low masonry wall. The wall was topped by four stuccoed brick columns which supported the portico. The excavation in 1869-72 showed that restoration was in progress at the time of the eruption. Inside the triclinium a small marble head of Bacchus from a herm (Mus. Naz. inv. no. 110 653) was found as well as a small marble ram (Mus. Naz. inv. no. 120 357), both probably garden decorations.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1869-1872
Bibliography  Dohl, p. 1. Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 74. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., p. 57.(worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 2 (1870-1873), col. 461. Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 28. (worldcat) Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 78. Trendelenberg, BdI(1871), p. 172.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 29 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Capella (I.iii.24)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_24/house_of_capella/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 15:31:46 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_24/house_of_capella/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 24
Garden House of Capella (I.iii.24)
Keywords  archaeological garden lararia mural paintings (visual works) peristyles (columnades) porticoes triclinia  Garden Description At the rear of the house, excavated in 1868, there was a peristyle garden (a) with a portico supported by three brick columns on the east and north sides. The south wall had a lararium painting and a crude animal painting on one corner of the south garden wall. This had been executed in the manner of a topiary painting according to the excavators, who reported a lion consuming a deer, below which there was a dog pouncing on a hare. A good view of the garden was obtained through the triclinium (b) on the north.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1868
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 24, no. 261. Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 74, p. 150, no. 456 . (worldcat) Idem, Desc., pp. 56-57.(worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 28. (worldcat) Idem, Gardens, vol.II, p. 313. (worldcat) Matz, BdI (1869), pp. 239-240. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 78. Schefold, WändP, p. 13 . Sogliano, “Pitture,” p. 225, no. 705.  Warscher, “Codex,” photo no. 54.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 29 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Actius Anicetus (I.iii.23)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_23/house_of_actius_anicetus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 12:55:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_23/house_of_actius_anicetus/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 23
Garden I.iii.20/22
Keywords  archaeological garden cisterns (plumbing components) gutters (building drainage components) mural paintings (visual works) peristyles (columnades) porticoes puteal  Garden Description This site was excavated in 1868 revealing a peristyle garden (a) at the rear of the house. A portico on the east and north side was supported by five columns connected by a low wall. There was an opening to the garden on the north. The middle of the garden had two cistern puteals. The west wall of the garden held the famous painting depicting the battle between the Nucerians and the Pompeians in the ampitheator (1.60 m. high by a little less than 2.00 m. wide; Mus. Naz. Inv. No. 112 222; Ruesch no. 1344). This event was recorded by Tacitus (Annals 14.17). A gutter went along the east, south, and north edges of the garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1868
Bibliography  DePetra, GiornSc, n.s., 1 (1865-1869), cols. 185-187 (where the address is given as I.ii). Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 74 and pp. 145-146, no. 401. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., pp. 52-53.(worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 27. (worldcat) Matz, BdI (1869), pp. 240-241. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 78. Niccolini, Case, vol. 4, “Supplemento,” p1. 32. Maiuri, NSc (1939), pp. 168-169. Schefold, WändP, p.12. Sogliano, “Pitture,” p. 204, no.604. Warscher, “Codex.” photos nos. 44-50.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 29 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.iii.20/22</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/houses_20&#43;22/i.iii.20&#43;22/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 13:25:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/houses_20&#43;22/i.iii.20&#43;22/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 20/22
Garden I.iii.20/22
Keywords  altars (religious fixtures) archaeological garden doliums gutters (building drainage components) peristyles (columnades) puteal triclinia  Garden Description At the rear of this house there was a garden (a) with a passageway on the north and the west. The garden had a gutter along the east, north, and west edges. Embedded in the garden were four large dolia. A large triclinium (b) on the east side had a window that looked out into the garden. Fiorelli surmised that the remains of one couch of a masonry triclinium in the west passageway indicated the possible presence of a room that had been destroyed by the earthquake. There was also a small altar on the right side of the peristyle and a terra-cotta puteal in the passageway.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 24, no. 25. Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 73. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., p. 54.(worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 27. (worldcat) Matz, BdI (1869), p. 242. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 78. Soprano, p. 308, no. 36. Warscher, “Codex.”  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 28 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.iii.3</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_3/i.iii.3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 13:03:42 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_3/i.iii.3/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 3
Garden I.iii.3
Keywords  alleys (streets) archaeological garden exedrae (site elements) gutters (building drainage components) hearths lararia peristyles (columnades) pilasters porticoes puteal tufa  Garden Description The front of this house excavated in 1869 had an unusual design in that it was set back some distance from the street. The peristyle garden was entered at the end of the entranceway at the rear of a long angiprotus (alleyway). Rooms of the house were located at the right and rear of the garden. The peristyle had undergone various changes and was supported on the east and north by tall tufa columns. The portico roof on the west was supported by two low brick columns and two pilasters surmounted by arches. A low wall enclosed the garden, joining the columns either side of the entrance between the two columns to the west. A terra-cotta puteal was adjacent to the west wall along with a hearth covered with a small vault decorated with a rough, bearded head supposed to be Vulcan. A large window on the south wall gave a view from the exedra (b) into the garden. The east peristyle wall contained a lararium niche and a gutter ran along the north, east, and west edges of the garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1869
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 24, no. 22. Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 72. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., pp. 52-53.(worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 1 (1868-69), cols. 300-301. Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 26. (worldcat) Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 78. Pernice, p. 34. Warscher, “Codex.” photos nos. 16-21.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 28 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Epidius Fortunatus (I.iii.3)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_3/house_of_epidius_fortunatus_i.iii.3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 19:24:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_3/house_of_epidius_fortunatus_i.iii.3/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 3
Garden House of Epidius Fortunatus (I.iii.3)
Keywords  archaeological garden aqueducts basins (vessels) gutters (building drainage components) peristyles (columnades) podiums (building divisions) porticoes puteal tablina tufa  Garden Description On the right of the tablinum were ten steps that led to the peristyle garden (a). A portico enclosed the garden on the west, north and east sides. This was supported by ten columns and two engaged columns which were stuccoed brick painted red. The north, east, and west edges of the garden had a gutter. There were two cistern openings, according to Mau, one located in the northeast corner of the garden with a tufa puteal and the other in the corresponding corner of the portico. Water emptied at the northeast corner from the gutter into the cistern and into the street at the southeast and southwest corners. An aqueduct pipe came out of the first column, (counting from the south, on the west portico), and ran between the gutter and the portico. The pipe rose, supported from the second column on the west side, to spurt a jet of water in the gutter. Flanking the west and the north porticos, it disappeared going to the northwest. On the west side it was possible in two places to let water flow into the gutter by a widening of the pipe. The gutter had openings to the gardens at these two points to serve as watering outlets. There were keys before and after the widen pipe sections to control the flow of water. Two branches of this pipe entered a room (b) off the northwest corner of the peristyle where there was a basin.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2 : Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Scavi, pp. 70-71. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., pp.50-51.(worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 26. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 181-182. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 77. Pernice, p. 14. Warscher, “Codex.” photos nos. 4, 6-10a.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 27 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa Della Grata Metallica; Casa Dell’Atrio Tetra-Stilo (I.ii.28)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_28/casa_della_grata_metallica_i.ii.28/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 15:01:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_28/casa_della_grata_metallica_i.ii.28/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 28
Garden Casa Della Grata Metallica; Casa Dell’Atrio Tetra-Stilo (I.ii.28)
Keywords  altars (religious fixtures) archaeological garden cisterns (plumbing components) peristyles (columnades) podiums (building divisions) porticoes tables (support furniture) tablina triclinia tufa  Garden Description At the rear of the house there was a peristyle garden (a) with a portico along the east side and part of the south. The excavation took place in 1873-74. A low wall joined three stuccoed brick columns and two engaged ones which supported the portico. There was an entrance to the garden on the south side opposite the door from the tablinium (b) and another on the east opposite the kitchen door (c), which was closed later according to Mau. The columns were white above the height of the wall and red below. Water was carried to the cistern by a wide gutter on the south and east edges of the garden, and Mau found some evidence of aqueduct water. There was a masonry triclinium (l.medius, 5.30 m.; l.imus, 3.85 m.; l.summus, 2.70 m.) with a circular table (dia. of support, 0.70 m. ) built against the west wall. Inside of each couch there were four niches (0.19 m. wide). The last niche in the south couch was larger in size and separated from the other three by the mouth of the cistern. There was a small masonry podium on the north wall with steps for access. A round tufa altar was located opposite the lectus summus (Fig. 3).
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I.ii.28; 10.11.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation dates 1873-1874
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Descr., p. 48. (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), col. 60. Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 25. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 250-252. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 77. Soprano, p. 293, no. 2 and figs. 28.6 and 29. Viola, “Scavi” p. 14. (worldcat) Warscher, “Codex.” photo no. 54-57.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 27 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.ii.17 B</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_17/i.ii.17_b/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2020 15:01:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_17/i.ii.17_b/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 17
Garden I.ii.17 B
Keywords  archaeological garden atriums mural paintings (visual works) peristyles (columnades) pillars porticoes statues statuettes (free-standing sculpture) tablina  Garden Description The peristyle garden to the east of the atrium was excavated in 1873. It had a portico on the north and west supported by two pillars, one at the northwest corner and the other in the middle of the north side. A gutter sloped towards the southeast corner as it went around the east, north, and west edges of the garden. A shrine-like structure was built against the east wall with the marble veneered façade above the level of the floor of the niche. The niche contained a marble statuette of Venus, her left arm supported by a statuette (1.04 m. high; Mus Naz. inv. no. 109 608; Ruesch no. 1325). The wall behind the statue was painted to represent blue drapery and the ceiling had a shell-like fluting. Two small marble statuettes of toads (Mus. Nac. inv. no. 109 609, 109 610) found in the garden and probably the one of two doves (Mus. Naz. inv. no. 120 407) found in the tablinum decorated the flowerbeds. There was also a marble head of a man identified as Agrippa, found cemented in a cup (total height 0.285 m.; Mus. Nac. inv. no. 109 611; Reusch no. 1081). The marble statuette of Hercules wrapped in a lion skin (0.70 m. high; Mus. Nac. inv. no. 109 677) found in the atrium was probably a garden decoration. The large room on the north had a fine view of the garden and the east and south walls of the garden were decorated with garden paintings. These were separated by narrow panels with a painting of a candelabrum, according to Mau, and each painting featured a fence with an amphora upon it. Behind this there was a thicket with birds. On either side of the amphora there was an ibis, and a pheasant in the center. Fiorelli mentioned observing animals in the paintings. Jashemski notes that no trace of the paintings remained when she examined the site, and further, she has never seen a pheasant represented in any garden paintings. Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation dates 1873
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 22, no. 10. de Franciscis, Ritratto, p. 25 and figs. 10-11. (worldcat) Döhl, p.1. Dwyer, Pomp. Sculpture, pp. 124, 12. (worldcat) Fiorelli, Descr., p. 44. (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), cols. 46-47, 48, 55. Grimal, p. 445, no. 1.  Jashemski, Gardens, 1::124-125. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, pp. 23-24. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 313. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 233-235. Ibid. (1874), pp. 265-266. Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 265-266.  Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 76. Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “L’arte,” p. 6 and pl. 14 (Venus). Schefold, WandP, p. 10. (worldcat)  Sogliano, “Pitture,” p. 223, no. 691. (worldcat)  Sogliano, “Scavi,” p. 310. (worldcat) Viola, “Scavi” pp. 12 and 76, no. 1, p.77, nos. 5, 12, p.79, nos. 45, 46. (worldcat) Warscher, “Codex,” photo no. 32.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.ii.6</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_6/i.ii.6/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2020 12:44:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_6/i.ii.6/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 6
Garden I.ii.6
Keywords  archaeological garden atriums graffiti (casual notations) gutters (building drainage components) inscription peristyles (columnades) piscinae porticoes puteal  Garden Description The west portico of the small peristyle garden at the rear of the house was entered through two doors directly from the atrium. The garden was enclosed on four sides by a portico supported by eight stuccoed brick columns. On the foreside, the two first columns on the left had a larger intercolumniation corresponding to the wide opening opposite the atrium. Between these columns stood a terra-cotta puteal covered with white stucco. A gutter around the edges of the garden was shown in the plan. The round pool in the center of the garden no longer exists, and only stumps of the columns remain today. One of the graffiti on the walls of the portico noted that on November 17 Puteolana gave birth to three males and two females (XV K(alendas) NOV(embres) PVTEOLANA PEPERIT MASCL(os) III FEMEL[as] II) (CIL IV.3890). Perhaps they were either piglets or puppies. Pigs were more common in ancient cities than is commonly realized.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Descr., p. 39. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, 1: 104-105 (for the graffito). (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 21. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 199. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. Gen.,” p. 76. Pernice, p. 18. Viola, “Scavi,” p 11. (worldcat) Warscher, “Codex.”  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 24 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Eisenstadt</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/eisenstadt/eisenstadt_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 09:31:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/eisenstadt/eisenstadt_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Pannonia
Location Eisenstadt
Eisenstadt (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Eisenstadt
Keywords  altars (religious fixtures) archaeological garden atriums peristyles (Roman courtyards) podiums (building divisions) porticoes villae rusticae  Garden Description The residence of this villa rustica was entered on the southeast by a portico (Fig. 1). After passing through a room interpreted as the atrium, one arrived in the open courtyard which had a peristyle on three sides (G on plan). On the northern edge of the courtyard was a podium (P on plan) near which votive altars to Diana and Silvanus were found, both gods of the woods and suitable subjects for a garden. This corner of the courtyard, thus, seems to have had religious character. In the middle of the courtyard was a square foundation, measuring 1.80 x 1.80 m., possibly the remains of a base for some kind of figure. The villa rustica was established in the early 2nd century and occupied probably until the 4th century.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the rural villa with a peristyle courtyard (G) and a podium (P) for sculpture. Adapted from Thomas 1964, fig. 73. (Rights statement.)   Dates Early 2nd century - 4th century
Bibliography  E.B. Thomas, Römische Villen in Pannonien, Budapest, 1964, pp. 137-151, fig. 73. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 197425
TGN ID 7003056
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban House or Schola in Aquincum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/aquincum/aquincum_urban_house_or_schola/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jul 2020 16:44:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/aquincum/aquincum_urban_house_or_schola/</guid>
      <description>Province Pannonia
Province Description Location Aquincum
Aquincum (Pleiades)
Location Description This town on the Danube river acquired the rank of municipium under Hadrian in 124 A.D. In the year 194 it was granted colonial status.
Garden Urban House or Schola in Aquincum
Keywords  archaeological garden bathhouses (water recreation structures) fountains peristyles (Roman courtyards) piscinae statues statuettes (free-standing sculpture)  Garden Description Very few houses of Mediterranean type have been discovered, and only one can be said with certainty to have had a garden (Fig. 1, G in Fig. 1). The peristyle courtyard was a prominent feature of this house of irregular plan and substantial size near the southern city wall. The house dates to the 3rd century, and it is thought to have been a clubhouse or schola for young men (collegium iuventutis), complete with a bath suite. In the middle of the courtyard, framed on four sides by a low wall supporting columns, was a square masonry pool (Fig. 2). In the center of the pool was a fountain consisting of a small marble satyr standing on a column of the same material. This decorative element and the unpaved ground strongly suggest the existence of a garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of a building with a peristyle garden courtyard (G) and a pool in its center. Adapted from Polenz and Póczy 1986, fig. 47.(Rights statement.)   Images   Fig. 2: The excavated courtyard building with its peristyle garden. Photo courtesy of M. Carroll.)   Dates 3rd century
Bibliography  A. Mócsy, Pannonia and Upper Moesia. A History of the Middle Danube Provinces of the Roman Empire, London, 1974, p. 166, pl. 16b. (worldcat) H. Polenz and K. Póczy, Das römische Budapest. Neue Ausgrabungen und Funde in Aquincum, Münster, 1986, p. 124, fig. 47, pl. 10. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 1971301
TGN ID 8713146
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Structures under the Collège Lumière in Vesontio</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vesontio/vesontio_structures_under_the_colle%CC%80ge_lumie%CC%80re/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 09:48:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vesontio/vesontio_structures_under_the_colle%CC%80ge_lumie%CC%80re/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Vesontio
Vesontio (Pleiades)
Location Description The defensibility offered by this unique geography made Caesar hasten to occupy Vesontio in 58 BC. The town came to have all the usual Roman structures– forum, baths, aqueduct, and amphitheater (on the other side of the Doubs, to the northwest.) But the most visible remnant is the Porte Noire (Black Gate) [3], a triumphal arch built by Marcus Aurelius at the southeastern end of the cardo maximus, today Grande Rue and still the center of city life.
Archaeology in a downtown area is always a matter of seizing opportunities as they are presented by new construction, remembering and recording what was found, and coming back years later to complete the picture. A good example of this process is at our second site, [2] on the map. In 1973, the Neptune Mosaic was discovered in rue de Lorraine, one of the largest floor decorations in all Gaul. The extent of the mosaic under nearby buildings made full excavation impossible. More than thirty years later, in 2004, construction of a gymnasium for the Collège Lumière (a middle school) gave archaeologists access to much more of the site, about 3000 square meters, for a salvage excavation. As expected, the continuation of the Neptune mosaic was found; moreover, three other mosaics of high quality, along with columns, sculpted blocks, peristyles, and monumental pools came to light. The results of this excavation have not been published; we are grateful to the excavators for sharing their preliminary results.
Garden Structures under the Collège Lumière in Vesontio
Keywords  colonnades kraters mosaics (visual works) opus signinum peristyles (Roman courtyards) piscinae porticoes reception rooms rinceaux terrazzo  Garden Description The results of the 2004 excavation at the Collège Lumière are still under study and the data are therefore still partial. This zone, close to the river and the artisinal quarter has, in the past, yielded most of the mosaics recorded for Besançon. The ancient structures discovered on 3000 square meters relate to a Gallo-Roman urbanization extending from the Augustan period to the third century and superimposed on a rather dense Gallic occupation of the first century BC. Two phases of construction from the late Augustan period up through the end of the first century, have thus far not permitted the confirmation of the possible presence of a garden. On the other, later constructions dating from the beginning and last third of the second century are rich in peristyles with open space suitable for a garden.
At the beginning of the second century, in a third phase, a structure of large dimension (at least 2500 m2) but undetermined purpose was built on fill and leveling of the abandoned earlier buildings. It will simplify descriptions to let “north” denote the direction that is actually northeast, the direction towards the river. In these terms, large rooms (the largest reaching 126 sq. m.) and corridors were bordered on the south by an open area, possibly a garden, with porticos on at least the north and west sides, and by one peristyle to the west and by another to the east. The walls of the porticos around these peristyles were decorated with painted plaster. The west peristyle (at least 22 x 20 m) is the most complete. Only one wall, the east wall of the west peristyle, is common to these second century structures and the preceding ones of first century. It may thus represent a property line. Originally, it opened over a large threshold between the largest of the rooms and the western peristyle. It was subsequently first reduced and then completely closed.
The fourth phase, a remodeling at the end of the second century, is the best preserved, but its purpose remains unclear. It has yielded a series of elements that allow us to follow the architectural reasoning of the builders. It kept the basic plan of the third state: a peristyle to the east, one to the west, and a large garden to the south. The rooms, however, are considerably rearranged. Three grand reception rooms (of 200, 85, and 65 m2 ) with floors decorated with luxurious mosaics are organized in a very regular fashion in relation to the two peristyles and garden by corridors or galleries. The floors of these numerous spaces of circulation were a terrazzo in an opus signinum matrix, except for the gallery of garden, which had a mosaic.
The largest of the rooms, decorated by the Neptune mosaic, opened on its north side through a colonnade onto the south of the east peristyle and through another colonnade on the opposite side to the garden on the south. The spacing of the columns was the same (4.6 m) on both colonnades. The excavated part of the east peristyle showed that it was 22.3 meters wide; if it was square, it would have had an area of about 500 square meters. Another large room decorated with the rinceaux mosaic (so called for the bands of scrolled foliage) also opens onto the east peristyle. The gallery that borders the garden was widened into the garden in front of the Neptune room; against the wall of this extension there was a pool at least 1.5 meters wide and probably about 13 meters long. Several paving stones of the bottom have survived. The last room, the one with the Medusa mosaic, would seem to have opened onto the garden. The garden was about .95 meters lower than the house and was reached by descending four steps. The north portico of the west peristyle was enlarged in this final phase; the interval between columns reached 6.7 meters. The presence of the closed wall that may have been a property line obliges us to ask Did this west peristyle really belong to the structure to the east or was it part of a different edifice that may have extended to the west outside the limits of the excavation?
A fragment of a little ornamental stone krater was found in the material that filled the east peristyle after its abandonment. From late antiquity is the foundation of a pool or cistern of about 3.5 by 2.5 meters. Its stones have been removed, and only the opus signinum mortar bearing the imprint of the stones has been found. This structure pierced through all the archaeological levels and into the natural earth.
Plans Images not available (?)  Fig. 1: Plan of the domus, now under the Collège Lumière.  Dates Gardens: Beginning and last third of second century
Excavation Dates 2004
Bibliography  C. Gaston and C. Munier “Une luxueuse domus de la find du IIe siècle à Besançon, college Lumière (Doubs, F)&amp;rdquo;&amp;rdquo; in Premières Journées archéologiques frontalières de l&amp;rsquo;Arc jurassien: Mandeure, sa campagne et ses relations d&amp;rsquo;Avenches à Luxeuil et d&amp;rsquo;Augst à Besançon. Ed, Cécile Bélet-Gonda, Presses Univ. Franche-Comté (2007), 103-112.  Pleiades ID 177657
TGN ID 7008356
Contributor Claudine Monier (ORCID: N/A)
Christophe Gaston (ORCID: https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6865-5108)
Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 20 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House in the Rue du Palais de Justice in Vesontio</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vesontio/vesontio_house_in_the_rue_du_palais_de_justice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2020 16:58:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vesontio/vesontio_house_in_the_rue_du_palais_de_justice/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Vesontio
Vesontio (Pleiades)
Location Description The defensibility offered by this unique geography made Caesar hasten to occupy Vesontio in 58 BC. The town came to have all the usual Roman structures– forum, baths, aqueduct, and amphitheater (on the other side of the Doubs, to the northwest.) But the most visible remnant is the Porte Noire (Black Gate) [3], a triumphal arch built by Marcus Aurelius at the southeastern end of the cardo maximus, today Grande Rue and still the center of city life.
Archaeology in a downtown area is always a matter of seizing opportunities as they are presented by new construction, remembering and recording what was found, and coming back years later to complete the picture. A good example of this process is at our second site, [2] on the map. In 1973, the Neptune Mosaic was discovered in rue de Lorraine, one of the largest floor decorations in all Gaul. The extent of the mosaic under nearby buildings made full excavation impossible. More than thirty years later, in 2004, construction of a gymnasium for the Collège Lumière (a middle school) gave archaeologists access to much more of the site, about 3000 square meters, for a salvage excavation. As expected, the continuation of the Neptune mosaic was found; moreover, three other mosaics of high quality, along with columns, sculpted blocks, peristyles, and monumental pools came to light. The results of this excavation have not been published; we are grateful to the excavators for sharing their preliminary results.
Garden House in the Rue du Palais de Justice in Vesontio
Keywords archaeological garden \
 domus fountains hypocausts mosaics (visual works) opus sectile (visual works) opus signinum oeci peristyles (columnades) piscinae porticoes terrazzo water wells  Garden Description In 2000-2001, at the time of construction a new judiciary facility, an area of 2000 square meters was excavated at the center of this loop. The results are in large part unpublished. On land that had been occupied since the end of the second century BC, two houses of perishable materials were built in the eastern part of the site in the beginning of the first century AD. They were abandoned at the beginning of the Flavian epoch, and replaced by two imposing domus that lasted up to the middle of the third century. They stood on opposite sides of a property line wall (tinted in purple in Fig. 1) that was parallel to a cardo running in a northwest-to-southeast direction some hundred meters away. The two houses had slightly different orientations. The eastern house doubtless opened onto a southwest-northeast street passing 50 meters beyond the eastern limit of the excavation but partially brought to light in 1989-90 during excavations when a new parking facility was being built for the city hall. In this house, two independent structures (oecus) (tinted pink in the figure) with floors once decorated with mosaics since disappeared are wrapped about and connected by a portico (yellow tint) of complex plan with galleries 3 meters wide and opening onto an open space (green tint) covering 110 square meters. The counterpart of this portico is in part visible on the other side of the larger room. An incompletely known peristyle borders this oecus to the east (on the lower right edge of the plan). Its gallery was decorated with a terrazzo floor of opus signinum with accents of crustae, thin stone slices of which an opus sectile is made. In this phase, the north domus had a peristyle of 75 square meters with galleries on three sides. To the west (lower left corner of the plan), there was a large open space of nearly 500 square meters, which may have been a garden. At its west end, the wall of an incomplete building ran by a well and a masonry square 2.16 meters on a side which may have been the base of a shrine or monument. These structures were aligned with the property line wall. There was as yet no pool.
In the second half of the second century, the “garden” was restructured. The building on the west side was abandoned, the shrine or monument was kept, and a large pool put in at the eastern end supported against the wall of a terrace supporting the house to the east and consequently having the same orientation. This rectangular pool (21.2 x 3.5 m) had on the garden side a semicircular apse 6.9 meters in diameter. As part of the same architectural ensemble, a portico formed the retro-scene of the pool. Its opus signinum floor was 80 centimeters above the surface of the pool. Another, wider portico ran along the north side of the area. A shim-shaped gap existed between it and the property-line wall because of the difference in orientation. The monumental character of the pool and the north portico suggests that this garden may have been independent of both houses and was possibly a public space or belonged to a house further west, outside the limits of excavation.
At the beginning of the third century, the two domus were transformed. In particular, polychrome mosaics were installed in the east house and rooms with hypocausts in the north house. The little shrine or monument at the western end of the garden was eliminated, but the pool was reconstructed without alteration. The paving stones that had been in a pool were in part removed and used to build a 3.8 x 2.9 meter platform which served as the base, presumably, of a quadrangular fountain in the north house in an open space which replaced the peristyle, which was then destroyed.
Images Images not available (?) FIGURES:
 Fig. 1: Houses at the Palais de Justice Fig. 2: Axonometric representation  Dates Beginning of the Flavian epoch - middle of the third century
Excavation Dates 2000-2001
Bibliography  C. Gaston, “Un bassin monumental et une fontaine dans les fouille du Palais de Justice de Besancon,” Revue Archéologique de l&amp;rsquo;Est, t. 52, 2003, p.417-428. Christophe Gaston: “Données récentes sur l&amp;rsquo;achitecture antique à Besançon,” Archéopages/Inrap. No. 8, Nov. 2002, p. 28-35. Laurent Vaxelaire, Philippe Barral, “Besançon: de l’oppidum à la ville romaine” in La naissance de la ville dans l’Antiquité, M. Reddé et al. ed., Paris, 2003, p. 254-256.  Pleiades ID 177657
TGN ID 7008356
Contributor Claudine Monier (ORCID: N/A)
Christophe Gaston (ORCID: https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6865-5108)
Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 19 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Bad Kreuznach</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/bad_kreuznach/bad_kreuznach_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 12:39:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/bad_kreuznach/bad_kreuznach_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Bad Kreuznach
Bad Kreuznach (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Bad Kreuznach
Keywords  apsed triclinium colonnades cryptoportici fountains gutters (building drainage components) lararia mosaics (visual works) peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes villae rusticae  Garden Description This villa, almost 6000 square meters in size, gives eloquent testimony to the wealth and status of the owner of the rural estate. The estate was built in the second half of the 2nd century and occupied until its destruction around 275.
The three-storied villa with more than 50 rooms on the ground floor alone, many decorated with mosaics and imported marble revetment, was centered on a colonnaded garden courtyard (G in Fig. 1). Many of the sandstone columns from the peristyle, as well as fragments of sculpture from the garden, were found in the courtyard. The house was built into a hill, and the courtyard was terraced on two levels. Around the edges of the garden was a ground level gutter. From the apsed triclinium on the south, with a mosaic floor and a marble fountain in the middle, there was an excellent view of the garden.
At the northeast of the villa was a garden (G in Fig. 1) with a lararium. On the southwest there was a garden (G in Fig. 1) with a fountain. The northern facade had a cryptoporticus below and a porticoed corridor on the story above. The service area of the villa rustica lay in front of the villa to the north.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the rural villa with gardens (G) in the central courtyard and in the corners of the house. Plan adapted from Cüppers 1990, fig. 204.(Rights statement)   Dates Second half of 2nd century - around 275
Bibliography  G. Rupprecht, &amp;ldquo;Die Kreuznacher Mosaikbodenvilla. Kurzbericht (Stand: April 1977),&amp;rdquo; Saalburg Jahrbuch 34, 1977:78-87. G. Rupprecht, &amp;ldquo;Leben auf dem Land,&amp;rdquo; Archäologie in Deutschland 4, 1986: 36-39. (worldcat) Heinz Cüppers, Die Römer in Rheinland-Pfalz, Stuttgart, 1990, pp.321-323, fig. 204. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981525
TGN ID 7012371
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 15 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House in Insula 16 in Aventicum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_house_in_insula_16/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 10:24:03 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_house_in_insula_16/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Aventicum
Aventicum (Pleiades)
Location Description The town was established in the Augustan period as the civitas capital of the Helvetii. At this time the orthogonal street grid was laid out. Most probably in AD 71, it became Colonia Pia Flavia Constans Emerita Helvetiorum Foederata. The town was destroyed or badly damaged around AD 260, and it was progressively abandoned thereafter.
Garden House in Insula 16 in Aventicum
Keywords  colonnades insulae peristyles (Roman courtyards)  Garden Description In Insula 16 East, northeast of the forum, were small shops and houses belonging to three different owners. These were demolished when the town was promoted to the status of colonia by Vespasian. The new house occupied the whole insula and was entered on the northeast.
In the middle of the insula was a large peristyle courtyard which may have been planted (G in Fig. 1). In the southwestern part of the building complex taverns and shops opened onto the colonnaded street.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the house with a possible peristyle garden (G) in Insula 16. Adapted from McKay 1986, fig. 186.   Dates AD 71
Bibliography  H. Bögli and D. Weidmann, &amp;ldquo;Nouvelles recherches à Aventicum,&amp;rdquo; Archäologie der Schweiz 2, 1978:71-72, fig. 2.(worldcat) A. G. McKay, Houses, Villas and Palaces in the Roman World, London, 1975, pp. 202-203, fig. 186. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 177495
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 15 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House in Insula 13 in Aventicum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_house_in_insula_13/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 10:06:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_house_in_insula_13/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Aventicum
Aventicum (Pleiades)
Location Description The town was established in the Augustan period as the civitas capital of the Helvetii. At this time the orthogonal street grid was laid out. Most probably in AD 71, it became Colonia Pia Flavia Constans Emerita Helvetiorum Foederata. The town was destroyed or badly damaged around AD 260, and it was progressively abandoned thereafter.
Garden House in Insula 13 in Aventicum
Keywords  archaeological garden bathhouses (water recreation structures) corridors fountains garden pavilions gutters (building drainage components) insulae peristyles (Roman courtyards) piscinae reception rooms  Garden Description Recent excavations in Insula 13 on the northwestern edge of the town have uncovered the remains of two large and luxurious houses separated from each other by a narrow corridor. They date to the late 1st century and were occupied until the middle of the 3rd century. Both buildings had a length of 60 meters, spanning the length of the insula. The eastern house included a private bath suite and an apsed reception room on the southwest.
The most remarkable feature of the building was a T-shaped garden courtyard (G in Fig. 1) surrounded by a peristyle on all sides (Fig. 1). A ground line gutter ran around the edge of the courtyard. In the southern part of the garden was a large pool paved with limestone slabs and measuring 6 x 12 meters On the northern edge of the pool was a rectangular fountain. To the north of this was a square structure measuring 5.40 x 5.40 meters which may have been a garden pavilion.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of a courtyard house in Insula 13 with a peristyle garden (G) and pool (grey). Plan adapted from Carroll 2001, fig. 20. (Rights statement)   Dates Houses: Late 1st century - Middle of 3rd century
Bibliography  J. Morel, &amp;ldquo;Chronique archéologique 1993,&amp;rdquo; Bull. de l&amp;rsquo;Association Pro Aventico 35, 1993: 19-21, figs. 8, 11. J. Morel, “L’habitat,” in : A. Hochuli-Gysel, ed., Avenches, capitale des Helvètes, Archéologie Suisse 24.1, 2001: 45-46, figs. 58, 60. (worldcat) M. Carroll, Romans, Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 55, fig. 20. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 177495
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 15 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Palatial House in Insula 7 in Aventicum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_palatial_house_in_insula_7/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 14:48:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_palatial_house_in_insula_7/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Aventicum
Aventicum (Pleiades)
Location Description The town was established in the Augustan period as the civitas capital of the Helvetii. At this time the orthogonal street grid was laid out. Most probably in AD 71, it became Colonia Pia Flavia Constans Emerita Helvetiorum Foederata. The town was destroyed or badly damaged around AD 260, and it was progressively abandoned thereafter.
Garden Palatial House in Insula 7 in Aventicum
Keywords  archaeological garden axial plan bathhouses (water recreation structures) drains exedrae (site elements) mosaics (visual works) palaces peristyles (Roman courtyards) piscinae presence chambers  Garden Description The remains of a palatial house (Palais de Derrière la Tour) were recently uncovered in excavations on the western edge of the city in an area characterized by luxurious domestic dwellings (Fig. 1). The house in its final state, from the Severan period to the middle of the 3rd century, had a peristyle courtyard measuring 42 x 69 meters. North of the courtyard was a reception room 12 x 18 meters in plan with a mosaic floor.
The courtyard was on two levels, divided on the north by a terrace wall with two small exedrae, possibly pools. An axially arranged central pathway between the reception room on the north and an apsed triclinium on the south further divided the courtyard into an eastern and a western half. Steps led up to the triclinium and to the northern wing of the house. A ground level gutter ran around the courtyard, and a covered drain crossed it beneath the central path. It can reasonably be assumed that the courtyard was designed as a garden (G in Fig. 1) with garden elements such as the path and the exedral pools. With the addition on the northeast of another wing terminating in a bath complex, the building ultimately had a length of around 200 meters. The excavators believe that the building in its latest phase had official character.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the courtyard house or palace on the western fringe of Insula 7, with a garden courtyard (G) with two small apsidal pools on one side. Plan adapted from Morel 1995, fig. 4. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Severnan Period - Middle of 3rd century
Bibliography  J. Morel, “Avenches VD, Derrière la Tour et insula 7 : Fouilles 1989/1990,” Annuaire de la Société Suisse de Préhistoire et d’Archéologie 74, 1991: 214-220, fig. 2. (worldcat) J. Morel, “Avenches, Palais de Derrière la Tour,” Bull. de l’Association Pro Aventico 37, 1995: 206-209, fig. 4.(worldcat) J. Morel, “L’habitat,” in : A. Hochuli-Gysel, ed., Avenches, capitale des Helvètes, Archéologie Suisse 24.1 2001: 47-49, fig. 62.(worldcat)  Pleiades ID 177495
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 14 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House in Insula 30 in Augusta Raurica</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ausgusta_raurica/augusta_raurica_house_in_insula_30/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 10:02:05 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ausgusta_raurica/augusta_raurica_house_in_insula_30/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Augusta Raurica
Augusta Raurica (Pleiades)
Location Description The town on the Rhine River possessed colonial status since the late 1st century BC. The street grid, as well as many public and residential buildings, are well known from excavations.
Garden House in Insula 30 in Augusta Raurica
Keywords  colonnades corridors insulae peristyles (Roman courtyards) triclinia vestibules water wells  Garden Description Insula 30, east of the central baths, was taken up by a single house built around 200 AD. This replaced several earlier structures on the site. The insula, including the street colonnades, had an overall area of ca. 48 x 60 meters.
The house had a peristyle courtyard of rectangular shape which was surrounded on three sides by a low wall supporting stone columns. The courtyard was unpaved and almost certainly planted (G in Fig. 1). Entering the house from the east, one passed through a vestibule before arriving in the peristyle corridor around the courtyard. The courtyard wall, enclosing an area 14 x 23.50 meters in size, was fronted by a water channel. There was a well in the north. From the triclinium to the west of the courtyard, one had a view directly into the courtyard.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of a house in Insula 30 with a garden courtyard (G). Plan adapted from Laur-Belart 1988, fig. 126. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Insula: 200 A.D.
Bibliography  R. Laur-Belart, Führer durch Augusta Raurica, 5th Ed., Basel, 1988, pp. 134-136, fig. 126. (worldcat) M. Carroll, Romans, Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 55, fig. 20. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 177494
TGN ID 7017586
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 14 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House in Insula 1 and 2 in Augusta Raurica</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ausgusta_raurica/augusta_raurica_house_in_insula_1_and_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 17:34:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ausgusta_raurica/augusta_raurica_house_in_insula_1_and_2/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Augusta Raurica
Augusta Raurica (Pleiades)
Location Description The town on the Rhine River possessed colonial status since the late 1st century BC. The street grid, as well as many public and residential buildings, are well known from excavations.
Garden House in Insula 1 and 2 in Augusta Raurica
Keywords archaeological garden \
 insulae peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes terrace gardens  Garden Description This house, built on sloping terrain on the northern edge of the city around AD 150, was enlarged twenty years later to incorporate at least two certain gardens (Fig. 1). It bordered north and south on streets and was flanked on the east and west by other houses. In this last phase after ca. 170, the house covered an area of about 2000 square meters. In the center of the building was an irregular peristyle courtyard, at the north end of which was a private bath complex.
East of the house was a long rectangular area open to the sky and divided into plots by a wall. In the northernmost plot a layer of humic soil 20-40 centimeters thick was excavated that the excavators interpret as evidence for a garden (G on plan).
The northern part of the house facing the street included an open terrace which may have been built up on demolished walls of the earlier house. Humus-rich soil in the terrace area may indicate that it was planted (G in Fig. 1). Immediately south of the terrace was a portico that offered a splendid view of the valley.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Augusta Raurica., House in insula 1 and 2. Adapted from Hufschidt.(Rights statement)   Images Dates House: AD 150 - ca. 170
Bibliography  P.-A. Schwarz, „Die Nordmauer und die Überreste der Innenbebauung der spätrömischen Befestigung auf Kastelen in Augusta Rauricorum. Vorbericht über die Grabung 1991.51,“ Jahresberichte aus Augst und Kaiseraugst 13, 1992: 47-76. (worldcat) T. Hufschmid, Kastelen 3. Die jüngeren Steinbauten in den Insulae 1 und 2 von Augusta Raurica. Forschungen in Augst 23, Augst, 1996. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 177494
TGN ID 7017586
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 14 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Large Building North of Forum in Arae Flaviae</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/arae_flaviae/arae_flaviae_large_building_north_of_forum/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 11:07:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/arae_flaviae/arae_flaviae_large_building_north_of_forum/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Arae Flaviae
Arae Flaviae (Pleiades)
Location Description This town on the Neckar river was granted municipal status around 84 AD or slightly later. In modern terms, it lies about halfway between Zurich and Stuttgart.
Garden Large Building north of Forum in Arae Flaviae
Keywords  archaeological garden colonnades corridors peristyles (Roman courtyards) vestibules  Garden Description This building ca. 95 meters in width consisted of several units built at different times. These may represent more than one house, or they may be parts of one large house. The southern part of the complex, entered from the colonnaded street on the west, had a vestibule or corridor leading into a peristyle courtyard. This may have been planted, although the excavators could find no clear evidence of this. Beyond the peristyle to the east was a series of rooms, including one large room presumably with representative character, and an open area interpreted as a courtyard or garden (G in Fig. 1). The complex was built at the earliest during the reign of Trajan, but additions and alterations followed throughout the 2nd and perhaps the 3rd century.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of a house north of the forum with a peristyle courtyard and open areas to the east, possibly both planted as gardens (G). Adapted from Sommer 1992, Beilage 1.2. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Complex built at the earliest during the reign of Trajan.
Bibliography  C. S. Sommer, &amp;ldquo;Municipium Arae Flaviae. Militärisches und ziviles Zentrum im rechtsrheinischen Obergermanien,&amp;rdquo; Bericht der Römisch-Germanischen Kommission 73, 1992: 301-302, Beilage 1.2.  Pleiades ID 118572
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 13 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban House on Lungenstrasse</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_lungenstrasse/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:53:55 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_lungenstrasse/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Garden Urban house on Lungenstrasse (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords  peristyles (Roman courtyards) mural paintings (visual works)  Garden Description In the second half of the 1st century A.D. a large peristyle house was constructed on the western fringe of the city, built on the remains of abandoned pottery kilns. The peristyle courtyard of the house was at least 13 x 21 m. in size, but the structural remains were badly damaged when a temple complex was erected on the site around the middle of the 2nd century Neither the complete ground plan nor the extent of the building could be determined.
In the leveled remains of the 1st century house were fragments of painted wall plaster, including fragments of scenes depicting gardens (Image 1). These show trees against a sky-blue background. It is uncertain which rooms of the house were decorated in this way.
Maps Images   Fragments of garden paintings from the peristyle courtyard house on Lungengasse (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium). Photo courtesy of M. Carroll.   Dates mid-first to mid-second century CE
Bibliography None
Pleiades ID 108751
TGN ID 7004446
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 13 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban House on Wolfsstrasse</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_wolfsstrasse/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:52:13 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_wolfsstrasse/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Garden Urban house on Wolfsstrasse (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords  urban villas villae urbanae colonnades peristyles (Roman courtyards) mural paintings (visual works)  Garden Description Only a fraction of this house in the immediate vicinity of the House on Gertrudenstraße was excavated. Enough was salvaged, however, to be able to recognize that the house was of the peristyle type (Plan 1). The house was built after the middle of the 1st century A.D. By the mid-4th century the building was ruinous and the stones of most of the walls were robbed for reuse elsewhere.
The peristyle courtyard was ca. 7 m. wide and 11.30 m. long. Both faces of the wall surrounding it were plastered and painted red. Presumably the wall was several courses high, much like a balustrade, with columns on top. There was a doorway or monumental entrance, 3.50 m. wide, to the courtyard at the southeast. The corridor around the garden was 3.10 m. wide and had a beaten earth floor resurfaced more than once. Most of the original earth in the courtyard had been disturbed or removed in post-Roman times, but there was clearly no sign of a paved surface or beaten earth floors that had been trodden in the courtyard, so that one might postulate the existence of loose garden soil here during the occupation of the house (G on Plan 1). In the northern part of the courtyard was a deep, circular shaft which may have been a well (W on Plan 1), the stone courses of which had been robbed out.
Maps Plans   Plan 1: Plan of the partially excavated courtyard house with a possible garden (G) containing a well (W) on Wolfsstraße. Adapted from Carroll-Spillecke 1997, fig. 7. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Middle of the first century CE until the fourth century CE
Bibliography  M. Carroll-Spillecke, “Ausgrabungen in einem römischen Wohnviertel in der Wolfsstraße/Richmodstraße in Köln,” Kölner Jahrbuch 30 (1997): 415-31. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108751
TGN ID 7004446
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 12 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban House on Gertrudenstrasse</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_gertrudenstrasse/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:51:27 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_gertrudenstrasse/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Garden Urban house on Gertrudenstrasse (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords  urban villas villae urbanae peristyles (Roman courtyards) apsed pools piscinae  Garden Description This Mediterranean-type house just inside the western city wall had a peristyle courtyard ca. 9 x 14 m. in size, in the middle of which was a pool (3 x 8 m.) with apsidal ends (P on Plan 1).
The courtyard was unpaved, and the presence of a source of water suggests that it was designed as a garden (G on Plan 1). Although the house was only partially excavated, evidence for several rebuildings from the second half of the 1st to the 4th century was retrieved. The peristyle courtyard was retained throughout, indicating the importance attached to the garden by generations of owners.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the partially preserved house with a peristyle courtyard garden (G) and pool (P) on Gertrudenstraße. Adapted from Thomas 1993, fig. 3. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Middle of the first century CE until the fourth century CE
Bibliography  R. Thomas, Römische Wandmalerei in Köln, Mainz, 1993, pp. 321-327, figs. 138-39. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108751
TGN ID 7004446
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 12 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Atrium House</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_atrium/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 07:38:05 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_atrium/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Garden Atrium House (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords  urban villas villae urbanae atrium houses atriums tablina colonnades peristyles (Roman courtyards) apsed pools piscinae  Garden Description West of the House of Dionysos stood the so-called &amp;ldquo;atrium house&amp;rdquo; which covered an area of 1400 sq. m. (Plan 1). It was built around the middle of the 1st century A.D.
Entering from the colonnaded street at the west, one passed through a room reconstructed as an atrium, continuing along a corridor around the tablinum, and arrived at a peristyle courtyard with a semicircular pool. This courtyard, approximately 10 x 13 m. in size, was almost certainly a garden (Plan 1, G). A ground level gutter ran around the edge of the unpaved courtyard. This part of the house remained unchanged until the destruction of the building in the 4th century.
Maps Plans   Plan 1: Plan of the so-called &amp;#39;atrium house&amp;#39; with an apsidal pool (P) in its garden courtyard (G). Adapted from Precht 1971, fig. 2. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Middle of the first century CE until the fourth century CE
Bibliography  G. Precht, &amp;ldquo;Die Ausgrabungen um den Kölner Dom. Vorbericht über die Untersuchungen,&amp;rdquo; Kölner Jahrbuch 12, 1971:55-56, fig. 2, pl. 7.2. (worldcat) H. Hellenkemper, &amp;ldquo;Architektur als Beitrag zur Geschichte der CCAA,&amp;rdquo; in H. Temporini, ed., Aufstieg und Niedergang der Römischen Welt II.4, Berlin, 1974, p. 810, figs. 20-21. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108751
TGN ID 7004446
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 09 July 2020
Related articles House of Dionysos (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Dionyius</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_dionysius/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 20:22:59 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_dionysius/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Garden House of Dionysius (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords  urban villas villae urbanae triclinia insulae peristyles (Roman courtyards) apsed pools axial plan piscinae  Garden Description The largest urban villa excavated thus far in Cologne is the House of Dionysos (3400 sq. m.), named after the early 3rd century mosaic floor decorated with Dionysiac motifs in the triclinium (Image 1??). The house occupies part of an insula in the northeastern corner of the city, bordered on the south by a street leading to the harbor.
The original house, erected after A.D. 50, was rebuilt under Vespasian and included a peristyle garden courtyard measuring 23 x 27 m. (G on Plan 1). The garden was surrounded on three sides by a peristyle, 3.35 m. in width. A ground level gutter ran around the edge of the garden. At this time, a masonry pool with a paved floor occupied a position in the eastern part of the garden. A piece of lead pipe and a bronze opening were found associated with the pool. This was later replaced in the second half of the 2nd century by an apsed pool (4.20 x 5.40 m.) in the western half of the garden which drained into the gutter at the west. The pool was axially arranged between the entrance to the house on the east and the dining room on the west, from which a view through a wide doorway onto the garden was afforded. The triclinium was unheated, leading the excavator to interpret it as a summer triclinium. The connection with the garden would, in this case, be quite understandable. An axial planting pattern in the garden with a path leading from the entrance of the house to the pool is possible. There is, however, no evidence for the planting pattern or the type of vegetation in this garden. The house was inhabited until the 4th century.
Maps   CAPTION   Plans   Plan 1: Plan of the House of Dionysos, built around a central courtyard garden (G) with a pool (grey). Plan adapted from Fremersdorf 1956, fig. 27. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Reign of Vespasian until the end of the fourth century CE
Bibliography  F. Fremersdorf, Das römische Haus mit dem Dionysosmosaik vor dem Südportal des Kölner Doms, Berlin, 1956. (worldcat) M. Carroll, Romans, Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 55, fig. 20. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108751
TGN ID 7004446
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>