<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/jurancon_pyr%C3%A9n%C3%A9es-atlantiques/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 12:39:10 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/jurancon_pyr%C3%A9n%C3%A9es-atlantiques/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa at the Pont d’Oly, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/jurancon_pyr%C3%A9n%C3%A9es-atlantiques/gallia_villa-at-the-pont-doly_yji/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 12:39:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/jurancon_pyr%C3%A9n%C3%A9es-atlantiques/gallia_villa-at-the-pont-doly_yji/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania
Province Description&amp;ndash;&amp;gt; A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location JURANCON
(Pleiades)
House Villa at the Pont d’Oly
House Description This luxurious villa of late antiquity is most remarkable for having been built on either side of a sizable stream, the Néez, which rises in the Pyrenees and flows into to the Gave on its left bank. This unique feature, however, proved the villa’s undoing, for the Néez changed its course and swept away a large part of the residential sector of the villa on its right (east) bank. The site has been known since 1770 and was excavated and mapped in the nineteenth century. A large area on the left bank was uncovered between 1850 and 1853 by a young English tourist, S. Baring Gould. Because of work on the bed of the Néez, there were salvage excavations on the right bank site in 1989-90 by G. Fabre and R. Monturet, but the results remain largely unpublished.
Garden Courtyard Garden
Keywords  archaeological garden porticos luxurious villa pavilions baths  Garden Description Each building covered about 2000 square meters with an elongated rectangular plan, and the two faced one another across the stream. The parallel long axes of the two buildings run to the north-northeast, but in this description we will take this direction as north. Each building had a portico façade parallel to stream. In the better preserved residential building on the west bank, this portico was about 30 meters long, had six columns, and was closed off at the north and south by roughly square pavilions. The scant remains of the building on the right (east) bank are consistent with the idea that each façade would have seemed to reflect the other. From the rear of the east bank building one looked out to the east onto a large semicircular courtyard. The courtyard was enclosed by a gallery running in a semicircle drawn with a radius of about ten meters and its center in the middle of the back wall of the building. Nothing is known of what was in the courtyard – indeed, half of it and the central portion of this house were completely carried away by the Néez. It would, however, have been a natural place for a garden beautifully visible from the central room of the house. Beyond this semicircle, further to the east, there was a vast rectangular space organized in a U [XIII – XIV]. Again, nothing is known of what was in its open area but a garden is certainly a possibility. The baths, the best known part of the structure, were connected to the house on the west bank.
Plans   Jurancon, Pont d&amp;#39;Oly. Plan of the building on the left bank of the neez by Laffolye in 1870. cl. Photographic archives of historical monuments     Plan supposes of the whole villa by R. Mounturet, after the 1989-91 excavations   Dates Unspecified
Excavation Dates 19th Century
Bibliography  Ch. Le Cœur, Notice sur les mosaïques de Jurançon (Basses-Pyrénées), Bull. du Comité de la Langue, de l’Histoire et des Arts de la France, 1853-54, n°2, p. 378-386 (worldcat) Gallia informations 1, 1991, p. 105-106 (worldcat) G. Fabre, Bilan scientifique, Aquitaine, 1991, p. 110 G. Fabre, Carte archéologique de la Gaule, (64) Pyrénées-Atlantiques, 1994, p. 213-214 worldcat Catherine Balmelle, Les demeures aristocratiques d&amp;rsquo;Aquitaine, societe et culture de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquite tardive dans le sou-ouest de la Gaule, Ausonius, supple. d&amp;rsquo;Aquitania 10, Bordeaux 2001, p. 354-357, plan p. 452. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 249927
TGN ID []()
Contributor Clopper Almon (https://www.econ.umd.edu/facultyprofile/almon/clopper)
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>