<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rural Villa on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/rural-villa/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Rural Villa on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/rural-villa/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/fliessem-otrang-villa-rural/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/fliessem-otrang-villa-rural/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location FLIESSEM-OTRANG (Germany)
FLIESSEM-OTRANG (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa
Keywords  villae rusticae mosaic porticoes courtyard  Garden Description This villa rustica was built on the slope of a hill about 30 kilometers north of Colonia Augusta Treverorum, close to the Roman road from Trier to Cologne, now B 51/E29. It is a kilometer or two south of the village of Fliessem. The original core of the villa is of second century date, but the building was enlarged considerably in the third century to take up an area of 4225 square meters (Fig. 1). It was occupied until around AD 400. The house (A on plan) occupied a position at the eastern end of the property, and in its final state it measured 60 x 60 meters and had 66 rooms, many of them decorated with mosaic floors. On the northern and southern sides were porticoes, and from the southern portico with its pavilions a view of the valley below was afforded.
The entrance to the house on the west was flanked by two protruding pavilions framing an open courtyard. Immediately to the west of this was another open courtyard enclosed by a wall. It might be expected, even if the evidence is sparse, that a garden or park was laid out at least in front of the entrance at the west (G on plan).
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  H. Mylius, &amp;ldquo;Die Rekonstruktion der römischen Villen von Nennig und Fliessem,&amp;rdquo; Bonner Jahrbuch 129, 1924:120-128, fig. 3, pl. 7; E. M. Wightman, Roman Trier and the Treveri, London, 1970, pp. 143-145, fig. 15; H. Cüppers, ed., Die Römer in Rheinland-Pfalz, Stuttgart,1990, pp. 367-371, figs. 264-265. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/1075378207) E. M. Wightman, Roman Trier and the Treveri, London, 1970, pp. 143-145, fig. 15 [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/1001859813) H. Cüppers, ed., Die Römer in Rheinland-Pfalz, Stuttgart,1990, pp. 367-371, figs. 264-265. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/924024101)  Pleiades ID 108982
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 12 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/nennig-villa-rural/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/nennig-villa-rural/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location NENNIG (Germany)
NENNIG (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa
Keywords  peristyle corridors bath building  Garden Description The villa of this rural estate of the third century and its grounds are the only parts of the complex which have been investigated (Fig. 1). The farm lay about 40 km. south of Trier on a gentle slope above the Moselle river. The villa is of the winged corridor type with a facade of over 45 meters in length, taking up an area of 4200 square meters. In the villa were two peristyle courtyards, but both were paved with slabs of red sandstone rather than having been laid out as gardens.
Parks were laid out on the grounds of the villa. A peristyle corridor 250 meters in length and 8.80 meters in width led from the villa to the bath building on the southwest, although it was not directly connected to either building. From the open-sided corridor one could enjoy the view of the almost certainly landscaped grounds, and of the terrain sloping down to the river. It is assumed that there was another peristyle corridor on the northeast. A grotto on the grounds of the villa belonged to the park.
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  P. Steiner, Die römische Villa von Nennig, Saarbrücken, 1955. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/1073267042) H. Mylius, &amp;ldquo;Die Rekonstruktion der römischen Villen von Nennig und Fliessem,&amp;rdquo; Bonner Jahrbuch 129, 1924:110-120, fig. 1, pls. 4-5. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/1075378207)  Pleiades ID 109198
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 12 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/veirherrenborn-rural-villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/veirherrenborn-rural-villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location VEIRHERRENBORN (Germany)
VEIRHERRENBORN (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa
Keywords  courtyard paddock  Garden Description The house stood in the middle of a farm complex 75 meters wide and 120 meters long. It dates to the early second century. The house (A on the plan, Fig. 1) is of the winged corridor type, measuring 19.30 x 22.40 meters.
On the west and east, in front of and behind the house, were open courtyards enclosed by a wall. The western courtyard has been interpreted as a garden (G on plan); the eastern one may have been a paddock.
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  H. Cüppers, ed., Die Römer in Rheinland-Pfalz, Stuttgart, 1990, p. 653, fig. 594. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/924024101)  Pleiades ID 109198
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 12 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/weitersbach-rural-villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/weitersbach-rural-villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location WELSCHBILLIG (Germany)
WELSCHBILLIG (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa
Keywords  palace portico herms  Garden Description This palatial villa, which has been interpreted as an imperial summer palace, lay within the confines of an imperial domain about 12 km. northwest of Colonia Augusta Treverorum. It was built during the reign of the emperor Valentinian I (364-375) or Gratian (367-383) who resided in the capital. Very little remains of the actual villa, although foundation walls of other buildings and a possible portico have been found.
The grounds of the villa were almost certainly landscaped in some form, as is suggested by a large decorative pool that may have been a decorative focus in a garden. It measured 18 x 60 meters and had three symmetrically arranged apses on the long sides. (Fig. 1) The walls of the pool were constructed of cut stone blocks and the bottom was paved with stone slabs. On top of the edges of the pool was an open-worked stone balustrade pierced at regular intervals by 112 limestone herms. The herms represent gods, Greeks, Romans, philosophers, generals and idealized figures such as putti, as well as Phrygians, Nubians and Germans. These were thrown into the pool in the 5th century, landing perhaps on layers of sediment at the bottom. As a result, the herms, of which 71 were retrieved in excavations, are in excellent condition. At the northern end of the pool was a rectangular building through which ran a drain from the pool. (Fig. 2, View of Model)
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  H. Wrede, Die spätantike Hermengalerie von Welschbillig. Römisch-Germanische Forschungen 32, Berlin, 1972 [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/223360098) H. Cüppers, ed., Die Römer in Rheinland-Pfalz, Stuttgart, 1990, pp. 665-667, figs. 607-609. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/924024101) P. Van Ossel, Établissements ruraux de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquité tardive dans le nord de la Gaule, Paris, 1992, pp. 277-278, fig. 90. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/445007864)  Pleiades ID 109456
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 12 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/welschbillig-rural-villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/welschbillig-rural-villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location WEITERSBACH (Germany)
WEITERSBACH (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa
Keywords  vegetable garden  Garden Description The enclosed farm compound measured 79 x 125/132 meters (less than one hectare). In the middle of the yard stood a house (A on plan) of the winged corridor type dating to the period between the end of the 1st and the later fourth century. (Fig. 1)
Southeast of the house was an open area of 900 square meters. enclosed by a wall. There were no traces of any building activity within this enclosure, leading the excavators to interpret the area as a utilitarian (vegetable) garden (G on plan).
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  E. Gose, &amp;ldquo;Jahresbericht&amp;rdquo;, Trierer Zeitschrift 24/26,1956-58: 511-525, figs. 106, 113. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/223360098) H. Cüppers, ed., Die Römer in Rheinland-Pfalz, Stuttgart, 1990, pp. 663-665, fig. 606. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/924024101) P. Van Ossel, Établissements ruraux de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquité tardive dans le nord de la Gaule, Paris, 1992, pp. 273-276, fig. 82. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/445007864)  Pleiades ID 109456
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 12 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/echternach-villa-rural/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/echternach-villa-rural/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location ECHTERNACH (Luxembourg)
ECHTERNACH (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa
Keywords  mosiacs courtyard peristyle  Garden Description This villa of a farm near Echternach was of the winged corridor type with sumptuous interior marble paneling, mosaics and wall paintings (Fig. 1). Originally constructed in the 60s of the first century AD, the villa was enlarged until it covered an area of 8928 square meters in the third century.
The protruding wings of the house on either side of the main entrance on the north framed a large, open courtyard, 29 x 74 meters in size, possibly a garden (G on plan). In the middle of this courtyard was a masonry pool of grand proportions (14.50 x 60 meters). In the middle of this stone-paved pool was a square base which once supported a statue, a sculptural group or perhaps a crater. The pool was retained as a decorative element throughout all the alterations of the estate until the destruction of the farm in the late 4th or early fifth century The southern peristyle courtyard (16.50 x 17 meters) within the house itself was initially designed as part of the bath complex in this wing, and in this courtyard was a swimming pool or natatio. Soon after the building of the house, the pool was filled in and the courtyard transformed into a garden (G on plan).
There was a garden from the very beginning in the western peristyle courtyard, as witnessed by the presence of garden soil (G on plan). This garden was later abandoned in the early second century.
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  J. Metzler, J. Zimmer and L. Bakker, Ausgrabungen in Echternach, Luxembourg, 1981; P. Van Ossel, Établissements ruraux de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquité tardive dans le nord de la Gaule, Paris, 1992, pp. 350-353, figs. 145-146. (worldcat)](http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/905778589)  Pleiades ID 108955
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/rural-villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/rural-villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location BAD DURKHEIM-UNGSTEIN (Germany)
BAD DURKHEIM-UNGSTEIN (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa
Keywords  villa rustica corridor courtyard  Garden Description The stone structures of this villa rustica, dating to the early second century, replaced earlier timber buildings. With the addition of an annex on the east in the early fourth century, the facade of the house acquired a length of 104 meters. The farm was occupied until the early fifth century.
The main residence is a villa of the winged corridor type (BEL 13.1.1). Two protruding wings on either wide of the entrance on the south framed an open courtyard which may have been planted (G on plan). Behind the house at the north were two more wings framing a second open courtyard (G on plan). This area, possibly a garden, was bordered on the north by a low wall.
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  H. Cüppers, ed., Die Römer in Rheinland-Pfalz, Stuttgart, 1990, pp. 317-319, figs. 156, 199. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108784
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>