<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>bathhouses on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/bathhouses/</link>
    <description>Recent content in bathhouses on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Jul 2020 16:44:26 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/bathhouses/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban House or Schola in Aquincum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/aquincum/aquincum_urban_house_or_schola/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jul 2020 16:44:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/aquincum/aquincum_urban_house_or_schola/</guid>
      <description>Province Pannonia
Province Description Location Aquincum
Aquincum (Pleiades)
Location Description This town on the Danube river acquired the rank of municipium under Hadrian in 124 A.D. In the year 194 it was granted colonial status.
Garden Urban House or Schola in Aquincum
Keywords  archaeological garden bathhouses (water recreation structures) fountains peristyles (Roman courtyards) piscinae statues statuettes (free-standing sculpture)  Garden Description Very few houses of Mediterranean type have been discovered, and only one can be said with certainty to have had a garden (Fig. 1, G in Fig. 1). The peristyle courtyard was a prominent feature of this house of irregular plan and substantial size near the southern city wall. The house dates to the 3rd century, and it is thought to have been a clubhouse or schola for young men (collegium iuventutis), complete with a bath suite. In the middle of the courtyard, framed on four sides by a low wall supporting columns, was a square masonry pool (Fig. 2). In the center of the pool was a fountain consisting of a small marble satyr standing on a column of the same material. This decorative element and the unpaved ground strongly suggest the existence of a garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of a building with a peristyle garden courtyard (G) and a pool in its center. Adapted from Polenz and Póczy 1986, fig. 47.(Rights statement.)   Images   Fig. 2: The excavated courtyard building with its peristyle garden. Photo courtesy of M. Carroll.)   Dates 3rd century
Bibliography  A. Mócsy, Pannonia and Upper Moesia. A History of the Middle Danube Provinces of the Roman Empire, London, 1974, p. 166, pl. 16b. (worldcat) H. Polenz and K. Póczy, Das römische Budapest. Neue Ausgrabungen und Funde in Aquincum, Münster, 1986, p. 124, fig. 47, pl. 10. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 1971301
TGN ID 8713146
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Oberentfelden</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/oberentfelden/oberentfelden_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 17:46:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/oberentfelden/oberentfelden_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Oberentfelden
Oberentfelden (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Oberentfelden
Keywords  archaeological garden bathhouses (water recreation structures) kitchen gardens nymphaea (garden structures) peristyles (columnades) villae rusticae  Garden Description The enclosed area of this villa rustica was 160 meters wide and at least 460 meters long; the eastern limits of the complex have not yet been found. The main residence and bath complex (A and B in Fig. 1), dating to the beginning of the 2nd century, stood on sloping land eight meters higher than the rest of the farmyard. At the eastern end of the service area (pars rustica) was a large peristyle building with a nymphaeum at the western end (D in Fig. 1). The open courtyard within this peristyle may have been a garden. Small kitchen gardens have been reconstructed between the various outbuildings and smaller houses (C in Fig. 1) in the pars rustica. Gardens here are possible, but it remains a matter of speculation whether these areas were actually planted.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the rural villa (A) with a bath (B), a nymphaeum (D) and various outbuildings and houses (C). Plan adapted from Drack and Fellmann 1988, fig. 418.   Dates 2nd century
Bibliography  W. Drack and R. Fellmann, Die Römer in der Schweiz, Stuttgart, 1988, pp. 457-459, fig. 418. (worldcat) R. Fellmann, La Suisse gallo-romaine. Cinq siècles d’histoire, Lausanne, 1992, pp. 152, 154, fig. 105. (worldcat) M. Carroll, Romans, Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 75, fig. 34. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 177596
TGN ID 8703779
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 17 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Hummetroth</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/hummetroth/hummetroth_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 11:47:11 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/hummetroth/hummetroth_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Hummetroth
Hummetroth (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Hummetroth
Keywords  apsed triclinium bathhouses (water recreation structures) corridors hypocausts porticoes reception rooms terrace gardens villae rusticae  Garden Description The enclosed farmyard, including the residential area (pars urbana) and the service zone with outbuildings and working areas (pars rustica), covered an area of 3.5 hectares. The house of this villa rustica of the 2nd century is of the winged corridor type with two protruding wings framing a large courtyard in front of the house at the south (Fig. 1).
The courtyard was divided into two zones by a terrace(?) wall, and in both zones a garden has been reconstructed (G in Fig. 1). Entering the house from the south, one passed through a large reception room to an apsed triclinium with hypocaust heating. A bath complex lay to the southwest, entered by the portico next to the garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the rural villa with a large terraced courtyard garden (G) to the south. Plan adapted from Baatz and Herrmann 1989, fig. 303a.   Dates 2nd century
Bibliography  D. Baatz and F.-R. Herrmann, eds., Die Römer in Hessen, 2nd ed., Stuttgart,1989, pp. 360-361, fig. 303a-b. (worldcat) M. Carroll, Romans,Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 74, fig. 29. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981525
TGN ID 7165467
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 16 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Friedberg Pfingstweide</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/friedberg-pfingstweide/friedberg-pfingstweide_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 18:12:31 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/friedberg-pfingstweide/friedberg-pfingstweide_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Friedberg Pfingstweide
Friedberg Pfingstweide (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Friedberg Pfingstweide
Keywords  archaeological garden bathhouses (water recreation structures) villae rusticae  Garden Description This villa rustica was situated on the northern slope of a valley through which a stream ran. The enclosed area of the farm occupied an area of 3.4 hectares (180 x 190 meters), and it was divided into a residential part (pars urbana) and a service area (pars rustica) by a road running east-west (Fig. 1). The front of the house (H in Fig. 1) faced north and had a view of the valley and the lower lying service area of the farm.
Built in the early 2nd century, the house was of the winged corridor type with a large open courtyard enclosed by the protruding wings of the house. The courtyard was divided into two zones that were possibly gardens (G in Fig. 1) and have been reconstructed as such. The farm was destroyed by fire in the first half of the 3rd century.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the villa (H) with a bath building (B) and with two possible garden enclosures (G) joined to the house at the north. Adapted from Baatz and Herrmann 1989, fig. 246.   Dates Early 2nd century - first half of 3rd century
Bibliography  D. Baatz and F.-R. Herrmann, eds., Die Römer in Hessen, 2nd ed., Stuttgart, 1989, pp. 307-309, fig. 246. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981525
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 16 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House in Insula 13 in Aventicum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_house_in_insula_13/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 10:06:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_house_in_insula_13/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Aventicum
Aventicum (Pleiades)
Location Description The town was established in the Augustan period as the civitas capital of the Helvetii. At this time the orthogonal street grid was laid out. Most probably in AD 71, it became Colonia Pia Flavia Constans Emerita Helvetiorum Foederata. The town was destroyed or badly damaged around AD 260, and it was progressively abandoned thereafter.
Garden House in Insula 13 in Aventicum
Keywords  archaeological garden bathhouses (water recreation structures) corridors fountains garden pavilions gutters (building drainage components) insulae peristyles (Roman courtyards) piscinae reception rooms  Garden Description Recent excavations in Insula 13 on the northwestern edge of the town have uncovered the remains of two large and luxurious houses separated from each other by a narrow corridor. They date to the late 1st century and were occupied until the middle of the 3rd century. Both buildings had a length of 60 meters, spanning the length of the insula. The eastern house included a private bath suite and an apsed reception room on the southwest.
The most remarkable feature of the building was a T-shaped garden courtyard (G in Fig. 1) surrounded by a peristyle on all sides (Fig. 1). A ground line gutter ran around the edge of the courtyard. In the southern part of the garden was a large pool paved with limestone slabs and measuring 6 x 12 meters On the northern edge of the pool was a rectangular fountain. To the north of this was a square structure measuring 5.40 x 5.40 meters which may have been a garden pavilion.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of a courtyard house in Insula 13 with a peristyle garden (G) and pool (grey). Plan adapted from Carroll 2001, fig. 20. (Rights statement)   Dates Houses: Late 1st century - Middle of 3rd century
Bibliography  J. Morel, &amp;ldquo;Chronique archéologique 1993,&amp;rdquo; Bull. de l&amp;rsquo;Association Pro Aventico 35, 1993: 19-21, figs. 8, 11. J. Morel, “L’habitat,” in : A. Hochuli-Gysel, ed., Avenches, capitale des Helvètes, Archéologie Suisse 24.1, 2001: 45-46, figs. 58, 60. (worldcat) M. Carroll, Romans, Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 55, fig. 20. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 177495
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 15 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Palatial House in Insula 7 in Aventicum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_palatial_house_in_insula_7/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 14:48:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_palatial_house_in_insula_7/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Aventicum
Aventicum (Pleiades)
Location Description The town was established in the Augustan period as the civitas capital of the Helvetii. At this time the orthogonal street grid was laid out. Most probably in AD 71, it became Colonia Pia Flavia Constans Emerita Helvetiorum Foederata. The town was destroyed or badly damaged around AD 260, and it was progressively abandoned thereafter.
Garden Palatial House in Insula 7 in Aventicum
Keywords  archaeological garden axial plan bathhouses (water recreation structures) drains exedrae (site elements) mosaics (visual works) palaces peristyles (Roman courtyards) piscinae presence chambers  Garden Description The remains of a palatial house (Palais de Derrière la Tour) were recently uncovered in excavations on the western edge of the city in an area characterized by luxurious domestic dwellings (Fig. 1). The house in its final state, from the Severan period to the middle of the 3rd century, had a peristyle courtyard measuring 42 x 69 meters. North of the courtyard was a reception room 12 x 18 meters in plan with a mosaic floor.
The courtyard was on two levels, divided on the north by a terrace wall with two small exedrae, possibly pools. An axially arranged central pathway between the reception room on the north and an apsed triclinium on the south further divided the courtyard into an eastern and a western half. Steps led up to the triclinium and to the northern wing of the house. A ground level gutter ran around the courtyard, and a covered drain crossed it beneath the central path. It can reasonably be assumed that the courtyard was designed as a garden (G in Fig. 1) with garden elements such as the path and the exedral pools. With the addition on the northeast of another wing terminating in a bath complex, the building ultimately had a length of around 200 meters. The excavators believe that the building in its latest phase had official character.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the courtyard house or palace on the western fringe of Insula 7, with a garden courtyard (G) with two small apsidal pools on one side. Plan adapted from Morel 1995, fig. 4. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Severnan Period - Middle of 3rd century
Bibliography  J. Morel, “Avenches VD, Derrière la Tour et insula 7 : Fouilles 1989/1990,” Annuaire de la Société Suisse de Préhistoire et d’Archéologie 74, 1991: 214-220, fig. 2. (worldcat) J. Morel, “Avenches, Palais de Derrière la Tour,” Bull. de l’Association Pro Aventico 37, 1995: 206-209, fig. 4.(worldcat) J. Morel, “L’habitat,” in : A. Hochuli-Gysel, ed., Avenches, capitale des Helvètes, Archéologie Suisse 24.1 2001: 47-49, fig. 62.(worldcat)  Pleiades ID 177495
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 14 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rustic villa at Rheinbach-Flerzheim</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/rheinbach-flerzheim/rheinbach-flerzheim/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:57:12 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/rheinbach-flerzheim/rheinbach-flerzheim/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Province Description Location Rheinbach-Flerzheim
Garden Rustic villa at Rheinbach-Flerzheim
Keywords  villae rusticae hedges bathhouses (water recreation structures) kitchen gardens piscinae  Garden Description There was no division between the residential and service parts of this modest farm. The house, with its bath (A and B on plan), and the outbuildings were built of stone at the beginning of the 2nd century (Plan 1). The winged corridor type house of this villa rustica was 37 m. long and 20 m. wide, and it had a bath attached to the back.
Enclosing the farm complex was a hedge or row of trees, the planting trenches of which were uncovered in excavations (gray wavy border on plan). Based on the palaeobotanical evidence of carbonised plant remains and pollen, a kitchen garden near the house and fruit trees on the property have been reconstructed. In front of the entrance to the main residence at the south were the remains of a small pool lined with clay. This has been taken as evidence for an ornamental garden surrounding the pool. On a farm of this modest size and simplicity, however, an ornamental garden seems rather unlikely. The farm was occupied until the mid-5th century.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the farmyard with its house (A) and bath (B) enclosed by a hedge (grey line). The open circles are wells. Adapted from Carroll 2001, fig. 38. (Rights statement).   Images Dates Second century CE to mid-fifth century CE
Bibliography  M. Gechter, &amp;ldquo;Der römische Gutshof von Rheinbach-Flerzheim,&amp;rdquo; in Spurensicherung. Archäologische Denkmalpflege in der Euregio Maas-Rhein, Mainz, 1992, pp. 249-54, 452-60. worldcat M. Carroll, Romans, Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 79, fig. 38. worldcat  Pleiades ID 981524
TGN ID 7192890
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 25 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Bancroft</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/bancroft/bancroft_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2020 18:04:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/bancroft/bancroft_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Bancroft
Garden Rural Villa in Bancroft
Keywords  archaeological garden bathhouses (water recreation structures) drains gazebos horticultural containers piscinae villae rusticae  Garden Description Excavations between 1983 and 1986 at this site in Buckinghamshire revealed a Roman villa of the winged corridor type, which was built in the late 3rd century and rebuilt and enlarged in the mid-4th century (Fig.1).
From the two projecting wings of the house at the northeast and southeast two walls ran eastward, forming an enclosed courtyard 35.5 meters in width and ca. 42 meters in length in front of the 4th century house. In the centre of the yard was a stone-built rectangular fishpond (P in Fig. 1), 2.6 x 13 meters in size and 50-80 centimeters deep which was continually fed by a drain running from an overflow in the cold plunge bath at the south end of the house. An overflow at the east end of the pool may have led to a nearby stream. Although traces of plantings or planting beds were not preserved in the gravelly subsoil, a shallow rectangular depression just west of the fishpool, filled with dark humic soil, may represent a flowerbed through which the water pipe feeding the pool ran. The courtyard therefore was at least partially planted as a garden (G in Fig. 1). Adjacent to the courtyard enclosure at the south was an octagonal structure with stone walls, interpreted as a possible gazebo (A in Fig. 1).
The villa complex that preceded the winged corridor house is also of interest in regard to gardens. The earlier aisled house of late 1st to late 2nd century date was part of a series of buildings and enclosures that included a walled area to the northeast measuring 27 x 18.3 meters in size. Inside this enclosure was a deposit of dark humic soil between 4 and 6 centimeters deep. Environmental analysis of soil samples from the enclosure suggests that the area was used as a kitchen garden with plants such as brassicas, celery, mustard, coriander, summer savory and caper spurge. Three ceramic vessels with at least one hole pierced through the side or the base, possibly planting pots, may have been associated with this phase of the villa garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the villa with its garden courtyard (G), a central pool (P), and a possible gazebo (A). Adapted from Zeepvat 1991, fig. 5.4.(Rights statement.)   Dates Roman villa&amp;hellip; built in the late 3rd century and rebuilt and enlarged in the mid-4th century.
Excavation Dates 1983-1986
Bibliography  R. J. Williams and R. J. Zeepvat, Bancroft. The late Bronze Age and Iron Age Settlement and Roman Villa and Temple-Mausoleum. Buckinghamshire Archaeological Society Monograph Series 7, Aylesbury, 1994, pp. 154, 163, 188-191, figs. 66, 80, 83, 85, 93, 101-103, pls. 57-59. (worldcat) R.J. Zeepvat, “Roman Gardens in Britain,” in: A. E. Brown, ed., Garden Archaeology. Council for British Archaeology Research Report 78, London, 1991, pp. 56-58, fig. 5.4. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 79312
TGN ID 7030316
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 07 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>