<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>fountains on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/fountains/</link>
    <description>Recent content in fountains on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Jul 2020 16:44:26 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/fountains/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban House or Schola in Aquincum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/aquincum/aquincum_urban_house_or_schola/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jul 2020 16:44:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/aquincum/aquincum_urban_house_or_schola/</guid>
      <description>Province Pannonia
Province Description Location Aquincum
Aquincum (Pleiades)
Location Description This town on the Danube river acquired the rank of municipium under Hadrian in 124 A.D. In the year 194 it was granted colonial status.
Garden Urban House or Schola in Aquincum
Keywords  archaeological garden bathhouses (water recreation structures) fountains peristyles (Roman courtyards) piscinae statues statuettes (free-standing sculpture)  Garden Description Very few houses of Mediterranean type have been discovered, and only one can be said with certainty to have had a garden (Fig. 1, G in Fig. 1). The peristyle courtyard was a prominent feature of this house of irregular plan and substantial size near the southern city wall. The house dates to the 3rd century, and it is thought to have been a clubhouse or schola for young men (collegium iuventutis), complete with a bath suite. In the middle of the courtyard, framed on four sides by a low wall supporting columns, was a square masonry pool (Fig. 2). In the center of the pool was a fountain consisting of a small marble satyr standing on a column of the same material. This decorative element and the unpaved ground strongly suggest the existence of a garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of a building with a peristyle garden courtyard (G) and a pool in its center. Adapted from Polenz and Póczy 1986, fig. 47.(Rights statement.)   Images   Fig. 2: The excavated courtyard building with its peristyle garden. Photo courtesy of M. Carroll.)   Dates 3rd century
Bibliography  A. Mócsy, Pannonia and Upper Moesia. A History of the Middle Danube Provinces of the Roman Empire, London, 1974, p. 166, pl. 16b. (worldcat) H. Polenz and K. Póczy, Das römische Budapest. Neue Ausgrabungen und Funde in Aquincum, Münster, 1986, p. 124, fig. 47, pl. 10. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 1971301
TGN ID 8713146
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House in the Rue du Palais de Justice in Vesontio</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vesontio/vesontio_house_in_the_rue_du_palais_de_justice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2020 16:58:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vesontio/vesontio_house_in_the_rue_du_palais_de_justice/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Vesontio
Vesontio (Pleiades)
Location Description The defensibility offered by this unique geography made Caesar hasten to occupy Vesontio in 58 BC. The town came to have all the usual Roman structures– forum, baths, aqueduct, and amphitheater (on the other side of the Doubs, to the northwest.) But the most visible remnant is the Porte Noire (Black Gate) [3], a triumphal arch built by Marcus Aurelius at the southeastern end of the cardo maximus, today Grande Rue and still the center of city life.
Archaeology in a downtown area is always a matter of seizing opportunities as they are presented by new construction, remembering and recording what was found, and coming back years later to complete the picture. A good example of this process is at our second site, [2] on the map. In 1973, the Neptune Mosaic was discovered in rue de Lorraine, one of the largest floor decorations in all Gaul. The extent of the mosaic under nearby buildings made full excavation impossible. More than thirty years later, in 2004, construction of a gymnasium for the Collège Lumière (a middle school) gave archaeologists access to much more of the site, about 3000 square meters, for a salvage excavation. As expected, the continuation of the Neptune mosaic was found; moreover, three other mosaics of high quality, along with columns, sculpted blocks, peristyles, and monumental pools came to light. The results of this excavation have not been published; we are grateful to the excavators for sharing their preliminary results.
Garden House in the Rue du Palais de Justice in Vesontio
Keywords archaeological garden \
 domus fountains hypocausts mosaics (visual works) opus sectile (visual works) opus signinum oeci peristyles (columnades) piscinae porticoes terrazzo water wells  Garden Description In 2000-2001, at the time of construction a new judiciary facility, an area of 2000 square meters was excavated at the center of this loop. The results are in large part unpublished. On land that had been occupied since the end of the second century BC, two houses of perishable materials were built in the eastern part of the site in the beginning of the first century AD. They were abandoned at the beginning of the Flavian epoch, and replaced by two imposing domus that lasted up to the middle of the third century. They stood on opposite sides of a property line wall (tinted in purple in Fig. 1) that was parallel to a cardo running in a northwest-to-southeast direction some hundred meters away. The two houses had slightly different orientations. The eastern house doubtless opened onto a southwest-northeast street passing 50 meters beyond the eastern limit of the excavation but partially brought to light in 1989-90 during excavations when a new parking facility was being built for the city hall. In this house, two independent structures (oecus) (tinted pink in the figure) with floors once decorated with mosaics since disappeared are wrapped about and connected by a portico (yellow tint) of complex plan with galleries 3 meters wide and opening onto an open space (green tint) covering 110 square meters. The counterpart of this portico is in part visible on the other side of the larger room. An incompletely known peristyle borders this oecus to the east (on the lower right edge of the plan). Its gallery was decorated with a terrazzo floor of opus signinum with accents of crustae, thin stone slices of which an opus sectile is made. In this phase, the north domus had a peristyle of 75 square meters with galleries on three sides. To the west (lower left corner of the plan), there was a large open space of nearly 500 square meters, which may have been a garden. At its west end, the wall of an incomplete building ran by a well and a masonry square 2.16 meters on a side which may have been the base of a shrine or monument. These structures were aligned with the property line wall. There was as yet no pool.
In the second half of the second century, the “garden” was restructured. The building on the west side was abandoned, the shrine or monument was kept, and a large pool put in at the eastern end supported against the wall of a terrace supporting the house to the east and consequently having the same orientation. This rectangular pool (21.2 x 3.5 m) had on the garden side a semicircular apse 6.9 meters in diameter. As part of the same architectural ensemble, a portico formed the retro-scene of the pool. Its opus signinum floor was 80 centimeters above the surface of the pool. Another, wider portico ran along the north side of the area. A shim-shaped gap existed between it and the property-line wall because of the difference in orientation. The monumental character of the pool and the north portico suggests that this garden may have been independent of both houses and was possibly a public space or belonged to a house further west, outside the limits of excavation.
At the beginning of the third century, the two domus were transformed. In particular, polychrome mosaics were installed in the east house and rooms with hypocausts in the north house. The little shrine or monument at the western end of the garden was eliminated, but the pool was reconstructed without alteration. The paving stones that had been in a pool were in part removed and used to build a 3.8 x 2.9 meter platform which served as the base, presumably, of a quadrangular fountain in the north house in an open space which replaced the peristyle, which was then destroyed.
Images Images not available (?) FIGURES:
 Fig. 1: Houses at the Palais de Justice Fig. 2: Axonometric representation  Dates Beginning of the Flavian epoch - middle of the third century
Excavation Dates 2000-2001
Bibliography  C. Gaston, “Un bassin monumental et une fontaine dans les fouille du Palais de Justice de Besancon,” Revue Archéologique de l&amp;rsquo;Est, t. 52, 2003, p.417-428. Christophe Gaston: “Données récentes sur l&amp;rsquo;achitecture antique à Besançon,” Archéopages/Inrap. No. 8, Nov. 2002, p. 28-35. Laurent Vaxelaire, Philippe Barral, “Besançon: de l’oppidum à la ville romaine” in La naissance de la ville dans l’Antiquité, M. Reddé et al. ed., Paris, 2003, p. 254-256.  Pleiades ID 177657
TGN ID 7008356
Contributor Claudine Monier (ORCID: N/A)
Christophe Gaston (ORCID: https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6865-5108)
Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 19 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Bad Kreuznach</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/bad_kreuznach/bad_kreuznach_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 12:39:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/bad_kreuznach/bad_kreuznach_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Bad Kreuznach
Bad Kreuznach (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Bad Kreuznach
Keywords  apsed triclinium colonnades cryptoportici fountains gutters (building drainage components) lararia mosaics (visual works) peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes villae rusticae  Garden Description This villa, almost 6000 square meters in size, gives eloquent testimony to the wealth and status of the owner of the rural estate. The estate was built in the second half of the 2nd century and occupied until its destruction around 275.
The three-storied villa with more than 50 rooms on the ground floor alone, many decorated with mosaics and imported marble revetment, was centered on a colonnaded garden courtyard (G in Fig. 1). Many of the sandstone columns from the peristyle, as well as fragments of sculpture from the garden, were found in the courtyard. The house was built into a hill, and the courtyard was terraced on two levels. Around the edges of the garden was a ground level gutter. From the apsed triclinium on the south, with a mosaic floor and a marble fountain in the middle, there was an excellent view of the garden.
At the northeast of the villa was a garden (G in Fig. 1) with a lararium. On the southwest there was a garden (G in Fig. 1) with a fountain. The northern facade had a cryptoporticus below and a porticoed corridor on the story above. The service area of the villa rustica lay in front of the villa to the north.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the rural villa with gardens (G) in the central courtyard and in the corners of the house. Plan adapted from Cüppers 1990, fig. 204.(Rights statement)   Dates Second half of 2nd century - around 275
Bibliography  G. Rupprecht, &amp;ldquo;Die Kreuznacher Mosaikbodenvilla. Kurzbericht (Stand: April 1977),&amp;rdquo; Saalburg Jahrbuch 34, 1977:78-87. G. Rupprecht, &amp;ldquo;Leben auf dem Land,&amp;rdquo; Archäologie in Deutschland 4, 1986: 36-39. (worldcat) Heinz Cüppers, Die Römer in Rheinland-Pfalz, Stuttgart, 1990, pp.321-323, fig. 204. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981525
TGN ID 7012371
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 15 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House in Insula 13 in Aventicum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_house_in_insula_13/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 10:06:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_house_in_insula_13/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Aventicum
Aventicum (Pleiades)
Location Description The town was established in the Augustan period as the civitas capital of the Helvetii. At this time the orthogonal street grid was laid out. Most probably in AD 71, it became Colonia Pia Flavia Constans Emerita Helvetiorum Foederata. The town was destroyed or badly damaged around AD 260, and it was progressively abandoned thereafter.
Garden House in Insula 13 in Aventicum
Keywords  archaeological garden bathhouses (water recreation structures) corridors fountains garden pavilions gutters (building drainage components) insulae peristyles (Roman courtyards) piscinae reception rooms  Garden Description Recent excavations in Insula 13 on the northwestern edge of the town have uncovered the remains of two large and luxurious houses separated from each other by a narrow corridor. They date to the late 1st century and were occupied until the middle of the 3rd century. Both buildings had a length of 60 meters, spanning the length of the insula. The eastern house included a private bath suite and an apsed reception room on the southwest.
The most remarkable feature of the building was a T-shaped garden courtyard (G in Fig. 1) surrounded by a peristyle on all sides (Fig. 1). A ground line gutter ran around the edge of the courtyard. In the southern part of the garden was a large pool paved with limestone slabs and measuring 6 x 12 meters On the northern edge of the pool was a rectangular fountain. To the north of this was a square structure measuring 5.40 x 5.40 meters which may have been a garden pavilion.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of a courtyard house in Insula 13 with a peristyle garden (G) and pool (grey). Plan adapted from Carroll 2001, fig. 20. (Rights statement)   Dates Houses: Late 1st century - Middle of 3rd century
Bibliography  J. Morel, &amp;ldquo;Chronique archéologique 1993,&amp;rdquo; Bull. de l&amp;rsquo;Association Pro Aventico 35, 1993: 19-21, figs. 8, 11. J. Morel, “L’habitat,” in : A. Hochuli-Gysel, ed., Avenches, capitale des Helvètes, Archéologie Suisse 24.1, 2001: 45-46, figs. 58, 60. (worldcat) M. Carroll, Romans, Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 55, fig. 20. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 177495
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 15 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>