<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/colonia_ulpia_xanten/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:54:29 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/colonia_ulpia_xanten/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Houses of Insula 7 in Colonia Ulpia Traiana</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/colonia_ulpia_xanten/colonia_xanten_insula7/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/colonia_ulpia_xanten/colonia_xanten_insula7/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Xanten
Xanten (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Industrial quarter
Sublocation Description This insula southeast of the forum is commonly referred to as an industrial quarter (Plan 1). It was divided into several long, narrow plots on which were houses, shops and workshops.
Garden The houses of Insula 7 in Colonia Ulpia Traiana (Xanten)
Keywords insulae
kitchen gardens
courtyards
Garden Description Between the buildings were open areas, some paved and equipped with ovens and pottery kilns, wells and latrines, others unpaved. Some of the small courtyards have been reconstructed by the excavators as kitchen gardens and shrine gardens (Image 1). Organic material from a well in this insula included the remains of peas, beans, lentils, apples, pears and herbs. These fruits and vegetables may have grown in kitchen gardens in the insula, but they may, on the other hand, have been brought into the city from nearby farms.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the houses in *Insula* 7 with paved (stippled) and unpaved courtyards. The black dots are wells. Adapted from Precht and Rüger 1991. Rights statement.   Images   Image 1. Model of the houses in *Insula* 7 with courtyard garden. Photo courtesy of M. Carroll.   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  H.G. Horn, ed., Die Römer in Nordrhein-Westfalen, Stuttgart, 1987, pp. 634-636, fig. 542 (incorrectly labeled as Insula 26). worldcat G. Precht and C.B. Rüger, Archaologischer Stadtplan. Colonia Ulpia Traiana, Cologne, 1991. worldcat  Periodo ID Pleiades ID 108896
TGN ID 7208125
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 July 2020
Related articles </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>