<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Lusitania on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/categories/lusitania/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Lusitania on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 11:20:32 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/categories/lusitania/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Basilica-House of the Theater</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/emerita_augusta/basilica-house_of_the_theater/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/emerita_augusta/basilica-house_of_the_theater/</guid>
      <description>Province Lusitania
Lusitania(Pleiades)
Province Description Despite the prior existence of urban centers like Metellinum, the capital of Lusitania was a new foundation, the Colonia Augusta Emerita (Mérida), which would also serve as the capital of one of the smaller juridical units (conventus) and would be the scene of flourishing activity in the succeeding centuries, its prosperity lasting until the late Roman and Visigothic era. Subsequently, a series of well-known Roman cities were built in what was then Lusitania but is now partly in Portugal and partly in Spain. As well as the capital, there were Conimbriga, Salmantica, Evora, Olisipo (now Lisbon), Pax Iulia (now Beja), and Metallium Viscascense (Aljustrel), this last recognized as the capital of an important mining area. The series of wealthy villae, such as that of La Cocosa, Milreu or San Cucufate are particularly noteworthy. Another of the important elements of the Roman era is the series of still visible ways of communication, of which the Vía de la Plata has most remaining, especially in the sections of Baños de Montemayor in Cáceres or the bridges that cross the rivers, such as that of San Pedro de Alcántara, or of Mérida.
Location Emerita Augusta
Emerita Augusta (Pleiades)
Location Description Geopolitical and economic motives together facilitated the prosperity of this great center of the Iberian peninsula. Marcus Vipsanius Agrippa, son-in-law of the emperor, was a benefactor of Augusta Emerita. The city was situated on the right bank of the Anas River (Rio Guardiana), today the Guadiana River. The site had the advantage of an easily crossed ford at the mouth of the Barraeca River (Rio Albarregas), and was an ideal site for surveillance and defense. The area immediately surrounding Augusta Emerita had rich granite quarries, sands from the riverbed, and other types of rock for the new constructions. The city’s topography determined the new rectilinear urban layout. The variations in ground level, due to small hills in the land, probably necessitated terracing, which is still discernible in today’s modern network of streets. The bridge over the Guadiana, the longest in the peninsula with a length of almost 800 meters, provided the N-S axis to which the street grid was aligned. The new colony also had an ambitious system of urban drainage. The sewers and water lines form a complete underground complex of canals. The works of hydraulic engineering, whose dates of construction and later stages of development are debated, support the notion that Augusta Emerita was a city with a grand, forward-looking vision.
At the intersection of the decumanus and cardo were two fora, one for the city&amp;rsquo;s functions and one for the Province&amp;rsquo;s functions. Some of the monumental buildings have been excavated. The Mérida fora, whose layouts resemble those in the other western imperial provinces, have iconographic programs that resemble those of Rome; the forum of Augusta Emerita is a particularly faithful reflection of the Forum Augustum. This imitative trend appears also in the two other provincial capitals of Hispania, Tarraco and Corduba and underscores the power which Augustan images and architecture had in the political, ideological fabric of the provinces.
The area of Augusta Emerita best known today, because of extensive excavations, is around the so-called Temple of Diana. The temple is actually dedicated to the imperial cult. The structures devoted to public performance - theater, amphitheater, and circus - surrounded the urban center. The theater was begun in 16-15 BC and the amphitheater in 8 BC, during the first decades of colonial presence. Augusta Emerita’s necropolis ran around the city’s urban perimeter and expanded as the city proper grew.
Because most of evidence from Merida was unearthed in old excavations, the context of many ancient objects is unknown. There is also a lack of analytical data on many of the areas which must originally have been gardened. The classification of the gardens of the Colonia Augusta Emerita is still under analysis. The study by Moreno is a basic survey article and should be understood to be part of all the bibliographies for Merida.
Bibliography  I. C. Moreno, “Los jardines de Mérida,” Mérida, excavaciones arqueológicas Nº. 2, 1996 , pp. 303-328. (worldcat)  Garden Basilica-House of the Theater
Keywords  colonnades courtyards impluvia  Garden Description This late-imperial domus was discovered by J. Ramón Mélida while excavating the backstage of the Theater. The existence of two rooms with apses at the east end led to the interpretation of the building as an early Christian basilica. Few of the structures in this residence of the 2nd and 4th centuries are visible today. These include a colonnaded courtyard with columns on small white marble bases, three each on the north and south sides and two each on the east and west sides, not counting those on the corners. In the northeast corner of the courtyard was a shallow pool resembling an impluvium. It was shifted off-center in the garden to be almost on the axis of the larger of the two apses. A rill, coated in opus signinum, ran along its north, south and west sides. In the center was a cistern capped by a wellhead made of marble slabs and lined with several layers of opus signinum.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the Basilica - House of the Theater. Adapted from Cassilla Moreno, p.315.   Dates 2nd and 4th centuries CE
Bibliography  R. Durán Cabello, ‘La técnica constructiva de la llamada ‘Casa Basílica’ de Mérida’, in La casa urbana hispanorromana : ponencias y comunicaciones., 1991, pp. 359-69. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 256155
TGN ID 7007664
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date 6 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Alcazaba</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/emerita_augusta/house_of_alcazaba/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/emerita_augusta/house_of_alcazaba/</guid>
      <description>Province Lusitania
Lusitania(Pleiades)
Province Description Despite the prior existence of urban centers like Metellinum, the capital of Lusitania was a new foundation, the Colonia Augusta Emerita (Mérida), which would also serve as the capital of one of the smaller juridical units (conventus) and would be the scene of flourishing activity in the succeeding centuries, its prosperity lasting until the late Roman and Visigothic era. Subsequently, a series of well-known Roman cities were built in what was then Lusitania but is now partly in Portugal and partly in Spain. As well as the capital, there were Conimbriga, Salmantica, Evora, Olisipo (now Lisbon), Pax Iulia (now Beja), and Metallium Viscascense (Aljustrel), this last recognized as the capital of an important mining area. The series of wealthy villae, such as that of La Cocosa, Milreu or San Cucufate are particularly noteworthy. Another of the important elements of the Roman era is the series of still visible ways of communication, of which the Vía de la Plata has most remaining, especially in the sections of Baños de Montemayor in Cáceres or the bridges that cross the rivers, such as that of San Pedro de Alcántara, or of Mérida.
Location Emerita Augusta
Emerita Augusta (Pleiades)
Location Description Geopolitical and economic motives together facilitated the prosperity of this great center of the Iberian peninsula. Marcus Vipsanius Agrippa, son-in-law of the emperor, was a benefactor of Augusta Emerita. The city was situated on the right bank of the Anas River (Rio Guardiana), today the Guadiana River. The site had the advantage of an easily crossed ford at the mouth of the Barraeca River (Rio Albarregas), and was an ideal site for surveillance and defense. The area immediately surrounding Augusta Emerita had rich granite quarries, sands from the riverbed, and other types of rock for the new constructions. The city’s topography determined the new rectilinear urban layout. The variations in ground level, due to small hills in the land, probably necessitated terracing, which is still discernible in today’s modern network of streets. The bridge over the Guadiana, the longest in the peninsula with a length of almost 800 meters, provided the N-S axis to which the street grid was aligned. The new colony also had an ambitious system of urban drainage. The sewers and water lines form a complete underground complex of canals. The works of hydraulic engineering, whose dates of construction and later stages of development are debated, support the notion that Augusta Emerita was a city with a grand, forward-looking vision.
At the intersection of the decumanus and cardo were two fora, one for the city&amp;rsquo;s functions and one for the Province&amp;rsquo;s functions. Some of the monumental buildings have been excavated. The Mérida fora, whose layouts resemble those in the other western imperial provinces, have iconographic programs that resemble those of Rome; the forum of Augusta Emerita is a particularly faithful reflection of the Forum Augustum. This imitative trend appears also in the two other provincial capitals of Hispania, Tarraco and Corduba and underscores the power which Augustan images and architecture had in the political, ideological fabric of the provinces.
The area of Augusta Emerita best known today, because of extensive excavations, is around the so-called Temple of Diana. The temple is actually dedicated to the imperial cult. The structures devoted to public performance - theater, amphitheater, and circus - surrounded the urban center. The theater was begun in 16-15 BC and the amphitheater in 8 BC, during the first decades of colonial presence. Augusta Emerita’s necropolis ran around the city’s urban perimeter and expanded as the city proper grew.
Because most of evidence from Merida was unearthed in old excavations, the context of many ancient objects is unknown. There is also a lack of analytical data on many of the areas which must originally have been gardened. The classification of the gardens of the Colonia Augusta Emerita is still under analysis. The study by Moreno is a basic survey article and should be understood to be part of all the bibliographies for Merida.
Bibliography  I. C. Moreno, “Los jardines de Mérida,” Mérida, excavaciones arqueológicas Nº. 2, 1996 , pp. 303-328. (worldcat)  Garden House of Alcazaba
Keywords  peristyles (Roman courtyards) mosaics (visual works)  Garden Description Within the enclosure of the Islamic Alcazaba, west of the city, are the remains of this great late-Imperial domus, excavated in the 1970&amp;rsquo;s by D. José Álvarez Sáenz de Buruaga. It remains unpublished. The principal element of its peristyle is a deep rectangular pool with a semicircular extension from the middle of one long side. The room opposite this pool, the largest of the house, was paved in opus sectile; several other rooms surrounding the peristyle had mosaic floors. The presence of a peristyle and pool strongly suggests a garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the House of Alcazaba. Adapted from Palma Garcia, p. 350.   Dates 4th century CE
Excavation Dates 1970&amp;rsquo;s
Bibliography  L. J. Hernández Ramírez, La pintura mural romana de Mérida. (Inserta en la estructura urbana y doméstica de la ciudad, UNED (unpublished doctoral dissertation), 1993, pp. 634-702, lam. 10 E. García Sandoval, “Excavaciones arqueológicas en la zona de Mérida: La Casa del Anfiteatro,&amp;quot; in C.A.N., 8(1964): 469-477 (worldcat) F. Palma Garcia, “Las casas romanos intramuros en Mérida” Mérida, excavaciones arqueológicos. 1997, p. 347-65 (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 64187403
TGN ID 8713074
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date 6 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Amphitheater</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/emerita_augusta/house_of_the_amphitheater/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/emerita_augusta/house_of_the_amphitheater/</guid>
      <description>Province Lusitania
Lusitania(Pleiades)
Province Description Despite the prior existence of urban centers like Metellinum, the capital of Lusitania was a new foundation, the Colonia Augusta Emerita (Mérida), which would also serve as the capital of one of the smaller juridical units (conventus) and would be the scene of flourishing activity in the succeeding centuries, its prosperity lasting until the late Roman and Visigothic era. Subsequently, a series of well-known Roman cities were built in what was then Lusitania but is now partly in Portugal and partly in Spain. As well as the capital, there were Conimbriga, Salmantica, Evora, Olisipo (now Lisbon), Pax Iulia (now Beja), and Metallium Viscascense (Aljustrel), this last recognized as the capital of an important mining area. The series of wealthy villae, such as that of La Cocosa, Milreu or San Cucufate are particularly noteworthy. Another of the important elements of the Roman era is the series of still visible ways of communication, of which the Vía de la Plata has most remaining, especially in the sections of Baños de Montemayor in Cáceres or the bridges that cross the rivers, such as that of San Pedro de Alcántara, or of Mérida.
Location Emerita Augusta
Emerita Augusta (Pleiades)
Location Description Geopolitical and economic motives together facilitated the prosperity of this great center of the Iberian peninsula. Marcus Vipsanius Agrippa, son-in-law of the emperor, was a benefactor of Augusta Emerita. The city was situated on the right bank of the Anas River (Rio Guardiana), today the Guadiana River. The site had the advantage of an easily crossed ford at the mouth of the Barraeca River (Rio Albarregas), and was an ideal site for surveillance and defense. The area immediately surrounding Augusta Emerita had rich granite quarries, sands from the riverbed, and other types of rock for the new constructions. The city’s topography determined the new rectilinear urban layout. The variations in ground level, due to small hills in the land, probably necessitated terracing, which is still discernible in today’s modern network of streets. The bridge over the Guadiana, the longest in the peninsula with a length of almost 800 meters, provided the N-S axis to which the street grid was aligned. The new colony also had an ambitious system of urban drainage. The sewers and water lines form a complete underground complex of canals. The works of hydraulic engineering, whose dates of construction and later stages of development are debated, support the notion that Augusta Emerita was a city with a grand, forward-looking vision.
At the intersection of the decumanus and cardo were two fora, one for the city&amp;rsquo;s functions and one for the Province&amp;rsquo;s functions. Some of the monumental buildings have been excavated. The Mérida fora, whose layouts resemble those in the other western imperial provinces, have iconographic programs that resemble those of Rome; the forum of Augusta Emerita is a particularly faithful reflection of the Forum Augustum. This imitative trend appears also in the two other provincial capitals of Hispania, Tarraco and Corduba and underscores the power which Augustan images and architecture had in the political, ideological fabric of the provinces.
The area of Augusta Emerita best known today, because of extensive excavations, is around the so-called Temple of Diana. The temple is actually dedicated to the imperial cult. The structures devoted to public performance - theater, amphitheater, and circus - surrounded the urban center. The theater was begun in 16-15 BC and the amphitheater in 8 BC, during the first decades of colonial presence. Augusta Emerita’s necropolis ran around the city’s urban perimeter and expanded as the city proper grew.
Because most of evidence from Merida was unearthed in old excavations, the context of many ancient objects is unknown. There is also a lack of analytical data on many of the areas which must originally have been gardened. The classification of the gardens of the Colonia Augusta Emerita is still under analysis. The study by Moreno is a basic survey article and should be understood to be part of all the bibliographies for Merida.
Bibliography  I. C. Moreno, “Los jardines de Mérida,” Mérida, excavaciones arqueológicas Nº. 2, 1996 , pp. 303-328. (worldcat)  Garden House of the Amphitheater
Keywords  peristyles (columnades) mosaics (visual works) water wells colonnades courtyards triclinia  Garden Description Next to the Amphitheater, on the east side of Augusta Emerita, are the remains of two extramural residences. The archaeological excavations of these domestic structures were begun in 1947 by José de Calasanz Serra Ráfols, who was succeeded by M. Pous, Álvarez Sáenz de Buruaga, and E. García Sandoval. Although chronologically distinct, the two houses are known together as the &amp;ldquo;House of the Amphitheater&amp;rdquo; due to their proximity to that monument.
The first of these houses is called the &amp;ldquo;House of the Water Tower&amp;rdquo; after a nearby water tower (Number 4 in LUS 4.1.1) and dates to the second century A.D. Today, only the remains of a few chambers and a colonnaded courtyard (Fig. 3) with a small channel running around the perimeter of its pavement survive.
The second house, which is better preserved, is more correctly dubbed the &amp;ldquo;House of the Amphitheater&amp;rdquo; (Figs. 4 and 5). It dates to the third century A.D. and remained in use until the fifth century A.D. The &amp;ldquo;House of the Amphitheater&amp;rdquo; was organized around a colonnaded courtyard of ample dimensions, whose interior served as a garden with individual rooms opening onto it. Roughly trapezoidal, it was surrounded on all sides by colonnades with granite columns originally sheathed with red stucco. The longer east and west sides had six columns, while the shorter north and south sides had five. A low rubble wall contained the lower portions of the shafts on the north, south, and east sides, leaving the west side open for easy access to the garden. At the foot of the colonnade and running along the garden edge (except on the west) was a canal of some depth with a semicircular curve on its eastern edge in front of an important chamber. Next to the curve and within the garden, a well was found.
The house, of sizeable proportions, boasted important painted and mosaic decoration. Of the three chambers situated along the southeast gallery, the center chamber had opus signinum pavement and has been interpreted as a triclinium, from which one could enjoy magnificent views of the garden. The pavement of the contiguous chamber to the northeast has a beautiful mosaic with representations of Venus and Cupid surrounded with floral designsand &amp;ldquo;The Mosaic of the Grape Harvest&amp;rdquo; (Mosaico de la Vendimia). They were repaired in antiquity.
An equally important second nucleus of this house consisted of a complex of rooms at its east end. This area had handsome mosaic pavements and communicated with the aforementioned peristyle through an L-shaped passageway. Its largest chamber, which had the character of a show room, if not a triclinium, is known as the &amp;ldquo;Hall of the Fish Mosaic&amp;rdquo; (Habitación del Mosaico de los Peces) and is dated to the 3rd century AD. Although this second group of rooms was probably organized around courtyards or gardens, none have been documented because this part of the residence remains unexcavated. The peristyle of the House of the Amphitheater, as well as the plan of the entire residence, has close parallels in the eastern Mediterranean which have been thoroughly studied by A. Balil.
Plans   Fig. 1: Relation of House of the Amphitheater (area 5 on the right) and House of the Water Tower (area 4 on the left. Also shown are: (1) a section of the city wall, (2) aqueduct of St. Lazarus, (3) the water tower, and (6) a mausoleum from the second half of the 3rd century. Adapted from the tourist guide issued by the Mérida Consorzio.     Fig. 2: Plan of the House of the Amphitheater. Adapted from Casillas Moreno, where it was taken from De Alvarado Barrena.   Images   Fig. 3: Photo looking northeast over the peristyle garden of the House of the Amphitheater.   Dates 2nd century CE and 3rd CE
Excavation Dates from 1947
Bibliography  A. Balil Illana, A. 1976: &amp;ldquo;Sobre la arquitectura doméstica en Augusta Emerita&amp;rdquo;, Augusta Emerita Actas del Bimilenario de Mérida, Mérida, 75-91. (worldcat) E. García Sandoval, Excavaciones arqueológicas en la zona de Mérida: La Casa del Anfiteatro,&amp;quot; in C.A.N., 8 (i964): 469-477 (worldcat) E. García Sandoval, Informe sobre las casa romanas de Mérida y excavaciones en la «Casa del Anfiteatro»,&amp;quot; in Excavaciones Arqueológicas en España nº. 49, Madrid, 1964. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 256155
TGN ID 7007664
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date 6 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Hill Garden</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/emerita_augusta/house_of_the_hill_garden/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/emerita_augusta/house_of_the_hill_garden/</guid>
      <description>Province Lusitania
Lusitania(Pleiades)
Province Description Despite the prior existence of urban centers like Metellinum, the capital of Lusitania was a new foundation, the Colonia Augusta Emerita (Mérida), which would also serve as the capital of one of the smaller juridical units (conventus) and would be the scene of flourishing activity in the succeeding centuries, its prosperity lasting until the late Roman and Visigothic era. Subsequently, a series of well-known Roman cities were built in what was then Lusitania but is now partly in Portugal and partly in Spain. As well as the capital, there were Conimbriga, Salmantica, Evora, Olisipo (now Lisbon), Pax Iulia (now Beja), and Metallium Viscascense (Aljustrel), this last recognized as the capital of an important mining area. The series of wealthy villae, such as that of La Cocosa, Milreu or San Cucufate are particularly noteworthy. Another of the important elements of the Roman era is the series of still visible ways of communication, of which the Vía de la Plata has most remaining, especially in the sections of Baños de Montemayor in Cáceres or the bridges that cross the rivers, such as that of San Pedro de Alcántara, or of Mérida.
Location Emerita Augusta
Emerita Augusta (Pleiades)
Location Description Geopolitical and economic motives together facilitated the prosperity of this great center of the Iberian peninsula. Marcus Vipsanius Agrippa, son-in-law of the emperor, was a benefactor of Augusta Emerita. The city was situated on the right bank of the Anas River (Rio Guardiana), today the Guadiana River. The site had the advantage of an easily crossed ford at the mouth of the Barraeca River (Rio Albarregas), and was an ideal site for surveillance and defense. The area immediately surrounding Augusta Emerita had rich granite quarries, sands from the riverbed, and other types of rock for the new constructions. The city’s topography determined the new rectilinear urban layout. The variations in ground level, due to small hills in the land, probably necessitated terracing, which is still discernible in today’s modern network of streets. The bridge over the Guadiana, the longest in the peninsula with a length of almost 800 meters, provided the N-S axis to which the street grid was aligned. The new colony also had an ambitious system of urban drainage. The sewers and water lines form a complete underground complex of canals. The works of hydraulic engineering, whose dates of construction and later stages of development are debated, support the notion that Augusta Emerita was a city with a grand, forward-looking vision.
At the intersection of the decumanus and cardo were two fora, one for the city&amp;rsquo;s functions and one for the Province&amp;rsquo;s functions. Some of the monumental buildings have been excavated. The Mérida fora, whose layouts resemble those in the other western imperial provinces, have iconographic programs that resemble those of Rome; the forum of Augusta Emerita is a particularly faithful reflection of the Forum Augustum. This imitative trend appears also in the two other provincial capitals of Hispania, Tarraco and Corduba and underscores the power which Augustan images and architecture had in the political, ideological fabric of the provinces.
The area of Augusta Emerita best known today, because of extensive excavations, is around the so-called Temple of Diana. The temple is actually dedicated to the imperial cult. The structures devoted to public performance - theater, amphitheater, and circus - surrounded the urban center. The theater was begun in 16-15 BC and the amphitheater in 8 BC, during the first decades of colonial presence. Augusta Emerita’s necropolis ran around the city’s urban perimeter and expanded as the city proper grew.
Because most of evidence from Merida was unearthed in old excavations, the context of many ancient objects is unknown. There is also a lack of analytical data on many of the areas which must originally have been gardened. The classification of the gardens of the Colonia Augusta Emerita is still under analysis. The study by Moreno is a basic survey article and should be understood to be part of all the bibliographies for Merida.
Bibliography  I. C. Moreno, “Los jardines de Mérida,” Mérida, excavaciones arqueológicas Nº. 2, 1996 , pp. 303-328. (worldcat)  Garden House of the Hill Garden
Keywords  peristyles (columnades) mosaics (visual works)  Garden Description Very little is known about the characteristics of this intramurally situated domus, whose remains were discovered in 1976 during explorations in the grounds of the ‘Hill Garden.’ In the emergency excavations carried out by José Álvarez Sáenz de Buruaga, the remains of two peristyles were discovered with mural paintings and mosaic pavements dated to the end of the second or early third century A.D. The structures of this house, only partially excavated, have been buried again for the sake of preservation and are no longer visible.
Dates The end of the 2nd or early 3rd century AD
Bibliography  A. Blanco Freijeiro, Corpus de mosaicos romanos de España, 1(1978): 48-49. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 256155
TGN ID 7007664
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Mithraeum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/emerita_augusta/house_of_the_mithraeum/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/emerita_augusta/house_of_the_mithraeum/</guid>
      <description>Province Lusitania
Lusitania(Pleiades)
Province Description Despite the prior existence of urban centers like Metellinum, the capital of Lusitania was a new foundation, the Colonia Augusta Emerita (Mérida), which would also serve as the capital of one of the smaller juridical units (conventus) and would be the scene of flourishing activity in the succeeding centuries, its prosperity lasting until the late Roman and Visigothic era. Subsequently, a series of well-known Roman cities were built in what was then Lusitania but is now partly in Portugal and partly in Spain. As well as the capital, there were Conimbriga, Salmantica, Evora, Olisipo (now Lisbon), Pax Iulia (now Beja), and Metallium Viscascense (Aljustrel), this last recognized as the capital of an important mining area. The series of wealthy villae, such as that of La Cocosa, Milreu or San Cucufate are particularly noteworthy. Another of the important elements of the Roman era is the series of still visible ways of communication, of which the Vía de la Plata has most remaining, especially in the sections of Baños de Montemayor in Cáceres or the bridges that cross the rivers, such as that of San Pedro de Alcántara, or of Mérida.
Location Emerita Augusta
Emerita Augusta (Pleiades)
Location Description Geopolitical and economic motives together facilitated the prosperity of this great center of the Iberian peninsula. Marcus Vipsanius Agrippa, son-in-law of the emperor, was a benefactor of Augusta Emerita. The city was situated on the right bank of the Anas River (Rio Guardiana), today the Guadiana River. The site had the advantage of an easily crossed ford at the mouth of the Barraeca River (Rio Albarregas), and was an ideal site for surveillance and defense. The area immediately surrounding Augusta Emerita had rich granite quarries, sands from the riverbed, and other types of rock for the new constructions. The city’s topography determined the new rectilinear urban layout. The variations in ground level, due to small hills in the land, probably necessitated terracing, which is still discernible in today’s modern network of streets. The bridge over the Guadiana, the longest in the peninsula with a length of almost 800 meters, provided the N-S axis to which the street grid was aligned. The new colony also had an ambitious system of urban drainage. The sewers and water lines form a complete underground complex of canals. The works of hydraulic engineering, whose dates of construction and later stages of development are debated, support the notion that Augusta Emerita was a city with a grand, forward-looking vision.
At the intersection of the decumanus and cardo were two fora, one for the city&amp;rsquo;s functions and one for the Province&amp;rsquo;s functions. Some of the monumental buildings have been excavated. The Mérida fora, whose layouts resemble those in the other western imperial provinces, have iconographic programs that resemble those of Rome; the forum of Augusta Emerita is a particularly faithful reflection of the Forum Augustum. This imitative trend appears also in the two other provincial capitals of Hispania, Tarraco and Corduba and underscores the power which Augustan images and architecture had in the political, ideological fabric of the provinces.
The area of Augusta Emerita best known today, because of extensive excavations, is around the so-called Temple of Diana. The temple is actually dedicated to the imperial cult. The structures devoted to public performance - theater, amphitheater, and circus - surrounded the urban center. The theater was begun in 16-15 BC and the amphitheater in 8 BC, during the first decades of colonial presence. Augusta Emerita’s necropolis ran around the city’s urban perimeter and expanded as the city proper grew.
Because most of evidence from Merida was unearthed in old excavations, the context of many ancient objects is unknown. There is also a lack of analytical data on many of the areas which must originally have been gardened. The classification of the gardens of the Colonia Augusta Emerita is still under analysis. The study by Moreno is a basic survey article and should be understood to be part of all the bibliographies for Merida.
Bibliography  I. C. Moreno, “Los jardines de Mérida,” Mérida, excavaciones arqueológicas Nº. 2, 1996 , pp. 303-328. (worldcat)  Garden House of the Mithraeum
Keywords  peristyles (columnades) colonnades rural villas atriums axial plan courtyards  Garden Description The great house built adjacent to the San Albin Hill, in the extreme southwest of the city, offers a handsome example of a suburban domus, whose refined decoration indicates an owner with intellectual and philosophical interests. The house derives its name from its proximity to the remains of a possible Mithraeum lying beneath the present-day bullring. The chronology given for this domus extends from the end of the first to the fourth century AD.
The peristyle surrounded a garden with a pool, and was situated on axis with the atrium but further south and at a lower level. Running between the granite columns of the portico is a brick wall (one meter in height) from which extended perpendicular salients on the side facing the pool. These were decorated with a program consisting of floral motives and rhomboidal openwork with bluish trefoils. Only part of this decorative program survives. From the southwest corner of the rectangular pool a brick water channel ran along the south and east sides of the area surrounding the pool to the north-east corner of the courtyard. The hydraulic apparatus was completed by a cistern with a granite rim on the west side of the peristyle. The relationship of these elements to the rest of the complex is unknown.
The lower part of the walls of the peristyle were painted with a dado of small rectangular panels with white and yellow rhomboids and floral decoration separated by white lines. Above this dado, green vertical bands separated large bluish panels decorated with vegetal designs and geometric motives suggesting candelabras. There were chambers, whose functions are unknown, on either side of the passageway that extended between this peristyle and the atrium to the north; the chamber on the west side, known as the ‘Painted Hall’ (‘Habitación de las Pinturas’), presents a pictorial program of candelabras and painted dados representing birds and plants, dated to the second century AD.
West-southwest of the peristyle, a group of interesting chambers were arrayed around a delightful garden of ample proportions. The latter consisted of a rectangular space surrounded by stucco-clad granite columns on all four sides as well as a channel running around the perimeter just in front of the columns, except on the west side where the channel curves inward to form a semi-circle. The interior of this space was clearly gardened, although the excavators found no clue as to its original appearance. On the extreme south side, attached to one of the columns, are the partial remains of a peculiar brick structure which had a hole in its lower part for the passage of water. Its function is unclear. The pictorial decoration of this viridarium resembles that of the peristyle’s dado.
The passage formed by the north colonnade gave access to three chambers, the middle one a triclinium, with mosaic pavements and wall dados painted with birds and vegetal themes. On the west side, facing the garden&amp;rsquo;s exedra, was a chamber with Bacchic murals (now in the Museo Nacional de Arte Romano) and below its floor, a great barrel-vaulted cistern. On the south side, several rooms formed what may have been a cubiculum (bedroom) with mosaics whose themes included Eros with a dove. Two subterranean rooms in the southeast corner of this same group probably provided cool refuge from the summer heat.
Plans   Fig. 1: House of the Mithraeum. Adapted from Casilla Moreno.   Images   Fig. 2: Central peristyle.     Fig. 3: Southwest peristyle.   Dates The end of the 1st to the 4th century AD
Bibliography  LL. Abad Casal, “Pintura romana en Mérida,’ in Augusta Emerita, Madrid, 1976, pp. 163-82 (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 256155
TGN ID 7007664
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date 6 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Houses Under the Museum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/emerita_augusta/houses_under_the_museum/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/emerita_augusta/houses_under_the_museum/</guid>
      <description>Province Lusitania
Lusitania(Pleiades)
Province Description Despite the prior existence of urban centers like Metellinum, the capital of Lusitania was a new foundation, the Colonia Augusta Emerita (Mérida), which would also serve as the capital of one of the smaller juridical units (conventus) and would be the scene of flourishing activity in the succeeding centuries, its prosperity lasting until the late Roman and Visigothic era. Subsequently, a series of well-known Roman cities were built in what was then Lusitania but is now partly in Portugal and partly in Spain. As well as the capital, there were Conimbriga, Salmantica, Evora, Olisipo (now Lisbon), Pax Iulia (now Beja), and Metallium Viscascense (Aljustrel), this last recognized as the capital of an important mining area. The series of wealthy villae, such as that of La Cocosa, Milreu or San Cucufate are particularly noteworthy. Another of the important elements of the Roman era is the series of still visible ways of communication, of which the Vía de la Plata has most remaining, especially in the sections of Baños de Montemayor in Cáceres or the bridges that cross the rivers, such as that of San Pedro de Alcántara, or of Mérida.
Location Emerita Augusta
Emerita Augusta (Pleiades)
Location Description Geopolitical and economic motives together facilitated the prosperity of this great center of the Iberian peninsula. Marcus Vipsanius Agrippa, son-in-law of the emperor, was a benefactor of Augusta Emerita. The city was situated on the right bank of the Anas River (Rio Guardiana), today the Guadiana River. The site had the advantage of an easily crossed ford at the mouth of the Barraeca River (Rio Albarregas), and was an ideal site for surveillance and defense. The area immediately surrounding Augusta Emerita had rich granite quarries, sands from the riverbed, and other types of rock for the new constructions. The city’s topography determined the new rectilinear urban layout. The variations in ground level, due to small hills in the land, probably necessitated terracing, which is still discernible in today’s modern network of streets. The bridge over the Guadiana, the longest in the peninsula with a length of almost 800 meters, provided the N-S axis to which the street grid was aligned. The new colony also had an ambitious system of urban drainage. The sewers and water lines form a complete underground complex of canals. The works of hydraulic engineering, whose dates of construction and later stages of development are debated, support the notion that Augusta Emerita was a city with a grand, forward-looking vision.
At the intersection of the decumanus and cardo were two fora, one for the city&amp;rsquo;s functions and one for the Province&amp;rsquo;s functions. Some of the monumental buildings have been excavated. The Mérida fora, whose layouts resemble those in the other western imperial provinces, have iconographic programs that resemble those of Rome; the forum of Augusta Emerita is a particularly faithful reflection of the Forum Augustum. This imitative trend appears also in the two other provincial capitals of Hispania, Tarraco and Corduba and underscores the power which Augustan images and architecture had in the political, ideological fabric of the provinces.
The area of Augusta Emerita best known today, because of extensive excavations, is around the so-called Temple of Diana. The temple is actually dedicated to the imperial cult. The structures devoted to public performance - theater, amphitheater, and circus - surrounded the urban center. The theater was begun in 16-15 BC and the amphitheater in 8 BC, during the first decades of colonial presence. Augusta Emerita’s necropolis ran around the city’s urban perimeter and expanded as the city proper grew.
Because most of evidence from Merida was unearthed in old excavations, the context of many ancient objects is unknown. There is also a lack of analytical data on many of the areas which must originally have been gardened. The classification of the gardens of the Colonia Augusta Emerita is still under analysis. The study by Moreno is a basic survey article and should be understood to be part of all the bibliographies for Merida.
Bibliography  I. C. Moreno, “Los jardines de Mérida,” Mérida, excavaciones arqueológicas Nº. 2, 1996 , pp. 303-328. (worldcat)  Garden Houses Under the Museum
Keywords  peristyles (columnades) courtyards porticoes exedrae (site elements)  Garden Description Prior to building the present Museo Nacional de Arte Romano, excavations were undertaken at the site in 1978 and 1979. Two suburban residences were explored and preserved in the crypt of the museum. These contained at least three courtyards. One was a colonnaded courtyard of ‘marble,’ and this small rectangular courtyard (at the rear of the crypt) consisted of a low wall of mortared rubble with simple marble columns of the Tuscan order. It was surrounded by incompletely excavated chambers, one of which had a program of wall paintings and stuccos which dated the complex to the period first through the fourth century A.D.
Another had a peristyle with an exedra. This was a small rectangular peristyle (near the stairs leading down to the crypt) with stucco-clad brick columns except in the corners where square pilasters were substituted. In the porticoes formed by these, the walls were painted. Wrapping around the courtyard proper were segments of a brick canal revetted with painted stucco. On its interiors, the canal was revetted with opus signinum and its floor had quarter-circle reinforcement. On the courtyard’s east side, off center, a semi-circular exedra led to what was probably the most impressive chamber in the house. The remains of another colonnaded court (in the southeast corner of the crypt) consisted of two rubblework walls forming a corner and supporting marble columns of the Tuscan order; the corridor formed by this colonnade was paved with opus signinum.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the houses under the Museum.   Dates The 4th century A.D
Excavation Dates 1978 and 1979
Bibliography  J. Barrera Antón (De), “El trabajo estucado en «Augusta Emerita»: los grandes frisos de la casa romana del solar del Museo”, in Extremadura Arqueológica, (Homenaje a la Dra Dª Milagro Gil Mascarell Boscá), 5(1995): 221-223. (worldcat) J. Hernández Ramírez, La pintura mural romana de Mérida. (Inserta en la estructura urbana y doméstica de la ciudad), UNED (unpublished doctoral disertation), 1993, pp. 1380-1506.  Pleiades ID 256155
TGN ID 7007664
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date 6 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Peristyle of the Theater</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/emerita_augusta/peristyle_of_the_theater/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/emerita_augusta/peristyle_of_the_theater/</guid>
      <description>Province Lusitania
Lusitania(Pleiades)
Province Description Despite the prior existence of urban centers like Metellinum, the capital of Lusitania was a new foundation, the Colonia Augusta Emerita (Mérida), which would also serve as the capital of one of the smaller juridical units (conventus) and would be the scene of flourishing activity in the succeeding centuries, its prosperity lasting until the late Roman and Visigothic era. Subsequently, a series of well-known Roman cities were built in what was then Lusitania but is now partly in Portugal and partly in Spain. As well as the capital, there were Conimbriga, Salmantica, Evora, Olisipo (now Lisbon), Pax Iulia (now Beja), and Metallium Viscascense (Aljustrel), this last recognized as the capital of an important mining area. The series of wealthy villae, such as that of La Cocosa, Milreu or San Cucufate are particularly noteworthy. Another of the important elements of the Roman era is the series of still visible ways of communication, of which the Vía de la Plata has most remaining, especially in the sections of Baños de Montemayor in Cáceres or the bridges that cross the rivers, such as that of San Pedro de Alcántara, or of Mérida.
Location Emerita Augusta
Emerita Augusta (Pleiades)
Location Description Geopolitical and economic motives together facilitated the prosperity of this great center of the Iberian peninsula. Marcus Vipsanius Agrippa, son-in-law of the emperor, was a benefactor of Augusta Emerita. The city was situated on the right bank of the Anas River (Rio Guardiana), today the Guadiana River. The site had the advantage of an easily crossed ford at the mouth of the Barraeca River (Rio Albarregas), and was an ideal site for surveillance and defense. The area immediately surrounding Augusta Emerita had rich granite quarries, sands from the riverbed, and other types of rock for the new constructions. The city’s topography determined the new rectilinear urban layout. The variations in ground level, due to small hills in the land, probably necessitated terracing, which is still discernible in today’s modern network of streets. The bridge over the Guadiana, the longest in the peninsula with a length of almost 800 meters, provided the N-S axis to which the street grid was aligned. The new colony also had an ambitious system of urban drainage. The sewers and water lines form a complete underground complex of canals. The works of hydraulic engineering, whose dates of construction and later stages of development are debated, support the notion that Augusta Emerita was a city with a grand, forward-looking vision.
At the intersection of the decumanus and cardo were two fora, one for the city&amp;rsquo;s functions and one for the Province&amp;rsquo;s functions. Some of the monumental buildings have been excavated. The Mérida fora, whose layouts resemble those in the other western imperial provinces, have iconographic programs that resemble those of Rome; the forum of Augusta Emerita is a particularly faithful reflection of the Forum Augustum. This imitative trend appears also in the two other provincial capitals of Hispania, Tarraco and Corduba and underscores the power which Augustan images and architecture had in the political, ideological fabric of the provinces.
The area of Augusta Emerita best known today, because of extensive excavations, is around the so-called Temple of Diana. The temple is actually dedicated to the imperial cult. The structures devoted to public performance - theater, amphitheater, and circus - surrounded the urban center. The theater was begun in 16-15 BC and the amphitheater in 8 BC, during the first decades of colonial presence. Augusta Emerita’s necropolis ran around the city’s urban perimeter and expanded as the city proper grew.
Because most of evidence from Merida was unearthed in old excavations, the context of many ancient objects is unknown. There is also a lack of analytical data on many of the areas which must originally have been gardened. The classification of the gardens of the Colonia Augusta Emerita is still under analysis. The study by Moreno is a basic survey article and should be understood to be part of all the bibliographies for Merida.
Bibliography  I. C. Moreno, “Los jardines de Mérida,” Mérida, excavaciones arqueológicas Nº. 2, 1996 , pp. 303-328. (worldcat)  Garden Peristyle of the Theater
Keywords  colonnades water supply systems peristyles (columnades) fountains  Garden Description The space behind the theater screen comprises one of the best preserved gardens of Augusta Emerita. It consisted of a rectangular enclosure surrounded on the north, east, and west sides by ambulatories formed by double colonnades of granite with Corinthian capitals and red-stuccoed bases. The wall within these walkways had niches with paintings, of which few traces remain. In addition to entering through the screen, access was also possible via a small flight of granite steps in the southeast corner from the street, which separated this monument from the Amphitheater.
A water channel bordered the exterior of the colonnade, emptying into two small square depressions in the northeast and northwest corners which connected to the drains traversing the north side of the peristyle. Water, indispensable for irrigation and the fountains, was in ample supply, probably owing to the theate&amp;rsquo;s proximity to the San Lázaro water canal. Parallel to the portico of the rear of the proscenium (stage), in the eastern part, ran a wall which expanded in the form of an exedra, forming a semicircular space for a statue. But the most interesting element of the peristyle, located at the back of it and on axis with the valva regia, was an aula sacar locate on plan, dedicated to the imperial cult. In front of this was a small marble fountain decorated with vegetal motifs. The aula sacra consisted of a small rectangular chamber with marble revetted walls and niches for statues. Inside, four toga-clad statues, a veiled head of Augustus, and a head of Tiberius were found.
While the theater belongs to multiple phases of construction, the aula sacra belongs to a Tiberian phase. The peristyle&amp;rsquo;s important program of sculptures and paintings, together with the green spaces, must have given the edifice a magnificent appearance. Unfortunately, many of its decorative elements, wall paintings, bronzes, and marble paving slabs do not survive, and there are few remaining works of statuary, although these are marble and well made.
Water, indispensable for irrigation and the fountains, was in ample supply, probably owing to the theate&amp;rsquo;s proximity to the San Lázaro water canal. The present appearance of the peristyle is the result of restorations carried out in 1964 by J. Menéndez-Pidal in which the south wing of the peristyle was resurrected and covered with a pergola and the fountain restored to working order.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the theater and peristyle.   Images   Fig. 2: Photo of the theater peristyle garden.     Fig. 3: Photo of the theater peristyle garden.     Fig. 4: Photo of the theater peristyle garden.     Fig. 5: Photo of the theater peristyle garden from the north side.   Dates 16-15 BC
Excavation Dates 1964
Bibliography  A. Floriano, “Excavaciones en Mérida (Campañas de 1934 y 1936)”, in Archivo Español de Arqueología, 55 (1944): 151-187 (worldcat) J.R. Mélida, “El teatro romano de Mérida,” R.A.B.M., 32, (1915): 1-38 (worldcat) P. Mateos Cruz and J. Marquez Pérez, ‘Neuvas structuras urbanas relacionadas con el Teatro Romano de Mérida: El pórtico de acceso,’ Mérida, excavaciones arqueológicas, 1997, pp.301-20 (worldcat) W. Trillmich, Die Prásenz des Kaiserhauses im Theater der Colonia Augusta Emerita , (unpublished disertation), University of München (1995)  Pleiades ID 256155
TGN ID 7007664
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date 6 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Temple of Diana</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/emerita_augusta/temple_of_diana/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/emerita_augusta/temple_of_diana/</guid>
      <description>Province Lusitania
Lusitania(Pleiades)
Province Description Despite the prior existence of urban centers like Metellinum, the capital of Lusitania was a new foundation, the Colonia Augusta Emerita (Mérida), which would also serve as the capital of one of the smaller juridical units (conventus) and would be the scene of flourishing activity in the succeeding centuries, its prosperity lasting until the late Roman and Visigothic era. Subsequently, a series of well-known Roman cities were built in what was then Lusitania but is now partly in Portugal and partly in Spain. As well as the capital, there were Conimbriga, Salmantica, Evora, Olisipo (now Lisbon), Pax Iulia (now Beja), and Metallium Viscascense (Aljustrel), this last recognized as the capital of an important mining area. The series of wealthy villae, such as that of La Cocosa, Milreu or San Cucufate are particularly noteworthy. Another of the important elements of the Roman era is the series of still visible ways of communication, of which the Vía de la Plata has most remaining, especially in the sections of Baños de Montemayor in Cáceres or the bridges that cross the rivers, such as that of San Pedro de Alcántara, or of Mérida.
Location Emerita Augusta
Emerita Augusta (Pleiades)
Location Description Geopolitical and economic motives together facilitated the prosperity of this great center of the Iberian peninsula. Marcus Vipsanius Agrippa, son-in-law of the emperor, was a benefactor of Augusta Emerita. The city was situated on the right bank of the Anas River (Rio Guardiana), today the Guadiana River. The site had the advantage of an easily crossed ford at the mouth of the Barraeca River (Rio Albarregas), and was an ideal site for surveillance and defense. The area immediately surrounding Augusta Emerita had rich granite quarries, sands from the riverbed, and other types of rock for the new constructions. The city’s topography determined the new rectilinear urban layout. The variations in ground level, due to small hills in the land, probably necessitated terracing, which is still discernible in today’s modern network of streets. The bridge over the Guadiana, the longest in the peninsula with a length of almost 800 meters, provided the N-S axis to which the street grid was aligned. The new colony also had an ambitious system of urban drainage. The sewers and water lines form a complete underground complex of canals. The works of hydraulic engineering, whose dates of construction and later stages of development are debated, support the notion that Augusta Emerita was a city with a grand, forward-looking vision.
At the intersection of the decumanus and cardo were two fora, one for the city&amp;rsquo;s functions and one for the Province&amp;rsquo;s functions. Some of the monumental buildings have been excavated. The Mérida fora, whose layouts resemble those in the other western imperial provinces, have iconographic programs that resemble those of Rome; the forum of Augusta Emerita is a particularly faithful reflection of the Forum Augustum. This imitative trend appears also in the two other provincial capitals of Hispania, Tarraco and Corduba and underscores the power which Augustan images and architecture had in the political, ideological fabric of the provinces.
The area of Augusta Emerita best known today, because of extensive excavations, is around the so-called Temple of Diana. The temple is actually dedicated to the imperial cult. The structures devoted to public performance - theater, amphitheater, and circus - surrounded the urban center. The theater was begun in 16-15 BC and the amphitheater in 8 BC, during the first decades of colonial presence. Augusta Emerita’s necropolis ran around the city’s urban perimeter and expanded as the city proper grew.
Because most of evidence from Merida was unearthed in old excavations, the context of many ancient objects is unknown. There is also a lack of analytical data on many of the areas which must originally have been gardened. The classification of the gardens of the Colonia Augusta Emerita is still under analysis. The study by Moreno is a basic survey article and should be understood to be part of all the bibliographies for Merida.
Bibliography  I. C. Moreno, “Los jardines de Mérida,” Mérida, excavaciones arqueológicas Nº. 2, 1996 , pp. 303-328. (worldcat)  Garden Temple of Diana
Keywords  porticoes fountains waterspouts courtyards  Garden Description The Temple of Diana is the only surviving religious building from the Augusta Emerita Forum. Despite its name, it was actually dedicated to the imperial cult and dates to the end of the Augustan period. Excavations conducted in 1972 by J. Mª. Álvarez Martínez produced some evidence for a garden in conjunction with the temple. The space surrounding the temple was interpreted as a garden area, enclosed by a portico, which contained two rectangular pools on the east and west sides of the temple. Of the sculptural pieces found outside the temple, some have been situated in the western pool: a bronze leg (forming part of an idealized figure and probably fixed on the base of the pool) and two marble fragments of tragic masks which could have served as fountain spouts.
Plans   Fig. 1: Temple of Diana. Adapted from Casillas Morena, p. 309.   Dates The end of the Augustan period
Excavation Dates 1972
Bibliography  J. Mª. Álvarez Martinez, J. L. de la Barrera Antón and A. Velázquez Jiménez, Mérida (Turismo Everest), León, 1995, p. 54. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 256155
TGN ID 7007664
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date 6 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fontao Villa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/lavra/lusitania_fontao-villa_xw/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/lavra/lusitania_fontao-villa_xw/</guid>
      <description>Province Lusitania Lusitania (Pleiades)
Province Description Despite the prior existence of urban centers like Metellinum, the capital of Lusitania was a new foundation, the Colonia Augusta Emerita (Mérida), which would also serve as the capital of one of the smaller juridical units (conventus) and would be the scene of flourishing activity in the succeeding centuries, its prosperity lasting until the late Roman and Visigothic era. Subsequently, a series of well-known Roman cities were built in what was then Lusitania but is now partly in Portugal and partly in Spain. As well as the capital, there were Conimbriga, Salmantica, Evora, Olisipo (now Lisbon), Pax Iulia (now Beja), and Metallium Viscascense (Aljustrel), this last recognized as the capital of an important mining area. The series of wealthy villae, such as that of La Cocosa, Milreu or San Cucufate are particularly noteworthy. Another of the important elements of the Roman era is the series of still visible ways of communication, of which the Vía de la Plata has most remaining, especially in the sections of Baños de Montemayor in Cáceres or the bridges that cross the rivers, such as that of San Pedro de Alcántara, or of Mérida.
Location Lavra
Lavra (Pleiades)
Garden Fontao Villa
Garden Description The remains of a large villa were discovered in 1900 under an abandoned Benedictine monastery. Among the structures identified are several basins that are usually found in gardens. The villa dates to the late empire.
Maps Plans Images Pleiades ID 532133456
Publication date 20 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Cantaber</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/conimbriga/lusitania_house-of-the-cantaber_xw/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/conimbriga/lusitania_house-of-the-cantaber_xw/</guid>
      <description>Province Lusitania Lusitania (Pleiades)
Province Description Despite the prior existence of urban centers like Metellinum, the capital of Lusitania was a new foundation, the Colonia Augusta Emerita (Mérida), which would also serve as the capital of one of the smaller juridical units (conventus) and would be the scene of flourishing activity in the succeeding centuries, its prosperity lasting until the late Roman and Visigothic era. Subsequently, a series of well-known Roman cities were built in what was then Lusitania but is now partly in Portugal and partly in Spain. As well as the capital, there were Conimbriga, Salmantica, Evora, Olisipo (now Lisbon), Pax Iulia (now Beja), and Metallium Viscascense (Aljustrel), this last recognized as the capital of an important mining area. The series of wealthy villae, such as that of La Cocosa, Milreu or San Cucufate are particularly noteworthy. Another of the important elements of the Roman era is the series of still visible ways of communication, of which the Vía de la Plata has most remaining, especially in the sections of Baños de Montemayor in Cáceres or the bridges that cross the rivers, such as that of San Pedro de Alcántara, or of Mérida.
Location Conimbriga
Conimbriga (Pleiades)
Location Description The pre-Roman oppidum of Conimbriga was made the capital of a civitas in the Augustan period and, thereafter, a forum, a public bath-house, an aqueduct and city walls were constructed. During the Flavian period, the city was made a municipium with ius Latii. At the end of the third or beginning of the fourth century AD, new fortification walls considerably reduced the area occupied by the city. In the time of the Suevi it was an Episcopal See, which was then transferred to Aeminium (the present day Coimbra) around A. D. 585, when the kingdom of the Suevi was conquered by the Visigoths. Further reduced in area and impoverished, the city survived until 986, at which date, according to Arab sources, it was destroyed by the great Muslim chief Almansor. In addition to the Augustan forum, which was completely rebuilt on a new ground plan under the Flavians, four bath houses have been excavated, and preliminary trial trenches established the plan of the amphitheater. Four domus have been excavated, three of which were left outside the wall built under the late empire. It is in these houses, all built around peristyles, that we find the gardens of Conimbriga.
Garden House of the Cantaber
Keywords  statuettes (free-standing sculpture) peristyles (columnades)  Garden Description Hidacio, bishop of Chaves and a chronicler of his age, records that the Suevi sacked Conimbriga in 465 and 468 A.D. and that in the second year “the most noble Cantaber” was killed and his family sold into slavery. This house is by far the finest inside the city walls, so it is reasonably guessed to be that of Cantaber. It is larger than the House of the Fountains with an area of more than 3,300 square meters. The garden is similar, although it is less elaborate, has slightly different proportions, and has no fountains. Although the house underwent structural alterations, the peristyle is part of the original plan, which does not appear to date from much later than the Flavian era.
Originally, a large area at the south end was a garden occupying nearly a third of the area of the house. It was later sacrificed to become baths, so it is tinted slightly green on the plan in Figure 1.
The large dimensions of this house required further open spaces for light and air. Two of these had flower beds, although on a much smaller scale.
South of the central peristyle was a large room that centered on the garden, and on the east side of it a large doorway opened open on a large pool with eight columns around the eastern half of the pool. Along the sides were masonry planters projecting a foot or so into the pool. They must certainly have been filled with earth where plants or flowers must have been grown. The boxes covered in pink mortar are clearly visible in the foreground in Figure 3. Traces of plinths in the spaces between the columns suggest that there may have been small statuettes there.
The other garden area was slightly farther south and against the east wall of the house. A portico ran around three sides but required only three columns, all on the west side. The rectangular pool (6.5 x2.5 m) had three basically square flower beds aligned in it. The two end squares, however, had semicircular niches cut out of the center of each side, while the center square had a circle cut out of its center and connected to the surrounding water. As in the House of the Fountains, flower beds in the pool appeared like islands in a lake (Fig. 4). One can imagine that this secluded spot was a favorite of the most noble Cantaber.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: House of Cantaber. Adapted from Hipólito Correia.   Images   Fig. 2: Main peristyle.     Fig. 3: Pool with pink planters.     Fig. 4: Secluded, three-column portico. Photo S.A.J. 1969.   Pleiades ID 236443
Publication date 20 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Fountains</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/conimbriga/lusitania_house-of-the-fountains_xw/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/conimbriga/lusitania_house-of-the-fountains_xw/</guid>
      <description>Province Lusitania Lusitania (Pleiades)
Province Description Despite the prior existence of urban centers like Metellinum, the capital of Lusitania was a new foundation, the Colonia Augusta Emerita (Mérida), which would also serve as the capital of one of the smaller juridical units (conventus) and would be the scene of flourishing activity in the succeeding centuries, its prosperity lasting until the late Roman and Visigothic era. Subsequently, a series of well-known Roman cities were built in what was then Lusitania but is now partly in Portugal and partly in Spain. As well as the capital, there were Conimbriga, Salmantica, Evora, Olisipo (now Lisbon), Pax Iulia (now Beja), and Metallium Viscascense (Aljustrel), this last recognized as the capital of an important mining area. The series of wealthy villae, such as that of La Cocosa, Milreu or San Cucufate are particularly noteworthy. Another of the important elements of the Roman era is the series of still visible ways of communication, of which the Vía de la Plata has most remaining, especially in the sections of Baños de Montemayor in Cáceres or the bridges that cross the rivers, such as that of San Pedro de Alcántara, or of Mérida.
Location Conimbriga
Conimbriga (Pleiades)
Location Description The pre-Roman oppidum of Conimbriga was made the capital of a civitas in the Augustan period and, thereafter, a forum, a public bath-house, an aqueduct and city walls were constructed. During the Flavian period, the city was made a municipium with ius Latii. At the end of the third or beginning of the fourth century AD, new fortification walls considerably reduced the area occupied by the city. In the time of the Suevi it was an Episcopal See, which was then transferred to Aeminium (the present day Coimbra) around A. D. 585, when the kingdom of the Suevi was conquered by the Visigoths. Further reduced in area and impoverished, the city survived until 986, at which date, according to Arab sources, it was destroyed by the great Muslim chief Almansor. In addition to the Augustan forum, which was completely rebuilt on a new ground plan under the Flavians, four bath houses have been excavated, and preliminary trial trenches established the plan of the amphitheater. Four domus have been excavated, three of which were left outside the wall built under the late empire. It is in these houses, all built around peristyles, that we find the gardens of Conimbriga.
Garden House of the Fountains
Keywords  mosaics (visual works) peristyles (columnades)  Garden Description This house is almost entirely excavated, the exception being its north facade, which is still covered by a local lane. It occupies an area of almost 3400 square meters. Its mosaics, published in their entirety, date from the second half of the second century A.D, or the Severan era. The construction of the house dates to between 150 and 175 AD. The house has a central peristyle with twenty-six columns. The area of the large open part (12m x 26m) is completely filled with a pool with a maximum depth of 0.90 meters, inside of which the architect installed six very formal flower-beds. On the edges of these, more than 500 water-jets played continually. The unusual design of this peristyle has its only parallel in the Domus Augustana built in Rome for the emperor Domitian by the architect Rabirius. This parallel, pointed out by L. Cremain 1959 in his L’architettura, has been related by other writers, none of whom has found anything similar in Roman domestic architecture in any part of the Empire.
The house has recently been the subject of a monograph by Isabelle Morand in which she undertakes to recover the geometrical and numerical principles used by the architect and to identify astronomical and astrological allusions in the house.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the House of the Fountains. Adapted from I. Morand.   Images   Fig. 2: Photo of the House of the Fountain in 2007 with the new roof.   Bibliography  Morand, I., La Maison aux jets d&amp;rsquo;eau de Conimbriga (Boccard, Paris, 2005). (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 236443
TGN ID 7031751
Publication date 20 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Skeletons</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/conimbriga/lusitania_house-of-skeletons_xw/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/conimbriga/lusitania_house-of-skeletons_xw/</guid>
      <description>Province Lusitania Lusitania (Pleiades)
Province Description Despite the prior existence of urban centers like Metellinum, the capital of Lusitania was a new foundation, the Colonia Augusta Emerita (Mérida), which would also serve as the capital of one of the smaller juridical units (conventus) and would be the scene of flourishing activity in the succeeding centuries, its prosperity lasting until the late Roman and Visigothic era. Subsequently, a series of well-known Roman cities were built in what was then Lusitania but is now partly in Portugal and partly in Spain. As well as the capital, there were Conimbriga, Salmantica, Evora, Olisipo (now Lisbon), Pax Iulia (now Beja), and Metallium Viscascense (Aljustrel), this last recognized as the capital of an important mining area. The series of wealthy villae, such as that of La Cocosa, Milreu or San Cucufate are particularly noteworthy. Another of the important elements of the Roman era is the series of still visible ways of communication, of which the Vía de la Plata has most remaining, especially in the sections of Baños de Montemayor in Cáceres or the bridges that cross the rivers, such as that of San Pedro de Alcántara, or of Mérida.
Location Conimbriga
Conimbriga (Pleiades)
Location Description The pre-Roman oppidum of Conimbriga was made the capital of a civitas in the Augustan period and, thereafter, a forum, a public bath-house, an aqueduct and city walls were constructed. During the Flavian period, the city was made a municipium with ius Latii. At the end of the third or beginning of the fourth century AD, new fortification walls considerably reduced the area occupied by the city. In the time of the Suevi it was an Episcopal See, which was then transferred to Aeminium (the present day Coimbra) around A. D. 585, when the kingdom of the Suevi was conquered by the Visigoths. Further reduced in area and impoverished, the city survived until 986, at which date, according to Arab sources, it was destroyed by the great Muslim chief Almansor. In addition to the Augustan forum, which was completely rebuilt on a new ground plan under the Flavians, four bath houses have been excavated, and preliminary trial trenches established the plan of the amphitheater. Four domus have been excavated, three of which were left outside the wall built under the late empire. It is in these houses, all built around peristyles, that we find the gardens of Conimbriga.
Garden House of the Skeletons
Keywords  mosaics (visual works) peristyles (Roman courtyards) axial plan  Garden Description The peristyle garden of the fourth domus follows a different pattern. In contrast to the House of the Swastika Mosaic, this house is very squarely centered on the garden. The axis of the entrance bisects the garden and the triclinium on the other side. A shallow rill with a small exedra on this axis winds around the peristyle, leaving a cultivated rectangle in the center. In front of the triclinium there is a square pool, also shallow, lined with slabs of limestone and set into the cultivated area but not joined to the rill.
The large mosaic of the bedroom (Fig. 1, C) was restored in the 1950&amp;rsquo;s; but even originally it was in relatively good condition. Elsewhere in the house, however, there are only a few patches of mosaic owing to the area have been used as a necropolis in the late empire, a use that gave the house the name by which it is now called.
The houses were excavated around 1940, at a time when there was no thought of recovering micro-remains from the soil of the flower-beds, which could have allowed the identification of the vegetal species present in these gardens. There is therefore no evidence as to what was planted. There is also no mention of sculptural elements, which may or may not have been present.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the House of the Skeletons.   Images   Fig. 2: Photo of peristyle at the House of the Skeleton.     Fig. 3: Photo showing the relation of the garden to other rooms of house.   Bibliography  J. Alarcão and R. Etienne, “Les jardins a Conimbriga (Portugal)” in Ancient Roman Gardens, Dumbarton Oaks Colloquium on the History of Landscape Architecture,no. 7. 1979, E. B. MacDougall and W. F. Jashemski eds. Washington, D. C., 1981, pp. 67-80. (worldcat) V. Hipólito Carreia, Conimbriga, Guide to the Ruins, Instituto Portugués de Museus, 2006. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 236443
Publication date 20 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Swastika Mosaic</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/conimbriga/lusitania_house-of-swastika-mosaic_xw/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/conimbriga/lusitania_house-of-swastika-mosaic_xw/</guid>
      <description>Province Lusitania Lusitania (Pleiades)
Province Description Despite the prior existence of urban centers like Metellinum, the capital of Lusitania was a new foundation, the Colonia Augusta Emerita (Mérida), which would also serve as the capital of one of the smaller juridical units (conventus) and would be the scene of flourishing activity in the succeeding centuries, its prosperity lasting until the late Roman and Visigothic era. Subsequently, a series of well-known Roman cities were built in what was then Lusitania but is now partly in Portugal and partly in Spain. As well as the capital, there were Conimbriga, Salmantica, Evora, Olisipo (now Lisbon), Pax Iulia (now Beja), and Metallium Viscascense (Aljustrel), this last recognized as the capital of an important mining area. The series of wealthy villae, such as that of La Cocosa, Milreu or San Cucufate are particularly noteworthy. Another of the important elements of the Roman era is the series of still visible ways of communication, of which the Vía de la Plata has most remaining, especially in the sections of Baños de Montemayor in Cáceres or the bridges that cross the rivers, such as that of San Pedro de Alcántara, or of Mérida.
Location Conimbriga
Conimbriga (Pleiades)
Location Description The pre-Roman oppidum of Conimbriga was made the capital of a civitas in the Augustan period and, thereafter, a forum, a public bath-house, an aqueduct and city walls were constructed. During the Flavian period, the city was made a municipium with ius Latii. At the end of the third or beginning of the fourth century AD, new fortification walls considerably reduced the area occupied by the city. In the time of the Suevi it was an Episcopal See, which was then transferred to Aeminium (the present day Coimbra) around A. D. 585, when the kingdom of the Suevi was conquered by the Visigoths. Further reduced in area and impoverished, the city survived until 986, at which date, according to Arab sources, it was destroyed by the great Muslim chief Almansor. In addition to the Augustan forum, which was completely rebuilt on a new ground plan under the Flavians, four bath houses have been excavated, and preliminary trial trenches established the plan of the amphitheater. Four domus have been excavated, three of which were left outside the wall built under the late empire. It is in these houses, all built around peristyles, that we find the gardens of Conimbriga.
Garden House of the Swastika Mosaic
Keywords  mosaics (visual works)  Garden Description Far more modest than the House of Cantaber but following the same general ideas of garden design, this house was left outside the new city wall built during the late empire. The mosaics, now in excellent condition after modern restoration, can be dated to the mid third century A.D., but the house is the result of several successive transformations. Presumably that history explains why the main room with the mosaic with many swastikas is not aligned with the axis of the garden, though two of its three doorways offered views of it.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: House of Swastika Mosaic.   Images   Fig. 2: Looking west over swastika mosaic to garden.   Pleiades ID 236443
Publication date 20 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Flavius M. f. Quadratus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/olisipo/lusitania_tomb-garden_xw/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/olisipo/lusitania_tomb-garden_xw/</guid>
      <description>Province Lusitania Lusitania (Pleiades)
Province Description Despite the prior existence of urban centers like Metellinum, the capital of Lusitania was a new foundation, the Colonia Augusta Emerita (Mérida), which would also serve as the capital of one of the smaller juridical units (conventus) and would be the scene of flourishing activity in the succeeding centuries, its prosperity lasting until the late Roman and Visigothic era. Subsequently, a series of well-known Roman cities were built in what was then Lusitania but is now partly in Portugal and partly in Spain. As well as the capital, there were Conimbriga, Salmantica, Evora, Olisipo (now Lisbon), Pax Iulia (now Beja), and Metallium Viscascense (Aljustrel), this last recognized as the capital of an important mining area. The series of wealthy villae, such as that of La Cocosa, Milreu or San Cucufate are particularly noteworthy. Another of the important elements of the Roman era is the series of still visible ways of communication, of which the Vía de la Plata has most remaining, especially in the sections of Baños de Montemayor in Cáceres or the bridges that cross the rivers, such as that of San Pedro de Alcántara, or of Mérida.
Location Olisipo
Olisipo (Pleiades)
Garden Tomb Garden of Flavius M. f. Quadratus
Keywords  tombs  Garden Description An inscription found immured in the corner of a house near Lisbon around 1735 records the epitaph of a standard bearer (aquilifer) of the second legion, [.] Flavius M. f. Quadratus, of the Galeria tribe, who made for himself a tomb monument with, it seems, a ‘circumvallation’ and a pavilion (cum munitioni[bus], tric[le]a[e]). Although no tomb garden is mentioned explicitly, the reference to a pavilion points to the presence of one; by ‘circumvallation’ (munitiones) Quadratus evidently means the perimeter wall that regularly enclosed tomb gardens.
Maps Plans Images Pleiades ID 256338
Publication date 20 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa de Hinojal</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/las_tiendas/lusitania_villa-el-hinojal_xw/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/las_tiendas/lusitania_villa-el-hinojal_xw/</guid>
      <description>Province Lusitania Lusitania (Pleiades)
Province Description Despite the prior existence of urban centers like Metellinum, the capital of Lusitania was a new foundation, the Colonia Augusta Emerita (Mérida), which would also serve as the capital of one of the smaller juridical units (conventus) and would be the scene of flourishing activity in the succeeding centuries, its prosperity lasting until the late Roman and Visigothic era. Subsequently, a series of well-known Roman cities were built in what was then Lusitania but is now partly in Portugal and partly in Spain. As well as the capital, there were Conimbriga, Salmantica, Evora, Olisipo (now Lisbon), Pax Iulia (now Beja), and Metallium Viscascense (Aljustrel), this last recognized as the capital of an important mining area. The series of wealthy villae, such as that of La Cocosa, Milreu or San Cucufate are particularly noteworthy. Another of the important elements of the Roman era is the series of still visible ways of communication, of which the Vía de la Plata has most remaining, especially in the sections of Baños de Montemayor in Cáceres or the bridges that cross the rivers, such as that of San Pedro de Alcántara, or of Mérida.
Location Las Tiendas
Las Tiendas (Pleiades)
Garden Villa el Hinojal
Keywords  peristyles (Roman courtyards) hypocausts  Garden Description In the early 1970&amp;rsquo;s, J. M. Álvarez Martinez began excavations at this site, whose report appeared in 1976. The villa was built around a central open space (11.7 x 6.3 m), which the archaeologists initially assumed was a peristyle. There was indeed a wall (0.70 meters high and 0.55 meters thick) around the central area, which was judged to a garden. But there was no trace of columns or bases or capitals of even imprints of where they had been. The passageways around the courtyard on the north, west, and south were definitely covered; and on the east, where the entrances to the walled area were, there was probably also a portico, for that wall had painted decoration which would hardly have been left exposed to the weather. The garden gave light to the rooms around it.
Though it seems clear that the principal room [10], with a mosaic representing the hunting of wild boar, was intended to have a view of the garden through its large entranceway, there was no gate to the garden at that point and the view must have been at least partially blocked by the wall around the garden. Inside the garden area there were also some low walls, presumably the edges of planting beds. A well was in the center of the garden, and a water conduit led off to the northwest where there were baths. In an unusual arrangement, there appear to have been baths also in the northeastern corner. Both areas had hypocausts and water-handling facilities.
The house appears to have been built at the end of the third or beginning of the fourth century A.D. However, there were bits of ceramic from the first, second and third centuries used as filler in the foundation beds below the mosaics. Abandonment seems to have come at the end of the fourth or early in the fifth century. The house thus presents a number of unusual features, including a ‘peristyle’ without columns, two baths in a relatively small house, a grand room with a view of the garden but blocked by a wall, and first century ceramic filler in a house that otherwise appears to date from around 300 AD. The excavation is still incomplete and the definitive report yet to be written.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Villa El Hinojal. Adapted from J. M. Alvarez Martinez, 1976.   Images Pleiades ID 213630148
Publication date 20 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa de La Cocosa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/la_cocosa/luisitania_villa-de-la-cocosa_xw/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/la_cocosa/luisitania_villa-de-la-cocosa_xw/</guid>
      <description>Province Lusitania Lusitania (Pleiades)
Province Description Despite the prior existence of urban centers like Metellinum, the capital of Lusitania was a new foundation, the Colonia Augusta Emerita (Mérida), which would also serve as the capital of one of the smaller juridical units (conventus) and would be the scene of flourishing activity in the succeeding centuries, its prosperity lasting until the late Roman and Visigothic era. Subsequently, a series of well-known Roman cities were built in what was then Lusitania but is now partly in Portugal and partly in Spain. As well as the capital, there were Conimbriga, Salmantica, Evora, Olisipo (now Lisbon), Pax Iulia (now Beja), and Metallium Viscascense (Aljustrel), this last recognized as the capital of an important mining area. The series of wealthy villae, such as that of La Cocosa, Milreu or San Cucufate are particularly noteworthy. Another of the important elements of the Roman era is the series of still visible ways of communication, of which the Vía de la Plata has most remaining, especially in the sections of Baños de Montemayor in Cáceres or the bridges that cross the rivers, such as that of San Pedro de Alcántara, or of Mérida.
Location La Cocosa
La Cocosa (Pleiades)
Garden Villa de La Cocosa
Keywords  peristyles (Roman courtyards) mosaics (visual works) podiums (building divisions)  Garden Description Rock is very scarce in this region, so it happened that sometime around 1940 workers removing stones from the ruined walls of this villa found the mosaic floor of the tepidarium. The owner informed the authorities in Badajoz, archaeologists were brought in, and the villa was fully excavated. A few years later, José de C. Serra Ráfols was entrusted with the job of mapping the site and preparing documentation based on his own work and the notes of his predecessors. His ample text of 173 pages plus 28 drawings and 37 photographs appeared in 1952. The mosaic from the tepidarium with a hippocampus (marine centaur) surrounded by dolphins and fish is in the Museo de Bellas Artes in Badajoz. This excavation, however, was done long before the interest in the archaeology of gardens, so it is hardly surprising that almost nothing is said about them.
The villa had a peristyle courtyard, (13 x 17 m), but as found, it was paved with a floor of crushed bricks embedded in concrete. It was not, however, necessarily always paved. Serra Ráfols felt that the original villa went back to the middle of the first century A.D, and that it was considerably amplified and given some mosaic floors in the middle of the second century A.D. Then later came proprietors “who felt a veritable passion for rustic pavements of crushed brick in concrete, which they put down everywhere” (p. 162). Previously, the inner court of the peristyle had presumably been a garden. The paved floor of the peristyle is some 18 centimeters below the level of the surrounding galleries. Around the perimeter of the central court, some 35 cm from the edge of the galleries, they built a wall about 30 cm high and 65 cm wide. The top of the wall was mostly flat but at the edges it had upward slanting lips that made of the whole a sort of shallow trough. It was too shallow to be for ornamental water, so Serra Ráfols conjectured that it was a sort of podium for potted plants. It would have elevated the plants somewhat and caught any excess of water given them. Indeed, it might have been especially nice for potted flowers, for it would bring their blossoms closer to eye level and also allow for frequent changes in order always to have plants in bloom. This structure is intact at the northwest corner of the peristyle (Fig. 2).
Twelve of the twenty column bases were found in place. A granite shaft 40 cm in diameter was also found, likely originally encased in ornamental stucco. There was a small semicircular pool, probably the basin of a fountain, in the middle of the west side of the peristyle. Similar small pools are found between the first and second columns from the west along the north and south sides.
Besides the central peristyle, there are several other areas that were possibly gardened. In the center of the west wing, area (Fig. 2, 12) was an unpaved, elongated courtyard that might well have had informal plantings such as fruit trees, figs, pomegranates, or oleanders. Between the rooms along the west side of the peristyle and the baths (69 – 87) at the eastern edge of the excavated area there was a large open area. It was probably a palaestra and not gardened. But south of it was an open area bounded on the east by the aqueduct (83 and 103) where a grave (105) was later dug. It could well have been a garden for vegetables or for the potted plants which were brought into peristyle in their season. Still further south, the area (88) to the southeast of the peristyle was open, but was probably more a farmyard than a garden. Even further south there was yet another courtyard (95) which could have been a garden, especially since a drain (97) led away from it. Little remains of the surrounding spaces; possibly they were storerooms. What seem to have been presses for oil or wine and a grain mill complete the picture of an agricultural establishment.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: La Cocosa section. Structure around perimeter of peristyle. Adapted from Serra Ráfols, figure 4.   Images   Fig. 2: Plan of the Villa of La Cocosa. Adapted from Serra Rafols.   Bibliography  J. de C. Serra Rafols, La villa romana de la Dehesa de ‘La Cocosa’. Badajoz, 1952. (worldcat) J. de C. Serra Rafols, ‘A propósito de la villa de La Cocosa. Rectificación.’ In Archivo Español de Arqueología, XXVI. CSIC, Madrid, 1953, p. 302. (worldcat) J. G. Gorges, Les villes hispano-romaines. Inventaire et problematique archaeologiques. Centre Pierre Paris, París, 1979, pp. 189-190. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 256109
Publication date 20 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa de Milreu</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/estoi/lusitania_villa-de-milreu_xw/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/estoi/lusitania_villa-de-milreu_xw/</guid>
      <description>Province Lusitania Lusitania (Pleiades)
Province Description Despite the prior existence of urban centers like Metellinum, the capital of Lusitania was a new foundation, the Colonia Augusta Emerita (Mérida), which would also serve as the capital of one of the smaller juridical units (conventus) and would be the scene of flourishing activity in the succeeding centuries, its prosperity lasting until the late Roman and Visigothic era. Subsequently, a series of well-known Roman cities were built in what was then Lusitania but is now partly in Portugal and partly in Spain. As well as the capital, there were Conimbriga, Salmantica, Evora, Olisipo (now Lisbon), Pax Iulia (now Beja), and Metallium Viscascense (Aljustrel), this last recognized as the capital of an important mining area. The series of wealthy villae, such as that of La Cocosa, Milreu or San Cucufate are particularly noteworthy. Another of the important elements of the Roman era is the series of still visible ways of communication, of which the Vía de la Plata has most remaining, especially in the sections of Baños de Montemayor in Cáceres or the bridges that cross the rivers, such as that of San Pedro de Alcántara, or of Mérida.
Location Estoi
Estoi (Pleiades)
Garden Villa de Milreu
Keywords  peristyles (Roman courtyards)  Garden Description The ruins of this villa are 0.9 km west of the center of Estoi. Strabo (3.2.5) mentions Ossonoba as a town on an estuary in this part of Lusitania. The Roman temple at the Milreu site, still standing to the springline of its vaults, always marked this spot as a Roman settlement, and many concluded that it must be Ossonoba. Among those of this opinion was Sebastião Philippes Martins Estácio da Veiga, who first excavated the site in 1877. He wrote that he had “brought to light the famous cathedral of Ossonoba.” Controversy swirled over the identification of the ruins as it became increasingly clear that they were those of an affluent villa. The dispute was not resolved until 1952 when Abel Viana produced irrefutable evidence that the ruins of Ossonoba lie under modern Faro.
The entrance, to the south of the villa, was flanked by semicircular pools at the near ends of gardened strips. Through a vestibule, one entered the peristyle (24.3 x 28.0 m). In the center was a deep pool, but around it ample space for a garden. The porticoes surrounding the peristyle were paved with mosaics. The late ones, from the mid-third century A.D., depict fish, dolphins, and mollusks with exceptional care; the earlier ones are primarily geometric. In the fish, the tesserae get smaller around the head, teeth, and eyes. Given this interest in marine life, it seems likely that the deep pool in the garden had fish.
On the west side of the peristyle, the triclinium was centered on the garden and its pool. There are traces of stone bases for the three couches, so we can be sure that the room was for dining rather than reception or business. At the west end, the triclinium had an apse. Farther west, the land dropped off rapidly, so that there was an excellent view in that direction. A walkway wrapped around the north, south, and west sides of the triclinium, to allow enjoyment of the vista. It therefore seems likely that the area close to the house on the west side would have been gardened. Moreover, there would have been plenty of water from the runoff of the baths, which were just next to the triclinium on the south.
The peristyle of this villa was a productive one. Five olive presses sat in the northwest corner of the peristyle but at a lower level. Wine presses were placed in a structure on the northeast corner of the peristyle. Much of this northeast area is now covered by a 15th century farmhouse. The Roman structures beneath it have been excavated and are visible through the modern glass floors of the farmhouse, a clever and effective way to preserve and present the Roman material while also preserving the attractive and historic farmhouse.
The archaeologists working on the site have not produced a detailed sequence of phases. Settlement on the site, however, seems to go back to the Bronze Age, while the first Roman structures date from the first century A.D. The second and third centuries A.D. saw the villa assume approximately its present form. The fine marine mosaics, found not only around the peristyle but in several of the numerous pools, date from the mid-fourth century AD. The temple was contemporaneous and appears to have been originally pagan, though before the end of the century it had been converted to a Christian church.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the Villa de Milreu adapted from Hauschild and Teichner.   Images   Fig. 2: Photo of the Villa de Milreu central peristyle.     Fig. 3: Photo of the fish mosaic   Pleiades ID 854718547
Publication date 20 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa de Torre de Palma</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/monforte/lusitania_villa-de-torre-palma_xw/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/monforte/lusitania_villa-de-torre-palma_xw/</guid>
      <description>Province Lusitania Lusitania (Pleiades)
Province Description Despite the prior existence of urban centers like Metellinum, the capital of Lusitania was a new foundation, the Colonia Augusta Emerita (Mérida), which would also serve as the capital of one of the smaller juridical units (conventus) and would be the scene of flourishing activity in the succeeding centuries, its prosperity lasting until the late Roman and Visigothic era. Subsequently, a series of well-known Roman cities were built in what was then Lusitania but is now partly in Portugal and partly in Spain. As well as the capital, there were Conimbriga, Salmantica, Evora, Olisipo (now Lisbon), Pax Iulia (now Beja), and Metallium Viscascense (Aljustrel), this last recognized as the capital of an important mining area. The series of wealthy villae, such as that of La Cocosa, Milreu or San Cucufate are particularly noteworthy. Another of the important elements of the Roman era is the series of still visible ways of communication, of which the Vía de la Plata has most remaining, especially in the sections of Baños de Montemayor in Cáceres or the bridges that cross the rivers, such as that of San Pedro de Alcántara, or of Mérida.
Location Monforte
Torre de Palma (Pleiades)
Garden Villa de Torre de Palma
Keywords  mosaics (visual works) apsed triclinium peristyles (Roman courtyards) doliums  Garden Description This villa was discovered by farm workers in 1947, and excavations were begun soon afterwards by the Museu Etnológico (now the Museu Arqueológico) in Lisbon. Hundreds of rooms were unearthed, and major mosaics and many crates of materials were removed to the museum. In 1983, American archaeologists from the University of Louisville became involved with the site through a project to re-excavate the Christian basilica in the northern end. When the 1983 campaign found coins from the mid fourth century A.D. embedded in the original floor of the basilica – thereby establishing it as the earliest known double-apsed church on the Iberian Peninsula – it became clear that much might be learned from re-excavation of the whole site with modern methods.
There is one space which was likely gardened as well as several other likely spots. The report of the University of Louisville team distinguishes a number of phases. The relative chronology is based largely on the identification of the building techniques of successive master masons, while absolute dates are determined from ceramics and embedded coins found during excavations in the 1980s. The first phase consists mainly of finds of ceramics and coins from the middle of the first century A.D. but includes also the little two-room structure in the East court.
In Phase 2 (Fig. 2), from the end of the first century to mid-second century A.D., an atrium-based house was constructed and, south of it, a large peristyle courtyard. Though the atrium was unusually large with six columns rather than four &amp;ndash; what Vitruvius called a ‘Corinthian’ atrium &amp;ndash; it seems unlikely to have been gardened. The peristyle courtyard to the south, marked East Court in Figure 2, is a much more probable area, not for a formal garden but for the kind of informal garden. The entrance to the house was from the south through this peristyle. To the west was an even larger courtyard but without a peristyle. The rooms around it were modest homes with hearths and an occasional half-buried dolium. The central area may have been more farmyard than garden but quite likely had some vegetables. The “Portico House” on the southeast corner is noteworthy for its “modern” design with the porches around the house rather than the house around the porches. The central hall may have been open to serve as a light well.
The third phase distinguished by Maloney and Hale covered several building campaigns and extended through the second half of the 3rd and perhaps into the very beginning of the 4th century AD. The northeast corner of the house was largely demolished and rebuilt with a central peristyle courtyard. A rather deep tank was in the center, and between it and the peristyle was an unpaved area that was almost certainly a garden, quite possibly formal. The granaries that had previously occupied part of the buildings around the east court were surpressed, indicating an “urbanization” or up-scaling of the area. The entrance remained on the south; the visitor would still have crossed the east court to get to the main house. The villa’s triclinium had a full, central view of the garden and pool. The tablinum or master&amp;rsquo;s office on the east side of the peristyle also had a fine view of the garden.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Torre de Palma, Plan of all exposed walls. From Maloney and Hale, p. 277.     Fig. 2: Phase 2 constructions. Adapted from Maloney and Hale.     Fig. 3: Phase 3 constructions. Adapted from Maloney and Hale.     Fig. 4: Phase 4 construction. Adapted from Maloney and Hale.   Images   Fig. 5: Photo of the peristyle seen from northwest corner.   Bibliography  M. Heleno, ‘A ‘villa’ lusitano-romano de Torre de Palma (Monforte),’ O Arqueólogo Portugés ser 2, 6 (1962) p. 313-38. (worldcat) J. G. Gorges, Les villes hispano-romaines. Inventaire et problematique archaeologiques. Centre Pierre Paris, París, 1979, pp. 189-190. (worldcat) S. J. Maloney and J. R. Hale, ‘The villa of Torre de Palma (Alto Alentejo)’ Journal of Roman Archaeology, vol. 9, 1996, p. 275-94. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 256478
Publication date 20 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa Sao Cucufate</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/vila_de_frades/lusitania_villa-sao-cucufate_xw/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/vila_de_frades/lusitania_villa-sao-cucufate_xw/</guid>
      <description>Province Lusitania Lusitania (Pleiades)
Province Description Despite the prior existence of urban centers like Metellinum, the capital of Lusitania was a new foundation, the Colonia Augusta Emerita (Mérida), which would also serve as the capital of one of the smaller juridical units (conventus) and would be the scene of flourishing activity in the succeeding centuries, its prosperity lasting until the late Roman and Visigothic era. Subsequently, a series of well-known Roman cities were built in what was then Lusitania but is now partly in Portugal and partly in Spain. As well as the capital, there were Conimbriga, Salmantica, Evora, Olisipo (now Lisbon), Pax Iulia (now Beja), and Metallium Viscascense (Aljustrel), this last recognized as the capital of an important mining area. The series of wealthy villae, such as that of La Cocosa, Milreu or San Cucufate are particularly noteworthy. Another of the important elements of the Roman era is the series of still visible ways of communication, of which the Vía de la Plata has most remaining, especially in the sections of Baños de Montemayor in Cáceres or the bridges that cross the rivers, such as that of San Pedro de Alcántara, or of Mérida.
Location Vila de Frades
OS. Cucufate (Pleiades)
Garden Villa Sao Cucufate
Keywords  tablina peristyles (Roman courtyards)  Garden Description This villa, which lies southeast of Lisbon, had multiple construction phases, investigated by J. Alarcão, R. Etienne, and F. Mayet. The key to distinguishing the first villa from the second turned out to be that the first was made of granite without mortar, while the second was built of schist. It was a modest structure with a patio [Fig. 1, 7], quite possibly an informal garden, surrounded on two sides by galleries [6]. Rooms [3], [4], and [5] were the family&amp;rsquo;s living quarters. Half-buried jars made clear that room [10] was a storeroom, presumably for grain, oil, and wine. Dating this phase is uncertain; some terra sigillata suggests a date in the mid 1st century.
About 130 AD, the family demolished much of its home and built in its place a much more spacious abode, which preserved the orientation and the width of the farmyard from the first phase. To the northwest, the old patio and its galleries gave way to a whole new structure: a peristyle with galleries on all four sides surrounded a central garden with a semicircular pool. The pool was a bit off-center, and the garden was aligned with the new principal room of the house, perhaps a tablinum, on the northwest side of the peristyle. Behind this room, further to the northwest, was a huge water tank holding some 800 cubic meters. The source of the water has not been identified. This tank supplied water to the pool, baths, and several smaller pools and fountains. Overflow from this tank was collected in a similar tank of half the capacity farther down the hill to the south. It could have served as a swimming pool in the summer and to irrigate gardens and orchards farther down the slope. The rooms on the southwest side of the peristyle opened onto a broad veranda with a good view. The rooms just to the east of the veranda were baths; their waste water would have irrigated the gardens. With this source of abundant water, it seems safe to guess that the very visible area just below the veranda was gardened. A small fountain with semicircular pool graced the northeastern end of the gallery behind the colonnade.
In about 360 AD much of the old villa was demolished and a new, two-story structure erected. The lower floor rose some seven meters high with barrel vaults so well built that many are still standing. The grand house of the owner was on the upper floor. The key to seeing the relation of this third phase to the second phase is the large water tank, which was preserved. Comparison of Figures 2 and 3 shows that the semicircular pool of the second phase peristyle survived, and that the galleries along the southwestern and northeastern sides of the peristyle were considerably extended. In fact, a guest entering from the main façade and bound for the elegant upper story would have to pass along the southeastern gallery to get to the stairs. That fact, coupled with the preservation of the pool, strongly suggests the former peristyle garden was maintained and extended along with the gallery.
The upper floor did not have a garden but offered splendid views of gardens, both in front and behind the house. Between the two end towers stretched, on the southwest (front) side, a roofed veranda over 40 meters long with a sturdy wooden rail. This emphasis on the vista leaves little doubt that the well-watered area in foreground, through which the guests arrived, would have been beautifully developed as a garden.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of São Cucufate, Phase 1. From Alarcão, Roteiros.     Fig. 2: Plan of Phase 2.     Fig. 3: Plan of Phase 3.   Images Bibliography  J. G. Gorges, pp. 124 and 477; J. de Alarcão, S. Cucufate. Roteiros da Arqueologia Portuguesa 5. Instituto Portugues do Patrimonio Arquitectónico, 1988. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 256422
Publication date 20 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
