<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>triclinium on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/triclinium/</link>
    <description>Recent content in triclinium on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/triclinium/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa del Tramezzo di Legno</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/herculaneum/tiffany_fong/casa_del-_tramezzo-_di_legno/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/herculaneum/tiffany_fong/casa_del-_tramezzo-_di_legno/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Garden Casa del Tramezzo di Legno
##Jashemski Catalogue 537.III.11.
Keywords  loggia triclinium  Garden Description 537.III.11. Casa del Tramezzo di Legno The excavation of this house was begun in 1869-1875, but the excavation of the garden and restoration of the house was completed in the time period from January 1928 to December 1929. A wide opening on the west offered a view of the garden from the triclinium(b) directly across the way. A narrow storeroom (c) on the south had a small loggiasupported by slender columns overhead which provided a view down into the garden. The south garden wall was decorated with a garden painting. A combination of the painting’s poor condition and the artist’s strange sense of perspective caused difficulty ininterpretation. The typical lattice fence would appear to recede to form an apse for the fountain, however the lattice is painted over the fountain, a robust bowl-shaped affair, making it appear neither in front nor in back. An arbor was perhaps included,but the plaster was extensively damaged in this area. The birds were unusual, a small light colored bird perched on the right rim of the fountain was unable to be identified and on each side of the fountain at the base was a large sleepy duck (Anas sp.).A small slender heron on the right is picking at a snake. Beyond the fence various indistinct shrubs are painted on a yellow background. Between the two east pillars of the north wall the cisternmouth received water collected by the gutter which ran around the perimeter of the garden.
Plans -
Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1869-1875
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, 1:59,and fig. 94 on p. 58 (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, Vol.II, P. 370 (worldcat) Maiuri, Herculaneum, pp. 35-36 (worldcat) Idem, Ercolano, pp. 231, 217-218 and fig. 162 (plan) on p. 208 (worldcat)  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa dell’Alcova</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/herculaneum/tiffany_fong/casa_dellalcova/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/herculaneum/tiffany_fong/casa_dellalcova/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Garden Casa dell’Alcova
##Jashemski Catalogue 542.IV.3-4. 543.IV.3-4.
Keywords  atrium triclinium procoeton  Garden Description 542.IV.3-4. A. Two separate dwellings were united to form this house, excavated in 1928-1929. The northern house has three courtyards. The first (a) is directly off of the vestibule, the second is a covered atrium(b) with a small courtyard that collected roof water, and the third courtyard (c) in the rear supplied light and air to the adjoining rooms and the triclinium. This was too badly damaged to ascertain if it was a garden or even if it once held potted plants. It was compared to the better preserved courtyard in the Casa a Graticcio by Maiuri.
543.IV.3-4. B. The more elegant dwelling to the south had a long corridor on one side of the large triclinium leading to a small paved courtyard with pillars (e) which supplied light and air to the house. The pillars on the south and east stood on a low wall, 0.80 m. high, with a planting area 15 cm. wide in between. This gives the area the feeling of window boxes placed below large windows. There was a well in the southeast corner of this courtyard which received rain water and beyond the courtyard was a secluded alcove. This consisted of an apsed room preceded by a procoeton.
Plans Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1928-1929
Bibliography  Maiuri, Ercolano, pp. 51, 389-391 and fig. 322 (plan) on p. 389 (worldcat)     Idem, Maiuri, Herculaneum, pp. 31 (worldcat)     Idem, Ercolano, pp. 51, 392 and fig. 322 (plan) on p. 389.(worldcat)  -
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa dell’Atrio a Mosaico</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/herculaneum/tiffany_fong/casa_dellatrio_a_mosaico/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/herculaneum/tiffany_fong/casa_dellatrio_a_mosaico/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Garden Casa dell’Atrio a Mosaico
##Jashemski Catalogue 541.IV.1-2
Keywords  portico exedra triclinium  Garden Description 541.IV.1-2 A windowed portico surrounded this garden (a) on the north, south and west. The east side was bordered by a narrow corridor which Maiuri proposed had glass in woodenframes set on the outside edge of the low wall. This wall had a planting space 0.16 m. wide in the top next to where the windows were set, creating a greenhouse environment. This luxurious house had an exedra(b) opening onto the center of the corridor and looking into the garden, which was slightly lower. On the oppositeside,the walls, columns, and the door posts were decorated with paintingsof shrubs, grapevines, ivy andoleander in flower as a continuation of the garden proper. A gutter circled the perimeter of the garden except by the entrance on the south, which was directly across from the grand triclinium-oecus(c). A rectangular marble-edged pool in the center of the garden had a water jet which could be viewed from either the exedra or the triclinium. The excavations in this garden in 1929-1930 uncovered a spherical white marble sundial. The triclinium-oecus opened to the south onto a long covered portico with an open terrace (d) beyond that looking out over the Bay. Potted plants most likely were placed here.
Plans Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1929-1930
Bibliography  Gibbs, Greek and Roman sundials, p. 148, no 1031G (worldcat)     Maiuri, Herculaneum, pp. 28-30 (worldcat)     Idem, Ercolano, pp. 290-293, 295, 298, 300 and fig. 223 (plan) on p. 280.(worldcat)  -
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa D’Argo</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/herculaneum/tiffany_fong/casa_dargo/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/herculaneum/tiffany_fong/casa_dargo/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Garden Casa D’Argo
##Jashemski Catalogue 533.II.2. 534.II.2.
Keywords  cisterns (plumbing components) triclinium peristyles porticoes gutters (building drainage components)  Garden Description 533.II.2. A. The earliest excavations of Herculaneum were done with underground tunnels. Several of these crossed this site and were discovered sixty three years later when further excavation of this patrician house was conducted in1828-1835. Eight brick columns and one engaged column stood on each of the long sides of the portico that bounded the large peristyle garden (a) on the east, north, and west sides. The north side was supported by four more columns and at the two front corners there was a pillar with an engaged column on each side. In the center of the north side two smaller pillars with one engaged column each framed a garden view from the triclinium. All the supporting members were coated with fine stucco. Gutters ringing the garden conveyed rain water to the cistern.
534.II.2. B. A second peristyle garden was located to the west of the first, but has only been partially excavated. It has stuccoed columns and pillars joined by a wall 0.4 m. high painted with plants and flowers.
Plans   Casa D’Argo   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1828-1835
Bibliography  A.C. BdI (1835),p. 130 (worldcat) Bonucci, BdI (1830), p.121 (worldcat) Bonucci, Le due Sicilie: Ercolano, fig. 11 (plan) and p. 37 (worldcat) Breton,Pompeia p. 519 (worldcat) Maiuri, Herculaneum, p. 24 (worldcat) Idem,Ercolano, pp. 367-368 and fig. 293 (plan) on p. 362 (worldcat) Niccolini,Real museo borbonico, vol. 7, fig. 59 (plan), description by Bechi, pp. 19-21 (worldcat)     Ruggiero, Ercolano, pp. 541-545 (contains the detailed reports of Bonucci)(worldcat)     -      Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>