<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>triclinia on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/triclinia/</link>
    <description>Recent content in triclinia on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 17:22:47 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/triclinia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>I.iii.25 A</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_25/i.iii.25_a/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 17:22:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_25/i.iii.25_a/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 25
Garden I.iii.25 A
Keywords  archaeological garden peristyles (columnades) porticoes statues statuettes (free-standing sculpture) triclinia  Garden Description This house had an irregular plan and a small peristyle garden (a) enclosed on three sides by a low masonry wall. The wall was topped by four stuccoed brick columns which supported the portico. The excavation in 1869-72 showed that restoration was in progress at the time of the eruption. Inside the triclinium a small marble head of Bacchus from a herm (Mus. Naz. inv. no. 110 653) was found as well as a small marble ram (Mus. Naz. inv. no. 120 357), both probably garden decorations.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1869-1872
Bibliography  Dohl, p. 1. Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 74. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., p. 57.(worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 2 (1870-1873), col. 461. Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 28. (worldcat) Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 78. Trendelenberg, BdI(1871), p. 172.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 29 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Capella (I.iii.24)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_24/house_of_capella/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 15:31:46 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_24/house_of_capella/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 24
Garden House of Capella (I.iii.24)
Keywords  archaeological garden lararia mural paintings (visual works) peristyles (columnades) porticoes triclinia  Garden Description At the rear of the house, excavated in 1868, there was a peristyle garden (a) with a portico supported by three brick columns on the east and north sides. The south wall had a lararium painting and a crude animal painting on one corner of the south garden wall. This had been executed in the manner of a topiary painting according to the excavators, who reported a lion consuming a deer, below which there was a dog pouncing on a hare. A good view of the garden was obtained through the triclinium (b) on the north.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1868
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 24, no. 261. Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 74, p. 150, no. 456 . (worldcat) Idem, Desc., pp. 56-57.(worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 28. (worldcat) Idem, Gardens, vol.II, p. 313. (worldcat) Matz, BdI (1869), pp. 239-240. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 78. Schefold, WändP, p. 13 . Sogliano, “Pitture,” p. 225, no. 705.  Warscher, “Codex,” photo no. 54.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 29 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.iii.20/22</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/houses_20&#43;22/i.iii.20&#43;22/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 13:25:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/houses_20&#43;22/i.iii.20&#43;22/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 20/22
Garden I.iii.20/22
Keywords  altars (religious fixtures) archaeological garden doliums gutters (building drainage components) peristyles (columnades) puteal triclinia  Garden Description At the rear of this house there was a garden (a) with a passageway on the north and the west. The garden had a gutter along the east, north, and west edges. Embedded in the garden were four large dolia. A large triclinium (b) on the east side had a window that looked out into the garden. Fiorelli surmised that the remains of one couch of a masonry triclinium in the west passageway indicated the possible presence of a room that had been destroyed by the earthquake. There was also a small altar on the right side of the peristyle and a terra-cotta puteal in the passageway.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 24, no. 25. Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 73. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., p. 54.(worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 27. (worldcat) Matz, BdI (1869), p. 242. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 78. Soprano, p. 308, no. 36. Warscher, “Codex.”  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 28 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa Della Grata Metallica; Casa Dell’Atrio Tetra-Stilo (I.ii.28)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_28/casa_della_grata_metallica_i.ii.28/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 15:01:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_28/casa_della_grata_metallica_i.ii.28/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 28
Garden Casa Della Grata Metallica; Casa Dell’Atrio Tetra-Stilo (I.ii.28)
Keywords  altars (religious fixtures) archaeological garden cisterns (plumbing components) peristyles (columnades) podiums (building divisions) porticoes tables (support furniture) tablina triclinia tufa  Garden Description At the rear of the house there was a peristyle garden (a) with a portico along the east side and part of the south. The excavation took place in 1873-74. A low wall joined three stuccoed brick columns and two engaged ones which supported the portico. There was an entrance to the garden on the south side opposite the door from the tablinium (b) and another on the east opposite the kitchen door (c), which was closed later according to Mau. The columns were white above the height of the wall and red below. Water was carried to the cistern by a wide gutter on the south and east edges of the garden, and Mau found some evidence of aqueduct water. There was a masonry triclinium (l.medius, 5.30 m.; l.imus, 3.85 m.; l.summus, 2.70 m.) with a circular table (dia. of support, 0.70 m. ) built against the west wall. Inside of each couch there were four niches (0.19 m. wide). The last niche in the south couch was larger in size and separated from the other three by the mouth of the cistern. There was a small masonry podium on the north wall with steps for access. A round tufa altar was located opposite the lectus summus (Fig. 3).
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I.ii.28; 10.11.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation dates 1873-1874
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Descr., p. 48. (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), col. 60. Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 25. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 250-252. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 77. Soprano, p. 293, no. 2 and figs. 28.6 and 29. Viola, “Scavi” p. 14. (worldcat) Warscher, “Codex.” photo no. 54-57.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 27 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Caupona; Officina Libraria (I.ii.24)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_24/caupona_officina_libraria_i.ii.24/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 10:02:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_24/caupona_officina_libraria_i.ii.24/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 24
Garden Caupona; Officina Libraria (I.ii.24)
Keywords  aedicula lararium archaeological garden atriums cauponae flowerpots podiums (building divisions) porticoes tables (support furniture) triclinia  Garden Description The garden (a) east of the atrium had a portico extending along the south and part of the west sides. A low wall (0.52 m. high) connected the columns and an entrance to the garden was located on the west. In 1873 the caupona was excavated. The garden contained a masonry triclinium (l.medius, 3.85 m.; l.summus and l.imus, 3.20 m.) with a table. The badly damaged triclinium revealed the amphoras used in its construction. A low podium along the north wall was thought by Fiorelli to have held flower pots. Mau reported a drainage channel at the corner of the triclinium formed by the l.meduis and the l.summus, although it is no longer evident. The base of an aedicula lararium remains against the east wall opposite the north end of the east couch.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation dates 1873
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 23, no. 17. Fiorelli, Descr., p. 47. (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), col. 60. Jashemski, Gardens, 1:179. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 25. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), p. 245. Ibid., (1874), pp. 253-256, 262-263. Mau-Kelsey, p. 404. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 77. Soprano, pp. 292-293, no. 1. Viola, “Scavi” p. 13. (worldcat) Warscher, “Codex.” photo no. 32.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 27 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of L. Vousius Faustus and M. Vousius Faustus (I.ii.10)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_10/house_of_l._vousius_faustus_and_m._volusius_faustus-i.ii.10/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2020 18:18:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_10/house_of_l._vousius_faustus_and_m._volusius_faustus-i.ii.10/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 10
Garden House of L. Vousius Faustus and M. Vousius Faustus (I.ii.10)
Keywords  aedicules archaeological garden biclinia drains lararia mural paintings (visual works) piscinae triclinia  Garden Description The garden at the rear of the house, excavated in 1873, is almost totally destroyed. According to Mau, most of the garden was occupied by a large pool (5.40 X 2.90 m.) which was sloped toward the west from where it drained into the street through a pipe. The pool was surrounded by a low wall about 0.55 m. high leaving only a narrow space between the pool and the walls. In the northwest corner were the two beds of a masonry biclinium which sloped toward the wall, as was customary. Rainwater falling on them was carried away by a terra-cotta drain which emptied into the pool. A square niche under the north couch provided a storage space. On the wall above this couch was a rectangular niche lararium with a roughly made aedicula facade (Fig. 3, 2.19.72). At the east end of this couch was a masonry table. Fiorelli reports a planting bed attached to the rear (east) wall. There was a view from the triclinium through the large window in the east wall, across the pool to the garden painting on the rear wall.
Garden Painting
When this garden was excavated in 1873, the excavators reported three panels on the east wall with garden paintings. The center panel had a body of water with swimming fish with assorted animals in the background that included a grazing deer and a springing leopard. The two panels on either side each had a large crater-shaped fountain surrounded by thick growth. Large red flowers and yellow apples could be identified to the left of each fountain and the right, pomegranates (Punica granatum L.). Jashemski examined this painting in 1964 to find it had been covered by a growth of ivy which had destroyed most of the painting. A section of a large pomegranate bush was all that was left intact at the time. She describes the leaves, painted in blue-green with darker shading and a few yellow leaves and the fruit, deep yellow with reddish-orange shading, as being rendered in an impressionistic manner. At the right of the entrance to the garden area was a cistern opening. Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I.ii.10; 2.19.72, S. A. Jashemski.   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1873
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 22, no. 6. Fiorelli, Descr., p. 42. (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), col. 57.  Jashemski, Gardens, 1:1 10-1 1 1. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 22. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 313. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 197-198. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. Gen.,” p. 76. Schefold, WandP, p. 9 (describes this painting as a paradeisos, with sea, deer, panther, and nymphaeum). (worldcat)  Sogliano, “Pitture,” p. 224, no. 694. (worldcat)  Soprano, p.305, no. 23. Viola, “Scavi” p. 11. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 24 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House in Insula 30 in Augusta Raurica</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ausgusta_raurica/augusta_raurica_house_in_insula_30/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 10:02:05 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ausgusta_raurica/augusta_raurica_house_in_insula_30/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Augusta Raurica
Augusta Raurica (Pleiades)
Location Description The town on the Rhine River possessed colonial status since the late 1st century BC. The street grid, as well as many public and residential buildings, are well known from excavations.
Garden House in Insula 30 in Augusta Raurica
Keywords  colonnades corridors insulae peristyles (Roman courtyards) triclinia vestibules water wells  Garden Description Insula 30, east of the central baths, was taken up by a single house built around 200 AD. This replaced several earlier structures on the site. The insula, including the street colonnades, had an overall area of ca. 48 x 60 meters.
The house had a peristyle courtyard of rectangular shape which was surrounded on three sides by a low wall supporting stone columns. The courtyard was unpaved and almost certainly planted (G in Fig. 1). Entering the house from the east, one passed through a vestibule before arriving in the peristyle corridor around the courtyard. The courtyard wall, enclosing an area 14 x 23.50 meters in size, was fronted by a water channel. There was a well in the north. From the triclinium to the west of the courtyard, one had a view directly into the courtyard.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of a house in Insula 30 with a garden courtyard (G). Plan adapted from Laur-Belart 1988, fig. 126. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Insula: 200 A.D.
Bibliography  R. Laur-Belart, Führer durch Augusta Raurica, 5th Ed., Basel, 1988, pp. 134-136, fig. 126. (worldcat) M. Carroll, Romans, Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 55, fig. 20. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 177494
TGN ID 7017586
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 14 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Dionyius</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_dionysius/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 20:22:59 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_dionysius/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Garden House of Dionysius (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords  urban villas villae urbanae triclinia insulae peristyles (Roman courtyards) apsed pools axial plan piscinae  Garden Description The largest urban villa excavated thus far in Cologne is the House of Dionysos (3400 sq. m.), named after the early 3rd century mosaic floor decorated with Dionysiac motifs in the triclinium (Image 1??). The house occupies part of an insula in the northeastern corner of the city, bordered on the south by a street leading to the harbor.
The original house, erected after A.D. 50, was rebuilt under Vespasian and included a peristyle garden courtyard measuring 23 x 27 m. (G on Plan 1). The garden was surrounded on three sides by a peristyle, 3.35 m. in width. A ground level gutter ran around the edge of the garden. At this time, a masonry pool with a paved floor occupied a position in the eastern part of the garden. A piece of lead pipe and a bronze opening were found associated with the pool. This was later replaced in the second half of the 2nd century by an apsed pool (4.20 x 5.40 m.) in the western half of the garden which drained into the gutter at the west. The pool was axially arranged between the entrance to the house on the east and the dining room on the west, from which a view through a wide doorway onto the garden was afforded. The triclinium was unheated, leading the excavator to interpret it as a summer triclinium. The connection with the garden would, in this case, be quite understandable. An axial planting pattern in the garden with a path leading from the entrance of the house to the pool is possible. There is, however, no evidence for the planting pattern or the type of vegetation in this garden. The house was inhabited until the 4th century.
Maps   CAPTION   Plans   Plan 1: Plan of the House of Dionysos, built around a central courtyard garden (G) with a pool (grey). Plan adapted from Fremersdorf 1956, fig. 27. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Reign of Vespasian until the end of the fourth century CE
Bibliography  F. Fremersdorf, Das römische Haus mit dem Dionysosmosaik vor dem Südportal des Kölner Doms, Berlin, 1956. (worldcat) M. Carroll, Romans, Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 55, fig. 20. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108751
TGN ID 7004446
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>