<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>triclinia on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/triclinia/</link>
    <description>Recent content in triclinia on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/triclinia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Peristyle garden in house of Julia Felix (II.iv.a).</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/region_ii_2/insula_iv/house/ii.iv.a/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/region_ii_2/insula_iv/house/ii.iv.a/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region II
House House of Julia Felix
Garden Peristyle garden in house of Julia Felix
Keywords  jet d&amp;rsquo;eau peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes statuettes (free-standing sculpture) triclinia  Garden Description A. Three separate gardens were located in this property. It occupies the entire insula and is one of the largest properties in the city. It was originally excavated in 1755-1757, stripped of its works of art and re-buried. In 1951-1952 it was re-excavated and restored but not published. Sixteen elegantly carved slender marble pillars support a portico which borders the peristyle garden (a) on the west.Fig.18, 5.29.59, Fig. 19, 5.32.50, Fig. 20, 5.25.59 An alcove (b) housed a summer triclinium (l. medius, 4.00 m.; l. imus and summus 3.00 m.) with marble faced couches that looked through the portico into the garden. Between the couches a niche supplied water that ran down small marble steps to a hole at the bottom. The water re-surfaced as a jet in the middle of the trilinium. A vine covered arbor stretched along the south and east side of the garden and beyond it in bays on the east wall were raised planting beds, alternating semicircular and square. These were covered with pumice and decorated with a band of Egyptian blue around the sides and top, the middle bay having four bands of Egyptian blue. The room (c) to the south of the triclinium had a garden representation (0.185 x 0.42 m.) on the north part of the west wall on the red middle zone. Four fish ponds connected to form a long channel down the center of the garden. The little marble bridges that crossed the channel and covered alcoves at the bottom of the pools provided shelter for the fish and eels. A number of statuettes were found during the two excavations of this site. More recently the pieces that were found are as follows: A marble satyr (0.475 m. preserved height; Pompeii inv. no. 8856) located at the north end of the pool, a seated terra-cotta figure of Pittacus of Mitylene (0.65 m. high; Pompeii inv. no. 2181-4) found at the edge of the pool, a small marble fountain statuette of a sea crab in a shell (0.19 m. wide; Pompeii inv. no. 1073/54). During the earlier excavation some of the items found were as follows: a satyr child (0.46 m. high; Muz. Naz. inv. no. 6108), a nude youth holding grapes in his right hand and a goose in his left (0.76 m. high; Muz. Naz. inv. no. 6342), a faun(Muz. Naz. inv. no. 6343), an old man covered with a cloth (0.49 m. high), a bird with a lizard in its beak (0.32 m. high), a marble mask of a smiling youth on a small column (0.54 m. high), and a marble relief (0.36m. long x 0.11 m. high) of an old man seated of a bench, perhaps this was a pinax. The heads of twelve marble herms, (one woman, one old man, three bearded men) were reported by PAH, but the post of only one is mentioned and only the feet of the thirteenth herm was found. A terra-cotta group of Caritas Romana was found in many pieces as well as multiple fragments of other terra-cotta statuettes which had been in the eleven niches in the peristyle portico. Chambalu believed the herms stood between these niches.
Plans   view form the portico     detail of the jet.     portico and garden   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography   Annali Dell&amp;rsquo;instituto Di Correspondenza Archeologica, 1830, p.50 worldcat
  Bonucci, Carlo.Pompei Descritta Da Carlo Bonucc, p.219 worldcat
  Bragantini, Irene. Pitture E Pavimenti Di Pompei. Roma: Ministero per i beni culturali e ambientali, Istituto centrale per il catalogo e la documentazione, 1981. Print.1:238 worldcat
  Chambalu,Die weiderverschüttete Besitzung der Julia Felix beim Amphitheater in Pompeji, Pp, 1895. Print. pp. 14-15 and plan of Weber (1757) after p. 20 worldcat
  Della Corte, Notizie degli scavi antichita (1958), p. 125, no. 238 (Pittakos inscription);worldcat
  Dwyer, Eugene J. Pompeian Oscilla Collections: (pls. 80-130) Mainz: Verlag Philipp von Zabern, 1981. Print. p. 279, no. 81worldcat
  F. Rakob, *Ein Grottentriklinium in Pompeji,*RM (1964), pp. 182-194;worldcat
  H. Döhl, Plastik aus Pompeji , tesi di libera d tingen 1976, pp. 8-10
  Idem, Pompeii (Novara), p. 111 worldcat
  Idem, Pomp. Sculpture, pp. 67, 128, and figs. 197, 212;
  Jashemski, Wilhelmina F, The Gardens of Pompeii, Herculaneum, and the Villas Destroyed by Vesuvius, New Rochelle: Aristide D. Caratzas, 1979. Print , 1:48, 110 and figs. 81 on p. 47, 82 on p. 48, 83 (marble statue at north end of pool), 84 (Pittacus), and 85 (sea-crab in shell) on p. 49; worldcat
  Jashemski, Wilhelmina F, and Stanley A. Jashemski, The Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the Villas Destroyed by Vesuvius. New Rochelle, NY: Caratzas, 1993. Print. pp. 86-88, 396worldcat
  Kapossy, Balázs. Brunnenfiguren Der Hellenistischen Und Römischen Zeit. Zürich, 1969. Print. pp 46, 50 worldcat
  Lorenz, Thuri. Galerien Von Griechischen Philosophen Und Dichterbildnissen Bei Den Römern. Mainz: Verlag Ph. von Zabern, 1965. Print. p. 39worldcat
  Maiuri, I giardini, Le Vie d’Italia, no.9 Sept 1961, p. 1139; worldcat
  Maiuri, Statuette fittilli di Pittaco di Mitilene, Archeologia Classica 4 (1952): 55-59; worldcat
  Maiuri, Pompei ed Ercolano:Fra case ed abitanti, pp. 74-75; worldcat
  Pompeianarum Antiquitatum Historia, vol. 1 pt. 1, pp. 13, 15, 16, 18, 19, 21, 28, 29, 30, 31, 34, 37, 39 (Apr. 13, 1755-Mar. 6, 1756);Ibid., vol. 1 pt. 2, pp. 98, 101; worlcat
  Richter, Greek Portraits, 3:34 and fig. 134; worlcat
  Richter, Portraits of the Greeks, 1:89a; worlcat
  Rohden, Hermann. Die Terracotten Von Pompeji. Stuttgart, 1880. Print. pp. 24, 47-48, 53, 57, 62 and plates 35.3, 36, 41.4, 47; worldcat
  Salsa Prina Ricotti, The Importance of Water in Roman Open Air Tricliniums, in Ancient Roman Villa Gardens, Dumbarton Oaks Colloquium on the History of Landscape Architecture, no. 10, Dumbarton Oaks, 1987, pp. 172-173; worlcat
  Sear, Frank B. Roman Wall and Vault Mosaics. Heidelberg: F.H. Kerle, 1977. Print. p.94 worlcat
  Zahn, Wilhelm.Die Schönsten Ornamente Und Merkwürdigsten Gemälde Aus Pompeji, Herkulanum Und Stabiae vol2.pl.100 (plan)worldcat
  Pleiades ID 955554415
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 2 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House in Insula 30 in Augusta Raurica</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ausgusta_raurica/augusta_raurica_house_in_insula_30/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 10:02:05 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ausgusta_raurica/augusta_raurica_house_in_insula_30/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Augusta Raurica
Augusta Raurica (Pleiades)
Location Description The town on the Rhine River possessed colonial status since the late 1st century BC. The street grid, as well as many public and residential buildings, are well known from excavations.
Garden House in Insula 30 in Augusta Raurica
Keywords  colonnades corridors insulae peristyles (Roman courtyards) triclinia vestibules water wells  Garden Description Insula 30, east of the central baths, was taken up by a single house built around 200 AD. This replaced several earlier structures on the site. The insula, including the street colonnades, had an overall area of ca. 48 x 60 meters.
The house had a peristyle courtyard of rectangular shape which was surrounded on three sides by a low wall supporting stone columns. The courtyard was unpaved and almost certainly planted (G in Fig. 1). Entering the house from the east, one passed through a vestibule before arriving in the peristyle corridor around the courtyard. The courtyard wall, enclosing an area 14 x 23.50 meters in size, was fronted by a water channel. There was a well in the north. From the triclinium to the west of the courtyard, one had a view directly into the courtyard.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of a house in Insula 30 with a garden courtyard (G). Plan adapted from Laur-Belart 1988, fig. 126. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Insula: 200 A.D.
Bibliography  R. Laur-Belart, Führer durch Augusta Raurica, 5th Ed., Basel, 1988, pp. 134-136, fig. 126. (worldcat) M. Carroll, Romans, Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 55, fig. 20. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 177494
TGN ID 7017586
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 14 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Dionyius</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_dionysius/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 20:22:59 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_dionysius/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Garden House of Dionysius (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords  urban villas villae urbanae triclinia insulae peristyles (Roman courtyards) apsed pools axial plan piscinae  Garden Description The largest urban villa excavated thus far in Cologne is the House of Dionysos (3400 sq. m.), named after the early 3rd century mosaic floor decorated with Dionysiac motifs in the triclinium (Image 1??). The house occupies part of an insula in the northeastern corner of the city, bordered on the south by a street leading to the harbor.
The original house, erected after A.D. 50, was rebuilt under Vespasian and included a peristyle garden courtyard measuring 23 x 27 m. (G on Plan 1). The garden was surrounded on three sides by a peristyle, 3.35 m. in width. A ground level gutter ran around the edge of the garden. At this time, a masonry pool with a paved floor occupied a position in the eastern part of the garden. A piece of lead pipe and a bronze opening were found associated with the pool. This was later replaced in the second half of the 2nd century by an apsed pool (4.20 x 5.40 m.) in the western half of the garden which drained into the gutter at the west. The pool was axially arranged between the entrance to the house on the east and the dining room on the west, from which a view through a wide doorway onto the garden was afforded. The triclinium was unheated, leading the excavator to interpret it as a summer triclinium. The connection with the garden would, in this case, be quite understandable. An axial planting pattern in the garden with a path leading from the entrance of the house to the pool is possible. There is, however, no evidence for the planting pattern or the type of vegetation in this garden. The house was inhabited until the 4th century.
Maps   CAPTION   Plans   Plan 1: Plan of the House of Dionysos, built around a central courtyard garden (G) with a pool (grey). Plan adapted from Fremersdorf 1956, fig. 27. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Reign of Vespasian until the end of the fourth century CE
Bibliography  F. Fremersdorf, Das römische Haus mit dem Dionysosmosaik vor dem Südportal des Kölner Doms, Berlin, 1956. (worldcat) M. Carroll, Romans, Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 55, fig. 20. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108751
TGN ID 7004446
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>