<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>triclinia on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/triclinia/</link>
    <description>Recent content in triclinia on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 00:10:10 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/triclinia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa del Larario Fiorito (II.ix.4)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_ix/casa_del_larario_fiorito/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_ix/casa_del_larario_fiorito/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region II
Insula Insula IX
Keywords  [ambulatione] triclinia charcoal] pollen  Garden Description Excavated in the later 1980s, (Fig. 76) this property features a garden, described by Ciarallo as “laid out in eight ground strips bordered by furrows.” She interprets this layout as a plant nursery, also taking into account that the root cavities throughout were small, 4-8 c. in diameter, with two larger cavities of 20 and 40 cm. The larger cavities flank the axis that divides the garden in half. (Fig. 77) Gardens excavated recently shed light on the layout, which might, alternatively, be seen to comprise two slightly wider beds and two narrow ones that run alongside ambulationes, providing a modest strolling garden adjacent to the triclinium. Elsewhere, gardens of the time of the eruption freatured a variety of plants along these rows that would have been observed and presumably admired by the stroller, either for their exotic origin or for skill in creating new varieties of unusual shapes of familiar plants. The team made 160 casts in this garden. Pollen and charcoal were also collected and indicate the presence of grape (Vitis), hazelnut (Corylus), Prunus, Oak (Quercus), and beech (Fagus). Beech and Oak are also seen in the pollen samples. Tree roots were interpreted as pine (Pinus) and olive (Olea).
Plans   Fig. 75, Plan of Region II, insula ix   Need Fig. 76
Images Need Fig. 77
Pleiades ID 456321707
TGN ID 7004658
Excavation Dates later 1980s
Bibliography  Ciarallo, Le problematiche botaniche dell’area archeologica Vesuviana, in M. Mastroroberto,ed. Archeologia e Botania: Atto del convegno di studi sul contributo della botanica alla conoscenza e alla conservazione delle aree archeologiche vesuviane, Pompei 7-9 aprile 1989, L&amp;rsquo;Erma di Bretschneider, 1990, 17-32. (worldcat)  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 10 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa del Larario Fiorito (II.ix.4.A)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_ix/ii.ix.6a/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_ix/ii.ix.6a/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region II
Insula Insula IX
Keywords  masonry triclinia pergolas lecti reservoirs lattices  Garden Description A. To the west of the Great Palaestra there was a large garden (a) which was partially excavated in 1954-1956. A low masonry wall with planting spaces in the top enclosed an elaborate masonry triclinium (l. medius, 4.45 m.; l. imus 4.20; l. summus 3.55 m.) with a table 0.65 x 0.75 m.) on the south, west and north sides. This was shaded by a pergola supported by four massive columns finished with stucco. Two elaborate mosaic fountains faced each other in front of the triclinium. Both fountains were an arched niche set into a rectangular façade surrounded by a pediment with a tiny arched niche in the center of the back which spewed water into the pool below. The bronze jet survived in the north fountain. Fig. 78, 12.8.71 Close to identical mosaics on both fountains features a panel with two fish and two ducks on the lower drum, and garden paintings on the on the east and west sides of the fountains as well as on the ends of the lectus imus and the lectus summus. Each fountain had a water reservoir built on the top with steps for access. The south reservoir was 0.63 x 1.06 m., 0.45 m. deep and the north one was 1.10 x 1.04 m., 0.45 m. deep. The lead supply pipe for the north reservoir was found intact, and Dr. De Caro surmised that these reservoirs were provisional prior to the completion of the aqueduct in this area. The paintings on these two elaborate mosaic fountains were quite faded but the details that could be discerned included a yellow-orange lattice fence at the bottom of each with a fountain painted in the center of each panel surrounded by flowering shrubs, trees and birds (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, fig. 261 on p. 176). The east sides of the mosaic fountains were visible from the entrance from the Great Palaestra. The east side of the south mosaic had a bowl–shaped fountain with a square rim with two pigeons sitting on the rim, the one on the right drinking. A date palm stands behind this fountain with three clusters of ripe fruit. One shrub on the right appears to be an oleander with red blooms and a small brown bird perched in the branches, but the remaining plants are too faint to be identified. The fountain painted on the east side of the north mosaic fountain is footed and crater-shaped with two handles. What appear to be two herons perch on the fence facing the fountain on either side, a blue one on the left and a white one on the right. The shrubs in back have the foliage of oleanders with two small birds flying about. From the triclinium the paintings on the west side of the mosaic fountains could be enjoyed. The west side of the north mosaic fountain had another crater-shaped, two handled fountain with a low base and a black bird sitting on the fence to the right. There are traces of a date palm behind the fountain and the rest of the foliage is badly faded but there appears to be some oleanders included in the painting. The west side of the south mosaic fountain had an image of an egg-shaped, footed fountain with a golden color and some detailing to suggest that it may represent a bronze fountain. To the top of the left there remains the crown of a palm tree with a small sparrow-like bird, and although most of the plaster on the right side has fallen there is enough evidence to surmise another palm tree could have been painted here along with some oleanders. Jashemski examined this garden in 1971 and found a series of cavities along the north wall and close to a complete planting pot (13 cm. high, 5.0 cm. dia. at the base, one hole in the bottom and three on the sides). The number of root cavities in the interior of the garden indicated that the triclinium was likely set in a vineyard with the usual number of trees but any evidence of the planting plan had been destroyed by the excavation truck traffic. There was a masonry altar opposite the triclinium near the west wall and a masonry pool in the northwest corner of the garden. The north couch of the triclinum had a garden painting on the east side showing a footed, bowl-shaped fountain centered behind a brown lattice fence. Two birds perch on the fountain but the foliage of the surrounding bushes is too damaged to identify. The south couch was decorated with a similar fence and some bushes. The serving table has traces of a peacock and flowering plants while the niches on the inside of the triclinium couches have some very well preserved garlands hanging between them. The low wall that enclosed the triclinium on the north had a section that survived with beautiful grape vines heavy with large ripe fruit clusters. Fig 79, 12.17.71, Fig. 80, 12.25.71
Plans   Fig. 75, Plan of Region II, insula ix   Images   Fig. 78, 12.8.71 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig 79, 12.17.71 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 80, 12.25.71 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)   Pleiades ID 456321707
TGN ID 7004658
Excavation Dates 1954-1956
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.I, p.176-177 and fig. 261 on p. 176 (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, pp. 97, 331-332 (worldcat) Maiuri, Pompeii, p. 84: “triclinium flanked by two mosaic polychrome water lilies” (sic) (worldcat) Neuerburg, L&amp;rsquo;architettura delle fontane e dei ninfei nell&amp;rsquo;Italia antica, pp. 120-121, no. 22 (worldcat) Bragantini et al., Pitture e pavimenti di Pompei, vol.I, p.243-244 (worldcat) Sear, Roman Wall and Vault Mosaics, RM, Supp. 23 (1977) pp. 76-77, no. 37. (worldcat)  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 10 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Caupona with Small Bath</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_viii/caupona_with_small_bathii.viii.5.a/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_viii/caupona_with_small_bathii.viii.5.a/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region II
Insula Insula VIII
Keywords  triclinia  Garden Description A. A very small bath was located at the left rear of the atrium in this unusual building. Behind this was a tiny garden (a) with three small triclinia on either side. The couches of these six triclinia were so low and narrow they must have been used as seats similar to the taberna attached to the house of Julia Felix, II.iv.7.
Plans   Fig. 62, Plan of Region II, insula viii   Pleiades ID 456321707
TGN ID 7004658
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p.94 (worldcat)  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 10 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>II.viii.2-3</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_viii/iii.viii.2-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_viii/iii.viii.2-3/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region II
Insula Insula VIII
Keywords  thermopolium triclinia lecti lararium  Garden Description Customers at this thermopolium were served at a counter at the street and at the masonry triclinium (l. medius, 3.60 m.; l. imus 2.85; l. summus 2.30 m.) in the rear garden. This was located against the north wall to the front of this long, narrow garden and had a round table (0.50 m. in dia.) between the couches and a rectangular table (0.65 x 0.89 m.) at the end of the lectus summus. A niche lararium was next to it with a tufa altar below decorated with a large carved club. A bench for cooking was built against the south wall at the west end with two arched openings for fuel storage underneath.
Plans   Fig. 62, Plan of Region II, insula viii   Pleiades ID 456321707
TGN ID 7004658
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p.92 (worldcat) Orr, Roman Domestic Religion: A Study of the Roman Household Deities and their Shrines at Pompeii and Herculaneum, no.65 (worldcat)  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 10 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>II.viii.6</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_viii/ii.viii.6/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_viii/ii.viii.6/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region II
Insula Insula VIII
Keywords  aedicula lararia strigillation triclinia dolium [lapilli] [sarculum] [dolabella]  Garden Description A large aedicula lararium on the east wall and a large triclinium (l. medius, 4.40 m.; l. imus 4.00; l. summus 3.80 m.; table between couches 1.00 x 1.67m.) were found in the large area attached to this humble house when excavation was started in 1953-1954. Human remains were uncovered with five gold coins, two gold rings, a strigil and seven medical instruments close to the -triclinium. Next to the shrine two terra-cotta votive offerings, a slender female winged figure (0.155 m. high; Pompeii inv. no. 10569) and a small draped figure with considerable red paint surviving on the drapery(figure (0.165 m. high; Pompeii inv. no. 10150) were found as well as a marble statuette of Hercules (ca. 0.57 high without base; Pompeii inv. no. 10138). South of the triclinium a doghouse had been built by mounting half of a dolium (0.70 x 0.50m.) on a masonry base 0.15 m. high. Further finds included a large terra-cotta funnel, but the function of this area could not be determined. Excavation by Jashemski in 1971-1972 revealed what appears to be a large commercial flower garden. Where the lapilli remained until the 1970s, the undamaged soil contours and root and stake cavities were well preserved. Circular watering depressions remained in one bed that held a small plant. Balloon photographs showed complicated bed arrangements and a path coming from the outside area to the middle of the garden where a left turn led to the triclinium and altar in front of the lararium. Fig.63, 17.7.73, Fig. 64, 8.33.73, Fig. 65, 21A.13.73 An extensive system of rain water collection and distribution had been built. Roof run off was collected in a large dolium on each side of the door and in a nearby pool. Additional water could be brought from outside sources and poured through an amphora tip in the east end of the north wall to fill a dolium imbedded in the northeast corner of the garden. The natural slope of the land was from north to south and the irrigation layout took advantage of this fact. When the dolium in the northeast corner overflowed the water ran down a channel along the east wall watering young trees planted in the channel until it fell into a second half dolium buried in the soil. This process would be repeated the length of the east wall and continued along the south wall. There were channels along the north and west walls and dividing all the beds in the interior of the garden. Fig. 66, 23.23.74, Fig. 67, 21.31.73, Fig. 68, 18.10.73 Eleven large tree root cavities were counted with dimensions of 30 cm. or more at ground level. One grew near the southwest corner of the shrine, three along the walls and seven scattered about the garden. Another huge, partially destroyed cavity about 2 m. could have been an olive tree that grew to the west of the cistern. Many other smaller tree root cavities were found, and carbonized cherries (Prunus cerasus L.) that were found here would identify at least some of these. Along the walls with the tree root cavities were terra-cotta pots similar to those found in the House of the Ship Europa. There were well preserved vine root cavities and post cavities for the pergola over the triclinium. Most of the garden cavities that remained were for the stakes that supported the frames for the shade structures for young bedding plants. Parallel to the west wall, 3.30m. away from it, a row of posts formed either a shed or an arbor with roofing support holes in the wall above. Two ancient gardening tools, a sarculum and a dolabella were found in the garden along with bones, teeth, perfume bottle fragments, and fragments of terra-cotta unguent containers. The house to this garden contained a large number of glass perfume bottles. The assessment of pollen and spores found here are shown in Jashemski, Gardens, 1:282-284 and in Tables F-H. Fig. 69, 21.15.73, Fig. 70, 7.33.73, Fig. 71, 11.8.73, Fig. 72, 11.31.71, Fig. 73, 21.30.72, Fig. 74, 11.20.74
Plans   Fig. 62, Plan of Region II, insula viii   Images   Fig.63, 17.7.73 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 64, 8.33.73 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 65, 21A.13.73 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 66, 23.23.74 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 67, 21.31.73 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 68, 18.10.73 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 69, 21.15.73 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 70, 7.33.73 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 71, 11.8.73 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 72, 11.31.71 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 73, 21.30.72 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 74, 11.20.74 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)   Pleiades ID 456321707
TGN ID 7004658
Excavation Dates 1953-1954, 1971-1972
Bibliography  Jashemski, The Garden of Hercules at Pompeii (II.viii.6): The Discovery of a Commercial Flower Garden, American Journal of Archaeology, 83 (1979) (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.I, p.279-288 and figs. 421-435 (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, pp.94-95 (worldcat) Meyer, p.432  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 10 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Peristyle garden in house of Julia Felix (II.iv.a).</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_iv/house/ii.iv.a/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_iv/house/ii.iv.a/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region II
House House of Julia Felix
Garden Peristyle garden in house of Julia Felix
Keywords  jet d&amp;rsquo;eau peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes statuettes (free-standing sculpture) triclinia  Garden Description A. Three separate gardens were located in this property. It occupies the entire insula and is one of the largest properties in the city. It was originally excavated in 1755-1757, stripped of its works of art and re-buried. In 1951-1952 it was re-excavated and restored but not published. Sixteen elegantly carved slender marble pillars support a portico which borders the peristyle garden (a) on the west.Fig.18, 5.29.59, Fig. 19, 5.32.50, Fig. 20, 5.25.59 An alcove (b) housed a summer triclinium (l. medius, 4.00 m.; l. imus and summus 3.00 m.) with marble faced couches that looked through the portico into the garden. Between the couches a niche supplied water that ran down small marble steps to a hole at the bottom. The water re-surfaced as a jet in the middle of the trilinium. A vine covered arbor stretched along the south and east side of the garden and beyond it in bays on the east wall were raised planting beds, alternating semicircular and square. These were covered with pumice and decorated with a band of Egyptian blue around the sides and top, the middle bay having four bands of Egyptian blue. The room (c) to the south of the triclinium had a garden representation (0.185 x 0.42 m.) on the north part of the west wall on the red middle zone. Four fish ponds connected to form a long channel down the center of the garden. The little marble bridges that crossed the channel and covered alcoves at the bottom of the pools provided shelter for the fish and eels. A number of statuettes were found during the two excavations of this site. More recently the pieces that were found are as follows: A marble satyr (0.475 m. preserved height; Pompeii inv. no. 8856) located at the north end of the pool, a seated terra-cotta figure of Pittacus of Mitylene (0.65 m. high; Pompeii inv. no. 2181-4) found at the edge of the pool, a small marble fountain statuette of a sea crab in a shell (0.19 m. wide; Pompeii inv. no. 1073/54). During the earlier excavation some of the items found were as follows: a satyr child (0.46 m. high; Muz. Naz. inv. no. 6108), a nude youth holding grapes in his right hand and a goose in his left (0.76 m. high; Muz. Naz. inv. no. 6342), a faun(Muz. Naz. inv. no. 6343), an old man covered with a cloth (0.49 m. high), a bird with a lizard in its beak (0.32 m. high), a marble mask of a smiling youth on a small column (0.54 m. high), and a marble relief (0.36m. long x 0.11 m. high) of an old man seated of a bench, perhaps this was a pinax. The heads of twelve marble herms, (one woman, one old man, three bearded men) were reported by PAH, but the post of only one is mentioned and only the feet of the thirteenth herm was found. A terra-cotta group of Caritas Romana was found in many pieces as well as multiple fragments of other terra-cotta statuettes which had been in the eleven niches in the peristyle portico. Chambalu believed the herms stood between these niches.
Plans   view form the portico     detail of the jet.     portico and garden   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography   Annali Dell&amp;rsquo;instituto Di Correspondenza Archeologica, 1830, p.50 worldcat
  Bonucci, Carlo.Pompei Descritta Da Carlo Bonucc, p.219 worldcat
  Bragantini, Irene. Pitture E Pavimenti Di Pompei. Roma: Ministero per i beni culturali e ambientali, Istituto centrale per il catalogo e la documentazione, 1981. Print.1:238 worldcat
  Chambalu,Die weiderverschüttete Besitzung der Julia Felix beim Amphitheater in Pompeji, Pp, 1895. Print. pp. 14-15 and plan of Weber (1757) after p. 20 worldcat
  Della Corte, Notizie degli scavi antichita (1958), p. 125, no. 238 (Pittakos inscription);worldcat
  Dwyer, Eugene J. Pompeian Oscilla Collections: (pls. 80-130) Mainz: Verlag Philipp von Zabern, 1981. Print. p. 279, no. 81worldcat
  F. Rakob, *Ein Grottentriklinium in Pompeji,*RM (1964), pp. 182-194;worldcat
  H. Döhl, Plastik aus Pompeji , tesi di libera d tingen 1976, pp. 8-10
  Idem, Pompeii (Novara), p. 111 worldcat
  Idem, Pomp. Sculpture, pp. 67, 128, and figs. 197, 212;
  Jashemski, Wilhelmina F, The Gardens of Pompeii, Herculaneum, and the Villas Destroyed by Vesuvius, New Rochelle: Aristide D. Caratzas, 1979. Print , 1:48, 110 and figs. 81 on p. 47, 82 on p. 48, 83 (marble statue at north end of pool), 84 (Pittacus), and 85 (sea-crab in shell) on p. 49; worldcat
  Jashemski, Wilhelmina F, and Stanley A. Jashemski, The Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the Villas Destroyed by Vesuvius. New Rochelle, NY: Caratzas, 1993. Print. pp. 86-88, 396worldcat
  Kapossy, Balázs. Brunnenfiguren Der Hellenistischen Und Römischen Zeit. Zürich, 1969. Print. pp 46, 50 worldcat
  Lorenz, Thuri. Galerien Von Griechischen Philosophen Und Dichterbildnissen Bei Den Römern. Mainz: Verlag Ph. von Zabern, 1965. Print. p. 39worldcat
  Maiuri, I giardini, Le Vie d’Italia, no.9 Sept 1961, p. 1139; worldcat
  Maiuri, Statuette fittilli di Pittaco di Mitilene, Archeologia Classica 4 (1952): 55-59; worldcat
  Maiuri, Pompei ed Ercolano:Fra case ed abitanti, pp. 74-75; worldcat
  Pompeianarum Antiquitatum Historia, vol. 1 pt. 1, pp. 13, 15, 16, 18, 19, 21, 28, 29, 30, 31, 34, 37, 39 (Apr. 13, 1755-Mar. 6, 1756);Ibid., vol. 1 pt. 2, pp. 98, 101; worlcat
  Richter, Greek Portraits, 3:34 and fig. 134; worlcat
  Richter, Portraits of the Greeks, 1:89a; worlcat
  Rohden, Hermann. Die Terracotten Von Pompeji. Stuttgart, 1880. Print. pp. 24, 47-48, 53, 57, 62 and plates 35.3, 36, 41.4, 47; worldcat
  Salsa Prina Ricotti, The Importance of Water in Roman Open Air Tricliniums, in Ancient Roman Villa Gardens, Dumbarton Oaks Colloquium on the History of Landscape Architecture, no. 10, Dumbarton Oaks, 1987, pp. 172-173; worlcat
  Sear, Frank B. Roman Wall and Vault Mosaics. Heidelberg: F.H. Kerle, 1977. Print. p.94 worlcat
  Zahn, Wilhelm.Die Schönsten Ornamente Und Merkwürdigsten Gemälde Aus Pompeji, Herkulanum Und Stabiae vol2.pl.100 (plan)worldcat
  Pleiades ID 955554415
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 2 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House in Insula 30 in Augusta Raurica</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ausgusta_raurica/augusta_raurica_house_in_insula_30/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 10:02:05 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ausgusta_raurica/augusta_raurica_house_in_insula_30/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Augusta Raurica
Augusta Raurica (Pleiades)
Location Description The town on the Rhine River possessed colonial status since the late 1st century BC. The street grid, as well as many public and residential buildings, are well known from excavations.
Garden House in Insula 30 in Augusta Raurica
Keywords  colonnades corridors insulae peristyles (Roman courtyards) triclinia vestibules water wells  Garden Description Insula 30, east of the central baths, was taken up by a single house built around 200 AD. This replaced several earlier structures on the site. The insula, including the street colonnades, had an overall area of ca. 48 x 60 meters.
The house had a peristyle courtyard of rectangular shape which was surrounded on three sides by a low wall supporting stone columns. The courtyard was unpaved and almost certainly planted (G in Fig. 1). Entering the house from the east, one passed through a vestibule before arriving in the peristyle corridor around the courtyard. The courtyard wall, enclosing an area 14 x 23.50 meters in size, was fronted by a water channel. There was a well in the north. From the triclinium to the west of the courtyard, one had a view directly into the courtyard.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of a house in Insula 30 with a garden courtyard (G). Plan adapted from Laur-Belart 1988, fig. 126. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Insula: 200 A.D.
Bibliography  R. Laur-Belart, Führer durch Augusta Raurica, 5th Ed., Basel, 1988, pp. 134-136, fig. 126. (worldcat) M. Carroll, Romans, Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 55, fig. 20. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 177494
TGN ID 7017586
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 14 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Dionyius</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_dionysius/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 20:22:59 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_dionysius/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Garden House of Dionysius (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords  urban villas villae urbanae triclinia insulae peristyles (Roman courtyards) apsed pools axial plan piscinae  Garden Description The largest urban villa excavated thus far in Cologne is the House of Dionysos (3400 sq. m.), named after the early 3rd century mosaic floor decorated with Dionysiac motifs in the triclinium (Image 1??). The house occupies part of an insula in the northeastern corner of the city, bordered on the south by a street leading to the harbor.
The original house, erected after A.D. 50, was rebuilt under Vespasian and included a peristyle garden courtyard measuring 23 x 27 m. (G on Plan 1). The garden was surrounded on three sides by a peristyle, 3.35 m. in width. A ground level gutter ran around the edge of the garden. At this time, a masonry pool with a paved floor occupied a position in the eastern part of the garden. A piece of lead pipe and a bronze opening were found associated with the pool. This was later replaced in the second half of the 2nd century by an apsed pool (4.20 x 5.40 m.) in the western half of the garden which drained into the gutter at the west. The pool was axially arranged between the entrance to the house on the east and the dining room on the west, from which a view through a wide doorway onto the garden was afforded. The triclinium was unheated, leading the excavator to interpret it as a summer triclinium. The connection with the garden would, in this case, be quite understandable. An axial planting pattern in the garden with a path leading from the entrance of the house to the pool is possible. There is, however, no evidence for the planting pattern or the type of vegetation in this garden. The house was inhabited until the 4th century.
Maps   CAPTION   Plans   Plan 1: Plan of the House of Dionysos, built around a central courtyard garden (G) with a pool (grey). Plan adapted from Fremersdorf 1956, fig. 27. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Reign of Vespasian until the end of the fourth century CE
Bibliography  F. Fremersdorf, Das römische Haus mit dem Dionysosmosaik vor dem Südportal des Kölner Doms, Berlin, 1956. (worldcat) M. Carroll, Romans, Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 55, fig. 20. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108751
TGN ID 7004446
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>