<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>porticoes on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/porticoes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in porticoes on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 12:00:02 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/porticoes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Grotto of catullus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/sirmio/grotto_of_catullus/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/sirmio/grotto_of_catullus/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Sirmio
Sirmio (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region X
Garden House of Grotto of Aatullus
Keywords  insulae cryptoportici vestibules piscinae peristyles (columnades) porticoes bathhouses (water recreation structures) atriums ditches water supply systems water baths gutters (building drainage components) drains loam basins (vessels) statues cisterns (plumbing components) terrazzo water wells orchards presence chambers fences (site elements) exedrae (site elements) garden pavilions reception rooms terrazzo  Garden Description Sirmio is known from a citation in Catullus’ XXXI° poem (paene insularum, Sirmio, insularumque ocelle &amp;hellip;) and in later road itineraries as a staging post (Sermione mansio) along the road between Verona and Brixia (Brescia), which passed to the south of the peninsula, forming part of the erritory of Verona. In several areas along this ancient coastline remains have been brought to light of large and sumptuous villas built on the coast, in large coves or high places, with beautiful panoramas.The remains of a villa, called by fifteenth-century visitors to the site “Grotte di Catullo”, after Verona’s poet Catullus, are situated at the northern tip of the Sirmione peninsula, on the southern bank of the Benacus(Lake Garda), the largest of the pre-alpine lakes (Fig.1). As one of the most interesting examples of Roman residential architecture in northern Italy, this villa deserves the designation of villa maritima, as other similar examples along the Campanium-Latium coast.The villa covers an area of around 20,000 square meters distributed on three terraces, which ascend the slope of the hill on a series of substructures. The building has a rectangular plan (167.5 x 105 meters), with two foreparts; on the S side at the main entrance and on the N side at the tip of the peninsula, towards which the villa faced, so as to be surrounded by the lake on three sides (Fig. 2).On the evidence of recent studies, the villa is dated to the Augustan-Tiberian period (end of the first century B.C. –start of the first century A.D.): it was constructed after the destruction of an earlier building, the existence of which has been documented in a small archaeological excavation beneath the floor of one of the rooms on the southern side of the villa. Modifications to the building, in particular the creation of the large baths area, date to the end of the first –second century A.D. The destruction of the villa came quickly, with all probability around the 3rd century: at that time the functioning of the villa seems to have stopped and no later maintenance or building interventions have been identified; a differing situation as regards the other villas in the lake Garda area, which had a continued life, with phases of great importance, up to the first half of the fifth century.The building, constructed as a whole and with axial and symmetrical criteria, is characterized by long terraces on the eastern, western and northern sides: these connect directly with the large terrace on the northern forepart, which was shaded by a veiled covering, as demonstrated by the characteristic elements which supported the posts found in this area. By the side of the terraces were long porticoes: the western one built over a double-nave cryptoporticus, which acted as a substructure, the eastern for the main part built directly on the natural bedrock. The residential rooms were distributed in the northern and southern areas, the western part of the latter being occupied by the baths complex (Fig. 3-4).While the substructures are well-preserved, the residential floor, situated on the higher level, has been subject to greater destruction over the course of the centuries, due to the systematic robbing of building materials, already started in ancient times, the collapse of part of the wall on the eastern side along the hill-side, and in the agricultural use of the land, presently occupied by a vast olive grove (Fig. 5). The villa has been excavated on several occasions from the start of the 19th century and subsequently backfilled, so that the plan and hypotheses for the reconstruction for a large part of the residential level, which has not been the object of new research in recent years, are based on the notes and drawings of the 19th century, not always reliable. Other excavations were conducted between 1941 and 1965; research aimed at defining the chronology of the building and resolving problems in the plan of several rooms in the southern area were undertaken between 1984 and 1994.The events endured by the structure render difficult and at times impossible, at present, to hypothesize the functions and characteristics of many of the residential rooms, as also with the various open spaces present within the building. Undoubtedly, other than the large peristyle (C), which occupied the central area of the building, other open spaces, now buried (courtyards or gardens), were to be found along the central N-S axis. In the southern part there was an open space (N), situated between the western part of the villa, destined as the baths complex, and the eastern part containing the living rooms. In this case, according to the interpretation of the director of the first excavations and more recently, the area functioned as a courtyard giving access and light to the rooms on its E, S and W sides. A wall divided the courtyard from the S side of the peristyle, to which direct access was possible by one or more entrances. Another hypothesis suggests that access between the two courtyards was not axial but by a side corridor, while a wall with windows would have permitted a view of the internal garden.Of the other open space (O), situated to the N, there is uncertainty as to its function. One can hypothesize, on the basis of the 19th century plans, an open space with porticoes on all four sides: perhaps another small peristyle. An element which would confirm its use as a courtyard or garden is the presence of a stone-built rainwater drain, still present in the 19th century and illustrated by Orti Manara in his publication on Sirmione. Some parts of this drain have been re-used in the walls of the Early Medieval church of San Salvatore in Sirmione. There are no precise indications for external gardens and it is only possible to hypothesize the natural setting in which the villa was situated. However it must be stated that artificial terraces had been made on the eastern side of the building, or more precisely the areas which corresponded to the N-E and S-E corners, formed by the two foreparts of the villa. In the first (H) the bedrock has been cut to a depth of around 4 meters to create a large terrace, which occupied the whole area as far as the drop in level towards the lake (Fig.6). It is interesting that the second artificial terrace (I), of more limited extension, at around 10 meters below the residential level of the villa and reached by a flight of steps, was still known in the 19th century, by ancient tradition and without apparent justification, as “the garden.”The large central open space (C), beginning from the 19th century, was identified as a courtyard-viridarium. It is formed by an area of around 4000 square meters, equivalent to about one fifth of the whole area of the villa (Fig.7). Both the 19th century excavations and more recent trenches have failed to locate the presence of structures or floors, and it is therefore possible to hypothesize that the area functioned as a garden, probably surrounded on all four sides by porticoes as indicated in the 19th century plans and supported by recent research.The present land use, with many trees, and the thin soil cover in respect to the original ground surface, no longer permit the acquisition of data to allow a more precise reconstruction of the ancient garden, its internal sub-divisions, the types of vegetation, the possible ornamentation. On the S side of the peristyle is located a large perfectly preserved underground cistern (66), of a length corresponding to the width of the peristyle (42.60 x 2.40 meters). It is covered by a herringbone floor in small bricks, 6 meters wide and around 50 meters long (fig.8). Rainwater, collected in this part of the building, flowed into the cistern through a series of lead fistulae which entered the S-E and S-W corners, as is demonstrated by holes in the floor created by the robbing of the lead pipes, of which fortunately a small part is still preserved in the S-W corner, where it enters the cistern. The floor of the cistern has a slope of 7-8% from S to N: on the northern side four channels collected rain water and allowed it to flow in an organized manner towards the garden, with a slope of 6% (fig.9). The channel was formed in the initial part by a prolongation of the herringbone brick floor, which with its tapering form towards the external area helped the entry of rainwater into the channel, which flowed beneath the ancient ground surface (Fig. 10). The channels, lined with hydraulic mortar, were excavated in the bedrock, which outcropped on the eastern side and were covered with thin stone slabs. On the opposite side they were constructed in the earth and only their lower parts are preserved, the covering and the ancient floor shaving been robbed. Given the slope of the channels, their conformation and number, it is to be excluded that they had the sole function of draining the rainwater from the brick floor, and it may be hypothesized that they also served the function of directing to the garden the water which was extracted from the cistern, perhaps for irrigation.Water was drawn from the cistern by one or more wells: in the 19th century a well-curb, which was said to have come from the area of cistern, was still preserved in Sirmione. By the side of the cut which housed one of the well-curbs, two square holes had been cut into the floor in ancient times. It is hypothesized that they held the posts for the structure supporting the ropes and vessel used to extract water from the cistern (girgillus).There are no other elements to help describe the form of the large peristyle. Two pieces which may have formed part of the decoration of the garden are composed of sculptural fragments: a head dating to the second century A.D., found in the soil inside the cistern (66), and a sundial, presently lost, but fortunately represented by a drawing. Given the location, the head must have come from the peristyle, and can be hypothesized as belonging to the statue of a Dioscuros (fig. 11). In Greek marble, it is broken at the level of the chin. The head is covered by a pilos, from which issue locks of hair, curling on the forehead and sides of the face.There are no useful clues to help reconstruct the vegetation, which may have been present in and around the villa.The climate of Lake Garda is sub-Mediterranean, determined by the notably large mass of water which tends to maintain a constant temperature, much milder than the rest of the cisalpine area. The cultivation of olives already existed in Roman times, as documented by botanical evidence from recent excavations at Sirmione and the strong spread of the plant both in the locality and the whole area around Lake Garda in the Early Medieval period. In the same manner grapes were probably also cultivated, indirectly represented by an inscription found near Sirmione (fig. 12). Probably also common in the Roman period were the native species, shrubs such as oleander and rosemary and trees such as cypress, bay, ash and several species of oak, documented in the last two examples by botanic remains found at Sirmione, recently analyzed by the Archaeobiological Laboratory of the Civic Museums of Como.
Plans {&amp;lt; figure src=&amp;rdquo;../images/sirmio-2.png&amp;rdquo; alt=&amp;quot;Fig. 2: Plan of House of Grotto of Catullus.&amp;rdquo; title=&amp;quot;Fig. 2: Plan of House of Grotto of Catullus&amp;rdquo; &amp;gt;}}
  Fig. 3: Plan of the residential rooms     Fig. 5: Aerial view of vast olive grove     Fig. 7: Aerial view of courtyard-viridarium     Fig. 11: statue of a Dioscuros     Fig. 12: Figure of Plant fossils   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1801
Bibliography  G.G. Orti Manara, La penisola di Sirmione sul lago di Garda, Verona 1856.(worldcat) N. Degrassi, Le Grotte di Catullo, Taranto 1956. (worldcat) M. MirabellaRoberti, La villa romana di Sirmione, Milano 1958, pp.157-162.(worldcat) T.P.Wiseman, Le Grotte di Catullo. Una villa romana e i suoi proprietari, Brescia 1990. (worldcat) E. Roffia, Sirmione, le “grotte di Catullo”, in Ville romane sul lago di Garda, a cura di E.Roffia, Brescia 1997, pp.141-169. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 870993210
TGN ID 7005771
Contributor Tom Elliott (https://pleiades.stoa.org/author/thomase)
Publication date 15 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb garden of A. Coelius C. f.</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/patavium/tomb_garden_of_a.-coelius_c.-f./</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/patavium/tomb_garden_of_a.-coelius_c.-f./</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Patavium
Patavium (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region X
Garden Tomb garden of A. Coelius C. f.
Keywords  tombs epitaphs stelae mausoleums  Garden Description A broken marble slab immured in the cathedral at Padua since the seventeenth century records the epitaph of A. Coelius C. f., who some time in the first or second century dedicated to the divine spirits (Dis Manibus) and to himself in perpetuity a garden that had once, it seems, belonged to an Arius (hortum… Arianum). Whether it had always been a tomb garden or was only then being converted to a funerary use is uncertain.
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date unspecified
Bibliography  CIL 5.2935  Pleiades ID 393473
TGN ID 77003085
Contributor Brady Kiesling (https://pleiades.stoa.org/author/bkiesling)
Publication date 15 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb garden of A. Coelius C. f.</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/region_x/patavium/tomb_garden_of_a_coelius_c_f/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/region_x/patavium/tomb_garden_of_a_coelius_c_f/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Patavium
Patavium (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region X
Garden Tomb garden of A. Coelius C. f.
Keywords  tombs epitaphs stelae mausoleums  Garden Description A broken marble slab immured in the cathedral at Padua since the seventeenth century records the epitaph of A. Coelius C. f., who some time in the first or second century dedicated to the divine spirits (Dis Manibus) and to himself in perpetuity a garden that had once, it seems, belonged to an Arius (hortum… Arianum). Whether it had always been a tomb garden or was only then being converted to a funerary use is uncertain.
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date unspecified
Bibliography  CIL 5.2935  Pleiades ID 393473
TGN ID 77003085
Contributor Brady Kiesling (https://pleiades.stoa.org/author/bkiesling)
Publication date 15 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of L. Ogius Patroclus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/altinum/tomb_garden_of_l.-ogius_patroclus/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/altinum/tomb_garden_of_l.-ogius_patroclus/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location ALTINUM
ALTINUM (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region X
Garden Tomb Garden of L. Ogius Patroclus
Keywords  tombs epitaphs stelae grove (sacred grove) vegetable gardens  Garden Description A marble slab reported at Altinum in the sixteenth century and now in Venice records, above a depiction of an axe, a plumb-line, and a tree with birds, the epitaph of L. Ogius Patroclus, who some time (probably) in the late first or second century, “following the tradition of dutiful respect maintained by the corporation of firemen, donated while still living the gardens with building adjoining the tomb, so that from their revenue roses and food would be supplied generously for his patron and, eventually, for himself” (secutus pietatem col(legii) cent(onariorum) hortos cum aedificio huic sepult(urae) {a} iunctos vivos donavit, ut ex reditu eor(um) largius rosae et esce patrono suo et quandoque sibi ponerentur). The pairing of roses for the dead and food for the living (rosae et escae) was common in Roman funerary celebrations at the grave site, which perhaps suggests that mixed planting of flowers and vegetables was common in Roman tomb gardens as well (cf. ILS 6711, 8371).
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 16th century
Bibliography  CIL 5.2176 ILS 8369  Pleiades ID 197110
TGN ID 4000603
Contributor Sean Gillies (https://pleiades.stoa.org/author/sgillies)
Publication date 15 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb garden of T. Vettius Hermes</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ix/vardagate/tomb_garden_of_t.-vettius_hermes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ix/vardagate/tomb_garden_of_t.-vettius_hermes/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Vardagate
Vardagate (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region IX
Garden Tomb garden of T. Vettius Hermes
Keywords  tombs epitaphs stelae  Garden Description A marble stele now in a church at Grazzano records the epitaph of T. Vettius Hermes, a freedman ointment dealer (seplasiarius). After a gnomic sentiment about chthonic birthand reunion (mater genuit materq(ue) recepiit), Hermes goes on to declare that “these gardens, as great and excellent as they are, (will) serve my ashes, for I shall appoint caretakers to dine on the proceeds from them on my birthday and on the day of roses, in perpetuity” (hi horti ita uti o(ptimi) m(aximi)/que sunt cineribus seruite(!) meis nam curatores substituam uti uescantur ex horum hortorum reditu natale meo et per rosam in perpetuo).
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date unspecified
Bibliography  CIL5.7454, cf. p. 7454 ILS8342  Pleiades ID 383809
TGN ID unspecified
Contributor Sean Gillies (https://pleiades.stoa.org/author/sgillies)
Publication date 15 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa at Pola&#34;</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/barbariga/villa_at_pola/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/barbariga/villa_at_pola/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location BARBARIGA
BARBARIGA (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region X
Garden Villa at Pola
Keywords  mosaics (visual works) cryptoportici gutters (building drainage components) podiums (building divisions) peristyles (columnades) porticoes tesserae villae urbanae reception rooms atrium houses mural paintings (visual works) presence chambers  Garden Description This large maritime villa consisted of two parts, labeled “summer villa” and “winter villa”. The “summer” quarters unfold around a U-shaped peristyle, open on the sea-side, with central garden measuring 31.8 x 26.2 m. (fig. 2: 4). No traces of a pool or fountain were found in the center of the garden. The portico, 2.40 m wide, had a mosaic floor in black tesserae with a white border. Many rooms looked into the peristyle, with the main one probably being a triclinium (Fig. 1). On the two opposite corners of this side of the courtyard were also service rooms: Room 6 was the kitchen, 15 maybe a storeroom (many amphorae were recovered, but the room had a mosaic floor). Of the rooms around the peristyle, Room 31 was the most lavishly decorated. The back wall presented a semicircular niche with a statue-base, the floor had an elaborate polychrome mosaic, and the walls were covered with marble slabs. South of the “summer villa” was a long cryptoportico, flanking a garden, no longer preserved, but known from nineteenth century archival documents. The villa was built in the first century A.D. and, at least in part, was used down to the sixth century A.D.
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1801
Bibliography  M. De Franceschini, 1998, Le ville romane della X regio: Venetia et Histria. Catalogo e carta archeologica dell’insediamento romano nel territorio, dall’età repubblicana al tardo impero, Roma.(worldcat)  Pleiades ID 870993210
TGN ID 7005771
Contributor Tom Elliott (https://pleiades.stoa.org/author/thomase)
Publication date 15 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa of the Bath</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/tergeste/villa_of_the_bath/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/tergeste/villa_of_the_bath/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Tergeste
Tergeste (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region X
Garden Villa of the Bath
Keywords  archaeological garden cisterns (plumbing components) gutters (building drainage components) villae urbanae peristyles (columnades) porticoes bathhouses (water recreation structures) water baths courtyards atrium houses corridors  Garden Description Remains discovered in 1888 revealed a large semicircular garden (Fig. 1: c) enclosed by a portico (b), into which opened a series of rooms (d to p). A corridor (a) connected this garden to a bath quarter that boasted a nymphaeum (t) and a panoramic view onto the sea. A similar semicircular portico and garden was in the villa of Anguillara Sabatia, but the radial disposition of the rooms of the ‘Villa della Terma’s’ pars urbana is unusual, revealing a desire to lend each room a view onto the garden. The preservation of this villa is poor because for centuries it was scavenged for building material. Dated material ranges from the first century B.C. (brick stamps) to the early fifth century A.D. (coins). It is possible that these remains were part of the nearby “Villa della Statua.”
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1888
Bibliography  M. De Franceschini, 1998, Le ville romane della X regio: Venetia et Histria. Catalogo e carta archeologica dell’insediamento romano nel territorio, dall’età repubblicana al tardo impero, Roma.(worldcat)  Pleiades ID 187578
TGN ID 7005539
Contributor Brady Kiesling
Publication date 15 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa of the Statue (I.iii.23)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/tergeste/villa_of_the_statue/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/tergeste/villa_of_the_statue/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Tergeste
Tergeste (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region X
Garden Villa of the Statue
Keywords  archaeological garden cisterns (plumbing components) gutters (building drainage components) mural paintings (visual works) peristyles (columnades) porticoes mosaic pergolas bathhouses (water recreation structures) water baths atrium houses atriums nymphaea (garden structures) tesserae ceramic tile opus sectile (visual works) opus signinum garden pavilions [apsed triclinium] [archaeological garden]  Garden Description A villa dating from the first century B.C. to at least the time of Marcus Aurelius was discovered near the modern via Miramare in Barcola. It overlooked the sea to the west and had a portico at the south (Fig. 1: B), with rooms opening onto it. The main nucleus of the villa unfolded around a rectangular garden surrounded by porticoes on all four sides (the long sides measure 24.5 m.; the short ones 15.2; Fig. 1: U). A rectangular brick pool with a black mosaic pavement was in the north-east portion of the garden (Fig. 1: a). It pre-dates the portico, since it was partly destroyed by the paving of the north-east portico. A terminus post quem for the construction of the portico was determined by a coin of Nero, found inside the pool.
During nineteenth century excavations, fragments of two superimposed wall paintings were recovered in Room C. The outer layer is not well enough preserved to identify any subject, but the preserved fragments beneath show branches and leaves with colored backgrounds of light blue, red, yellow and white. It is, therefore, possible that this cycle of painting depicted a garden, echoing the view of the real plantings visible through the doorway.
North of the peristyle was the bath quarter (Fig. 1: G, H, I, M, P), but it is not completely clear how the two parts of the villa were connected. In a partially excavated Tuscan type atrium (G) with an impluvium, several fragments of a marble torso were recovered, possible from a copy of the Polykleitan Doryphoros or Diadumenos. On the west side of the villa facing the sea was a porticoed garden (Z) and large semicircular exedra (24 m in diameter). Under the mosaic floor of this exedra are traces of an earlier room (Fig. 1: a) with a mosaic floor. On axis with the center of the exedra and garden was a triclinium (6.2 x 12 m) with a black-and-white mosaic floor. Another exedra (7.5 x 15 m), with a black-and-white mosaic floor, had large windows looking to the sea, and beside it a staircase leading to the water’s edge and to a dock.
Dates 100 B.C.
Excavation Date 19th century
Bibliography  M. De Franceschini, 1998, Le ville romane della X regio: Venetia et Histria. Catalogo e carta archeologica dell’insediamento romano nel territorio, dall’età repubblicana al tardo impero, Roma.(worldcat)  Pleiades ID 187578
TGN ID 7005539
Contributor Brady Kiesling
Publication date 15 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>II.ix.6.B</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_ix/ii.ix.6b/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_ix/ii.ix.6b/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region II
Insula Insula IX
Keywords  peristyles porticoes pilasters puteals lararia opus signinum doliums  Garden Description B. This vineyard section of the property was excavated in 1984 by Dr. De Caro. A small peristyle garden (b) was enclosed on the east and south by a three column portico with a pilaster on the southwest corner. A low wall joined the pilaster and the west column on the south side with a terra-cotta puteal incorporated into it. The north and east sides of the garden had a gutter. The south part of this vineyard had a small house with a garden painting on the west wall. The excavators found the painting to be badly damaged but a section showing a lattice fence 0.68 m. high with leaves and flowers behind remained on the right two-thirds of the building. All of the painting above the fence had been lost. A huge lararium was built against the north portion of the wall which partially covered the image of a Frejus type statuette of Venus 0.87 m. high. An entrance from the east portico¬ led directly to the vineyard which had been in production at the time of the eruption. At the front of the house on the west end a treading floor for the grapes had been built. The floor was raised, enclosed by a low wall 18 cm. high, and paved with opus signinum. The juice would run into a pair of dolium buried in the soil at the east edge of the floor. Fig. 81, 16.11.70, Fig. 82, 7.14.71; Fig. 83, 7.16.71; Fig. 84, 7.28.71; Fig. 85, 9.25.71, Fig. 86, 9.26.71, Fig. 87, 49.10.64, Fig. 88, 54.20.64.
Plans   Fig. 75, Plan of Region II, insula ix   Images   Fig. 81, 16.11.70 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 82, 7.14.71 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 83, 7.16.71 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 84, 7.28.71 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 85, 9.25.71 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 86, 9.26.71 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 87, 49.10.64 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 88, 54.20.64. (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)   Pleiades ID 456321707
TGN ID 7004658
Excavation Dates 1984
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, pp. 97-98, 333 (worldcat)  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 10 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Peristyle garden in house of Julia Felix (II.iv.a).</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_iv/house/ii.iv.a/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_iv/house/ii.iv.a/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region II
House House of Julia Felix
Garden Peristyle garden in house of Julia Felix
Keywords  jet d&amp;rsquo;eau peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes statuettes (free-standing sculpture) triclinia  Garden Description A. Three separate gardens were located in this property. It occupies the entire insula and is one of the largest properties in the city. It was originally excavated in 1755-1757, stripped of its works of art and re-buried. In 1951-1952 it was re-excavated and restored but not published. Sixteen elegantly carved slender marble pillars support a portico which borders the peristyle garden (a) on the west.Fig.18, 5.29.59, Fig. 19, 5.32.50, Fig. 20, 5.25.59 An alcove (b) housed a summer triclinium (l. medius, 4.00 m.; l. imus and summus 3.00 m.) with marble faced couches that looked through the portico into the garden. Between the couches a niche supplied water that ran down small marble steps to a hole at the bottom. The water re-surfaced as a jet in the middle of the trilinium. A vine covered arbor stretched along the south and east side of the garden and beyond it in bays on the east wall were raised planting beds, alternating semicircular and square. These were covered with pumice and decorated with a band of Egyptian blue around the sides and top, the middle bay having four bands of Egyptian blue. The room (c) to the south of the triclinium had a garden representation (0.185 x 0.42 m.) on the north part of the west wall on the red middle zone. Four fish ponds connected to form a long channel down the center of the garden. The little marble bridges that crossed the channel and covered alcoves at the bottom of the pools provided shelter for the fish and eels. A number of statuettes were found during the two excavations of this site. More recently the pieces that were found are as follows: A marble satyr (0.475 m. preserved height; Pompeii inv. no. 8856) located at the north end of the pool, a seated terra-cotta figure of Pittacus of Mitylene (0.65 m. high; Pompeii inv. no. 2181-4) found at the edge of the pool, a small marble fountain statuette of a sea crab in a shell (0.19 m. wide; Pompeii inv. no. 1073/54). During the earlier excavation some of the items found were as follows: a satyr child (0.46 m. high; Muz. Naz. inv. no. 6108), a nude youth holding grapes in his right hand and a goose in his left (0.76 m. high; Muz. Naz. inv. no. 6342), a faun(Muz. Naz. inv. no. 6343), an old man covered with a cloth (0.49 m. high), a bird with a lizard in its beak (0.32 m. high), a marble mask of a smiling youth on a small column (0.54 m. high), and a marble relief (0.36m. long x 0.11 m. high) of an old man seated of a bench, perhaps this was a pinax. The heads of twelve marble herms, (one woman, one old man, three bearded men) were reported by PAH, but the post of only one is mentioned and only the feet of the thirteenth herm was found. A terra-cotta group of Caritas Romana was found in many pieces as well as multiple fragments of other terra-cotta statuettes which had been in the eleven niches in the peristyle portico. Chambalu believed the herms stood between these niches.
Plans   view form the portico     detail of the jet.     portico and garden   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography   Annali Dell&amp;rsquo;instituto Di Correspondenza Archeologica, 1830, p.50 worldcat
  Bonucci, Carlo.Pompei Descritta Da Carlo Bonucc, p.219 worldcat
  Bragantini, Irene. Pitture E Pavimenti Di Pompei. Roma: Ministero per i beni culturali e ambientali, Istituto centrale per il catalogo e la documentazione, 1981. Print.1:238 worldcat
  Chambalu,Die weiderverschüttete Besitzung der Julia Felix beim Amphitheater in Pompeji, Pp, 1895. Print. pp. 14-15 and plan of Weber (1757) after p. 20 worldcat
  Della Corte, Notizie degli scavi antichita (1958), p. 125, no. 238 (Pittakos inscription);worldcat
  Dwyer, Eugene J. Pompeian Oscilla Collections: (pls. 80-130) Mainz: Verlag Philipp von Zabern, 1981. Print. p. 279, no. 81worldcat
  F. Rakob, *Ein Grottentriklinium in Pompeji,*RM (1964), pp. 182-194;worldcat
  H. Döhl, Plastik aus Pompeji , tesi di libera d tingen 1976, pp. 8-10
  Idem, Pompeii (Novara), p. 111 worldcat
  Idem, Pomp. Sculpture, pp. 67, 128, and figs. 197, 212;
  Jashemski, Wilhelmina F, The Gardens of Pompeii, Herculaneum, and the Villas Destroyed by Vesuvius, New Rochelle: Aristide D. Caratzas, 1979. Print , 1:48, 110 and figs. 81 on p. 47, 82 on p. 48, 83 (marble statue at north end of pool), 84 (Pittacus), and 85 (sea-crab in shell) on p. 49; worldcat
  Jashemski, Wilhelmina F, and Stanley A. Jashemski, The Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the Villas Destroyed by Vesuvius. New Rochelle, NY: Caratzas, 1993. Print. pp. 86-88, 396worldcat
  Kapossy, Balázs. Brunnenfiguren Der Hellenistischen Und Römischen Zeit. Zürich, 1969. Print. pp 46, 50 worldcat
  Lorenz, Thuri. Galerien Von Griechischen Philosophen Und Dichterbildnissen Bei Den Römern. Mainz: Verlag Ph. von Zabern, 1965. Print. p. 39worldcat
  Maiuri, I giardini, Le Vie d’Italia, no.9 Sept 1961, p. 1139; worldcat
  Maiuri, Statuette fittilli di Pittaco di Mitilene, Archeologia Classica 4 (1952): 55-59; worldcat
  Maiuri, Pompei ed Ercolano:Fra case ed abitanti, pp. 74-75; worldcat
  Pompeianarum Antiquitatum Historia, vol. 1 pt. 1, pp. 13, 15, 16, 18, 19, 21, 28, 29, 30, 31, 34, 37, 39 (Apr. 13, 1755-Mar. 6, 1756);Ibid., vol. 1 pt. 2, pp. 98, 101; worlcat
  Richter, Greek Portraits, 3:34 and fig. 134; worlcat
  Richter, Portraits of the Greeks, 1:89a; worlcat
  Rohden, Hermann. Die Terracotten Von Pompeji. Stuttgart, 1880. Print. pp. 24, 47-48, 53, 57, 62 and plates 35.3, 36, 41.4, 47; worldcat
  Salsa Prina Ricotti, The Importance of Water in Roman Open Air Tricliniums, in Ancient Roman Villa Gardens, Dumbarton Oaks Colloquium on the History of Landscape Architecture, no. 10, Dumbarton Oaks, 1987, pp. 172-173; worlcat
  Sear, Frank B. Roman Wall and Vault Mosaics. Heidelberg: F.H. Kerle, 1977. Print. p.94 worlcat
  Zahn, Wilhelm.Die Schönsten Ornamente Und Merkwürdigsten Gemälde Aus Pompeji, Herkulanum Und Stabiae vol2.pl.100 (plan)worldcat
  Pleiades ID 955554415
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 2 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb garden of T. Vettius Hermes (I.iii.23)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_xi/vardagate/tomb_garden_of_t.-vettius_hermes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_xi/vardagate/tomb_garden_of_t.-vettius_hermes/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Vardagate
Vardagate (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region IX
Garden Tomb garden of T. Vettius Hermes
Keywords  tombs epitaphs stelae  Garden Description A marble stele now in a church at Grazzano records the epitaph of T. Vettius Hermes, a freedman ointment dealer (seplasiarius). After a gnomic sentiment about chthonic birthand reunion (mater genuit materq(ue) recepiit), Hermes goes on to declare that “these gardens, as great and excellent as they are, (will) serve my ashes, for I shall appoint caretakers to dine on the proceeds from them on my birthday and on the day of roses, in perpetuity” (hi horti ita uti o(ptimi) m(aximi)/que sunt cineribus seruite(!) meis nam curatores substituam uti uescantur ex horum hortorum reditu natale meo et per rosam in perpetuo).
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date unspecified
Bibliography  CIL5.7454, cf. p. 7454 ILS8342  Pleiades ID 383809
TGN ID unspecified
Contributor Sean Gillies (https://pleiades.stoa.org/author/sgillies)
Publication date 25 Oct 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Funerary Grove of Q. Cervonius Chryseros</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/aquileia/funerary_grove_of_q.-cervonius_chryseros/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/aquileia/funerary_grove_of_q.-cervonius_chryseros/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Aquileia
Aquileia (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region X
Garden Funerary Grove of Q. Cervonius Chryseros
Keywords  tombs stelae grove (sacred grove) altars (religious fixtures)  Garden Description A small inscribed altar of (probably) the Julio-Claudian era found by Mommsen among the stones of Aquileia and now lost records on its left and right sides dedications to Dis Pater and (H)era respectively and, on its front, the name of the dedicant, a consul’s aide (acc(ensus) co(n)s(ularis)) and local sevir at Florentia, Q. Cervonius Chryseros, who built “the grove, the enclosure wall, the altars, the mound (? molem), and the seats” (lucum, maceriem, aras, molem, [s]edilia). The dedication to Dis Pater suggests a funerary context, which leads Chioffi to identify the molis as a tomb monument of some ill-defined type (perhaps an irregular mound?). A Roman soldier serving in lower Germany at Carvium (Herwen) was buried by his two heirs ad molem, “near (or at) the mound” (AE 1939, 130). The same Chryseros perhaps appears as the owner of a slave, Fausta, who in fulfillment of a vow dedicated another monument to Dis Pater at Aquileia (CIL 5.35*).
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date unspecified
Bibliography  G. B. Brusin, Inscriptiones Aquileiae, Udine 1991-1993, no. 192.(worldcat) S. Panciera, Libitina e dintorni : Libitina e i luci sepolcrali, Rome 2004, nn. 17-31. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 187290
TGN ID 7005553
Contributor Sean Gillies (https://pleiades.stoa.org/author/sgillies)
Publication date 15 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa di Galba (VII.2)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/insula_vii/casa_di_galba/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/insula_vii/casa_di_galba/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Insula Insula VII
Garden Casa di Galba
Keywords  stuccoing porticoes peristyle houses exedrae  Garden Description The excavation of this site was begun in 1873-1874 and is still incomplete. A silver bust, supposedly of the emperor Galba, found in the street in front of this house gave the site its name. Twelve stuccoed tuffa columns support a portico which encloses this peristyle garden. A marble faced cruciform basin in the center contained a small column with a fountain. The columns were connected by a low wall with an entrance on the east opposite the exedra providing a view of the garden and fountain.
Plans   Plan of the new excavations of Herculaneum (Maiuri, Herculaneum)   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography Maiuri, Herculaneum, pp. 25-26 (worldcat) Maiuri, Ercolano, pp. 405-406 and fig. 340 (plan) on p. 404 (worldcat) Ruggiero, Ercolano, p. 663 (worldcat)
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 20 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Eisenstadt</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/eisenstadt/eisenstadt_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 09:31:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/eisenstadt/eisenstadt_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Pannonia
Location Eisenstadt
Eisenstadt (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Eisenstadt
Keywords  altars (religious fixtures) archaeological garden atriums peristyles (Roman courtyards) podiums (building divisions) porticoes villae rusticae  Garden Description The residence of this villa rustica was entered on the southeast by a portico (Fig. 1). After passing through a room interpreted as the atrium, one arrived in the open courtyard which had a peristyle on three sides (G on plan). On the northern edge of the courtyard was a podium (P on plan) near which votive altars to Diana and Silvanus were found, both gods of the woods and suitable subjects for a garden. This corner of the courtyard, thus, seems to have had religious character. In the middle of the courtyard was a square foundation, measuring 1.80 x 1.80 m., possibly the remains of a base for some kind of figure. The villa rustica was established in the early 2nd century and occupied probably until the 4th century.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the rural villa with a peristyle courtyard (G) and a podium (P) for sculpture. Adapted from Thomas 1964, fig. 73. (Rights statement.)   Dates Early 2nd century - 4th century
Bibliography  E.B. Thomas, Römische Villen in Pannonien, Budapest, 1964, pp. 137-151, fig. 73. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 197425
TGN ID 7003056
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Structures under the Collège Lumière in Vesontio</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vesontio/vesontio_structures_under_the_colle%CC%80ge_lumie%CC%80re/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 09:48:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vesontio/vesontio_structures_under_the_colle%CC%80ge_lumie%CC%80re/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Vesontio
Vesontio (Pleiades)
Location Description The defensibility offered by this unique geography made Caesar hasten to occupy Vesontio in 58 BC. The town came to have all the usual Roman structures– forum, baths, aqueduct, and amphitheater (on the other side of the Doubs, to the northwest.) But the most visible remnant is the Porte Noire (Black Gate) [3], a triumphal arch built by Marcus Aurelius at the southeastern end of the cardo maximus, today Grande Rue and still the center of city life.
Archaeology in a downtown area is always a matter of seizing opportunities as they are presented by new construction, remembering and recording what was found, and coming back years later to complete the picture. A good example of this process is at our second site, [2] on the map. In 1973, the Neptune Mosaic was discovered in rue de Lorraine, one of the largest floor decorations in all Gaul. The extent of the mosaic under nearby buildings made full excavation impossible. More than thirty years later, in 2004, construction of a gymnasium for the Collège Lumière (a middle school) gave archaeologists access to much more of the site, about 3000 square meters, for a salvage excavation. As expected, the continuation of the Neptune mosaic was found; moreover, three other mosaics of high quality, along with columns, sculpted blocks, peristyles, and monumental pools came to light. The results of this excavation have not been published; we are grateful to the excavators for sharing their preliminary results.
Garden Structures under the Collège Lumière in Vesontio
Keywords  colonnades kraters mosaics (visual works) opus signinum peristyles (Roman courtyards) piscinae porticoes reception rooms rinceaux terrazzo  Garden Description The results of the 2004 excavation at the Collège Lumière are still under study and the data are therefore still partial. This zone, close to the river and the artisinal quarter has, in the past, yielded most of the mosaics recorded for Besançon. The ancient structures discovered on 3000 square meters relate to a Gallo-Roman urbanization extending from the Augustan period to the third century and superimposed on a rather dense Gallic occupation of the first century BC. Two phases of construction from the late Augustan period up through the end of the first century, have thus far not permitted the confirmation of the possible presence of a garden. On the other, later constructions dating from the beginning and last third of the second century are rich in peristyles with open space suitable for a garden.
At the beginning of the second century, in a third phase, a structure of large dimension (at least 2500 m2) but undetermined purpose was built on fill and leveling of the abandoned earlier buildings. It will simplify descriptions to let “north” denote the direction that is actually northeast, the direction towards the river. In these terms, large rooms (the largest reaching 126 sq. m.) and corridors were bordered on the south by an open area, possibly a garden, with porticos on at least the north and west sides, and by one peristyle to the west and by another to the east. The walls of the porticos around these peristyles were decorated with painted plaster. The west peristyle (at least 22 x 20 m) is the most complete. Only one wall, the east wall of the west peristyle, is common to these second century structures and the preceding ones of first century. It may thus represent a property line. Originally, it opened over a large threshold between the largest of the rooms and the western peristyle. It was subsequently first reduced and then completely closed.
The fourth phase, a remodeling at the end of the second century, is the best preserved, but its purpose remains unclear. It has yielded a series of elements that allow us to follow the architectural reasoning of the builders. It kept the basic plan of the third state: a peristyle to the east, one to the west, and a large garden to the south. The rooms, however, are considerably rearranged. Three grand reception rooms (of 200, 85, and 65 m2 ) with floors decorated with luxurious mosaics are organized in a very regular fashion in relation to the two peristyles and garden by corridors or galleries. The floors of these numerous spaces of circulation were a terrazzo in an opus signinum matrix, except for the gallery of garden, which had a mosaic.
The largest of the rooms, decorated by the Neptune mosaic, opened on its north side through a colonnade onto the south of the east peristyle and through another colonnade on the opposite side to the garden on the south. The spacing of the columns was the same (4.6 m) on both colonnades. The excavated part of the east peristyle showed that it was 22.3 meters wide; if it was square, it would have had an area of about 500 square meters. Another large room decorated with the rinceaux mosaic (so called for the bands of scrolled foliage) also opens onto the east peristyle. The gallery that borders the garden was widened into the garden in front of the Neptune room; against the wall of this extension there was a pool at least 1.5 meters wide and probably about 13 meters long. Several paving stones of the bottom have survived. The last room, the one with the Medusa mosaic, would seem to have opened onto the garden. The garden was about .95 meters lower than the house and was reached by descending four steps. The north portico of the west peristyle was enlarged in this final phase; the interval between columns reached 6.7 meters. The presence of the closed wall that may have been a property line obliges us to ask Did this west peristyle really belong to the structure to the east or was it part of a different edifice that may have extended to the west outside the limits of the excavation?
A fragment of a little ornamental stone krater was found in the material that filled the east peristyle after its abandonment. From late antiquity is the foundation of a pool or cistern of about 3.5 by 2.5 meters. Its stones have been removed, and only the opus signinum mortar bearing the imprint of the stones has been found. This structure pierced through all the archaeological levels and into the natural earth.
Plans Images not available (?)  Fig. 1: Plan of the domus, now under the Collège Lumière.  Dates Gardens: Beginning and last third of second century
Excavation Dates 2004
Bibliography  C. Gaston and C. Munier “Une luxueuse domus de la find du IIe siècle à Besançon, college Lumière (Doubs, F)&amp;rdquo;&amp;rdquo; in Premières Journées archéologiques frontalières de l&amp;rsquo;Arc jurassien: Mandeure, sa campagne et ses relations d&amp;rsquo;Avenches à Luxeuil et d&amp;rsquo;Augst à Besançon. Ed, Cécile Bélet-Gonda, Presses Univ. Franche-Comté (2007), 103-112.  Pleiades ID 177657
TGN ID 7008356
Contributor Claudine Monier (ORCID: N/A)
Christophe Gaston (ORCID: https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6865-5108)
Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 20 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House in the Rue du Palais de Justice in Vesontio</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vesontio/vesontio_house_in_the_rue_du_palais_de_justice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2020 16:58:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vesontio/vesontio_house_in_the_rue_du_palais_de_justice/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Vesontio
Vesontio (Pleiades)
Location Description The defensibility offered by this unique geography made Caesar hasten to occupy Vesontio in 58 BC. The town came to have all the usual Roman structures– forum, baths, aqueduct, and amphitheater (on the other side of the Doubs, to the northwest.) But the most visible remnant is the Porte Noire (Black Gate) [3], a triumphal arch built by Marcus Aurelius at the southeastern end of the cardo maximus, today Grande Rue and still the center of city life.
Archaeology in a downtown area is always a matter of seizing opportunities as they are presented by new construction, remembering and recording what was found, and coming back years later to complete the picture. A good example of this process is at our second site, [2] on the map. In 1973, the Neptune Mosaic was discovered in rue de Lorraine, one of the largest floor decorations in all Gaul. The extent of the mosaic under nearby buildings made full excavation impossible. More than thirty years later, in 2004, construction of a gymnasium for the Collège Lumière (a middle school) gave archaeologists access to much more of the site, about 3000 square meters, for a salvage excavation. As expected, the continuation of the Neptune mosaic was found; moreover, three other mosaics of high quality, along with columns, sculpted blocks, peristyles, and monumental pools came to light. The results of this excavation have not been published; we are grateful to the excavators for sharing their preliminary results.
Garden House in the Rue du Palais de Justice in Vesontio
Keywords archaeological garden \
 domus fountains hypocausts mosaics (visual works) opus sectile (visual works) opus signinum oeci peristyles (columnades) piscinae porticoes terrazzo water wells  Garden Description In 2000-2001, at the time of construction a new judiciary facility, an area of 2000 square meters was excavated at the center of this loop. The results are in large part unpublished. On land that had been occupied since the end of the second century BC, two houses of perishable materials were built in the eastern part of the site in the beginning of the first century AD. They were abandoned at the beginning of the Flavian epoch, and replaced by two imposing domus that lasted up to the middle of the third century. They stood on opposite sides of a property line wall (tinted in purple in Fig. 1) that was parallel to a cardo running in a northwest-to-southeast direction some hundred meters away. The two houses had slightly different orientations. The eastern house doubtless opened onto a southwest-northeast street passing 50 meters beyond the eastern limit of the excavation but partially brought to light in 1989-90 during excavations when a new parking facility was being built for the city hall. In this house, two independent structures (oecus) (tinted pink in the figure) with floors once decorated with mosaics since disappeared are wrapped about and connected by a portico (yellow tint) of complex plan with galleries 3 meters wide and opening onto an open space (green tint) covering 110 square meters. The counterpart of this portico is in part visible on the other side of the larger room. An incompletely known peristyle borders this oecus to the east (on the lower right edge of the plan). Its gallery was decorated with a terrazzo floor of opus signinum with accents of crustae, thin stone slices of which an opus sectile is made. In this phase, the north domus had a peristyle of 75 square meters with galleries on three sides. To the west (lower left corner of the plan), there was a large open space of nearly 500 square meters, which may have been a garden. At its west end, the wall of an incomplete building ran by a well and a masonry square 2.16 meters on a side which may have been the base of a shrine or monument. These structures were aligned with the property line wall. There was as yet no pool.
In the second half of the second century, the “garden” was restructured. The building on the west side was abandoned, the shrine or monument was kept, and a large pool put in at the eastern end supported against the wall of a terrace supporting the house to the east and consequently having the same orientation. This rectangular pool (21.2 x 3.5 m) had on the garden side a semicircular apse 6.9 meters in diameter. As part of the same architectural ensemble, a portico formed the retro-scene of the pool. Its opus signinum floor was 80 centimeters above the surface of the pool. Another, wider portico ran along the north side of the area. A shim-shaped gap existed between it and the property-line wall because of the difference in orientation. The monumental character of the pool and the north portico suggests that this garden may have been independent of both houses and was possibly a public space or belonged to a house further west, outside the limits of excavation.
At the beginning of the third century, the two domus were transformed. In particular, polychrome mosaics were installed in the east house and rooms with hypocausts in the north house. The little shrine or monument at the western end of the garden was eliminated, but the pool was reconstructed without alteration. The paving stones that had been in a pool were in part removed and used to build a 3.8 x 2.9 meter platform which served as the base, presumably, of a quadrangular fountain in the north house in an open space which replaced the peristyle, which was then destroyed.
Images Images not available (?) FIGURES:
 Fig. 1: Houses at the Palais de Justice Fig. 2: Axonometric representation  Dates Beginning of the Flavian epoch - middle of the third century
Excavation Dates 2000-2001
Bibliography  C. Gaston, “Un bassin monumental et une fontaine dans les fouille du Palais de Justice de Besancon,” Revue Archéologique de l&amp;rsquo;Est, t. 52, 2003, p.417-428. Christophe Gaston: “Données récentes sur l&amp;rsquo;achitecture antique à Besançon,” Archéopages/Inrap. No. 8, Nov. 2002, p. 28-35. Laurent Vaxelaire, Philippe Barral, “Besançon: de l’oppidum à la ville romaine” in La naissance de la ville dans l’Antiquité, M. Reddé et al. ed., Paris, 2003, p. 254-256.  Pleiades ID 177657
TGN ID 7008356
Contributor Claudine Monier (ORCID: N/A)
Christophe Gaston (ORCID: https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6865-5108)
Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 19 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa in Vallon (Sur Dompierre, Canton de Fribourg, Switzerland)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vallon/vallon_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2020 17:12:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vallon/vallon_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Vallon
Vallon (Pleiades)
Garden Villa in Vallon (Sur Dompierre, Canton de Fribourg, Switzerland)
Keywords  arbors barns cisterns (plumbing components) ceramic tile ditches fences (site elements) hearths horrea kitchen gardens mosaics (visual works) orchards pedestals pillars piscinae porticoes sherds tesserae villae rusticae water supply systems  Garden Description Located 6km south-east of Avenches/ Aventicum, the capital of the Helvetian tribe, this site is situated on a small alluvial terrace at the bottom of a hillside. The area is bordered by a stream, the Laret, characterized by a flow, sometimes torrential, that has fluctuated during the past centuries. To the west, on the right bank, stands the rocky spur of Carignan (Fig. 1). Due to the relatively restrictive topography, human settlements favoured the left bank until the Middle Ages.
On the spur east of the stream, a building made of a light structure, apparently isolated, is constructed at the beginning of the 1st c. CE; it is bordered on its southern and northern sides by two roads. During the years 30/40 CE, a peripheral gallery on wooden pillars is placed around it. Its layout rather suggests an annex of a villa rustica or perhaps even a simple house in an urban context. Between 50 and 70 CE, it is surrounded by two other constructions, which together with the first building take on the characteristic shape of an “L”. The northern house is made of several habitation rooms; as it is bordered by a portico, it recalls the dwelling places of the medium-sized villae rusticae discovered in Switzerland. The southern building, surrounded by galleries, is laid out around a 100 m2 large kitchen, containing a large central hearth, which separates, to the south, the rooms designed for habitation, and the areas, to the north, apparently dedicated to utilitarian activities. At the back of the southern construction, a fourth building was erected, a barn (horreum) recognizable because of the network of pillars that supported an elevated floor.
A wall section, placed under a later separating wall, already indicates the existence of a division of the area between the northern and southern parts of the garden. The occupation layer is marked by a number of undated hollow structures. A ditch, boarded on the east by two big oval pits, distinguishes itself by its orientation which is parallel to the front of the central building, but its function still remains unknown: could it be an early garden arrangement? The only palynological analysis undertaken in a trench opened in the north building, suggest a tree canopy composed of a mixture of oaks, birches and hazel trees, in the second half of the 1st century CE; alders and willow trees could be found along the stream banks. An abundance of ferns and conifers grew in the surrounding areas. Herbaceous vegetation was intermingled with cereals. The information in our possession is too scarce to allow us to interpret it as a garden. Traces of equidistant posts or peg holes appear to form the outline of structures that are still difficult to explain (light arbour-like construction?). This open space is confined by a small bank to the south. Below it, the area is crossed by two long perpendicular depressions that could have a natural origin (paleochannel?), re-used as rubbish disposals at the beginning of our era. The south-east oriented channel, originally interpreted as a clay extraction pit, was cleared over a distance of approximately thirty meters. It was seven to eight meters wide, 1,2 meters deep and contained, in its lower part, several conduits made from pine trees (fig. 3). These timber elements were not assembled but stored in a humid environment before being used. The preparation and preservation of wood for plumbing systems, suggests the existence, from the first Antique settlements, of a very elaborate running water supply system, its use in domestic and/or handicraft or farming activities still needs to be clarified. Dendrochronology reveals two time series, dated to the autumn/winter 3/4 CE and 32/33 CE. These dates, that are contemporary with the first building stages of the villa, are very early for Switzerland and are close to Avenche’s first dated constructions.
The edges of the channel, which are gradually filled in, are bordered by two small fences in the last quarter of the Ist century; these fittings may be the result of a wish to stabilize the banks of the channel, clearly still under water at that time. Later on, the channel is filled in by a new rubbish disposal that seals the fences. We know nothing about the appearance of the area (courtyard or garden?) which extended between the channel and the southern building.
The profound architectural developments that took place in the three habitation buildings from the years 150/160 CE, had repercussions on the gardens (fig. 2). The occupation layer of the courtyards to the west of the buildings is raised by bringing in a large amount of ballast material. The subdivision of the garden zone is not precisely known. To the west of the constructed area, in the northern area bordered by the waterway, a pedestal indicates the presence of a statuary decoration that will be removed by the next generation. A long masonry wall, decorated with pillars presumably sculpted, is the only partition element brought to light. It marks the boundaries of an area interpreted as an ornamental garden, onto which the northern building and the northern part of the central building open. Divided into two zones, the oriental part of the northern garden is covered with tiles, revealing in its northern corner a fountain; it is replaced, in its western part, by soil around which a fence was probably built. It communicates directly with a second ornamental garden situated on the side of the central building, maybe destined for the private use of the family and close relatives. Here too, the remains are sparse: a patch stretches along the separation wall with the northern garden. A path followed the central building. Others must have crossed beds of plants edged with vertical ceramic elements. In other places, wooden posts formed rows that are still difficult to elucidate but that may indicate the outline of arbours. In the same place were found meander shaped ditches which do not follow the exact same orientation as the buildings (fig. 4). Were they hedges that were part of a vegetal maze? Despite the absence of palynological facts, they can be compared to the ditches excavated in the gardens of the Fishbourne Villa (England) or to those in the pars urbana of Dietikon’s villae (canton of Zurich).
At the end of the first archaeological excavations (1985-2000), we favoured the hypothesis of a subdivision of the area to the west of the buildings into three juxtaposed courtyards which echoed the tripartition of the constructions. They contained two ornamental gardens, in the north and in the center, and a courtyard that sheltered a kitchen garden and an orchard at the front of the southern building, dedicated to utilitarian activities (fig. 5). The recent research does not support a division of the area into three distinctive courtyards (2006/2010). The second garden, which presents a regular incline to the south, does not show any tangible boundary. Did it occupy the whole area in the front of the south building, or were they garden arrangements (hedges) dividing it? (fig. 6) Traces of vegetation being very hard to spot on the surface of the ground of the gardens, no definitive conclusion can be drawn.
The recent discovery of the lower part of a pool in front of the south building has also casts doubts on its utilitarian function. The structure itself, laid on a foundation of stakes made from oak and alder wood dated by dendrochonology to the years after 160 CE, has been almost entirely retrieved. The interpretation of this structure is still under discussion: it could be a cistern but it is more likely to be an ornamental pool that could have been enhanced by a parietal mosaic composed of the many glass tesserae that were found nearby. The structure, standing against the south building, would be oriented not towards the construction itself, but towards the courtyard where no garden arrangement has been uncovered.
Whereas the courtyards have offered very few traces for the Early Roman Period, the Late Antique Period marks a turning point in the history of Vallon’s gardens. Following a fire, the buildings are reorganized and areas dedicated to handicraft activities appear in the porticoes. A new function is attributed to the courtyards. The rubble of the partially demolished north and central buildings is discarded in the northern garden and the northern part of the second courtyard. To the south of themeander shaped ditches, is built a construction consisting of posts and sill plates, equipped with a ground hearth made out of ceramic tiles. The late occupation of the gardens seems to be linked to the salvage and transformation of building materials collected in the edifices. Other post structures (constructions? enclosures?) almost cover the whole area in the front of the southern building. The archaeological objects found (pottery fragments, over a hundred coins) suggest that this occupation partly covers the IVth century and does not go further than the beginning of the Vth century.
After the disappearance of the Antique site, the land continues to be occupied during the Early Middle Ages. The discovery of channels supports the hypothesis that the areas between the new buildings or on their sides, were well enough built to see the creation of an ornamental garden. However, the remains are too disrupted to allow further discussion.
Maps   Fig. 1: Vallon location map. (Rights Statement)     Fig. 2 : map of the habitation zone in the second half of the IInd century of our era.(Rights Statement)   Images   Fig. 3 : pine wood conduits preserved in one of the channels. Photo Fribourg State Archaeological Service. (Rights Statement)     Fig. 4 : ditches uncovered in the courtyard in front of the central building (2006). Photo Fribourg State Archaeological Service. (Rights Statement)     Fig. 5 : scale model of the habitation area in the second half of the IInd century. Built before the research in the gardens was resumed, it presents a considerable partitioning of the various open spaces. Photo Fribourg State Archaeological Service. (Rights Statement)     Fig. 6 : watercolour of the habitation area integrating the first results obtained by excavating the gardens. Please note the less significant partition between the different courtyards. The cistern at the front of the south building (to the right) is highly hypothetical; it seems rather to be an ornamental pool. Watercolour: Bernard Reymond, Yverdon-les-Bains (Switzerland). (Rights Statement)   Dates Beginning of the 1st c. CE - beginning of the Vth century
Excavation Dates 1985-2000, 2006/2010
Bibliography No bibliography listed Pleiades ID 981525
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor Michel Fuchs (ORCID: 0000-0001-8176-8393)
Jacques Monnier (ORCID: N/A)
Publication date 18 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Hummetroth</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/hummetroth/hummetroth_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 11:47:11 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/hummetroth/hummetroth_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Hummetroth
Hummetroth (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Hummetroth
Keywords  apsed triclinium bathhouses (water recreation structures) corridors hypocausts porticoes reception rooms terrace gardens villae rusticae  Garden Description The enclosed farmyard, including the residential area (pars urbana) and the service zone with outbuildings and working areas (pars rustica), covered an area of 3.5 hectares. The house of this villa rustica of the 2nd century is of the winged corridor type with two protruding wings framing a large courtyard in front of the house at the south (Fig. 1).
The courtyard was divided into two zones by a terrace(?) wall, and in both zones a garden has been reconstructed (G in Fig. 1). Entering the house from the south, one passed through a large reception room to an apsed triclinium with hypocaust heating. A bath complex lay to the southwest, entered by the portico next to the garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the rural villa with a large terraced courtyard garden (G) to the south. Plan adapted from Baatz and Herrmann 1989, fig. 303a.   Dates 2nd century
Bibliography  D. Baatz and F.-R. Herrmann, eds., Die Römer in Hessen, 2nd ed., Stuttgart,1989, pp. 360-361, fig. 303a-b. (worldcat) M. Carroll, Romans,Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 74, fig. 29. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981525
TGN ID 7165467
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 16 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Ferpicloz</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ferpicloz/ferpicloz_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 15:32:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ferpicloz/ferpicloz_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Ferpicloz
Ferpicloz (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Ferpicloz
Keywords archaeological garden \
 porticoes villae rusticae  Garden Description The house of this villa rustica was of the winged corridor type (A in Fig. 1) with a porticoed facade (Fig. 1). Attached to the eastern end of the house, measuring 37 x 46 meters, was a wall running east-west which has been interpreted as the protective wall of a garden (G in Fig. 1).
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the rural villa (A) with a possible garden (G) protected by a wall to the east of the main building. The shoreline of the lake is dotted. Adapted from Drack and Fellmann 1988, fig. 369. (Rights Statement)   Dates unspecified
Bibliography  W. Drack and R. Fellmann, Die Römer in der Schweiz, Stuttgart, 1988, pp. 394-395, fig. 369. (worldcat) R. Fellmann, La Suisse gallo-romaine. Cinq siècles d’histoire, Lausanne, 1992, p. 157, fig. 116.3. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981525
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 15 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Dietikon</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/dietikon/dietikon_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 13:09:50 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/dietikon/dietikon_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Dietikon
Dietikon (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Dietikon
Keywords  archaeological garden axial plan corridors pergolas piscinae porticoes villae rusticae  Garden Description This villa rustica complex was built on a site at the bottom of a valley near and parallel to the river Limmat. Dietikon was situated on an important land and water traffic route from the Bündner Alps to Vindonissa and further north to the Rhine. Recent excavations supply valuable evidence for a garden in front of the entrance to a rural residence, giving insight into the appearance of other similar villas at which, for one reason or another, no physical remains of gardens have been retrieved. The excavations revealed a first villa with timber buildings dating to the Tiberian period, or early 1st century AD. Around the middle of the 1st century AD these first buildings were replaced by an axially-constructed stone-built villa complex with an enclosure, covering a total surface of 13 hectares (Fig. 1 and 4).
In the residential part of the farm (pars urbana) was a large corridor villa with two protruding wings enclosing a courtyard area on three sides. This area was planted as an ornamental garden in the mid-1st century (Fig 2, G in Fig. 2). On either side of the central path, garden zones were bordered by bedding trenches, 20-25 centimeters deep and 20-40 centimeters wide. The line of plantings flanking the path are curved to form two niches (Fig. 3). In Dietikon, digging of planting trenches would have been necessary because the massive layers of construction debris deposited to level this area for the building would have hampered a successful growing of garden plants. The archaeobotanical analysis of several soil samples revealed little of relevance, but box hedges have been suggested as the vegetation in the bedding trenches, forming a low living edge to these formal garden beds, and possibly climbing plants such as ivy along the porticoed façade. Shallow pits in the plots surrounded by the hedges may be the remains of bedding pits for trees or shrubs. A timber pergola in the courtyard ran parallel to the northeast wing of the house. To the west of the courtyard garden was a timber-lined pool fed by a stream, interpreted as a fishpond. Bedding trenches for hedges surrounded it.
In the late 1st century, around AD 70, the timber-lined pool in the west was replaced by a masonry pool lined with water-proof plaster on the same spot (Fig. 5). This was possibly fed by water from a small stream. At the same time, the timber pergola was dismantled, its place taken by a large masonry pool, 3 x 22 meters in plan. The planting pattern of the courtyard garden was retained (Fig. 5) until after the middle of the 2nd century when the pools were destroyed and the garden leveled.
Plans   Fig. 1: Overall plan of the site during the 2nd half of the 1st century and 1st half 2nd century AD. Plan courtesy of Christa Ebnöther.     Fig. 2: Plan of the main building with its garden, phase 1, ca. 50-70 AD. Plan courtesy of Christa Ebnöther.     Fig. 3: Plan of the main building showing the curved plantings flanking the path. (Rights Statement)   Images   Fig. 4: Reconstructed perspective drawing. (Rights Statement)     Fig. 5: Photo of the masonry pool with planting pattern of the courtyard garden retained. (Rights Statement)   Dates Garden: Late 1st century (~70 CE) - Middle of the 2nd century
First buildings: Early 1st century CE - Middle of 1st century CE
Stone-built villa: Middle of the 1st century CE
Bibliography  C. Ebnöther, &amp;ldquo;Die Gartenanlage in der pars urbana des Gutshofes von Dietikon ZH,&amp;rdquo; Archäologie der Schweiz 14, 1991:250-256. (worldcat) C. Ebnöther, Der römische Gutshof in Dietikon. Monographien der Kantonsarchäologie Zürich 25, Zürich, 1995, pp. 36-45, 49-50, figs. 21, 36-37,41-42. (worldcat) L. Flutsch, U. Niffeler, F. Rossi, eds., La Suisse du Paléolithique à l’aube du Moyen-Age (SPM) V. Epoque romaine/Età Romana, Basel, 2002, p. 143, fig. 140. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981525
TGN ID 7007345
Contributor Christa Ebnöther
Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 15 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Bad Kreuznach</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/bad_kreuznach/bad_kreuznach_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 12:39:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/bad_kreuznach/bad_kreuznach_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Bad Kreuznach
Bad Kreuznach (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Bad Kreuznach
Keywords  apsed triclinium colonnades cryptoportici fountains gutters (building drainage components) lararia mosaics (visual works) peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes villae rusticae  Garden Description This villa, almost 6000 square meters in size, gives eloquent testimony to the wealth and status of the owner of the rural estate. The estate was built in the second half of the 2nd century and occupied until its destruction around 275.
The three-storied villa with more than 50 rooms on the ground floor alone, many decorated with mosaics and imported marble revetment, was centered on a colonnaded garden courtyard (G in Fig. 1). Many of the sandstone columns from the peristyle, as well as fragments of sculpture from the garden, were found in the courtyard. The house was built into a hill, and the courtyard was terraced on two levels. Around the edges of the garden was a ground level gutter. From the apsed triclinium on the south, with a mosaic floor and a marble fountain in the middle, there was an excellent view of the garden.
At the northeast of the villa was a garden (G in Fig. 1) with a lararium. On the southwest there was a garden (G in Fig. 1) with a fountain. The northern facade had a cryptoporticus below and a porticoed corridor on the story above. The service area of the villa rustica lay in front of the villa to the north.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the rural villa with gardens (G) in the central courtyard and in the corners of the house. Plan adapted from Cüppers 1990, fig. 204.(Rights statement)   Dates Second half of 2nd century - around 275
Bibliography  G. Rupprecht, &amp;ldquo;Die Kreuznacher Mosaikbodenvilla. Kurzbericht (Stand: April 1977),&amp;rdquo; Saalburg Jahrbuch 34, 1977:78-87. G. Rupprecht, &amp;ldquo;Leben auf dem Land,&amp;rdquo; Archäologie in Deutschland 4, 1986: 36-39. (worldcat) Heinz Cüppers, Die Römer in Rheinland-Pfalz, Stuttgart, 1990, pp.321-323, fig. 204. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981525
TGN ID 7012371
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 15 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House in Insula 1 and 2 in Augusta Raurica</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ausgusta_raurica/augusta_raurica_house_in_insula_1_and_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 17:34:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ausgusta_raurica/augusta_raurica_house_in_insula_1_and_2/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Augusta Raurica
Augusta Raurica (Pleiades)
Location Description The town on the Rhine River possessed colonial status since the late 1st century BC. The street grid, as well as many public and residential buildings, are well known from excavations.
Garden House in Insula 1 and 2 in Augusta Raurica
Keywords archaeological garden \
 insulae peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes terrace gardens  Garden Description This house, built on sloping terrain on the northern edge of the city around AD 150, was enlarged twenty years later to incorporate at least two certain gardens (Fig. 1). It bordered north and south on streets and was flanked on the east and west by other houses. In this last phase after ca. 170, the house covered an area of about 2000 square meters. In the center of the building was an irregular peristyle courtyard, at the north end of which was a private bath complex.
East of the house was a long rectangular area open to the sky and divided into plots by a wall. In the northernmost plot a layer of humic soil 20-40 centimeters thick was excavated that the excavators interpret as evidence for a garden (G on plan).
The northern part of the house facing the street included an open terrace which may have been built up on demolished walls of the earlier house. Humus-rich soil in the terrace area may indicate that it was planted (G in Fig. 1). Immediately south of the terrace was a portico that offered a splendid view of the valley.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Augusta Raurica., House in insula 1 and 2. Adapted from Hufschidt.(Rights statement)   Images Dates House: AD 150 - ca. 170
Bibliography  P.-A. Schwarz, „Die Nordmauer und die Überreste der Innenbebauung der spätrömischen Befestigung auf Kastelen in Augusta Rauricorum. Vorbericht über die Grabung 1991.51,“ Jahresberichte aus Augst und Kaiseraugst 13, 1992: 47-76. (worldcat) T. Hufschmid, Kastelen 3. Die jüngeren Steinbauten in den Insulae 1 und 2 von Augusta Raurica. Forschungen in Augst 23, Augst, 1996. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 177494
TGN ID 7017586
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 14 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural villa at Voerendaal</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/voerendaal/voerendaal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:58:07 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/voerendaal/voerendaal/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Province Description Location Voerendaal
Voerendaal (Pleiades)
Garden Rural villa at Voerendaal
Keywords  villae rusticae porticoes piscinae hedges courtyards  Garden Description The stone-built structures of this villa rustica near the Meuse river, the largest excavated thus far in the Netherlands, were erected in the early 2nd century and repeatedly enlarged until the abandonment of the farm around 300 A.D. (Plan 1). The total area of the farm, including the cultivated land, is calculated to have been ca. 150 hectares. The main residence (A on plan) lay in the northern half of the complex which measured 167 x 214 m. (3.5 hectares) in size. The porticoed facade in its final state was 190 m. long.
In front of the house to the south was a large area (17 x 37 m.), enclosed by a stone wall on two sides and villa porticoes on the other sides. This has been interpreted as a formal garden (G on plan) with low plantings, hedges and a pool (P on plan; Image 1 [NO IMAGE INCLUDED]). The main road leading from the gate in the south to the house in the north cut through this enclosed area. The excavators postulate a vegetable garden behind the house for easy, daily access. The boundaries of the farm complex were planted with a row of trees or a hedge, the planting pits of which had survived. The many carbonized grains of wheat and chaff found in and around a large building in the northeastern part of the courtyard enclosure suggest that wheat grown in the fields of the farm was processed here. The main crop at Voerendaal was spelt; very little emmer or bread wheat was present in the organic remains.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the rural villa with a possible walled garden (G) and its pool (P) south of the house (A). Hedges (rows of dots) enclosed the farmyard. Adapted from Willems 1992, Fig. 307. (Rights statement).   Images Dates Early second century CE to ca. 300 CE
Bibliography  W.J.H. Willems, &amp;ldquo;Die kaiserzeitliche Villa von Voerendaal&amp;rdquo;, in Spurensicherung. Archäologische Denkmalpflege in der Euregio Maas-Rhein, Mainz, 1992, pp. 526-534, figs. 307-308. worldcat P. Van Ossel, Établissements ruraux de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquité tardive dans le nord de la Gaule, Paris, 1992, pp. 363-365, fig. 155. worldcat  Pleiades ID 109442
TGN ID 7272601
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>