<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>caupona on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/caupona/</link>
    <description>Recent content in caupona on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 17:25:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/caupona/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>II.i.7B/8-9</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_i.md/ii.i.7b-9/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 17:25:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_i.md/ii.i.7b-9/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region II
Insula Insula I
Keywords  tabernae amphorae (storage vessels)  Garden Vineyard with large masonry triclinium, treading floor and courtyard garden.
Garden Description A. The access to this garden featured an arched niche high on the garden wall located either side of the direct entrance from the street at entrance 8. A further entrance (7A) from the street was located on the east wall. The masonry triclinium (l. medius, 3.60 m.; l. imus 3.20 l. summus 2.43 m.) in the northwest corner had a round table (0.55 m. in dia.) between the couches and a rectangular table (0.65 x 1.03 m.) built against the north wall. A cistern opening was found to the south of the triclinium. To the left of entrance 8, a small room was excavated in 1985 to reveal a treading floor that allowed the juice from the grapes to flow into a small dolium. This indicates that the garden was most likely planted in vines.
B. Entrance 8 opened directly into a courtyard garden. A cistern opening in the northeast corner of the garden was fed by a gutter along the east edge. To the right of the door on the east wall was a small niche lararium with an aedicula façade. To the right of this niche, a painting of Hercules was displayed in a red border. Below this was a garden setting with an altar and a crested serpent painted in low stucco relief. In the interior area of this property, stairs leading to an upper floor and a hearth in a kitchen area were located. The stairs likely led to accommodation.
Bibliography W. F. Jashemski, 1993, Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius. Volume 2, Appendices, p.75. (worldcat) Halsted B. Van der Poel, Laurentino García y García, and Joan McConnell, 1986, Corpus topographicum Pompeianum Pars IIIA, p.40-41 (worldcat)
Pleiades ID 456321707
TGN ID 7004658
Excavation Dates 1939, 1953-1955, 1983
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250) Jessica Venner (https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5828-6222)
Publication date 19 February 2021</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>II.1.3-7</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_i.md/ii.1.3-7/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 15:25:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_i.md/ii.1.3-7/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region II
Insula Insula I
Keywords  cauponae amphorae (storage vessels)  Garden Small garden to the rear of a caupona
Garden Description The garden in the southeast section of this area was shared the house at entrance 3 and shops 4, 5, and 6 on the Via dell’Abbondanza. It was also possible to enter the garden from the side street at entrance 7. Jashemski established in 1975 that the area had been planted due to the presence of scattered root cavities, but extensive damage to the soil prevented the recovery of an accurate planting plan.
Bibliography W. F. Jashemski, 1993, Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius. Volume 2, Appendices, p.75. (worldcat)
Pleiades ID 456321707
TGN ID 7004658
Excavation Dates Unspecified
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 19 February 2021</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>II.viii.2-3</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_viii/ii.viii.5.b/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_viii/ii.viii.5.b/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region II
Insula Insula VIII
Keywords  caupona  Garden Description B. Another small garden (b) was found to the rear of the caupona.
Plans   Fig. 62, Plan of Region II, insula viii   Pleiades ID 456321707
TGN ID 7004658
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p.94 (worldcat)  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 10 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>