<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Italia on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/categories/italia/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Italia on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/categories/italia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa A Graticcio</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/herculaneum/tiffany-fong/casa_a_graticcio/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/herculaneum/tiffany-fong/casa_a_graticcio/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Garden Casa A Graticcio
##Jashemski Catalogue 538.III.13-15.
Keywords N/A
Garden Description 538.III.13-15. This multi-family dwelling was excavated in 1927-1929. There was a small paved courtyard (a) 1.97 x 2.97 m. located to provide light and air to the surrounding apartments which was enclosed on the east, north and west by a low wall 0.76 m. high which formeda catch basin for rainwater. Herbs or flowers could be grown in the planting space (14 cm. wide x 25 cm. deep) on the top of the wall. The middle of the north side of the wall contained the mouth of a well that was 0.90 m. dia. and in the floor of the passageway to the west of the courtyard there was the mouth of a cistern covered by a circular piece of marble. There was a windlass with a rope found in a nearby room undoubtedly used to draw water from either of these fixtures. According to Maiuri, there could be a large cistern underground connecting the mouth of cistern in the passageway and the mouth of the well.
Plans Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1927-1929
Bibliography  Maiuri, Herculaneum, pp. 32-33 (worldcat) Idem, Ercolano, pp. 412-413 and fig. 345 (plan) on p. 407 (worldcat)  -
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa del Paprio Dipinto</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/herculaneum/tiffany-fong/casa_del_paprio_dipinto/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/herculaneum/tiffany-fong/casa_del_paprio_dipinto/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Garden Casa del Paprio Dipinto
##Jashemski Catalogue 544.IV.8-9.
Keywords  impluvium  Garden Description 544.IV.8-9. This narrow house excavated in 1929-1932 had a small paved courtyard serving as both a light well and an impluvium. This area could have held potted plants. A hunt scene once decorated the back wall, featuring lions and bulls, scenes more typically found on the walls of more luxurious dwellings.
Plans Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1929-1932
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 370 (worldcat)     Maiuri, Herculaneum, pp. 32 (worldcat)     Idem, Ercolano, pp. 424 and fig. 365 (plan) on p. 424. (worldcat)  -
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa del Tramezzo di Legno</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/herculaneum/tiffany-fong/casa_del-_tramezzo-_di_legno/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/herculaneum/tiffany-fong/casa_del-_tramezzo-_di_legno/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Garden Casa del Tramezzo di Legno
##Jashemski Catalogue 537.III.11.
Keywords  loggia triclinium  Garden Description 537.III.11. Casa del Tramezzo di Legno The excavation of this house was begun in 1869-1875, but the excavation of the garden and restoration of the house was completed in the time period from January 1928 to December 1929. A wide opening on the west offered a view of the garden from the triclinium(b) directly across the way. A narrow storeroom (c) on the south had a small loggiasupported by slender columns overhead which provided a view down into the garden. The south garden wall was decorated with a garden painting. A combination of the painting’s poor condition and the artist’s strange sense of perspective caused difficulty ininterpretation. The typical lattice fence would appear to recede to form an apse for the fountain, however the lattice is painted over the fountain, a robust bowl-shaped affair, making it appear neither in front nor in back. An arbor was perhaps included,but the plaster was extensively damaged in this area. The birds were unusual, a small light colored bird perched on the right rim of the fountain was unable to be identified and on each side of the fountain at the base was a large sleepy duck (Anas sp.).A small slender heron on the right is picking at a snake. Beyond the fence various indistinct shrubs are painted on a yellow background. Between the two east pillars of the north wall the cisternmouth received water collected by the gutter which ran around the perimeter of the garden.
Plans -
Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1869-1875
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, 1:59,and fig. 94 on p. 58 (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, Vol.II, P. 370 (worldcat) Maiuri, Herculaneum, pp. 35-36 (worldcat) Idem, Ercolano, pp. 231, 217-218 and fig. 162 (plan) on p. 208 (worldcat)  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa dello Scheletro</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/herculaneum/tiffany-fong/casa_dello_scheletro/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/herculaneum/tiffany-fong/casa_dello_scheletro/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Garden Casa dello Scheletro
##Jashemski Catalogue 536.III.3.
Keywords  aedicules tympanum pergola amorino  Garden Description The small light well of this house had once been occupied by a pool. By the time of the eruption it had been filled with soil and converted to a small garden (a). During this change an aedicula was built on a high podium against the back wall, decorated with mosaic and shells, and garden paintings were added to the light well walls. The walls on the east and south had panels framed on the top and sides with a wide red band and a smaller black one inside. The south wall had panels on both sides of the mosaic aedicule, and of all the panels, the left panel of the south wall was the best preserved, although the GARDENS OF THE ROMAN EMPIREITALIA2center third is missing. In this panel the lattice fence is evident and a tympanumis suspended form the center of the top. This panel also has traces of what could have been a trellised pergola just to the left of the aedicula. The garden in the background is filled with densely planted bushes and a bird is perched on a branch on either edge of the panel. A masonry base was uncovered in the pool which had at one time supported a fountain jet or statuette. The excavation was begun in 1830-1831, resumed in 1869-1871, and completed in 1927. The niche of the aedecula shrine was decorated with a cluster of acanthus leaves with a female face in the center. A small roof was set in the wall to protect the painting and above this was a marble relief of an amorino flying to the left carrying a filled money purse. An iron grate was built over the top of this light well to prevent intruders from gaining access from the neighbor’s roofs. To the north was an apsed room which gained light and air from this area.
Plans   Herculaneum 536.III.3.Casa dello Scheletro   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1830-1831; 1869-1871; 1927
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, pp. 369-370 (worldcat) Maiuri, Herculaneum, pp. 35-36 (worldcat) Idem, Ercolano, pp. 51, 272-274 and fig. 213 (plan) on p. 266; Sear, Roman wall and vault mosaics no. 26, pp. 66-67, calls the shrine a fountain.(worldcat)  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa dell’Alcova</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/herculaneum/tiffany-fong/casa_dellalcova/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/herculaneum/tiffany-fong/casa_dellalcova/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Garden Casa dell’Alcova
##Jashemski Catalogue 542.IV.3-4. 543.IV.3-4.
Keywords  atrium triclinium procoeton  Garden Description 542.IV.3-4. A. Two separate dwellings were united to form this house, excavated in 1928-1929. The northern house has three courtyards. The first (a) is directly off of the vestibule, the second is a covered atrium(b) with a small courtyard that collected roof water, and the third courtyard (c) in the rear supplied light and air to the adjoining rooms and the triclinium. This was too badly damaged to ascertain if it was a garden or even if it once held potted plants. It was compared to the better preserved courtyard in the Casa a Graticcio by Maiuri.
543.IV.3-4. B. The more elegant dwelling to the south had a long corridor on one side of the large triclinium leading to a small paved courtyard with pillars (e) which supplied light and air to the house. The pillars on the south and east stood on a low wall, 0.80 m. high, with a planting area 15 cm. wide in between. This gives the area the feeling of window boxes placed below large windows. There was a well in the southeast corner of this courtyard which received rain water and beyond the courtyard was a secluded alcove. This consisted of an apsed room preceded by a procoeton.
Plans Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1928-1929
Bibliography  Maiuri, Ercolano, pp. 51, 389-391 and fig. 322 (plan) on p. 389 (worldcat)     Idem, Maiuri, Herculaneum, pp. 31 (worldcat)     Idem, Ercolano, pp. 51, 392 and fig. 322 (plan) on p. 389.(worldcat)  -
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa dell’Ara Laterizia</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/herculaneum/tiffany-fong/casa_dellara_laterizia/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/herculaneum/tiffany-fong/casa_dellara_laterizia/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Garden Casa dell’Ara Laterizia
##Jashemski Catalogue 539.III.17. 540.III.19-18/1-2
Keywords  sacellum portico opus reticulatum  Garden Description 539.III.17. At the rear of this small house there was a courtyard with an impressive brick altar against the rear wall. Maiuri felt this was probably a roofed area which would have been a sacellum. This area was excavated in 1927-1929 and may have held a few potted plants.
540.III.19-18/1-2 Because it was one of the largest houses in Herculaneum commanding a fine view of the Bay, it was initially thought that this residence was a hotel when it was excavated between the years of 1835 to 1855. The large garden (a) was also mistaken for a poultry yard but the discovery of the carbonized trunk of a pear tree (Pyrus communis L.) would indicate this area could have been planted in fruit trees. A portico surrounded the garden eight steps (1.10) above the garden level while the gutter ran one step below the portico and at each corner there was a shallow square basin for purifying the household water. The gutter conveyed the rain water to a cistern below the two wells, the openings of which were located between the columns in the middle of the east and west walls. A low masonry wall of opus reticulatum which went between the columns was a later addition. The garden was entered by way of masonry steps in the center of the south side.
Plans Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1835-1855
Bibliography  A.C. BdI (1835),p. 129 (worldcat) Maiuri, Herculaneum, pp. 26-27 (worldcat) Trotter, “Identificazione di un tronco d’albero carbonizzato rinvenuto nei recenti scavi di Ercolano,” Annali del Regio Instituto Superiore Agrario di Portici, ser. 3, vol. 5 (1932), pp. 1-6 and pls. 1, 2 (worldcat) Idem, Ercolano, pp. 51, 330-331 and fig. 258 (plan) on p. 474-475 (for reference to Bonucci’s brief and inaccurate account of the excavation of this house, as preserved by Ruggerio) (worldcat)  -
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa dell’Atrio a Mosaico</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/herculaneum/tiffany-fong/casa_dellatrio_a_mosaico/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/herculaneum/tiffany-fong/casa_dellatrio_a_mosaico/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Garden Casa dell’Atrio a Mosaico
##Jashemski Catalogue 541.IV.1-2
Keywords  portico exedra triclinium  Garden Description 541.IV.1-2 A windowed portico surrounded this garden (a) on the north, south and west. The east side was bordered by a narrow corridor which Maiuri proposed had glass in woodenframes set on the outside edge of the low wall. This wall had a planting space 0.16 m. wide in the top next to where the windows were set, creating a greenhouse environment. This luxurious house had an exedra(b) opening onto the center of the corridor and looking into the garden, which was slightly lower. On the oppositeside,the walls, columns, and the door posts were decorated with paintingsof shrubs, grapevines, ivy andoleander in flower as a continuation of the garden proper. A gutter circled the perimeter of the garden except by the entrance on the south, which was directly across from the grand triclinium-oecus(c). A rectangular marble-edged pool in the center of the garden had a water jet which could be viewed from either the exedra or the triclinium. The excavations in this garden in 1929-1930 uncovered a spherical white marble sundial. The triclinium-oecus opened to the south onto a long covered portico with an open terrace (d) beyond that looking out over the Bay. Potted plants most likely were placed here.
Plans Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1929-1930
Bibliography  Gibbs, Greek and Roman sundials, p. 148, no 1031G (worldcat)     Maiuri, Herculaneum, pp. 28-30 (worldcat)     Idem, Ercolano, pp. 290-293, 295, 298, 300 and fig. 223 (plan) on p. 280.(worldcat)  -
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa D’Argo</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/herculaneum/tiffany-fong/casa_dargo/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/herculaneum/tiffany-fong/casa_dargo/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Garden Casa D’Argo
##Jashemski Catalogue 533.II.2. 534.II.2.
Keywords  cisterns (plumbing components) triclinium peristyles porticoes gutters (building drainage components)  Garden Description 533.II.2. A. The earliest excavations of Herculaneum were done with underground tunnels. Several of these crossed this site and were discovered sixty three years later when further excavation of this patrician house was conducted in1828-1835. Eight brick columns and one engaged column stood on each of the long sides of the portico that bounded the large peristyle garden (a) on the east, north, and west sides. The north side was supported by four more columns and at the two front corners there was a pillar with an engaged column on each side. In the center of the north side two smaller pillars with one engaged column each framed a garden view from the triclinium. All the supporting members were coated with fine stucco. Gutters ringing the garden conveyed rain water to the cistern.
534.II.2. B. A second peristyle garden was located to the west of the first, but has only been partially excavated. It has stuccoed columns and pillars joined by a wall 0.4 m. high painted with plants and flowers.
Plans   Casa D’Argo   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1828-1835
Bibliography  A.C. BdI (1835),p. 130 (worldcat) Bonucci, BdI (1830), p.121 (worldcat) Bonucci, Le due Sicilie: Ercolano, fig. 11 (plan) and p. 37 (worldcat) Breton,Pompeia p. 519 (worldcat) Maiuri, Herculaneum, p. 24 (worldcat) Idem,Ercolano, pp. 367-368 and fig. 293 (plan) on p. 362 (worldcat) Niccolini,Real museo borbonico, vol. 7, fig. 59 (plan), description by Bechi, pp. 19-21 (worldcat)     Ruggiero, Ercolano, pp. 541-545 (contains the detailed reports of Bonucci)(worldcat)     -      Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casadetta del Genio</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/herculaneum/tiffany-fong/casadetta_del_genio/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/herculaneum/tiffany-fong/casadetta_del_genio/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Garden Casadetta del Genio
##Jashemski Catalogue 535.II.3.
Keywords  porticoes  Garden Description This house was partially excavated in 1829-1830 and again in 1850. The portico had a floor on the east slightly lower than the sections on the north and south. A pool (a) was located in the center of the garden with a semi-circular extension on the east end and two small marble posts which probably held herms. The pool measured 2.35 m. wide, 0.87 m. deep and was only excavated to a length of 6.50 m.
Plans   Casadetta del Genio   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897 Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1829-1830; 1850
Bibliography    Maiuri, Herculaneum, p. 25 (worldcat)   Idem, Ercolano, pp. 375-377 and fig. 307 (plan) on p. 376 (worldcat)     Ruggiero, Ercolano, pp. 562, 566, 574 (worldcat)      Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Ceres; Casa di Cerere (I.ix.13-14)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ix/houses_13-14/house_of_ceres/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2020 13:13:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ix/houses_13-14/house_of_ceres/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula IX
House House 13-14
Garden House of Ceres; Casa di Cerere (I.ix.13-14)
Keywords  amorini archaeological garden basins (vessels) colonnades fountains mural paintings (visual works) peristyles (columnades) porticoes statues statuettes (free-standing sculpture) tablina triclinia vases  Garden Description The natural rising slope of the land made this long upper garden (a) at the rear of the house visible from the entrance at the south. A side door on the west wall to the rear offered access to the garden through a colonnaded portico. Garden paintings adorned the retaining wall that separated the upper garden from the rest. Fig. 3. These rather crude images were visible from the atrium through a window in the tablinium. Fig. 4. The paintings were divided into three panels on the retaining wall by wide black bands and they continued along the short extension of the wall on the west above the small basin that was built in the corner. Jashemski reported that the west panel was the best preserved when she examined it in 1968. She recorded seeing from left to right starting over the basin, a few oleander bushes and a date palm. A lattice fence begins at the basin and above that there was evidence of more oleanders, some with red blossoms and a bowl-shaped footed basin with a large bird perched on the rim on the left, (the plaster had fallen away with the right side of the rim). Following were more oleanders, a date palm and a cattle egret (Bubulcus ibis L.) perched on the fence with more oleanders behind. More than half of the center panel did not survive, but here the fence is solid, rather than lattice, and encloses a pool, although the right section of the pool is missing and the remaining part are barely visible. It appears that a sphinx was represented on the top of the left end of the fence. Jashemski remarks that this panel had the characteristics of a garden representation. A garland is painted along the base of the fence in both panels. The last panel had nothing but faint traces of images surviving.A garden representation was painted in the center of the large middle panel of the east wall of the triclinium (b). It is a simple rendering painted in yellow of a lattice fence enclosing a garden with an apsed niche in the center of the front and back. To either side there is an angular niche, four total, and eight tall posts rise from the corners and on either side of the apsed niche in front. The two front posts have ornamental vases on top. The west wall had a similar representation.Fig. 5. The excavation took place in 1951-52 and among other objects found were four small marble fountain statues of amorini sliding down the backs of dolphins (0.33-0.40 m. high; Pompeii inv. nos. 8126-8129.)
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ix, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 12, p. 44 (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: 43.19.68, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).     Fig. 4: 35.13.66, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).     Fig. 5: 39.17.68, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1951-52
Bibliography  DeVos, “Scavi nuovi sconoscuti (1.9.13),” Meded 38 (1976): 38, 49-50, 62 and pl. 35 (plan), 51, 50 and figs.27,32. Döhl, p. 5 (?I.9&amp;hellip;.). Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, pp. 45, 323,395.(worldcat) Kapossy, p. 39. PPP, 1:109. PPP, 1:109.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 10 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.ix.12</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ix/house_12/i.ix.12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2020 13:05:24 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ix/house_12/i.ix.12/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula IX
House House 12
Garden I.ix.12
Keywords  archaeological garden columns (architectural elements) lararia peristyles (columnades) pillars porticoes  Garden Description A low wall connected the three columns and a pillar that supported the portico of this peristyle garden (a) located to the back of the house. The portico enclosed the garden on the on the east and south and entry was gained on the south between two of the columns. The excavation was done in 1952-53 and uncovered a lararium niche on the west garden wall.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ix, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 12, p. 44 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1952-1953
Bibliography  DeVos, “Scavi nuovi sconoscuti (1.9.13),” Meded 38 (1976), pl. 35 (plan). Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 45. (worldcat) Orr, no. 4.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 10 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Caupona of Amarantus Pompeianus (I.ix.11)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ix/house_11/caupona_of_amarantus_pompeianus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2020 12:42:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ix/house_11/caupona_of_amarantus_pompeianus/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula ix
House House 11
Garden I.ix.11
Keywords  amphorae (storage vessels) archaeological garden lapilli lararia peristyles (Roman courtyards) terrace gardens  Garden Description The peristyle of this house was built before the earthquake of 62 BC. When the lapilli was removed, excavators found the courtyard filled with amphorae, although its original use as a garden was noted by Jashemski. The British School in Rome returned in the early 1990s to undertake strategraphic excavation of the garden, in tandem with systematic environmental retrieval methods. This investigation revealed that the site was terraced. Fertile soils were then brought in from alluvial areas for cultivation. Marks in the soil profile indicated small scale spade horticulture. Archaeobotanical remains revealed burnt waste from crop cleaning and mineralized latrine contents, both of which are characteristic of fertilizer. However, assemblages of burnt bones and plants indicated small deposits of votive offerings buried in the garden, a significant new finding that may be associated with the lararia found in the houses and gardens. Many of the plant species are those seen in the garden paintings, and, overall, the excavators were able to see in the archaeobotanical record a shift from arable cultivation in the pre-Roman levels to the cultivation of olives, vines and fruit trees.
At the time of the eruption, trees and shrubs grew in the garden, as excavators found root cavities. However, pollen evidence of bracken and weeds suggests that the garden was either overgrown or abandoned, at least from its original purposes.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ix, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 12, p. 44 (Rights Statement).   Dates Built before 62 BCE
Excavation Date Early 1990s
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol. II, p. 45. (worldcat) J. Berry, “The Conditions of Domestic Life in Pompeii in AD 79: A Case Study of Houses 11 and 12, Insula 9, Region I.” in Papers of the British School at Rome, Vol 65 (1997) pp. 103-125. (worldcat) M. Fulford, A. Wallace-Hadrill, G. Clark, A. Clarke, H. Eckardt, A. Locker, A. Powell, M. Rendeli, D. Richards, J. Robinson, M.Robinson, J. Timby, “Towards a History of Pre-Roman Pompeii: Excavation beneath the House of Amaranthus” Papers of the British School at Rome 67 (1999): 37-144. M.A. Robinson, “Wet-sieving and flotation for biological remains” in M. Fulfor and A. Wallace-Hadrill, The House of Amaranthus at Pompeii (1.9.11-12); and interim report on survey and excavation in 1995-6. Rivista di Studi Pompeiani 7 (1995-96): 108-110. CIL IV.10345 (for amphoras found in the garden February, 1953). DeVos, “Scavi nuovi sconoscuti (1.9.13),” Meded 38 (1976), pl. 35 (plan).  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Kathryn Gleason (ORCID:0000-0001-6260-8378)
Publication date 10 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.ix.9/10</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ix/houses_9&#43;10/i.ix.9&#43;10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2020 11:47:48 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ix/houses_9&#43;10/i.ix.9&#43;10/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula IX
House House 9/10
Garden I.ix.9/10
Keywords  archaeological garden columns (architectural elements) engaged columns pilasters porticoes stairs  Garden Description To the rear of this house a raised garden (a), three steps up, had a portico on the east. The portico was supported by two columns on the east, an engaged column and a pilaster.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ix, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 12, p. 44 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date Bibliography  DeVos, “Scavi nuovi sconoscuti (1.9.13),” Meded 38 (1976), pl. 35 (plan). Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 44. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 10 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.ix.8</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ix/house_8/i.ix.8/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2020 11:43:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ix/house_8/i.ix.8/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula IX
House House 8
Garden I.ix.8
Keywords  archaeological garden cisterns (plumbing components) puteal  Garden Description The garden (a) and cistern that was in the southwest corner of this house had been paved over by A.D. 79. There was a puteal in the courtyard.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ix, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 12, p. 44 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified - 70 CE
Excavation Date Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 44. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 10 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Fruit Orchard; Casa del Frutteto; Dei Cubicoli Floreali (I.ix.5) B</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ix/house_5/house_of_the_fruit_orchard_b/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2020 11:22:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ix/house_5/house_of_the_fruit_orchard_b/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula IX
House House 5
Garden House of the Fruit Orchard; Casa del Frutteto; Dei Cubicoli Floreali (I.ix.5) B
Keywords  archaeological garden mural paintings (visual works) peristyles (columnades)  Garden Description B. The room to the east of the peristyle was painted in three horizontal zones. The east wall was the only section that survived in its entirety. The bottom zone had a simple decoration on a black background; the top zone was painted black. The middle zone featured a lattice fence with garden representations behind it. Slender trellis-like supports, similar to those in the other room, divided the each wall into three panels on the north, east and south sides. Part of the south wall was occupied by a window. Each panel included the representation of a tree. The east wall is viewed immediately upon entering the room and here the fence forms an asped bay in the center where an elaborate footed marble basin is painted. Resting in the basin is a golden jewel bedecked urceus as was used in the worship of Isis. Standing on a pedestal behind the fence on either side of this basin is a fluted egg-shaped marble fountain with a pink blossomed rose bush (Rosa sp.) on one side and a flowering bush with four petaled lavender flowers on the other (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, figs. 123-125 on p. 77). A fig tree with ripe fruit is featured on the center panel with a large snake coiling up the trunk. Two birds fly towards the top of the tree while one is perched on the right side. To either side of the fig tree stands an oleander bush without blossoms, the flowers may have upstaged the fig tree if present (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, figs. 123, 385 on pp. 77 and 262). The bush on the left hand side has a small bird with a reddish tail perched on its branches, possibly a nightingale (Luscinia megarhynchos C.L.Brehm). The two narrow side panels each show a tall strawberry tree with ripe fruit. Although Maiuri misidentified these as a sorb, the fruit is well preserved enough to positively identify these as strawberry trees. The south wall sustained considerable damage, lacking the bottom zone and part of the middle zone. A delicate two-handled, footed, bowl shaped fountain is painted in the center of the space to the east of the window. It sits on a pedestal behind the fence with a bush with stylized white buds on either side. These may represent myrtles and beyond these a rose bush with pink blooms occupies either end of the panel. A pear tree is in the upper zone in the east panel with four birds perched on it. A jay (Garrulus glandarius L.) sits on the upper right with a female oriole (Oriolus oriolus L.) perched below. The other two and a bird flying towards the tree from the right cannot be identified (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, fig. 388 on p. 263). In the middle panel above the window there is a lemon tree with beautiful fruit and a female oriole (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, fig. 420 on p. 281). Three other unidentified birds sit on branches or fly to the top of the tree. The lower part of this painting is lost. The west panel was badly damaged but the tree image that remains has ripe fruit which Jashemski identifies as pomegranate as opposed to Maiuri’s identification as a peach. She also differs with Maiuri’s identification of the flowering bush above the door which he said was a honeysuckle, but Jashemski has identified as a flowering viburnum. A bird is flying towards this bush and in the narrow panel on either side of this are oleanders in bloom, the north panel almost all gone. The paintings on the north wall are identical to the ones on the south with the exception being the two rose bushes on the east end are replaced by a bush with four petaled lavender flowers which mirrors the same figure on the adjacent corner of the east wall. In the upper zone of the west panel a female oriole perches in a cherry tree (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1 fig. 418 on p. 280). Two flying birds cannot be positively identified but the one on the left may be an oriole and the other has the silhouette that suggests a martin. The right side of the painting was destroyed. A yellow plum tree (Prunus domestica L.) with what is perhaps another oriole dominates the center panel and a large bird flies towards a bush to the lower right. This panel sustained considerable damage. The panel next to it on the right has a blue plum tree accompanied by four birds including a turtledove on the upper right, and probably a female oriole on the left. The damage to the top of this panel took out most of another bird. A low branch holds what is either a greenfinch (Carduelis chloris L.) or a redstart (Phoenicurus phoenicurus L.), the colors faded enough to make identification difficult (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1 fig. 389 on p. 263). Low bushes without blooms and a profusion of birds fill the spaces under these trees. The fragments of the ceiling show that it was painted to represent a grape arbor with clusters of fruit, birds and flying amorini, and Dionysiac symbols such as masks, musical instruments, drinking horns, and oscilla. Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ix, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 12, p. 44 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1951
Bibliography  Bastet, pp. 75-76. De Vos, Guida, p. 124. Jashemski, Gardens, 1:74-77 and figs. 117, 118, 120, 122 on p. 74-76, fig. 126 on p. 78, figs. 171-173 on pp. 106-107, and fig. 408 on p. 274; 1:77-79 and figs. 123-125 on p. 77, figs. 385, 388, 389 on pp. 262-263 and figs. 418 and 420 on pp. 280-281. (worldcat) Idem, Gardens, vol.II, pp. 44, 320-322.(worldcat) Le Corsu, “Un oratoire pompéien consacré à Dionysos-Osiris,” RevueArch, fasc. 2 (1967): 239, 242-249 (little mention of plant material). Maiuri, Rom., Paint., pp. 124, 129. Maiuri, BdA, (1952), pp. 7-9. Idem, Rom.Paint., pp. 127-129. Michel, pp. 386-390. Peters, “Van Prima Porta,” pp. 6-8. PPP, 1:95-96, 1:101-102. Schefold, WändP, p.38. Sichtermann, Antike Welt (1974), no. 3, pp. 41-48.   Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Unknown
Publication date 10 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Fruit Orchard; Casa del Frutteto; Dei Cubicoli Floreali (I.ix.5)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ix/house_5/house_of_the_fruit_orchard/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 18:25:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ix/house_5/house_of_the_fruit_orchard/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula IX
House House 5
Garden House of the Fruit Orchard; Casa del Frutteto; Dei Cubicoli Floreali (I.ix.5)
Keywords  archaeological garden atriums cisterns (plumbing components) columns (architectural elements) cubicula (domestic spaces) mural paintings (visual works) porticoes statues statuettes (free-standing sculpture) trellises  Garden Description A portico with three columns, red on the bottom, white on the top, enclosed this peristyle garden (a) on the north, east and south sides. The excavating work in 1951 revealed a cistern opening at the edge of the north portico and a gutter on the north, east and south side of the garden. Paintings of orchards adorned two small cubicula (b and c) and gave this house its name.
A. The room (b) off the east side of the atrium had walls divided horizontally into four zones. At the base there are hart’s-tongue ferns (Phyllitis scolopendrium L.) Newman and acanthus (Acanthus mollis L.) painted on a black dado. The next band is painted to represent a fence of woven reeds and then a luxuriant garden of trees and flowers beyond with an azure sky above. The other three walls are divided into three panels each by vertical figures that Maiuri describes as trellis supports rather than columns. The door on the west wall leaves room for only a narrow panel on either side. The center of each panel on the north, east, and south walls features a pinax or Egyptian statue. Excluded is the west panel on the south wall, for much of the space is taken up by a window. Each of these paintings features a profusion of birds. The upper zone is illustrated with urns, sculptured pinakes with Egyptian motifs and garlands from which are suspended masks and round oscilla as well as various birds, all against a blue background. The birds in this zone include the egret (Egretta sp.), magpie (Pica pica L.), blackbird (Turdus merula L.), white pigeon/dove (Streptopelia sp.), hooded crow (Corvus corone cornix L.), and house sparrow (Passer domesticus italiae Vieillot). (Jashemski, Gardens, vol.1, figs. 117 on p. 74, 171, 173 on pp. 106-107). Identification of the subjects painted is made possible by the extreme attention to detail that the artist utilized. Starting on the east wall, viewed first upon entering, the left panel shows a statue of a standing pharaoh facing a similar statue in the right panel. Behind the pharaoh is a fabulous lemon tree loaded with fruit (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, fig 126 on p. 78). The left of the panel has fragments of what was a myrtle with white blossoms, and on the right is an oleander with pink flowers. At the base of the statue are carefully rendered corn poppies (Papaver rhoeas L.) (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, fig. 118 on p. 75). An oleander bush with deep pink blossoms and a perching bird stands behind a pinax in the center panel. The oleander is flanked by what appear to be laurel bushes with whitish flower buds with an additional viburnum (Viburnum tinus L.) to the far left and a myrtle on the far right. A white pigeon perched on the fence to the far left looks to the right. The base of the pinax has a mound of ivy (hedera helix subsp. Poetarum Nyman) covered with bright yellow berries flanked by roses on the right and a plant with four petaled flowers on the left. The standing pharaoh in the right panel was badly damaged but the image of a cherry tree with bright red fruit that stands behind it remains (Jashemski, Gardens, vol.1, figs. 117 and 121 on pp. 74 and 75). The damaged images of the plants at the sides of the pharaoh appear to be similar to the other panel with a myrtle on the right and an oleander to the left. It is likely the flowers at the base of the statue were corn poppies. The left panel on the south wall is decorated with a swallow perching in a viburnum bush in full bloom behind a seated pharaoh facing west (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, figs. 117 and 122 on p. 74 and 76). A tall, slender laurel with whitish blossoms stands in the left background and an oleander with deep pink blossoms is on the right. Shorter oleanders with pink blossoms grow beside the statue on the left and to the right a short viburnum and myrtle are in bloom. The flowers painted at the base of the statue on the left are poppies, but there is too much damage to confidently identify the remaining yellow to orange flowers along the front. The center panel features a sculptured, painted pinax, an oleander with pink blooms behind it and what is probably a female turtledove (Streptopelia turtur L.) perched in the branches. A dark bird, possibly a blackbird, is flying to the top to the bush (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, fig. 408 on p. 274). Another tall laurel in bloom is painted on the left and a strawberry tree (Arbutus unedo L.) displays showy red-ribbed fruit (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, fig. 120 on p. 75). A young palm is growing in front of the pinax flanked by a myrtle with white blossoms to the on the right and a blossoming oleander to the left. The low flowers on the bottom of the left appear to be roses, but those on the right were completely lost. The paintings around the window in the west panel include a tall oleander on the left of the window and above, identified by the leaves, are a myrtle on the left and a viburnum on the right. Perching above the window is a white dove/pigeon. Left of the window to the bottom are Madonna lilies (Lilium candidum L.), found only two other times in the garden paintings of Pompeii that are presently known. On the left of the door in the west wall there is a bush, no blooms, above the fence and an oleander in bloom on the right. The garlands painted on the rest of the walls are missing but a white dove/pigeon on the wing is shown against a clear blue sky on either side of the door. Extensive damage occurred on the north wall. The west panel has a seated pharaoh facing the similar figure on the right panel with a tall viburnum bush in bloom behind. The bushes on either side are so badly damaged that identification is uncertain, perhaps laurels. A short oleander can be identified to the left of the statue while only the outline of four petals flowers survived on the base of this side. The center panel is slightly better preserved; the sculptured, painted pinax has a tall flowering oleander in back flanked by a tall laurel on the left and a tall viburnum on the right. The foreground figures are a myrtle in bloom on the left, a short oleander on the right, and a damaged unidentified plant in the center. The flowering plants in the foreground are unidentifiable. A statue of a seated Egyptian is shown on the right panel facing his counterpart on the left. Behind the statue are, from left to right, an oleander, a strawberry tree and a laurel. A shrub and a palm as tall as the statue are located to its left and on the right is a flowering oleander. Damage has completely erased the flowers that were presumably painted at the bottom of this panel.Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ix, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 12, p. 44 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1951
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, 1:74-77 and figs. 117, 118, 120, 122 on p. 74-76, fig. 126 on p. 78, figs. 171-173 on pp. 106-107, and fig. 408 on p. 274. (worldcat) Idem, Gardens, vol.II, pp. 44, 317-320. (worldcat) Bastet, p. 75. De Vos, Guida, p. 124. Idem, Rom.Paint., pp. 127-129. (worldcat) Le Corsu, “Un oratoire pompéien consacré à Dionysos-Osiris,” RevueArch, fasc. 2 (1967): 239, 242-249 (little mention of plant material). Maiuri, BdA, (1952), pp. 7-9. Michel, pp. 386-390. Peters, “Van Prima Porta,” pp. 6-8. PPP, 1:95-96. Schefold, WändP, p.38. Sichtermann, Antike Welt (1974), no. 3, pp. 41-45.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 09 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Successus (I.ix.3)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ix/house_3/house_of_successus/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 17:59:16 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ix/house_3/house_of_successus/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula IX
House House 3
Garden House of Successus (I.ix.3)
Keywords  archaeological garden atriums cubicula (domestic spaces) graffiti (casual notations) inscription mural paintings (visual works) porticoes statues statuettes (free-standing sculpture) tables (support furniture)  Garden Description A portrait of a little boy painted on the north wall of the cubiculum, to the left of the atrium, with the graffito PVER/SUCCUSSVS (CIL IV. 9992a) gave this house its name. Excavated in 1952, the garden (a) at the rear of the house had a portico, and a table base carved as a statuette of a small boy with a dove (Pompeii inv. no. 20395) was discovered in the north portico. Fig. 3, Fig. 4. The room in the southwest corner of the garden (b) had a garden representation on the large white middle panel on the south wall of the room. It was framed by a narrow reddish-brown border and painted in shades of brown and white on a light blue-green background. Two gardens enclosed by a wooden fence contained an open apse-shaped area in between them with a round pool. A jet in the center jetted water which descended in two separate streams. The gardens on the side were cut off by the frame. A figure across the front of the painting was perhaps a fence defining a passageway.Fig. 5.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ix, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 12, p. 44 (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: 18.15.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).     Fig. 4: 18.16.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).     Fig. 5: 18.22.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1952
Bibliography  Della Corte, Case, p. 339, no. 723a. Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, fig. 160 on p. 102 (for the portrait). (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, pp. 44; 395. (worldcat) Maiuri, Pompeii, p. 82. (worldcat) Schefold, WandP, p. 38.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 09 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Beautiful Impluvium; Casa del Bell Impluvio (I.ix.1)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ix/house_1/house_of_the_beautiful_impluvium/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 14:57:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ix/house_1/house_of_the_beautiful_impluvium/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula IX
House House 1
Garden House of the Beautiful Impluvium; Casa del Bell Impluvio (I.ix.1)
Keywords  archaeological garden atriums cubicula (domestic spaces) fountains impluvia inscription mural paintings (visual works) pergolas peristyles (columnades) porticoes predellas  Garden Description According to Eschebach’s plan, there was a portico at the rear of this house that enclosed this peristyle garden (a) on four sides. A small section of the foundation wall remains on the south end of the east side. The cubiculum (b) to the east of the atrium has a garden representation on the west half of the black predella on the south wall. It was poorly preserved but the left section shows a garden with a lattice fence and a pergola. Faint images remain of a similar pergola on the right side. The center of the painting, (which is 0.09 x 0.84 m.) has an open area with a crater perhaps serving as a fountain in a pergola. Two additional pergolas stand to either side. Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ix, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 12, p. 44 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date Bibliography  CIL IV. 10274, 10333 (for amphoras found in the garden March 3, 1952). de Vos, p.135 in Bastet.  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, pp. 44; 395. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 09 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa dei Quattro Stili; House of L.V.P. (I.viii.17/11)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_viii/houses_17&#43;11/casa_dei_quattro_stili/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 14:28:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_viii/houses_17&#43;11/casa_dei_quattro_stili/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VIII
House House 17/11
Garden Casa dei Quattro Stili; House of L.V.P. (I.viii.17/11)
Keywords  archaeological garden inscription peristyles (columnades) pillars porticoes roofing tile  Garden Description A portico supported by four pillars at the back of this house enclosed this peristyle garden (a) on the west. There was a passageway to the north of this garden that provided a back entrance to this house. A roof tile found in the garden in 1938 was inscribed FVLGVR (CIL IV.8223) and marked the spot where lightning had struck and where all affected items were buried.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula viii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 11, p.42; I.viii-ix: plan in Eschebach (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 43. (worldcat) Maiuri, “Fulgur conditum,” RendNap, n.s., 21 (1942): 53-72 and figs. 1 (plan) and 2 on pp. 56-57.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 09 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of M. Epidius Primus (I.viii.14)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_viii/house_14/house_of_m._epidius_primus/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 10:46:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_viii/house_14/house_of_m._epidius_primus/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VIII
House House 14
Garden House of M. Epidius Primus (I.viii.14)
Keywords  archaeological garden atriums cisterns (plumbing components) gutters (building drainage components) viridarium  Garden Description This house was excavated in 1941. The atrium led directly to a little viridarium (a), with a cistern in the southwest corner. A gutter bordered the garden on the south, west and north sides.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula viii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 11, p.42; I.viii-ix: plan in Eschebach (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1941
Bibliography  Della Corte, NSc (1946), p. 108. Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 43. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 09 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House and Workshop of A. Granius Romanus (I.viii.13)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_viii/house_13/house_and_workshop_of_a._granius_romanus/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 10:39:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_viii/house_13/house_and_workshop_of_a._granius_romanus/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VIII
House House 13
Garden House and Workshop of A. Granius Romanus (I.viii.13)
Keywords  archaeological garden graffiti (casual notations) inscription lararia  Garden Description The courtyard (a) at the front of this house was covered on the west and north and led to a second courtyard (b) at the rear of the house. In the northwest corner of the passageway there was a large lararium. Too much damage had been sustained to determine if any of the areas had been planted, and graffiti on the wall indicated to Della Corte that business had been conducted here because of all the numerical notations.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula viii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 11, p.42; I.viii-ix: plan in Eschebach (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date Bibliography  Della Corte, Case, p. 327. Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 43. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 09 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.viii.10 B</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_viii/house_10/i.viii.10_b/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 10:35:46 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_viii/house_10/i.viii.10_b/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VIII
House House 10
Garden I.viii.10 B
Keywords Garden Description B. At the southwest corner of the house, the courtyard (b) was possibly a garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula viii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 11, p.42; I.viii-ix: plan in Eschebach (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 43. (worldcat) Maiuri, RM (1953-54), p. 91.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 09 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Caupona-Hospitium dei &#34;Pulcinella&#34; (I.viii.10)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_viii/house_10/caupona-hospitium_dei_pulcinella/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 09:29:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_viii/house_10/caupona-hospitium_dei_pulcinella/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VIII
House House 10
Garden Caupona-Hospitium dei &amp;ldquo;Pulcinella&amp;rdquo; (I.viii.10)
Keywords  archaeological garden lararia mural paintings (visual works) peristyles (columnades) porticoes  Garden Description A. This house had no atrium and the peristyle was entered directly from the street. The peristyle garden (a) was enclosed on the east and the south by a portico. Two lararium flanked the door to a basement on the north end of the east portico. The one on the right was well preserved with paintings of an altar, two Lares, serpents, and a rectangular niche painted with what appear to be poppies. When a layer of plaster crumbled from the wall in March 1949 it revealed a painting of a pottery shop and led Maiuri to believe that there had been a pottery shop entrance to the street from the room on the left. Two other paintings on the façade depict Mercury and costumed men attired as Neapolitan Punch and Judy puppets. This gave the house the identity as a caupona-hospitium of the “Pulcinella.”
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula viii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 11, p.42; I.viii-ix: plan in Eschebach (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date Bibliography  Della Corte, Case, p. 326, no. 675. Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, pp. 42-43. (worldcat) Maiuri, RM (1953-54), pp. 89-91 (the house is erroneously numbered I.v.10) on the plan, fig, 1.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 09 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of L. Vetutius Placidus and Ascula (at the rear of Themopolium no. 8) (I.viii.9)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_viii/house_9/house_of_l._vetutius_placidus/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2020 19:18:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_viii/house_9/house_of_l._vetutius_placidus/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VIII
House House 9
Garden House of L. Vetutius Placidus and Ascula (at the rear of Themopolium no. 8) (I.viii.9)
Keywords  archaeological garden columns (architectural elements) engaged columns fulcrum monopodia mural paintings (visual works) pergolas porticoes tables (support furniture) triclinia  Garden Description An entrance to this small garden (a) was made through the east wall. It was located at the rear of the house and there was a portico on the north supported by two free standing columns and one engaged, all covered with red stucco and connected by a low wall. Fig. 3. A pergola supported by two red columns shaded a masonry triclinium built against the east wall. One column stood on the lectus imus while the other was on a slate base on the corner of the lectus imus. The pergola frame was mortised directly into the back wall at the level of the column capitals. The lectus imus (2.70 m.), the lectus medius (3.00), and the lectus summus (2.86 m.) formed an unusual triclinium because the lectus imus is shorter than the two sides. The lectus summus had a fulcrum and the table measured 0.82 x 0.48 m. The couches were decorated with polychrome floral and geometric designs and the outsides were coated with yellow plaster. It appears there were large animal paintings on the east wall but little of the plaster remains. Excavation uncovered a round monopodium table of marble in the garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula viii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 11, p.42; I.viii-ix: plan in Eschebach (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I. viii. 18.13.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date Bibliography  Della Corte, NSc (1946), p. 95. Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 42. (worldcat) Schefold, WändP, p. 37.  Soprano, p. 297, no. 7.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 09 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Indian Statuette (I.viii.5)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_viii/house_5/house_of_the_indian_statuette/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2020 19:11:52 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_viii/house_5/house_of_the_indian_statuette/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VIII
House House 5
Garden House of the Indian Statuette (I.viii.5)
Keywords  archaeological garden chests (case furniture) columns (architectural elements) gutters (building drainage components) peristyles (columnades) porticoes statues statuettes (free-standing sculpture)  Garden Description A portico enclosed this garden (a) on the north, east and south sides, and the portico on the west had been closed to create rooms. These enclosed columns can be observed incorporated into the wall but only one of the other columns remains standing. The garden was surrounded by a gutter. A small Indian statuette (0.25 m. high) was found in the adjacent shop and it is believed to have been stored in a wooden chest in one of the rooms off the portico with other domestic items. It had tumbled into the shop when the southwest corner of the peristyle collapsed.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula viii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 11, p.42; I.viii-ix: plan in Eschebach (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date Bibliography  Della Corte, Case, p. 334. Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 42. (worldcat) Maiuri, “Statuetta eburnea d’art indiana a Pompei,” LeArti (1938), pp. 111-115. Idem, “Navalia pompeiana,” RendNap, n.s., 33 (1959): 22.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 08 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.viii.2</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_viii/house_2/i.viii.2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2020 19:02:52 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_viii/house_2/i.viii.2/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VIII
House House 2
Garden I.viii.2
Keywords  archaeological garden atriums cisterns (plumbing components) columns (architectural elements) gutters (building drainage components) peristyles (columnades) porticoes tablina  Garden Description The peristyle garden (a) was reached from the atrium by ascending two steps to the tablinium. It was enclosed by a portico on four sides but all of the columns and the floor of the north, east and west portico was destroyed by bombing in WWII. A large cistern under the peristyle collected the water by way of the gutter at the edge of the garden. There was an adjacent dyeshop (19) at the rear which used this water supply.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula viii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 11, p.42; I.viii-ix: plan in Eschebach (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date Bibliography  Della Corte, Case, pp. 333-334. Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 42. (worldcat) Moeller, Wool Trade, pp.35-36. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 08 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shop-House (I.vii.18) *Appendix II*</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vii/house_18/shop-house_appendix_ii_i.vii.18/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2020 18:54:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vii/house_18/shop-house_appendix_ii_i.vii.18/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VII
House House 18
Garden Shop-House (I.vii.18)
Keywords  archaeological garden atriums mural paintings (visual works)  Garden Description Two paintings were found on the west wall of the atrium behind this shop, one was of a porticus villa on the sea and the second was a garden representation (o.16 x 0.43 m.). The garden was surrounded by a lattice fence which was drawn wider in the front than the rear and had a rectangular pool in front with ducks swimming.Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula vii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 10, p. 37; *NSc* (1929), pl. 18; Spinazzola, *Scavi nuovi*, vol. 1, after p. 679; Ibid, vol. 2, after p. 1027; entire insula in Eschebach (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date Bibliography  Idem, Gardens, vol.II, p. 395. (worldcat) Maiuri, NSc (1929), p. 380 and fig. 14 on p. 381 (where the address is given as I.vii. y). Schefold, WändP, p. 35.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 08 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shop-House (I.vii.15-17)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vii/houses_15-17/shop-house_i.vii.15-17/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2020 18:49:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vii/houses_15-17/shop-house_i.vii.15-17/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VII
House House 15-17
Garden Shop-House (I.vii.15-17)
Keywords  archaeological garden tables (support furniture) triclinia  Garden Description The shop-house was laid out in a very irregular manner and the garden (a) took up most of the space. There was a masonry triclinium in the southern part of the garden. This had a lectus imus and a lectus summus that both were 3.80 m. in length and the lectus medius was 4.24 m. in length. The rectangular table measured 1.10 x 0.75 m.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula vii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 10, p. 37; *NSc* (1929), pl. 18; Spinazzola, *Scavi nuovi*, vol. 1, after p. 679; Ibid, vol. 2, after p. 1027; entire insula in Eschebach (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date Bibliography  Idem, Gardens, vol.II, p. 41. (worldcat) Soprano, p. 296, no. 6.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 08 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.vii.10-12/19 C</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vii/houses_10-12&#43;19/i.vii.10-12&#43;19_c/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2020 18:40:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vii/houses_10-12&#43;19/i.vii.10-12&#43;19_c/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VII
House House 10-12/19
Garden I.vii.10-12/19
Keywords  archaeological garden impluvia mural paintings (visual works) tablina water wells  Garden Description C. Behind the tablinium, and seen from the entrance (no. 19), a small light well served as a garden. Fig. 3. It was painted to represent a garden and the floor had been paved. The only surviving images were the usual fence with faint traces of oleander bushes and birds. Further traces indicated that a statuette of Venus standing on a marble base in an apsed niche in the lattice fence may have been represented on the east wall. The lattice fence on the north wall was painted to represent a rectangular niche.Water was piped from the garden above through the lower part of the rear wall and possible supplied a jet in the middle of the impluvium, as surmised by Maiuri.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula vii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 10, p. 37; *NSc* (1929), pl. 18; Spinazzola, *Scavi nuovi*, vol. 1, after p. 679; Ibid, vol. 2, after p. 1027; entire insula in Eschebach (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I.vii. 3.35.72, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date Bibliography  Della Corte, Case, p. 318. Grimal, p. 447, no. 5A (where the small court is incorrectly located as 10 on fig. 37 instead of 9). Jashemski, Gardens, 1:61 and no. 19 and 20 on p. 345. (worldcat) Idem, Gardens, vol.II, p. 41. (worldcat) Maiuri, NSc (1929), p 336 (where the light well is incorrectly labeled as cortiletto 10). PPP, 1:76. Warscher, “”Flora pomp.,” p. 21. Zanker, p. 50.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 08 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.vii.10-12/19 B</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vii/houses_10-12&#43;19/i.vii.10-12&#43;19_b/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2020 18:06:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vii/houses_10-12&#43;19/i.vii.10-12&#43;19_b/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VII
House House 10-12/19
Garden I.vii.10-12/19
Keywords  archaeological garden cisterns (plumbing components) columns (architectural elements) doliums engaged columns exedrae (site elements) fountains mural paintings (visual works) peristyles (columnades) porticoes puteal stairs statues statuettes (free-standing sculpture)  Garden Description This peristyle garden (f) was entered by way of seven steps from the garden of the House of the Ephebe. This part of the building had once been a se parate house (19). A portico supported by seven columns, two of them engaged, enclosed the garden on the north and part of the east side. The columns were plastered masonry, painted white on the top and red on the bottom and each had a rectangular hole, 1.70 m. from the bottom, on the side in line with the other columns. It is speculated that these were for wooden beams that held privacy screens or mats which would shield the garden area from heat and cold. The intercolumniation in front of the excedra (g) did not have these holes, as it offered a fine view on the garden. A lead pipe with a tap directed water from the garden above into a dolium near the corner column. The pipe attached to the column had been shaped to resemble a snake fountain. Nearby a cistern collected water from the channels on the portico roof and a puteal was located on the top of the cistern. East–west furrows were preserved in the soil and the south, west and part of the east wall of the garden had garden paintings. Two large niches were located in the north wall of the portico east of the garden steps and there was an arched niche in the west wall of the north portico. In the excedra off the north portico a broken herm of Dionysus (0.12 x 0.19), was found, which was possible a garden decoration. The walls of this peristyle garden were painted with very fine garden paintings on part of the east wall and the other three sides. Slender painted columns complete with painted garlands suspended between them, created the appearance of extending the portico and divided the walls into panels. Fig. 3. The excavators found the paintings had been badly damaged, the best preserved was the north panel on the west wall (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, fig. 93 on p. 58). This showed a slender marble crater-fountain on a decorated column standing in a semi-circular niche formed by a low lattice fence. A photograph taken at the time of excavation shows that behind the fence the bushes represented were myrtles with an oleander on the right. In the background there was a date palm with lower leaves trimmed and new growth showing. This palm was flanked by two laurel trees (Laurus nobilis L.). Various birds occupied the thickets and there was a bird perched on the fence, one on the rim of the fountain and one on one of the garlands. The center panel next to this was partially preserved and what remained was the painting of a shallow, round, bubbling fountain supported by three legs located in a three sided niche formed by the lattice fence. Again there were myrtles behind the fence with a slender cypress on the right. Traces of a date palm remain in the center background. The center of the south wall was occupied by a statuette of Venus standing on a circular base, although this had to be deduced from the part of the painting which survived, which only went knee high on the statue. A fragment of a narrow animal painting survived on the west wall above a garden painting. Fig. 4.Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula vii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 10, p. 37; *NSc* (1929), pl. 18; Spinazzola, *Scavi nuovi*, vol. 1, after p. 679; Ibid, vol. 2, after p. 1027; entire insula in Eschebach (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I.vii. 4.5.72, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).     Fig. 4: I.vii. 3.35.72, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date Bibliography  Borda, p. 70, fig. on p. 68. Boyce, p. 26, no. 42, 43. Della Corte, Case, p. 318. Grimal, p. 447, no. 5B. Jashemski, Gardens, 1: 57-58 and fig. 93 on p. 58. (worldcat) Idem, Gardens, vol.II, p. 41. (worldcat) Maiuri, NSc (1929), pp. 367, 369, 370, 371 and fig. 1 (plan) on p. 35. Maiuri, NSc, (1929), p. 370 and pl. 20. Idem, MonPittAnt, sec. 3, Pompeii, fasc.2 (1939), p. 34. Peters, Landscape, p. 8. (worldcat) PPP, 1:76. Schefold, WändP, pp. 2, 36, early third style. Schefold, Vergessenes Pompeii, p. 152. (worldcat) Warscher, “”Flora pomp.,” p. 22. Zanker, p. 50.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 08 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Ephebe; Casa Dell’Efebo; House of P. Cornelius Teges (or Tages) (I.vii.10-12/19)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vii/houses_10-12&#43;19/house_of_the_ephebe/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2020 16:18:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vii/houses_10-12&#43;19/house_of_the_ephebe/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VII
House House 10-12/19
Garden House of the Ephebe; Casa Dell’Efebo; House of P. Cornelius Teges (or Tages) (I.vii.10-12/19)
Keywords  aedicules archaeological garden atriums basins (vessels) busts (sculpture) candelabras (candleholders) columns (architectural elements) exedrae (site elements) fences (site elements) fountains mural paintings (visual works) pergolas pillars piscinae porticoes stairs statues statuettes (free-standing sculpture) tables (support furniture) tablina trellises triclinia vegetable gardens vestibules  Garden Description A. This house was made by combining several small houses. The upper garden (a) had an unusual portico on the north with various diameter columns, plastered and painted red, and two pillars. A third column on a square base supported an extension of the portico, which was a step lower and formed by an extension of the vestibule at entrance 12. The triclinium (b), tablinium (c), and exedra (d) on the upper level of the portico were protected from cold and rain by some sort of screen installed between the columns and the west pillar. Most scholars surmise these were wooden but Maiuri proposed that they were glass, although he did not find any glass fragments during excavation. (Window panes surviving from this period from other sites are on display at the Museo Archaeological in Naples and in the deposito at Pompeii).
Two steps below the portico was the garden (a). The back wall had a large animal painting and a small aedicula with a semicircular niche. A relief of Dianna and two deer adorned the front and inside a bronze statuette fountain of Pomona (0.38 m. high; Mus. Naz. inv. no. 144 276) stood holding a bivalve shell filled with fruit. Water jetted from the shell, down four marble steps and into the small square pool below. A marble covered channel divided the lectus medius of the triclinium in two parts and carried the water to a small jet in the center of the low triclinium table. Four large columns supported a vine-covered pergola that shaded the triclinium. The soil near the columns had root cavities, as reported by Maiuri, but no further details were recorded. Fig. 3.
This was the best preserved triclinium (l. medius, 4.60 m.; l. imus and l. summus 4.40 x 0.88 m.) in the entire city. Each couch had a marble faced step along the top, and on the sides of the triclinium was painted a series of Nilotic scenes. There were two complete paintings while the rest of the work comprised a continuous frieze. These scenes depicted Egyptian life that revolved around the periodic inundation of the Nile. Activities pictured included men fishing, a woman spinning under a canopy, worshipers visiting shrines, (some shrines in enclosures, some with extensive gardens), banquet scenes, an erotic scene in a caupona, and a pigmy slave driving a coclea (water screw). Fig. 4.
Attached to each of the north columns of the pergola was a low column (1.00 m. high) which most likely served as bases for statuettes. In front and a little to the west of the lectus summus was a large masonry base (0.93 m. high; 0.685 m. in dia.) where Maiuri surmised that the famous bronze statue of the Ephebe stood. This statue (1.49 m. high; Mus. Naz. inv. no. 143 753) had been made into a gilded lamp stand holding candelabra brackets and was found in the atrium where it had been wrapped and placed for protection against the impending disaster. At either end of the portico was an additional pair of low circular bases for statuettes. Four broken marble statuettes were found in the triclinium where they most likely were brought for protection or perhaps for repair after the earthquake. A statuette of Pan holding a fruit-filled calathos on his left shoulder and a ram’s head in his right hand (0.60 m. high with base; Pompeii inv. no. 3682) was reconstructed from nineteen fragments. The white marble piece had been completely gilded. There was also an inebriated satyr of white marble, (the head was missing) sprawled on a gray marble rock and opening a wineskin (0.32 m. long; 0.27 m. high with base; Pompeii inv. no. 3684). Only the necklace, bracelet, and several other details were gilded on this piece. A completely gilded statuette of a deer suckling a fawn (0.35 m. long; 0.22 m. high; Pompeii inv. no. 3683) and the remains of a gray marble base with white marble goat feet of Pan standing on a scabellum, the typical instrument of satyrs, (0.28 m. long; 0. 105 m. high; Pompeii inv. no. 3685) were found there. There were also four vulgar silver-plated statuettes of placentarii or pastry vendors (each with base, 0.255 m. high; Mus. Naz. inv. nos. 143 758, 143 759, 143 761, 143 761 bis). Each carried a silver tray which Maiuri surmised were used to hold food delicacies served at dinner parties in the garden triclinium. The statuettes as well as the delicacies were found stored together in the house.
A trellis fence separated the triclinium from the eastern part of the garden. Fig. 5. The trellis was supported by four slender marble posts and on top of these were four small sculptured heads. These pieces were: an archaic style head of Zeus rendered in white marble (0.19 m. high) with traces of bright colors, an archaic bust of Hera (0.135 m. high) and also a head of a woman (0.145 m. high) carved in yellow marble, and a Bacchic head of a child made from red marble. A plain round table and a curved marble seat were found in the center of the garden. Fig. 6. The excavation revealed soil arranged in furrows, as customary for vegetable gardens, and root cavities of small plants.
Water was supplied to the garden by way of overflow channels from the triclinium fountain. A basin, with two terra-cotta openings which would regulate the flow of water to either half of the garden, was located at the edge of the garden. The south wall at the rear of the triclinium once had a large hunt scene, but the only surviving part was the lower register. To the left of the aedicula fountain the images of a large deer and a bird remain, and to the right a bull flees from an unidentified attacker. A feline is crouched under a large tree in the lower right and other trees are sketchily depicted in the background.Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula vii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 10, p. 37; *NSc* (1929), pl. 18; Spinazzola, *Scavi nuovi*, vol. 1, after p. 679; Ibid, vol. 2, after p. 1027; entire insula in Eschebach (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I.vii. 11.32.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).     Fig. 4: I.vii. 14.3.68, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).     Fig. 5: I.vii. 33.27.61, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).     Fig. 6: I.vii. 11.33.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date Bibliography  Boyce, p. 26, no. 41. Chamoux, BCH 74 (1950): 70-79. Della Corte, Case, pp. 317-318. Döhl, pp. 4-5. Jashemski, Gardens, 1:50, 92-93, 113 and figs. 145-149 on pp. 93-94,1:57, 92 and fig. 145 on p. 93.(worldcat) Idem, Gardens, vol.II, pp. 38–41, 316-317. (worldcat) Kapossy, p.13. Maiuri, “La raffigurazione del placentarius in quattro bronzetti pompeiani,” BdA (1925), pp.268-275. Idem, &amp;ldquo;L’efebodi Via dell’Abbondanza a Pompei,” BdA (1926), pp. 337-353. Idem, NSc (1927), pp. 49-68, 70-74 and fig 9 (plan) on p. 33. Maiuri, MonPittAnt, sec. 3, Pompeii, fasc. 2 (1939), pp. 23-27, pls. 3-5 (paintings on triclinium). Maiuri, Pompeii (Novara), pp. 105-106. (worldcat) Mauiri, NSc, (1929), p. 370 and pl. 20. Idem, MonPittAnt, sec. 3, Pompeii, fasc.2 (1939), p. 27 and pl. 20 (detail of right of painting). Michel, pp. 394, 400. Neuerburg, pp. 117-119, no. 18. PPP, 1:70.  Schefold, WändP, p. 34.  Soprano, p. 295, no. 5 and fig. 31 on p. 296. Zanker, pp. 500-501.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 08 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Priest Amandus (I.vii.7)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vii/house_7/house_of_the_priest_amandus/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2020 16:01:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vii/house_7/house_of_the_priest_amandus/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VII
House House 7
Garden House of the Priest Amandus (I.vii.7)
Keywords  aedicules archaeological garden atriums cisterns (plumbing components) columns (architectural elements) engaged columns lararia peristyles (columnades) porticoes puteal tables (support furniture) triclinia  Garden Description One step above the level of the triclinium of this small house with an irregular floor plan was a peristyle garden (a). It was to the west of the atrium and enclosed on the north and east by a portico. Fig. 3. Five columns supported the portico and two engaged columns on the west wall continued the order of the peristyle. A large tree root cavity (the cast measures 0.80 x0.82) indicated that the garden was well shaded and nail holes in the wall would suggest that vines had been trained to grow in that area. A large window located in the room to the west (b) gave a view into the garden. A puteal was located over the cistern opening in the northwest corner of the peristyle and another puteal was additionally found in the garden as well as a cartibulum (table) decorated on one side with lions heads and a small circular base most likely used for a statuette. A lararium on the west wall consisted of an aedicula façade with an arched niche. Fig. 4, Fig. 5.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula vii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 10, p. 37; *NSc* (1929), pl. 18; Spinazzola, *Scavi nuovi*, vol. 1, after p. 679; Ibid, vol. 2, after p. 1027; entire insula in Eschebach (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I.vii. 13.18.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).     Fig. 4: I.vii. 22.12.68, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).     Fig. 5: I.vii. 22.22.68, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date Bibliography  Boyce, p. 25, no. 39. Jashemski, Gardens, 1:30. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, pp. 37–38. (worldcat) Maiuri, NSc (1927), pp. 26-27 and fig. 1 (plan) on p. 4. Maiuri, Pompeii (Novara), p. 112. (worldcat) Idem, “I giardini,” Le Vie d’Italia, no.9 (Sept 1961), p. 1138.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 08 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of M. Fabius Amandio [Della Corte, Maiuri]; of P. Cornelius Cornthus [Spinazzola] (I.vii.2-3)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vii/houses_2-3/house_of_m._fabius_amandio/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2020 10:28:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vii/houses_2-3/house_of_m._fabius_amandio/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VII
House House 2-3
Garden House of M. Fabius Amandio [Della Corte, Maiuri]; of P. Cornelius Cornthus [Spinazzola] (I.vii.2-3)
Keywords  archaeological garden atriums mural paintings (visual works) piscinae  Garden Description A very small garden was located in the light well at the rear of the atrium. The small raised garden (about 0.50 m. high) had a tiny semicircular pool fed by roof water. Fig. 3; Fig. 4. Three marble bases (0.16 x0.21 m.) were most likely place at the edge of the pool. A garden painting adorned the wall behind pool. This was the painting of a garden fence and a slender, footed fountain before it. Fig. 5. The water jets have attracted a peacock and two small birds that are perched on the rim (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, fig. 97 on p. 60). The elaborate plant motif on the foot of the fountain suggested to Maiuri that the artist was depicting a bronze fountain rather than a marble one. A dense thicket painted behind the fence has small fruit, the blossom ends are clearly visible, with white myrtle blossoms mixed with the foliage. Jashemski differs with Maiuri’s description of this as an oleander thicket with blossoms and berries; as she points out that oleander has enlongated pods as opposed to round berries. The east wall was yellow with plants painted on it, but only the north panel survived, and nothing remains of the work on the west and north walls. Fig. 6.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula vii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 10, p. 37; *NSc* (1929), pl. 18; Spinazzola, *Scavi nuovi*, vol. 1, after p. 679; Ibid, vol. 2, after p. 1027; entire insula in Eschebach (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I.vii. 54.8.64, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).     Fig. 4: I.vii. 54.7.54, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).     Fig. 5: I.vii. 53.38.64, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).     Fig. 6: I.vii. 12.36.72, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date Bibliography  Della Corte, Case, p. 313. Grimal, p. 446, no. 4. Jashemski, Gardens, 1:60 and fig. 97 on p. 60. (worldcat) Idem, Gardens, vol.II, p. 37, 316.(worldcat) Maiuri, NSc (1927), pp. 8, 11 and fig. 1 (plan) on p. 4. Maiuri, Pompeii (Novara), pp. 112. (worldcat) Idem, MonPittAnt, sec. 3, Pompeii, fasc.2 (1939), p. 2.  Michel, p. 382.  PPP, 1:55. Schefold, WändP, p.30 (says that this garden painting imitates the second style of the Villa of Livia). Spinazzola, Scavi nuovi, see large plan at back of book. (worldcat) Warscher, “Flora pomp.,” p. 24.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 08 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of P. Paquius Proculus [Della Corte, Maiuri]; House of C. Cuspius Pansa [Spinazzola](I.vii.1)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vii/house_1/house_of_p._paquius_proculus/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2020 16:40:11 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vii/house_1/house_of_p._paquius_proculus/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VII
House House 1
Garden House of P. Paquius Proculus [Della Corte, Maiuri]; House of C. Cuspius Pansa Spinazzola
Keywords  archaeological garden basins (vessels) columns (architectural elements) gutters (building drainage components) loggias oeci pergolas peristyles (columnades) piscinae porticoes puteal tablina triclinia  Garden Description This elegant house was excavated in 1923. To the rear was a large and sunny peristyle garden (a) with a portico on four sides supported by sixteen columns. At the northeast corner stood a lava puteal with a gutter that ran around the edges of the garden. In the center of the garden a wooden triclinium was shaded by a pergola supported by four columns. The nails and the imprint of the wooden structure of the triclinium were clearly preserved. A marble faced rectangular pool, with an apse-shaped extension to the north and a fountain jet, was located in front of the triclinium. Fig. 3, Fig. 4. This pool was connected to a smaller marble basin between the couches of the triclinium. An excellent view of the garden was afforded from the large salon (b) at the rear of the tablinum with two columns at the entrance of the portico. The oecus (c) also opened on the north portico with a fine view of the garden and the loggia above had a view of the garden as well as views to the sea and the Lattari Mountains. Fig. 5.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula vii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 10, p. 37; *NSc* (1929), pl. 18; Spinazzola, *Scavi nuovi*, vol. 1, after p. 679; Ibid, vol. 2, after p. 1027; entire insula in Eschebach (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I. vii. 13.11.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).     Fig. 4: I.vii. 13.12.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).     Fig. 5: I.vii. 61.3.57, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1923
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, 1:92. (worldcat) Idem, Gardens, vol.II, p. 37. (worldcat) Maiuri, NSc (1929), p. 386 and fig. 18 (plan of triclinium) on p. 387, fig. 20 (plan) on p. 389. Maiuri, Pompeii (Novara), pp. 100-101. (worldcat) Pernice, p. 13. Soprano, p. 307, no. 30; Spinazzola, Scavi nuovi, p. 299 and fig. 334 (plan) on p. 297. (worldcat) Warscher, “Codex,” VI. Viii. appendix on water and photo no. 66.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 08 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of L. Ceius Secundus; House of the Ceii; of Queen Elena; of Fabia and Tyrannus (I.vi.15)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vi/house_15/house_of_l._ceius_secundus/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2020 10:58:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vi/house_15/house_of_l._ceius_secundus/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VI
House House 15
Garden House of L. Ceius Secundus; House of the Ceii; of Queen Elena; of Fabia and Tyrannus (I.vi.15)
Keywords  archaeological garden apotheca basins (vessels) cisterns (plumbing components) fountains garden lights garden ornaments gutters (building drainage components) mural paintings (visual works) statues statuettes (free-standing sculpture)  Garden Description This small garden (a) was located at the rear of the house and featured a portio on part of the south side and a gutter along the south and east sides which carried water to the cistern. Preserved on the rear wall was one of the best animal paintings found in Pompeii, with three large openings provided in the painting to accommodate garden lights. Fig. 3, Fig. 4, Fig. 5, Fig. 6, Fig. 7, Fig. 8. On either side of the animal painting at the lower part of the wall is a garden painting with a sphinx crouching in oleanders with dark red blossoms holding a fountain basin. The fountain on the right would appear to pour water into the actual gutter below. (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, fig. 113 on p. 70). A realistic border of myrtle (Myrtus communis L.) and ivy (Hedera helix L.) is painted along the bottom of the wall with birds flying across a red background (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, figs. 43, 111, 112 on pp. 29, 69). Just above this, branches of ivy are painted along the bottom of an expansive wild animal scene. A bull is being pursued by a lion across a rocky lake shore on the lower foreground, wolves and wild boars occupy the center of the picture on the opposite shore, on the right a leopard is chasing two rams, and two gazelles are painted on the left (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, figs. 111, 112 on p. 69).Brackets for garden lights had been installed where three large holes remained in this animal painting. The outside walls of the apotheca (storeroom) on the southwest corner of the garden had painted garden motifs. There was a garden scene painted on a reddish background depicting a statue of a water nymph with a two handled basin appearing to catch water from the roof and directing it to the gutter below. To the left are bushes with a tawny owl (Strix aluco L.) and to the right is a white pigeon or rock dove (Columba livia Gmelin) (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, figs. 111, 114 on pp. 69, 70.). Over this was a panel with two peacocks (Pavo cristatus L.) facing a bronze garden ornament that consists of a leafy stalk topped by a round shield. (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, fig. 111 on p. 69). Flowering plants fill in the bottom while the top of the panel is graced with two garlands and two flying birds, a swallow (Hirundo rustica L.) on the left and a large headed bird on the right which could be a shrike (Lanius sp.) Although the outside wall of the apotheca was badly damaged, to the right of the window paintings of a bush with red blossoms and a myrtle bush on a yellow background survived.The east and west walls were decorated with large Egyptian landscapes. Another garden decoration, a marble dove (0.29 m. long) was found in the kitchen.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula vi, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 9, p. 34; *NSc* (1929), pl 18; Spinnazola, *Scavi nuovi*, vol. 1, after p. 679; Ibid., vol. 2, after p. 1027 (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I. vi. 3.31.72, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).     Fig. 4: I. vi. 5.13.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).     Fig. 5: I. vi. 5.17.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).     Fig. 6: I. vi. 5.18.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).     Fig. 7: I.vi. 16.24.68, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).     Fig. 8: I. vi. 45.18.64, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, 1:69-70, 113 and fig. 111 on p. 69. (worldcat) Idem, Gardens, 1:69-70 and figs. 43 on p. 29, 111-114 on pp. 69-70. (worldcat)  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 36. (worldcat) Idem, Gardens, vol.II, p. 315.(worldcat) Idem, Natural History, Dec. 1964, p. 37. (worldcat) Maiuri, Boll. D’Arte n.s. 5 (1926) p. 69, fig. 112.  Michel, p. 399.  Peters, Landscape, pp. 172-173. (worldcat) PPP, 1:43-44. Schefold, WandP, p. 28. Spinazzola, Scavi nuovi, pp. 275-277, 280and fig. 282 (plan) on p. 258, figs. 304, 306, and 307 on pp. 275-277. (worldcat) Zanker, pp. 504-506.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 07 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Stallus Eros (I.vi.13)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vi/house_13/house_of_stallus_eros/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2020 10:14:45 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vi/house_13/house_of_stallus_eros/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VI
House House 13
Garden House of Stallus Eros (I.vi.13)
Keywords  archaeological garden lararia mural paintings (visual works) viridarium  Garden Description At the rear of this house a masonry wall surrounded the small garden (a) which was undergoing extensive repairs at the time of the eruption. A lararium niche was located on the east wall and the rear wall held remnants of a garden painting. Fig. 3, Fig. 4, Fig. 5, Fig. 6. This painting was evidently in poor condition at the time of the eruption. Maiuri mentions the painting in his excavation report: “una grande parete dipinta con una pittura di paesaggio.” A detailed description is given by Della Corte who stated that the viridarium was given the illusion of enlargement by the paintings of woodland trees and flowering plants. He reported the usual lattice fence painted in the foreground with a tetrastyle pavilion and a statue of a winged female sphinx painted at each end of the fence. Oscilla were painted to appear to hang from the upper border of the large wall. A painting of Orpheus charming the beasts was barely visible on the right side of the wall. Seated on a dark red cloak between gigantic rocks in a landscape, his lyre against his leg, a variety of animals approached him. A section of the painting that survived on the right depicted a peacock, a goose, a cock, a wild boar, and a large black guinea hen. The painting was photographed at the time of excavation in 1929 (Mus. Naz. negative C/1614). Jashemski examined this site in 1964 and found part of a narrow panel still visible to the right of the large panel, although covered by vines. This panel was separated from the rest by a dark vertical stripe. At the bottom a lattice fence had daisy-like flowers growing through it, with both rounded and pointed petals. Above the fence two roughly painted cypress trees (Cupressus sempervirens L.) flank several bushes which are not Acacia vera as suggested by Grimal. Jashemski notes that Grimal wrote his description on the basis of one sentence of Maiuri and the Museo Nazionale photograph included in Maiuri’s report. He also had Warscher’s photograph of the sphinx detail from the large panel but could not identify where it was located in the large panel. Jashemski also speculated that it was likely there had been an identical narrow panel on the other side of the large panel, but all the plaster had fallen leaving no trace of decorations. The best preserved section of the painting that Jashemski found was a large bush painted on the left side of the large panel. The bush could not be identified by the form of the fruit and/or flowers but perched in the bush was a crudely depicted owl identified as Athene noctua Scopoli by way of its big head and hefty legs. Another bird was painted on a higher branch to the right which may have been a thrush. Another bush just below and to the right edge of the painting and a large cypress to the right of the bush with the owl was shown in the Museo nazionale negative C/1614. Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula vi, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 9, p. 34; *NSc* (1929), pl 18; Spinnazola, *Scavi nuovi*, vol. 1, after p. 679; Ibid., vol. 2, after p. 1027 (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I.vi. 5.6.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).     Fig. 4: I.vi. 5.7.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).     Fig. 5: I.vi. 34.29.64, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).     Fig. 6: I.vi. 35.6.64, S.A.Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1929
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 25, no. 38. de Vos, Meded 39 (1977): 39.  Della Corte, Case, p. 269.  Grimal, p. 446, no.3. Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 36. (worldcat) Idem, Gardens, vol.II, p. 313-314. (worldcat) Maiuri, NSc (1929), p. 434 and fig. 44 (plan) on p. 432and fig. 45 . PPP, 1:39. Schefold, WändP, p. 26.   Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 07 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa Dei Quadretti Teatralli; House of the Calavii (I.vi.11)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vi/house_11/casa_dei_quadretti_teatralli/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2020 09:50:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vi/house_11/casa_dei_quadretti_teatralli/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VI
House House 11
Garden Casa Dei Quadretti Teatralli; House of the Calavii (I.vi.11)
Keywords  archaeological garden cisterns (plumbing components) columns (architectural elements) mural paintings (visual works) porticoes puteal wine cellars  Garden Description A partially completed wall joined the columns supporting the portico at the rear of this house. Next to this was a small garden (a) which was in an extreme state of ruin at the time of excavation due to the weakening of the wine cellar vaults below. The vaults had openings to admit light and air for the wine aging and a cistern was also located under the garden. On the portico to the east there was a large terra-cotta puteal. Fig. 3. A room on the south end of the east portico contains a garden representation on the west wall. Barely a third of the representation survived and what remains is extremely faded. It is painted in yellow on a small dark green panel in the center of a red wall and shows a pergola with a lattice fence extending from both sides and a section of fence in front. Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula vi, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 9, p. 34; *NSc* (1929), pl 18; Spinnazola, *Scavi nuovi*, vol. 1, after p. 679; Ibid., vol. 2, after p. 1027 (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I. vi. 13.9.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 36. (worldcat) Idem, Gardens, vol.II, p. 395. (worldcat) Maiuri, NSc (1929), pp. 414-415 and fig. 26 (plan) on p. 401.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 07 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shop (I.vi.8-9)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vi/houses_8-9/shop_i.vi.8-9/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 22:12:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vi/houses_8-9/shop_i.vi.8-9/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VI
House House 8-9
Garden Shop (I.vi.8-9)
Keywords  archaeological garden columns (architectural elements) doghouses peristyles (columnades) porticoes puteal tufa  Garden Description This modest house had rooms opening off the small peristyle garden (a) at the rear of the structure. The rooms had been remodeled to serve as a shop and at the time of the eruption, were in disrepair. Four columns, two of tufa, two of brick, supported the peristyle portico on the north and east sides and were connected by a low wall with an entrance to the garden on the east side. Fig. 3. A terra-cotta puteal was located on the east side of the portico. The house to the rear was completely destroyed necessitated the building of a crude doghouse in the last intercolumniation on the east side. Keeping a dog would have prevented intruders from entering through the ruins and robbing the shop as well as the adjacent house (no. 11) where the shopkeeper most likely resided. Fig. 4.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula vi, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 9, p. 34; *NSc* (1929), pl 18; Spinnazola, *Scavi nuovi*, vol. 1, after p. 679; Ibid., vol. 2, after p. 1027 (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I.vi. 6.7.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).     Fig. 4: I.vi. 6.8.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 35. (worldcat) Maiuri, NSc (1929), pp. 393-395 and fig. 26 (plan) on p. 401. Pernice, p. 32 and pl. 21.1.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 06 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fullonica of Stephanus (I.vi.7)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vi/house_7/fullonica_of_stephanus/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 19:56:52 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vi/house_7/fullonica_of_stephanus/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VI
House House 7
Garden Fullonica of Stephanus (I.vi.7)
Keywords  archaeological garden fullery gutters (building drainage components) peristyles (columnades) pillars porticoes  Garden Description This house had been converted to a fullery and the small peristyle garden to the rear probably served as a drying area. Five pillars of the portico were connected by a low, marble topped wall. This enclosed the raised garden on the east, north and west sides with a deep gutter running around the garden along the wall. Fig. 3, Fig. 4.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula vi, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 9, p. 34; *NSc* (1929), pl 18; Spinnazola, *Scavi nuovi*, vol. 1, after p. 679; Ibid., vol. 2, after p. 1027 (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I.iv. 6.29.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).     Fig. 4: I.iv. 6.36.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, 1:198. (worldcat) Idem, Gardens, vol.II, p. 35. (worldcat) Moeller, Wool Trade, p.42. (worldcat) Spinazzola, Scavi nuovi, p.773 and fig. 744 (plan) on p. 765. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 06 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Lararium: Casa Del Larario; Sacello Iliaco (I.vi.4)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vi/house_4/house_of_the_lararium/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 13:24:46 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vi/house_4/house_of_the_lararium/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VI
House House 4
Garden House of the Lararium: Casa Del Larario; Sacello Iliaco (I.vi.4)
Keywords  archaeological garden atriums flower gardens piscinae tablina  Garden Description A small garden (a) was located at the rear of the tablinum accessed by a passageway from the atrium. A small pool (0.70 m. deep) was centered in the garden enclosed by a crudely built double wall with a space in between for flowers. At the time of the eruption the house was undergoing extensive repairs.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula vi, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 9, p. 34; *NSc* (1929), pl 18; Spinnazola, *Scavi nuovi*, vol. 1, after p. 679; Ibid., vol. 2, after p. 1027 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates Bibliography  Della Corte, NSc (1913), pp. 356-357 and fig. 1 (plan) on p. 356. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 35. (worldcat) Spinazzola, Scavi nuovi, p. 446 and fig. 493 (plan) on p. 433. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 06 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.v.3/16 B</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_v/houses_3&#43;16/i.v.3&#43;16/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2020 19:32:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_v/houses_3&#43;16/i.v.3&#43;16/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula V
House House 3/16
Garden I.v.3/16 B
Keywords  archaeological garden columns (architectural elements) cryptoportici fulcrum human remains loggias pillars pilasters stairs tables (support furniture) triclinia vegetable gardens  Garden Description B. At the rear of the house, a large enclosed garden (b) had been increased in size by reducing the wings of the cryptoporticus. The last owner had built a spacious loggia (5 x 20 m.) above the north wing of the cryptoporticus overlooking the garden. A high wall joined the five pillars and the roof supporting pilaster and formed windows into the garden. At the west end of the loggia was a masonry triclinium with side couches, each having a fulcrum (foot), (l. medius 4.41m.; l.summus and l. imus 4.68 m.; dia. of table 0.55m.). A large area was left open for tables or dancers, suggesting to Spinoza that this could have been a public gathering place. There were low seats in front of the side couches and extended along the terrace walls that may have been intended for children according to Soprano. A kitchen was located on the north side of the loggia. Six steps from the southeast corner of the loggia led up into the garden which had been raised to the level of the windows in the cryptoporticus. Della Corte thought that this garden had been used to raise many cabbages and leeks. The remains of eleven victims of the volcanic eruption were found in the garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula v, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 8, p. 33; Viola, *Scavi*, pl. 1; Niccolini, *Case*, vol. 3, “*Topografia*,” pl. 10 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates Bibliography  Della Corte, Case, p. 228. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 34. (worldcat) Maruri, NSc (1933), pp. 256, 258-259, 272 and pl. 5 (plan). Salza Prina Ricotti, “Cucine,” 268-271. Soprano, pp. 294-295, no. 4 and fig. 30. Spinazzola, NSc (1914), pp. 256, 259-262, 287, 365-368. Spinazzola, Scavi nuovi, pp.121-122, 442, 444-445, 451, 453. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 06 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Cryptoporticus; Casa Del Crirtoportico; Casa Omerica; House of T. Lucretius Carus (I.v.3/16)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_v/houses_3&#43;16/house_of_the_cryptoporticus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2020 19:15:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_v/houses_3&#43;16/house_of_the_cryptoporticus/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula V
House House 3/16
Garden House of the Cryptoporticus; Casa Del Crirtoportico; Casa Omerica; House of T. Lucretius Carus (I.v.3/16)
Keywords  archaeological garden atriums busts (sculpture) columns (architectural elements) cryptoportici lararia loggias mural paintings (visual works) peristyles (columnades) pillars porticoes stairs  Garden Description A. A passageway from the atrium led to a modest peristyle garden (a) visible through a window in the rear wall. A low wall enclosed the garden on the north and east sides along with five brick columns covered with white stucco and a pillar supporting the roof of the portico. A large, well preserved wall painting survived on the west wall of the north portico as well as a niche lararium decorated with a painted bust of Mercury. From the garden a flight of stairs led down to an elegant cryptoporticus (underground portico) illuminated by light from the adjacent garden through high windows. A solarium terrace, or loggia, overlooking the large garden (b) could be reached by another flight of stairs form the east portico.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula v, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 8, p. 33; Viola, *Scavi*, pl. 1; Niccolini, *Case*, vol. 3, “*Topografia*,” pl. 10 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates Bibliography  Boyce, p. 25, no. 36. Della Corte, NSc (1914), pp. 74-75. Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 34. (worldcat) Spinazzola, NSc (1914), pp. 259-263. Spinazzola, Scavi nuovi, p.441 and fig. 493 (plan) on p. 433. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 05 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.v.3</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_v/house_3/i.v.3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2020 16:34:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_v/house_3/i.v.3/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula V
House House 3
Garden I.v.3
Keywords  archaeological garden lararia stables (animal housing) troughs (containers)  Garden Description This site had been destroyed in antiquity and probably had been a hospitium. Excavated in 1874, the remains of a watering trough for animals and a stable were uncovered. Often demolished sites were planted but it could not be determined if there was vegetation present at the time of the eruption. The west wall contained an arched lararium niche.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula v, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 8, p. 33; Viola, *Scavi*, pl. 1; Niccolini, *Case*, vol. 3, “*Topografia*,” pl. 10 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1874
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 25, no. 34. Fiorelli, Desc., pp. 452-453. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 33. (worldcat) Viola, “Scavi” p. 16.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 04 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.v.2</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_v/house_2/i.v.2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2020 15:25:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_v/house_2/i.v.2/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula V
House House 2
Garden I.v.2
Keywords  archaeological garden kitchen gardens peristyles (columnades) pomerium  Garden Description B. The south half of the insula was also excavated in 1873-74. It was accessed from the back door in the peristyle garden of the tannery by descending six steps. This was a large open area (b) that had been cleared of previous structures. Formerly there had been five doors in the south wall leading to the pomerium but these were closed up. This area could have been used as a kitchen garden as suggested by Tatiana Warscher or for drying leather as suggested by Viola.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula v, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 8, p. 33; Viola, *Scavi*, pl. 1; Niccolini, *Case*, vol. 3, “*Topografia*,” pl. 10 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1873-1874
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Desc., p. 452. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 33. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), p. 275. Niccolini, Case, vol. 4, “Nuovi scavi, 1874-1882,” p. 2. Sogliano, GiorSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), cols. 10, 49, excavation finished in 1874. Viola, “Scavi” p. 15. Warscher, “Codex.&amp;rdquo;  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 03 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Officina Coriarioum of M. Vesonius Primus (I.v.2)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_v/house_2/officina_coriarioum_of_m._vesonius_primus/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 18:12:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_v/house_2/officina_coriarioum_of_m._vesonius_primus/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula V
House House 2
Garden Officina Coriarioum of M. Vesonius Primus (I.v.2)
Keywords  archaeological garden mosaics (visual works) opus signinum peristyles (Roman courtyards) pillars porticoes tables (support furniture) triclinia  Garden Description A. This tannery was excavated in 1873-1874. The peristyle courtyard had a portico to the north and east supported by brick pillars which had been most likely been built when the original house was converted to a tannery. Against the west wall there was a masonry triclinium (l.medius 4.99 m.; l.summus and l.imus 4.96 m.; table, 1.78 x 0.93 m.). The top of the triclinium table held the famous mosaic of a skull (0.45 x 0.50 m. Mus. Naz. inv. no. 109 982;; Reusch no. 163). The mosaic representing the Epicurian philosophy features a large skull over a butterfly on a wheel representing the soul and time. On either side of the skull are the possessions of both the rich and poor with a plumb line hanging over the skull indicating the equalizing power of death.The northeastern part of the courtyard was a rectangle, the north side of which was formed by the three first intercolumniations counting from the northeast corner of the north portico, and the east side by the first two intercolumniations counting from the same corner. This area was paved with opus signinum. The little area around the triclinium between the paved area and the west wall was believed to be a garden according to Mau.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula v, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 8, p. 33; Viola, *Scavi*, pl. 1; Niccolini, *Case*, vol. 3, “*Topografia*,” pl. 10 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1873-1874
Bibliography  Brendel, “Untersuchungen zur Allegorie des pompejanischen Totenkopfmosaiks,” RM (1934), pp 157-179. Fiorelli, Desc., p. 452. (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), col. 93. Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, fig. 268 on p. 181 and p. 198. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 33. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 272-275. Mau-Kelsey, pp. 398-399. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 48 (mosaic). Niccolini, Case, vol. 4, “Nuovi scavi, 1874-1882,” p. 1. Sogliano, GiorSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), cols. 9-10 and pl. 2. Soprano, p. 294, no. 3. Viola, “Scavi” p. 15. Warscher, “Codex,” photo no. 32.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 03 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.iv.22</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iv/house_22/i.iv.22/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 15:24:28 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iv/house_22/i.iv.22/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula IV
House House 22
Garden I.iv.22
Keywords  archaeological garden atriums triclinia viridarium  Garden Description Directly to the rear of the atrium, a small viridarium (a) with a paved space (1.70 x2.50 m.) behind it suggested use as a summer triclinium to Fiorelli. Soprano was certain that there was an outdoor triclinium of wood or other material located here.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iv, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 7, p. 29; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12; Niccolini, *Case*, vol.3, “*Topografia*,” pl.8 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 69. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., p. 68.(worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 32. (worldcat) Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 80. Soprano, p. 307, no. 29.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 02 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Caupona of Copious (I.iv.11)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iv/house_11/caupona_of_copious/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 15:14:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iv/house_11/caupona_of_copious/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula IV
House House 11
Garden Caupona of Copious (I.iv.11)
Keywords  archaeological garden altars (religious fixtures) lararia latrines  Garden Description This modest caupona had a garden (a) at the rear that was raised one step higher than the rest of the building. It once had a masonry altar with a lararium painting above but both of these have been lost. A latrine was located at the southeast corner of the garden (Fig. 3).
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iv, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 7, p. 29; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12; Niccolini, *Case*, vol.3, “*Topografia*,” pl.8 (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I.iv.11; 20.18.66, S.A.Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 25, no. 31 (incorrectly calls the garden a room). Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 68. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., p. 66.(worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, 1:171. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 32. (worldcat) Schefold, WändP, p. 17 (also calls the garden a room).  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 02 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.iv.9</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iv/house_9/i.iv.9/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 14:45:28 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iv/house_9/i.iv.9/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula IV
House House 9
Garden I.iv.9
Keywords  archaeological garden cisterns (plumbing components) lararia tablina viridarium  Garden Description This garden contains a cistern opening and form the entrance a viridarium (a) at the rear of the tablinium and a niche lararium are clearly visible (Fig. 3).
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iv, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 7, p. 29; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12; Niccolini, *Case*, vol.3, “*Topografia*,” pl.8 (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I.iv.9; 44.28.61, S.A.Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 24, no. 30. Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 68. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., p. 66.(worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 34. (worldcat) Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 79.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 02 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.iv.5/25 C</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iv/houses_5&#43;25/i.iv.5&#43;25_c/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 14:06:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iv/houses_5&#43;25/i.iv.5&#43;25_c/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula IV
House House 5/25
Garden I.iv.5/25 C
Keywords  archaeological garden columns (architectural elements) exedrae (site elements) gutters (building drainage components) peristyles (columnades) porticoes puteal triclinia vestibules  Garden Description C. The north peristyle garden (f) belonged originally to a house whose entrance was on the Via dell’Abbondanza. It was accessed by a flight of steps from the central peristyle which lies about two meters below. A portico surrounded this garden on the south, east, and most of the north sides. Between the two middle columns on the east side there was a travertine puteal. A large exedra (g) proceeded by a vestibule offered a view of the garden from the west, as did the triclinium (h) from the east. The columns were made of brick and Sarno sandstone and faced with stucco, just like the ones in the central peristyle. They were unfluted except the ones opposite the entrances to the large excedra, the triclinium, and the atrium to the north. A gutter surrounded the garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iv, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 7, p. 29; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12; Niccolini, *Case*, vol.3, “*Topografia*,” pl.8 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates Bibliography  Breton, p. 481. Dwyer, Pomp. Sculpture, pp. 82, 83, 107-108. (worldcat) Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 67.(worldcat) “Giornale dei Soprastanti,” Feb 12-13, 1863. Idem, Desc., pp. 64-65. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 33-32. (worldcat) Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen,” p. 79. Overbeck-Mau, pp. 364-366.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 02 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.iv.5/25 B</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iv/houses_5&#43;25/i.iv.5&#43;25_b/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 14:06:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iv/houses_5&#43;25/i.iv.5&#43;25_b/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula IV
House House 5/25
Garden I.iv.5/25 B
Keywords  altars (religious fixtures) archaeological garden columns (architectural elements) gutters (building drainage components) lychnophoros oeci peristyles (columnades) porticoes puteal statues  Garden Description B. The center peristyle was separated from the south peristyle (d) by a long wall that had six windows and two doors. These offered a grand view into the southern peristyle. In an earlier period this peristyle must have been considered the most important component for each of the six windows corresponded to an intercolumniation in the southern peristyle. The twenty portico columns were fluted above, plain below, and faced with stucco over brick and Sarno limestone. The northeast corner had a portico with a marble puteal. This garden was bounded by a gutter and in this peristyle there was a white marble altar (0.255 high; Mus. Naz. inv. no. 110022). The middle peristyle was supposedly where the famous bronze statue of Apollo playing a cithara (1.58 m. high with base; Mus. Naz. inv. no. 5630; Reusch no. 831) was found on November 8, 1853. It probably came from the southeast corner of the southern peristyle for the middle peristyle was not excavated until five years after the Apollo was found. Niccolini (Case, vol.3, “L’arte” p. 8) was the first to mistakenly report the location where the bronze was discovered. Maiuri thought that the Apollo may have been adapted as a lychnophoros. Several smaller rooms looked out over the garden as well as a large oecus (e) on the east.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iv, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 7, p. 29; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12; Niccolini, *Case*, vol.3, “*Topografia*,” pl.8 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1848, 1853
Bibliography  Baset, p. 492. Brun, BdI (1863), p. 92-93. Döhl, p. 2. Dwyer, Pomp. Sculpture, pp. 79-81, 83-84, 88-89. (worldcat) Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 66.(worldcat) “Giornale dei Soprastanti,” April 7, 1859; 658-688. Idem, Desc., p. 62. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, 1:21-22 and fig. 28 on p. 21. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 31. (worldcat) Lugebil, BdI (1861), p. 261. MB, vol. 15, pl. 33. Maiuri, BdA, n.s. (1926), p. 350. Minervini, BullArchNap, n.s., 2 (Nov. 8, 1853):65. Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “L’arte,” pl. 5. Overbeck-Mau, pp. 363, 544-545. PAH, 2:583 (Nov 8, 1853). 586-587 (Dec. 5, 1853). 670 (Nov. 18, 1868). 671-673 (Nov. 3-Dec. 13, 1858). 685-688 (Sept. 14-Nov.30, 1859). Pernice, p. 30 and pl. 19.4.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 02 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Citharist; Casa Del Citarista; House of L. Popidius Secundus Agustianus and L. Popidus Ampliatus (I.iv.5/25)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iv/houses_5&#43;25/house_of_the_citharist/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 13:04:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iv/houses_5&#43;25/house_of_the_citharist/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula IV
House House 5/25
Garden House of the Citharist; Casa Del Citarista; House of L. Popidius Secundus Agustianus and L. Popidus Ampliatus (I.iv.5/25)
Keywords  archaeological garden architraves (entablature) basins (vessels) columns (architectural elements) cisterns (plumbing components) fountains gutters (building drainage components) herms oscilla peltae piscinae porticoes predellas puteal statues statuettes (free-standing sculpture) tondi waterspouts  Garden Description A. Excavation took place at this large house intermittently from 1853 to 1869. There were three large parallel, adjacent gardens. A portico, supported by seventeen stuccoed columns made of brick and Sarno limestone, enclosed the center garden (a). The columns were red, fluted at the top and plain at the bottom. A gutter went around the perimeter of the garden. A semicircular basin was located at the west end of the garden around which six spectacular bronze animals were discovered in 1861. The bronzes were as follows: a boar with a fountain spouting from its mouth (0.56 m. high; Mus. Naz. inv. no. 4900); two dogs (0.51 and 0.25 m. high; for boar and dogs); a leaping stag with no trace of fountain fittings (0.61 high; Mus. Naz. inv. no. 4902; Reusch no. 823); a lion with an open mouth, possibly for a fountain, which originally stood on his hind legs (039m. high; Mus. Naz. inv. no. 4897; Reusch no. 820); a serpent with a spout in its mouth (0,51 high; Mus. Naz. inv. no. 4898; Reusch no. 822). The Museo Nazionale was said to have preserve the original placements of the statues. After careful study of this Dwyer concluded that the boar would have stood on the projecting spur of the fountain basin with the dogs attacking his from either side of the rim. The leaping lion would have been next to them and the serpent to their right. The stag would have stood on the rim of the basin at the extreme left. The entire group could have been seen from the large room (b) opening off the west portico, which was lacking one column to facilitate the view. (Eschebach incorrectly included this column on his plan.) Two double herms, each representing Bacchus and Ariadne, were found at the edge of the basin. Dwyer was not able to locate these. There eleven marble oscilla, six circular ones (tondi) (Mus. Naz. inv. nos. 6551, 6642, 6646, 6652, formerly 6667 but now at Pompeii, inv. no. 20486, one with inv. no. unknown). Five had the shape of a pelta (Mus. Naz. inv. no. 6660, 6661, 6664, 6665, formerly 6658 but now at Pompeii, inv. no. 20489). These white marble oscillae each had an iron hook at the top, but no rod, which indicates that were suspended from the architrave between the columns by a cord. Dwyer suggests that the peltae were probably alternated with the round shields. One oscillum had a maenad on one side; the rest had a faun or satyr on each side. A large rectangular pool (3.50 m. wide x 10.80 m. long; 1.40 m. deep) was excavated in February 1926 by Maruri. Two high steps (0.45 m. and 0.40 m.) descended into the pool on the west side. A much smaller semicircular pool had been built around these steps and into the larger pool which had been filled with rubble (Fig. 4). This was probably built after the earthquake when the entrance on the Via dell’Abbondanza was joined to the house. The cistern opening in the southwest corner of the garden had a lave puteal, but the one in the east portico had no puteal. To the northeast of garden (a) there was a large room (c) which contained garden representations painted on the black predella under both of the side panels on the south wall. These were recorded by Spinazzola in drawings (Fig. 4). Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iv, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 7, p. 29; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12; Niccolini, *Case*, vol.3, “*Topografia*,” pl.8 (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I.iv.5,25; 20.4.66, S.A.Jashemski (Rights Statement).     Fig. 4: I.iv.5; 64.25.57, S.A.Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1853-1869, 1926
Bibliography  Baset, p. 26.  Breton, pp. 489-490. Brun, BdI (1863), p. 91. Döhl, pp. 2-3. Dwyer, “Ocilla”, pp. 261-264, nos. 1-11. Elia, MonPittAnt, sec. 3, Pompei, fasc. 1 (1937), p. 4 and fig. 3.  Fiorelli, GiornSc (1861), pp.387, 388, 392-394, 397, 399-400. Fiorelli, Scavi, pp.66-67 and pl. 165, nn. 182-183. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., p. 62. (worldcat) Idem, Pomp. Sculpture,pp. 80-83, 89-97. Jashemski, Gardens, 1:21-22 and figs. 28 and 29 on pp. 21, 22. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, pp. 29–30. (worldcat) Idem, Gardens, vol.II, p. 394. (worldcat) Kapossy, pp. 48, 51, 52. Lugebil, BdI (1861), p. 240. Maiuri, NSc (1931), pp. 575-576. Mau-Kelsey, fig. 181 (plan) on p. 352. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p .79 and pl. 14. Overbeck-Mau, pp. 359-361 and fig. 179 (plan) on p. 360. PPP, 1:10.  PAH, 2: 685-688 (Sept. 17–Nov. 30, 1859). Pernice, p.14 and pl. 8.2. Schefold, WändP, p. 15.  Spinazzola, Scavi nuovi, figs. 646, 647 on p. 654, n. 336. (worldcat) Van Buren, MAAR 10 (1932) pls. I, 2. Ward-Perkins and Claridge, no. 83.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 02 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.iv.2</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iv/house_2/i.iv.2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2020 13:10:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iv/house_2/i.iv.2/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula IV
House House 2
Garden I.iv.2
Keywords  archaeological garden cisterns (plumbing components) engaged columns peristyles (columnades) porticoes tablina triclinia  Garden Description This peristyle garden (a) had two entrances on the west and the south. It was located at the rear of the tablinium and had a portico on the west and south enclosed by a low wall and supported by columns. At the west entrance there was a cistern. A large window that looked out into the garden located in the triclinium (b) was framed by two engaged columns (Fig. 3).
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iv, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 7, p. 29; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12; Niccolini, *Case*, vol.3, “*Topografia*,” pl.8 (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I.iv.2; 18.7.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 65. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., p. 60.(worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 29. (worldcat) Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 79.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 01 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.iii.30</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_30/i.iii.30/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jul 2020 14:58:21 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_30/i.iii.30/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 30
Garden I.iii.30
Keywords  amorini archaeological garden bas-reliefs (sculpture) busts (sculpture) lararia peristyles (columnades) porticoes  Garden Description This small house, excavated in 1872, had no atrium and the peristyle garden (a) was to the right of the north end of the entrance passageway. A portico enclosed the garden on the west, north, and part of the south sides. Part of the portico had been closed to make rooms. Paintings of amorini decorated the peristyle with two little busts that may have been portraits of the owners. A lararium painting and an arched niche were located in the west wall of the peristyle. A small marble column with bas-relief of foliage most likely served as garden decoration.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1872
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 24, no. 29. Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 75. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., p. 60.(worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 2 (1870-1873), col. 462. Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 28. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 185-186. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 49. Warscher, “Codex.”  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 30 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.iii.25 B</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_25/i.iii.25_b/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 17:22:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_25/i.iii.25_b/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 25
Garden I.iii.25 B
Keywords  peristyles (columnades) viridarium  Garden Description The viridarium (b) lay across the entire width of the house to the rear. The west (rear) of the peristyle garden (a) was completely open to the viridarium.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 75. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., p. 58.(worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 28. (worldcat) Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 78. Trendelenberg, BdI(1871), p. 172. Warscher, “Codex.”  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 29 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.iii.25 A</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_25/i.iii.25_a/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 17:22:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_25/i.iii.25_a/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 25
Garden I.iii.25 A
Keywords  archaeological garden peristyles (columnades) porticoes statues statuettes (free-standing sculpture) triclinia  Garden Description This house had an irregular plan and a small peristyle garden (a) enclosed on three sides by a low masonry wall. The wall was topped by four stuccoed brick columns which supported the portico. The excavation in 1869-72 showed that restoration was in progress at the time of the eruption. Inside the triclinium a small marble head of Bacchus from a herm (Mus. Naz. inv. no. 110 653) was found as well as a small marble ram (Mus. Naz. inv. no. 120 357), both probably garden decorations.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1869-1872
Bibliography  Dohl, p. 1. Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 74. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., p. 57.(worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 2 (1870-1873), col. 461. Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 28. (worldcat) Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 78. Trendelenberg, BdI(1871), p. 172.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 29 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Capella (I.iii.24)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_24/house_of_capella/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 15:31:46 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_24/house_of_capella/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 24
Garden House of Capella (I.iii.24)
Keywords  archaeological garden lararia mural paintings (visual works) peristyles (columnades) porticoes triclinia  Garden Description At the rear of the house, excavated in 1868, there was a peristyle garden (a) with a portico supported by three brick columns on the east and north sides. The south wall had a lararium painting and a crude animal painting on one corner of the south garden wall. This had been executed in the manner of a topiary painting according to the excavators, who reported a lion consuming a deer, below which there was a dog pouncing on a hare. A good view of the garden was obtained through the triclinium (b) on the north.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1868
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 24, no. 261. Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 74, p. 150, no. 456 . (worldcat) Idem, Desc., pp. 56-57.(worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 28. (worldcat) Idem, Gardens, vol.II, p. 313. (worldcat) Matz, BdI (1869), pp. 239-240. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 78. Schefold, WändP, p. 13 . Sogliano, “Pitture,” p. 225, no. 705.  Warscher, “Codex,” photo no. 54.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 29 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Actius Anicetus (I.iii.23)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_23/house_of_actius_anicetus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 12:55:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_23/house_of_actius_anicetus/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 23
Garden I.iii.20/22
Keywords  archaeological garden cisterns (plumbing components) gutters (building drainage components) mural paintings (visual works) peristyles (columnades) porticoes puteal  Garden Description This site was excavated in 1868 revealing a peristyle garden (a) at the rear of the house. A portico on the east and north side was supported by five columns connected by a low wall. There was an opening to the garden on the north. The middle of the garden had two cistern puteals. The west wall of the garden held the famous painting depicting the battle between the Nucerians and the Pompeians in the ampitheator (1.60 m. high by a little less than 2.00 m. wide; Mus. Naz. Inv. No. 112 222; Ruesch no. 1344). This event was recorded by Tacitus (Annals 14.17). A gutter went along the east, south, and north edges of the garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1868
Bibliography  DePetra, GiornSc, n.s., 1 (1865-1869), cols. 185-187 (where the address is given as I.ii). Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 74 and pp. 145-146, no. 401. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., pp. 52-53.(worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 27. (worldcat) Matz, BdI (1869), pp. 240-241. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 78. Niccolini, Case, vol. 4, “Supplemento,” p1. 32. Maiuri, NSc (1939), pp. 168-169. Schefold, WändP, p.12. Sogliano, “Pitture,” p. 204, no.604. Warscher, “Codex.” photos nos. 44-50.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 29 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.iii.20/22</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/houses_20&#43;22/i.iii.20&#43;22/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 13:25:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/houses_20&#43;22/i.iii.20&#43;22/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 20/22
Garden I.iii.20/22
Keywords  altars (religious fixtures) archaeological garden doliums gutters (building drainage components) peristyles (columnades) puteal triclinia  Garden Description At the rear of this house there was a garden (a) with a passageway on the north and the west. The garden had a gutter along the east, north, and west edges. Embedded in the garden were four large dolia. A large triclinium (b) on the east side had a window that looked out into the garden. Fiorelli surmised that the remains of one couch of a masonry triclinium in the west passageway indicated the possible presence of a room that had been destroyed by the earthquake. There was also a small altar on the right side of the peristyle and a terra-cotta puteal in the passageway.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 24, no. 25. Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 73. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., p. 54.(worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 27. (worldcat) Matz, BdI (1869), p. 242. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 78. Soprano, p. 308, no. 36. Warscher, “Codex.”  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 28 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.iii.3</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_3/i.iii.3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 13:03:42 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_3/i.iii.3/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 3
Garden I.iii.3
Keywords  alleys (streets) archaeological garden exedrae (site elements) gutters (building drainage components) hearths lararia peristyles (columnades) pilasters porticoes puteal tufa  Garden Description The front of this house excavated in 1869 had an unusual design in that it was set back some distance from the street. The peristyle garden was entered at the end of the entranceway at the rear of a long angiprotus (alleyway). Rooms of the house were located at the right and rear of the garden. The peristyle had undergone various changes and was supported on the east and north by tall tufa columns. The portico roof on the west was supported by two low brick columns and two pilasters surmounted by arches. A low wall enclosed the garden, joining the columns either side of the entrance between the two columns to the west. A terra-cotta puteal was adjacent to the west wall along with a hearth covered with a small vault decorated with a rough, bearded head supposed to be Vulcan. A large window on the south wall gave a view from the exedra (b) into the garden. The east peristyle wall contained a lararium niche and a gutter ran along the north, east, and west edges of the garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1869
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 24, no. 22. Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 72. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., pp. 52-53.(worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 1 (1868-69), cols. 300-301. Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 26. (worldcat) Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 78. Pernice, p. 34. Warscher, “Codex.” photos nos. 16-21.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 28 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Epidius Fortunatus (I.iii.3)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_3/house_of_epidius_fortunatus_i.iii.3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 19:24:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_3/house_of_epidius_fortunatus_i.iii.3/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 3
Garden House of Epidius Fortunatus (I.iii.3)
Keywords  archaeological garden aqueducts basins (vessels) gutters (building drainage components) peristyles (columnades) podiums (building divisions) porticoes puteal tablina tufa  Garden Description On the right of the tablinum were ten steps that led to the peristyle garden (a). A portico enclosed the garden on the west, north and east sides. This was supported by ten columns and two engaged columns which were stuccoed brick painted red. The north, east, and west edges of the garden had a gutter. There were two cistern openings, according to Mau, one located in the northeast corner of the garden with a tufa puteal and the other in the corresponding corner of the portico. Water emptied at the northeast corner from the gutter into the cistern and into the street at the southeast and southwest corners. An aqueduct pipe came out of the first column, (counting from the south, on the west portico), and ran between the gutter and the portico. The pipe rose, supported from the second column on the west side, to spurt a jet of water in the gutter. Flanking the west and the north porticos, it disappeared going to the northwest. On the west side it was possible in two places to let water flow into the gutter by a widening of the pipe. The gutter had openings to the gardens at these two points to serve as watering outlets. There were keys before and after the widen pipe sections to control the flow of water. Two branches of this pipe entered a room (b) off the northwest corner of the peristyle where there was a basin.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2 : Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Scavi, pp. 70-71. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., pp.50-51.(worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 26. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 181-182. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 77. Pernice, p. 14. Warscher, “Codex.” photos nos. 4, 6-10a.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 27 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa Della Grata Metallica; Casa Dell’Atrio Tetra-Stilo (I.ii.28)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_28/casa_della_grata_metallica_i.ii.28/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 15:01:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_28/casa_della_grata_metallica_i.ii.28/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 28
Garden Casa Della Grata Metallica; Casa Dell’Atrio Tetra-Stilo (I.ii.28)
Keywords  altars (religious fixtures) archaeological garden cisterns (plumbing components) peristyles (columnades) podiums (building divisions) porticoes tables (support furniture) tablina triclinia tufa  Garden Description At the rear of the house there was a peristyle garden (a) with a portico along the east side and part of the south. The excavation took place in 1873-74. A low wall joined three stuccoed brick columns and two engaged ones which supported the portico. There was an entrance to the garden on the south side opposite the door from the tablinium (b) and another on the east opposite the kitchen door (c), which was closed later according to Mau. The columns were white above the height of the wall and red below. Water was carried to the cistern by a wide gutter on the south and east edges of the garden, and Mau found some evidence of aqueduct water. There was a masonry triclinium (l.medius, 5.30 m.; l.imus, 3.85 m.; l.summus, 2.70 m.) with a circular table (dia. of support, 0.70 m. ) built against the west wall. Inside of each couch there were four niches (0.19 m. wide). The last niche in the south couch was larger in size and separated from the other three by the mouth of the cistern. There was a small masonry podium on the north wall with steps for access. A round tufa altar was located opposite the lectus summus (Fig. 3).
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I.ii.28; 10.11.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation dates 1873-1874
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Descr., p. 48. (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), col. 60. Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 25. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 250-252. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 77. Soprano, p. 293, no. 2 and figs. 28.6 and 29. Viola, “Scavi” p. 14. (worldcat) Warscher, “Codex.” photo no. 54-57.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 27 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Caupona; Officina Libraria (I.ii.24)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_24/caupona_officina_libraria_i.ii.24/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 10:02:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_24/caupona_officina_libraria_i.ii.24/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 24
Garden Caupona; Officina Libraria (I.ii.24)
Keywords  aedicula lararium archaeological garden atriums cauponae flowerpots podiums (building divisions) porticoes tables (support furniture) triclinia  Garden Description The garden (a) east of the atrium had a portico extending along the south and part of the west sides. A low wall (0.52 m. high) connected the columns and an entrance to the garden was located on the west. In 1873 the caupona was excavated. The garden contained a masonry triclinium (l.medius, 3.85 m.; l.summus and l.imus, 3.20 m.) with a table. The badly damaged triclinium revealed the amphoras used in its construction. A low podium along the north wall was thought by Fiorelli to have held flower pots. Mau reported a drainage channel at the corner of the triclinium formed by the l.meduis and the l.summus, although it is no longer evident. The base of an aedicula lararium remains against the east wall opposite the north end of the east couch.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation dates 1873
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 23, no. 17. Fiorelli, Descr., p. 47. (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), col. 60. Jashemski, Gardens, 1:179. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 25. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), p. 245. Ibid., (1874), pp. 253-256, 262-263. Mau-Kelsey, p. 404. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 77. Soprano, pp. 292-293, no. 1. Viola, “Scavi” p. 13. (worldcat) Warscher, “Codex.” photo no. 32.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 27 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Caupona (I.ii.22)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_22/cauponai.ii.22/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 15:51:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_22/cauponai.ii.22/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 22
Garden House of L. Vousius Faustus and M. Vousius Faustus (I.ii.10)
Keywords  amphorae (storage vessels) archaeological garden cauponae inscription pillars porticoes  Garden Description This caupona was excavated in 1873 but the reports offer insufficient details to determine if the open area had been planted. The room was entered directly from the street and the open area (a), had a portico on the north and east supported by one pillar. Fifteen amphoras with inscriptions were uncovered here.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation dates 1873
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Descr., p. 46. (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), col. 47-48. Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 24. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), p. 263. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. Gen.,” p. 76. Viola, “Scavi” p. 13. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Caupona of Innulus (I.ii.20)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_20/caupona_of_innulus-i.ii.20/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 15:39:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_20/caupona_of_innulus-i.ii.20/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 20
Garden Caupona of Innulus (I.ii.20)
Keywords  archaeological garden cauponae biclinia lararia tables (support furniture)  Garden Description This small caupona had a garden (a) at the rear with a roofed passageway on the east and the south. It was excavated in 1873 and a masonry biclinium (l.medius, 2.65m.; l.imus 2.94 m.) with a round table (dia. 0.93 m.) was uncovered in the northwest corner and a niche lararium on the north garden wall.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation dates 1873
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 23, no. 13. Fiorelli, Descr., p. 45. (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), col. 47-48. Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 24. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), p. 264. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr.,&amp;rdquo; pg. 77. Soprano, p.305, no. 24. Viola, “Scavi” pp. 12-13. (worldcat) Warscher, “Codex.”  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.ii.17 B</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_17/i.ii.17_b/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2020 15:01:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_17/i.ii.17_b/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 17
Garden I.ii.17 B
Keywords  archaeological garden atriums mural paintings (visual works) peristyles (columnades) pillars porticoes statues statuettes (free-standing sculpture) tablina  Garden Description The peristyle garden to the east of the atrium was excavated in 1873. It had a portico on the north and west supported by two pillars, one at the northwest corner and the other in the middle of the north side. A gutter sloped towards the southeast corner as it went around the east, north, and west edges of the garden. A shrine-like structure was built against the east wall with the marble veneered façade above the level of the floor of the niche. The niche contained a marble statuette of Venus, her left arm supported by a statuette (1.04 m. high; Mus Naz. inv. no. 109 608; Ruesch no. 1325). The wall behind the statue was painted to represent blue drapery and the ceiling had a shell-like fluting. Two small marble statuettes of toads (Mus. Nac. inv. no. 109 609, 109 610) found in the garden and probably the one of two doves (Mus. Naz. inv. no. 120 407) found in the tablinum decorated the flowerbeds. There was also a marble head of a man identified as Agrippa, found cemented in a cup (total height 0.285 m.; Mus. Nac. inv. no. 109 611; Reusch no. 1081). The marble statuette of Hercules wrapped in a lion skin (0.70 m. high; Mus. Nac. inv. no. 109 677) found in the atrium was probably a garden decoration. The large room on the north had a fine view of the garden and the east and south walls of the garden were decorated with garden paintings. These were separated by narrow panels with a painting of a candelabrum, according to Mau, and each painting featured a fence with an amphora upon it. Behind this there was a thicket with birds. On either side of the amphora there was an ibis, and a pheasant in the center. Fiorelli mentioned observing animals in the paintings. Jashemski notes that no trace of the paintings remained when she examined the site, and further, she has never seen a pheasant represented in any garden paintings. Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation dates 1873
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 22, no. 10. de Franciscis, Ritratto, p. 25 and figs. 10-11. (worldcat) Döhl, p.1. Dwyer, Pomp. Sculpture, pp. 124, 12. (worldcat) Fiorelli, Descr., p. 44. (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), cols. 46-47, 48, 55. Grimal, p. 445, no. 1.  Jashemski, Gardens, 1::124-125. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, pp. 23-24. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 313. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 233-235. Ibid. (1874), pp. 265-266. Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 265-266.  Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 76. Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “L’arte,” p. 6 and pl. 14 (Venus). Schefold, WandP, p. 10. (worldcat)  Sogliano, “Pitture,” p. 223, no. 691. (worldcat)  Sogliano, “Scavi,” p. 310. (worldcat) Viola, “Scavi” pp. 12 and 76, no. 1, p.77, nos. 5, 12, p.79, nos. 45, 46. (worldcat) Warscher, “Codex,” photo no. 32.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.ii.17 A</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_17/i.ii.17_a/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2020 15:00:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_17/i.ii.17_a/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 17
Garden I.ii.17 A
Keywords  archaeological garden mural paintings (visual works) piscinae tablina  Garden Description At the rear of the house was a very small garden entered from the tablinum. Excavated in 1872, much of the garden was occupied by two small raised pools, according to Mau. (Fig. 3) Attached to the west wall was a masonry pool 0.58 m. deep on the inside and 0.73 m. high on the outside. The other pool was to the south and there was a garden painting on the rear wall.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, *Scavi*, pl. 1; Niccolini, *Case*, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I.ii.17; 10.13.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation dates 1872
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Descr., p. 44. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 23. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 264-265. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. Gen.,” p. 76. Viola, “Scavi” p. 12. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 25 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.ii.16</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_16/i.ii.16/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2020 14:27:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_16/i.ii.16/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 16
Garden I.ii.16
Keywords  aedicula lararium archaeological garden fountains pillars podiums (building divisions) porticoes puteal statues statuettes (free-standing sculpture)  Garden Description This house was excavated in 1873. The entranceway led directly to the portico which enclosed the garden on the north and east. In the northwest corner of the portico a masonry aedicula lararium formed an arched niche on top of a solid podium. A low wall connected the columns and pillars of the portico. There was an entrance to the garden on the east side and a gutter along the east and north edges of the garden. A terra-cotta statuette of a seated old man holding a scroll in his right hand and wearing a short sleeved tunic (0.60 m. high; Mus. Naz. Inv. No. 109 622; Ruesh no. 453) served as a fountain. This statue has been variously identified, but most likely was the Greek philosopher Antisthenes (ca. 445-360), a devoted follower of Socrates. A terra-cotta puteal was also found in the garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation dates 1873
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 22, no. 6. Curtius, &amp;ldquo;Miszellen zur Geschichte des greichischen Porträts,” RM (1944), p. 38. Dohl, p. 1. Dwyer, Pomp. Sculpture, p. 128. (worldcat) Fiorelli, Descr., p. 42. (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), col. 46, 177-179 and pl. 6. Ippel, AA (1939), pp 367-368. Jashemski, Gardens, 1:48. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 22-23. (worldcat) Kapossy, p. 47. Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “L’arte,” pl. 12. Pernice p. 34. Richter, Greek Portraits 3, pp. 33-34, fig. 133. (worldcat) Idem, Portraits of the Greeks, 2:181 and fig. no. 105. (worldcat) Viola, “Scavi” p. 12 and p. 79, no. 1. (worldcat) Von Rohden, pp. 21, 44-45 and pl. 32. Warscher, “Codex.”  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 25 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.ii.15</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_15/i.ii.15/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2020 14:20:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_15/i.ii.15/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 15
Garden I.ii.15
Keywords  archaeological garden impluvia  Garden Description This humble house was excavated in 1873. It had no garden but the impluvium was surrounded by a low masonry wall. The top contained a planting bed which served as a small garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1873
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Descr., p. 42. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 22. (worldcat) Viola, “Scavi” p. 12. (worldcat) Warscher, “Codex.”  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 25 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of L. Vousius Faustus and M. Vousius Faustus (I.ii.10)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_10/house_of_l._vousius_faustus_and_m._volusius_faustus-i.ii.10/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2020 18:18:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_10/house_of_l._vousius_faustus_and_m._volusius_faustus-i.ii.10/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 10
Garden House of L. Vousius Faustus and M. Vousius Faustus (I.ii.10)
Keywords  aedicules archaeological garden biclinia drains lararia mural paintings (visual works) piscinae triclinia  Garden Description The garden at the rear of the house, excavated in 1873, is almost totally destroyed. According to Mau, most of the garden was occupied by a large pool (5.40 X 2.90 m.) which was sloped toward the west from where it drained into the street through a pipe. The pool was surrounded by a low wall about 0.55 m. high leaving only a narrow space between the pool and the walls. In the northwest corner were the two beds of a masonry biclinium which sloped toward the wall, as was customary. Rainwater falling on them was carried away by a terra-cotta drain which emptied into the pool. A square niche under the north couch provided a storage space. On the wall above this couch was a rectangular niche lararium with a roughly made aedicula facade (Fig. 3, 2.19.72). At the east end of this couch was a masonry table. Fiorelli reports a planting bed attached to the rear (east) wall. There was a view from the triclinium through the large window in the east wall, across the pool to the garden painting on the rear wall.
Garden Painting
When this garden was excavated in 1873, the excavators reported three panels on the east wall with garden paintings. The center panel had a body of water with swimming fish with assorted animals in the background that included a grazing deer and a springing leopard. The two panels on either side each had a large crater-shaped fountain surrounded by thick growth. Large red flowers and yellow apples could be identified to the left of each fountain and the right, pomegranates (Punica granatum L.). Jashemski examined this painting in 1964 to find it had been covered by a growth of ivy which had destroyed most of the painting. A section of a large pomegranate bush was all that was left intact at the time. She describes the leaves, painted in blue-green with darker shading and a few yellow leaves and the fruit, deep yellow with reddish-orange shading, as being rendered in an impressionistic manner. At the right of the entrance to the garden area was a cistern opening. Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I.ii.10; 2.19.72, S. A. Jashemski.   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1873
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 22, no. 6. Fiorelli, Descr., p. 42. (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), col. 57.  Jashemski, Gardens, 1:1 10-1 1 1. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 22. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 313. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 197-198. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. Gen.,” p. 76. Schefold, WandP, p. 9 (describes this painting as a paradeisos, with sea, deer, panther, and nymphaeum). (worldcat)  Sogliano, “Pitture,” p. 224, no. 694. (worldcat)  Soprano, p.305, no. 23. Viola, “Scavi” p. 11. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 24 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.ii.6</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_6/i.ii.6/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2020 12:44:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_6/i.ii.6/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 6
Garden I.ii.6
Keywords  archaeological garden atriums graffiti (casual notations) gutters (building drainage components) inscription peristyles (columnades) piscinae porticoes puteal  Garden Description The west portico of the small peristyle garden at the rear of the house was entered through two doors directly from the atrium. The garden was enclosed on four sides by a portico supported by eight stuccoed brick columns. On the foreside, the two first columns on the left had a larger intercolumniation corresponding to the wide opening opposite the atrium. Between these columns stood a terra-cotta puteal covered with white stucco. A gutter around the edges of the garden was shown in the plan. The round pool in the center of the garden no longer exists, and only stumps of the columns remain today. One of the graffiti on the walls of the portico noted that on November 17 Puteolana gave birth to three males and two females (XV K(alendas) NOV(embres) PVTEOLANA PEPERIT MASCL(os) III FEMEL[as] II) (CIL IV.3890). Perhaps they were either piglets or puppies. Pigs were more common in ancient cities than is commonly realized.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Descr., p. 39. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, 1: 104-105 (for the graffito). (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 21. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 199. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. Gen.,” p. 76. Pernice, p. 18. Viola, “Scavi,” p 11. (worldcat) Warscher, “Codex.”  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 24 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.ii.3</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_3/i.ii.3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2020 16:14:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_3/i.ii.3/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 3
Garden I.ii.3
Keywords  archaeological garden tufa vestibules viridarium  Garden Description The small viridarium (a) at the rear of the house had narrow, slightly raised beds along the walls on the north and east side. These beds were for the cultivation of flowers, according to Fiorelli. A small vestibule on the north side of the garden was decorated with remnants of tufa columns brought from another site.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Descr., p. 37. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 21. (worldcat) Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. Gen.,” p. 76. Viola, “Scavi,” p 10. (worldcat) Warscher, “Codex,” photo, no. 12.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 23 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>