<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>cistern on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/cistern/</link>
    <description>Recent content in cistern on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 17:25:51 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/cistern/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>II.i.7B/8-9</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_i.md/ii.i.7b-9/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 17:25:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_i.md/ii.i.7b-9/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region II
Insula Insula I
Keywords  tabernae amphorae (storage vessels)  Garden Vineyard with large masonry triclinium, treading floor and courtyard garden.
Garden Description A. The access to this garden featured an arched niche high on the garden wall located either side of the direct entrance from the street at entrance 8. A further entrance (7A) from the street was located on the east wall. The masonry triclinium (l. medius, 3.60 m.; l. imus 3.20 l. summus 2.43 m.) in the northwest corner had a round table (0.55 m. in dia.) between the couches and a rectangular table (0.65 x 1.03 m.) built against the north wall. A cistern opening was found to the south of the triclinium. To the left of entrance 8, a small room was excavated in 1985 to reveal a treading floor that allowed the juice from the grapes to flow into a small dolium. This indicates that the garden was most likely planted in vines.
B. Entrance 8 opened directly into a courtyard garden. A cistern opening in the northeast corner of the garden was fed by a gutter along the east edge. To the right of the door on the east wall was a small niche lararium with an aedicula façade. To the right of this niche, a painting of Hercules was displayed in a red border. Below this was a garden setting with an altar and a crested serpent painted in low stucco relief. In the interior area of this property, stairs leading to an upper floor and a hearth in a kitchen area were located. The stairs likely led to accommodation.
Bibliography W. F. Jashemski, 1993, Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius. Volume 2, Appendices, p.75. (worldcat) Halsted B. Van der Poel, Laurentino García y García, and Joan McConnell, 1986, Corpus topographicum Pompeianum Pars IIIA, p.40-41 (worldcat)
Pleiades ID 456321707
TGN ID 7004658
Excavation Dates 1939, 1953-1955, 1983
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250) Jessica Venner (https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5828-6222)
Publication date 19 February 2021</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa D’Argo</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/tiffany_fong/casa_dargo/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/tiffany_fong/casa_dargo/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Garden Casa D’Argo
##Jashemski Catalogue 533.II.2. 534.II.2.
Keywords  cisterns (plumbing components) triclinium peristyles porticoes gutters (building drainage components)  Garden Description 533.II.2. A. The earliest excavations of Herculaneum were done with underground tunnels. Several of these crossed this site and were discovered sixty three years later when further excavation of this patrician house was conducted in1828-1835. Eight brick columns and one engaged column stood on each of the long sides of the portico that bounded the large peristyle garden (a) on the east, north, and west sides. The north side was supported by four more columns and at the two front corners there was a pillar with an engaged column on each side. In the center of the north side two smaller pillars with one engaged column each framed a garden view from the triclinium. All the supporting members were coated with fine stucco. Gutters ringing the garden conveyed rain water to the cistern.
534.II.2. B. A second peristyle garden was located to the west of the first, but has only been partially excavated. It has stuccoed columns and pillars joined by a wall 0.4 m. high painted with plants and flowers.
Plans   Casa D’Argo   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1828-1835
Bibliography  A.C. BdI (1835),p. 130 (worldcat) Bonucci, BdI (1830), p.121 (worldcat) Bonucci, Le due Sicilie: Ercolano, fig. 11 (plan) and p. 37 (worldcat) Breton,Pompeia p. 519 (worldcat) Maiuri, Herculaneum, p. 24 (worldcat) Idem,Ercolano, pp. 367-368 and fig. 293 (plan) on p. 362 (worldcat) Niccolini,Real museo borbonico, vol. 7, fig. 59 (plan), description by Bechi, pp. 19-21 (worldcat)     Ruggiero, Ercolano, pp. 541-545 (contains the detailed reports of Bonucci)(worldcat)     -      Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa D’Argo</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tiffany_fong/casa_dargo/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tiffany_fong/casa_dargo/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Insula II
House 2
Garden Casa D’Argo
Keywords  cisterns (plumbing components) triclinium peristyles porticoes gutters (building drainage components)  Garden Description 533.II.2. A. The earliest excavations of Herculaneum were done with underground tunnels. Several of these crossed this site and were discovered sixty three years later when further excavation of this patrician house was conducted in1828-1835. Eight brick columns and one engaged column stood on each of the long sides of the portico that bounded the large peristyle garden (a) on the east, north, and west sides. The north side was supported by four more columns and at the two front corners there was a pillar with an engaged column on each side. In the center of the north side two smaller pillars with one engaged column each framed a garden view from the triclinium. All the supporting members were coated with fine stucco. Gutters ringing the garden conveyed rain water to the cistern.
534.II.2. B. A second peristyle garden was located to the west of the first, but has only been partially excavated. It has stuccoed columns and pillars joined by a wall 0.4 m. high painted with plants and flowers.
Plans   Plan of Casa D’Argo   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1828-1835
Bibliography -BdI (1835),p. 130 (worldcat) -BdI (1830), p.121 (worldcat)
 Bonucci, Le due Sicilie: Ercolano, fig. 11 (plan) and p. 37 (worldcat) Breton,Pompeia p. 519 (worldcat) Maiuri, Herculaneum, p. 24 (worldcat) Maiuri,Ercolano, pp. 367-368 and fig. 293 (plan) on p. 362 (worldcat) Niccolini,Real museo borbonico, vol. 7, fig. 59 (plan), description by Bechi, pp. 19-21 (worldcat)     Ruggiero, Ercolano, pp. 541-545 (contains the detailed reports of Bonucci)(worldcat)     -      Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
