<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/yuming_huang/gigthis/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 07:38:05 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/yuming_huang/gigthis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Suburban Villa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/yuming_huang/gigthis/suburban_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 07:38:05 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/yuming_huang/gigthis/suburban_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa proconsularis
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location Gigthis (Bou Ghara)
Gigthis (Pleiades)
Location Description The important site Gigthis (50ha) largely excavated in the beginning of the last century by Constans was located on the opposite side of the Jerba Island, on the Gulf of Bou Grara. The remains of Gigthis stretches out along the foothills going down the coast in a fertile region known for its olive groves.
Garden Suburban Villa
Keywords Garden Description On the other side of the fortified enceinte, one hundred and fifty kilometers south was a large building that belonged to an architect according to an inscription found near the peristyle. This huge suburban villa incompletely excavated, was laid out around two peristyles (Plan view, Fig. 1).
A large peristyle of twenty columns onto which rooms opened may have had a garden.
On the south of the peristyle was another courtyard with a portico of three columns on the east and west sides. The courtyard may have been planted.
Maps Plans Fig. 1: Plan of the villa
Images Dates unknown
Bibliography  L.A Constans, Gigthis, NouvArch ,1916, pp. 99-104. [(worldcat)]((/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/yuming_huang/gigthis/)  Pleiades ID 344380
TGN ID 5003665
Contributor Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X)
Publication date 1 Nov 2020
Related articles </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
