<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>tablinium on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/tablinium/</link>
    <description>Recent content in tablinium on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 17:12:19 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/tablinium/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>II.i.2 (House of Aemilius Primio and Aemiluis Saturninus)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_i.md/ii.i.2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 17:12:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_i.md/ii.i.2/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region II
Insula Insula I
Keywords  tabernae amphorae (storage vessels)  House House of Aemilius Primio and Aemiluis Saturninus
Garden Small garden to the rear of a [taberna] (http://www.getty.edu/vow/AATFullDisplay?find=tabernae&amp;amp;logic=AND&amp;amp;note=&amp;amp;english=N&amp;amp;prev_page=1&amp;amp;subjectid=300005366)
Garden Description Behind the shop, living quarters were located, including a garden to the rear. The west garden wall was topped with the broken amphorae; this wall was shared with the rear open area in I.i.1.
Bibliography W. F. Jashemski, 1993, Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the villas destroyed by Vesuvius. Volume 2, Appendices, p.75. (worldcat)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa del Salone Nero (VI.13/11)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/insula_vi/house_13/casa_del_salone_nero/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/insula_vi/house_13/casa_del_salone_nero/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Insula Insula VI
House House 13
Garden Casa del Salone Nero
Keywords  porticos tablinium  Garden Description Excavation of this garden (a) to the rear of this elegant house took place in the spring of 1939. The garden was completely surround by a portico which had eight columns and two pillars on the north side with engaged columns placed strategically so as to provide an unimpeded view from the tablinium. The southwest corner of the garden was the location of a small pool (0.82 x 0.63).
Plans   Plan of the new excavations of Herculaneum (Maiuri, Herculaneum)     Herculaneum VI.11-19,25-26-Casa del Salone Nero   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography Maiuri, Ercolano, p. 240 and fig. 187 (plan) on p. 239 (worldcat)
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 20 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa del Bicentenario</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tiffany_fong2/casa_del_bicentenario/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tiffany_fong2/casa_del_bicentenario/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Insula V
House 15-16
Garden Casa del Bicentenario
Keywords  [portico] [tablinium] [dolium] [puteal]   Garden Description 551.V.15-16. Two hundred years after the first excavation efforts started at Herculaneum in 1738, this house was excavated and the restoration finished, thereby receiving its name. A passageway with windows bordered the garden (a) on the west and a portico with seven columns joined by a low wall stood on the east and north of this garden measuring 9.90 x 4.90 meters. A wide water channel encircled the garden on three sides and there were two entrances, one opposite the tablinium on the north and the other at the southeast corner of the garden. The neck of a large dolium formed the mouth of a well with a heavy masonry puteal located in the center of the garden
Plans   Plan of Casa A Graticcio   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1738
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 371 Maiuri, Herculaneum,p. 48; Maiuri, Ercolano, pp.51, 233 and fig. 174 (plan) on p. 222  -
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>