<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/winkel-seeb/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 10:34:59 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/winkel-seeb/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Winkel-Seeb</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/winkel-seeb/winkel-seeb_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 10:34:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/winkel-seeb/winkel-seeb_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Winkel-Seeb
Winkel-Seeb (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Winkel-Seeb
Keywords archaeological garden \
corridors
pergolas
porticoes
rural villas
terrace gardens
villae rusticae
well houses
Garden Description The residential and service parts of this villa rustica occupied an area of ca. 7 hectares. The lateral walls of the complex could be followed over a length of 395 meters, but it is assumed that they once extended up to the lake southeast of the farm. The house, measuring 56.70 x 82.40 meters, was of the winged corridor type (Fig. 12.1). The villa rustica was built in the first half of the 1st century A.C. and inhabited until its destruction in 250. The two protruding wings on either side of the entrance on the north extended to the dividing wall between the pars urbana and the pars rustica. These may have been built as covered porticoes or pergolas. The large terraced courtyard between them was possibly laid out as a garden or park (G in Fig. 1). Immediately north of the dividing wall was a well-house.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the rural villa with porticoes enclosing a possible garden (G) in front of the house. Plan adapted from Drack and Fellmann 1988, fig. 511. (Rights Statement)   Dates First half of 1st century A.C. - 250
Bibliography  W. Drack and R. Fellmann, Die Römer in der Schweiz, Stuttgart, 1988, pp. 550-555, figs. 511-512. (worldcat) Ch. Jacquat, Der römische Garten in Seeb, Zürich, 1988. (worldcat) W. Drack, Der römische Gutshof bei Seeb, Gem. Winkel. Berichte der Zürcher Denkmalpflege. Archäologische Monographien 8, Zürich, 1990. (worldcat) M. Carroll, Romans, Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 75, fig. 29. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 177667
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 20 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>