<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>House of the Arsenal (Maison de l’Arsenal) on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/house-of-the-arsenal-maison-de-larsenal/</link>
    <description>Recent content in House of the Arsenal (Maison de l’Arsenal) on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/house-of-the-arsenal-maison-de-larsenal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>House of the Arsenal (Maison de l’Arsenal)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/house-of-the-arsenal-maison-de-larsenal/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/house-of-the-arsenal-maison-de-larsenal/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location DIVODURUM MEDIOMATRICORUM (Metz, France)
DIVODURUM MEDIOMATRICORUM (Pleiades)
Sublocation Description In the valley of the Moselle, Divodurum Mediomatricorum, a former Gallic oppidum on the hill of Ste-Croix, became an urban center in the Augustan period. It had an amphitheater, an aqueduct, several baths, and a sewer network with a large collector.
Garden HHouse of the Arsenal (Maison de l’Arsenal)
Keywords  courtyard porticoes hypocausts  Garden Description A large house (40 x 40 m) of the second century covered the site of three adjacent buildings going back to the years 60-80 (Fig 1). It was built around a central courtyard [1] 18 meters on a side, bordered by porticos on the east, south, and west. The courtyard, doubtless treated as a garden, had a rectangular pool that has been partially excavated. On the axis of the pool, on the north side and seemingly opening directly onto the courtyard was a large, 60-square-meter room [2] heated by hypocausts.
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Ph. Brunella, D. Meckenbenner, Cl. Lefebvre, P. Thion, Metz, cinq années de recherches archéologiques 1982-1987, Dalph, Gumra, 1990, p.33-36, fig.36. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108927
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
