<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>terrace gardens on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/terrace-gardens/</link>
    <description>Recent content in terrace gardens on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 11:47:11 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/terrace-gardens/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Hummetroth</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/hummetroth/hummetroth_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 11:47:11 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/hummetroth/hummetroth_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Hummetroth
Hummetroth (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Hummetroth
Keywords apsed triclinium
bathhouses (water recreation structures)
corridors
hypocausts
porticoes
reception rooms
rural villas
terrace gardens
villae rusticae
Garden Description The enclosed farmyard, including the residential area (pars urbana) and the service zone with outbuildings and working areas (pars rustica), covered an area of 3.5 hectares. The house of this villa rustica of the 2nd century is of the winged corridor type with two protruding wings framing a large courtyard in front of the house at the south (Fig. 1).
The courtyard was divided into two zones by a terrace(?) wall, and in both zones a garden has been reconstructed (G in Fig. 1). Entering the house from the south, one passed through a large reception room to an apsed triclinium with hypocaust heating. A bath complex lay to the southwest, entered by the portico next to the garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the rural villa with a large terraced courtyard garden (G) to the south. Plan adapted from Baatz and Herrmann 1989, fig. 303a.   Dates 2nd century
Bibliography  D. Baatz and F.-R. Herrmann, eds., Die Römer in Hessen, 2nd ed., Stuttgart,1989, pp. 360-361, fig. 303a-b. (worldcat) M. Carroll, Romans,Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 74, fig. 29. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981525
TGN ID 7165467
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 16 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House in Insula 1 and 2 in Augusta Raurica</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ausgusta_raurica/augusta_raurica_house_in_insula_1_and_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 17:34:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ausgusta_raurica/augusta_raurica_house_in_insula_1_and_2/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Augusta Raurica
Augusta Raurica (Pleiades)
Location Description The town on the Rhine River possessed colonial status since the late 1st century BC. The street grid, as well as many public and residential buildings, are well known from excavations.
Garden House in Insula 1 and 2 in Augusta Raurica
Keywords archaeological garden \
insulae
peristyles (Roman courtyards)
porticoes
terrace gardens
Garden Description This house, built on sloping terrain on the northern edge of the city around AD 150, was enlarged twenty years later to incorporate at least two certain gardens (Fig. 1). It bordered north and south on streets and was flanked on the east and west by other houses. In this last phase after ca. 170, the house covered an area of about 2000 square meters. In the center of the building was an irregular peristyle courtyard, at the north end of which was a private bath complex.
East of the house was a long rectangular area open to the sky and divided into plots by a wall. In the northernmost plot a layer of humic soil 20-40 centimeters thick was excavated that the excavators interpret as evidence for a garden (G on plan).
The northern part of the house facing the street included an open terrace which may have been built up on demolished walls of the earlier house. Humus-rich soil in the terrace area may indicate that it was planted (G in Fig. 1). Immediately south of the terrace was a portico that offered a splendid view of the valley.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Augusta Raurica., House in insula 1 and 2. Adapted from Hufschidt.(Rights statement)   Images Dates House: AD 150 - ca. 170
Bibliography  P.-A. Schwarz, „Die Nordmauer und die Überreste der Innenbebauung der spätrömischen Befestigung auf Kastelen in Augusta Rauricorum. Vorbericht über die Grabung 1991.51,“ Jahresberichte aus Augst und Kaiseraugst 13, 1992: 47-76. (worldcat) T. Hufschmid, Kastelen 3. Die jüngeren Steinbauten in den Insulae 1 und 2 von Augusta Raurica. Forschungen in Augst 23, Augst, 1996. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 177494
TGN ID 7017586
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 14 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Sudeley/Spoonley Wood</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/sudeley/sudeley_spoonley_wood_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 18:57:34 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/sudeley/sudeley_spoonley_wood_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Sudeley/Spoonley Wood
Sudeley/Spoonley Wood (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Sudeley/Spoonley Wood
Keywords archaeological garden
axial plan \
terrace gardens
rural villas
villae rusticae
Garden Description The main residence of this rural estate in Gloucestershire, excavated in 1882, is of the winged corridor type (Fig. 1). From the north and south corners of the house, walls ran in a westerly direction to enclose an open courtyard (G in Fig. 1) approximately 65 meters wide and 45 meters deep from the outer boundary to the main entrance of the house. A paved path was axially arranged in the courtyard to connect the entrance to the courtyard with that of the residential building. The western third of the courtyard is marked off by low scarps which may be remains of garden terraces (T in Fig. 1). Finds from the site indicate a 3rd/4th century date for the complex.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the villa with a path (stippled) leading through a courtyard garden (G) and garden. (Rights statement)   Images Dates 3rd/4th century for the complex.
Excavation Dates 1882
Bibliography  Ancient and Historical Monuments in the County of Gloucester Vol. 1. Royal Commission on Historical Monuments of England, London, 1976, pp. 113-114, fig. on p. 114. (worldcat) C. Taylor, The Archaeology of Gardens. Shire Archaeology Series 30, Aylesbury, 1983, pp. 30-31, fig. 1. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 79693
TGN ID 7030316
Contributor Maureen Carroll
ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>