<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/taron-sadirac-villenave_pyr%C3%A9n%C3%A9es-atlantiques/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:07:01 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/taron-sadirac-villenave_pyr%C3%A9n%C3%A9es-atlantiques/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa de Taron, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/taron-sadirac-villenave_pyr%C3%A9n%C3%A9es-atlantiques/gallia_aquitania_villa_de_taron_j.zhou/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:07:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/taron-sadirac-villenave_pyr%C3%A9n%C3%A9es-atlantiques/gallia_aquitania_villa_de_taron_j.zhou/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_Aquitania Gallia_Aquitania (Pleiades)
Province Description A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location Taron-Sadirac-Viellenave, Pyrénées-Atlantiques
Taron-Sadirac-Viellenave, Pyrénées-Atlantiques (Pleiades)
House Villa de Taron
House Description Vestiges of this villa in the valley of the Petit Lées are found in an area of some 2.5 hectares around the Romanesque church built over the southern part of the villa. It sat upon a terrace with a gentle slope towards the east. The church kept the same orientation as the villa under it, which is almost exactly true north-south and east-west. The remains of the villa were noted in the eighteenth century. Excavations conducted in 1995-96 by Ph. Vergain were able to ascertain an original construction in the first century.
Garden Keywords  mosaics (visual works) peristyles (columnades)  Garden Description According to Vergain, a remodeling in the third century created the peristyle which may have been planted as a garden. Four phases have been detected for late antiquity; the mosaic decorations come from the last.
Plans   Fig. 1: Taron. Plan R. Monturet, IRAA, Pau, according to Vergain et al. 1997, 154, fig. 3.     Fig. 2: Plan of the Villa de Taron (cat. n° 61).   Dates 18 Century CE
Excavation Dates 1995CE-1996CE
Bibliography  Philippe Vergain, &amp;ldquo;Taron&amp;rdquo; Bilan scientifique de la region Aquitaine 1995, Ministère de la culture Direction du patrimoine Sous-direction de l&amp;rsquo;archéologie 1996, p 115-116. Note：(worldcat) G. Fabre, CAG, 64, 1994, p. 88-89, n°108. (worldcat) Catherine Balmelle, Les demeures aristocratiques d&amp;rsquo;Aquitaine, societe et culture de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquite tardive dans le sou-ouest de la Gaule, Ausonius, supple. d&amp;rsquo;Aquitania 10, Bordeaux 2001, p. 420-421, plan p.449. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 249923
TGN ID Contributor Clopper Almon
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>