<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gallia Lugdunensis on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/categories/gallia-lugdunensis/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Gallia Lugdunensis on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/categories/gallia-lugdunensis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Vaise - House with the Xenia</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/vaise-house_with_the_xenia/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/vaise-house_with_the_xenia/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location LUGDUNUM (Lyon, France)
LUGDUNUM (Pleiades)
Garden House with Pilasters (Clos du Verbe Incarné)
Keywords  domus porticoes courtyard drain  Garden Description Xenia were gifts of game, fish, poultry, fruits or vegetables given by a host to a guest to be cooked to the guest’s liking. Here, the name comes from the discovery of a pinax (a painted ceramic tablet) showing xenia. This house was discovered during excavation of the southern sector of the Saint-Pierre land management zone (ZAC) in a suburban quarter of Lyon. The building –one hesitates whether to call it a suburban villa or a domus–extends over 630 square meters. There are traces of occupation of the site in Augustan times, but the house (29 x 24 m) was built in the reign of Tiberius. It is organized in two perpendicular wings around a courtyard with porticos in a U. The galleries are 3.5 meters wide. In this first phase, nine rooms were placed around the court.
The limit of the court on the west is not certain [phase II, 1]. As a hypothesis, an original court of 17.74 meters by 16.40 meters –nearly square but with an extra, sixth, span on the west –has been proposed. The columns, with a maximum diameter of 37 centimeters, were made of semi-circular bricks cemented and covered with white plaster. They rested on limestone bases roughly squared off. A little later, around the end of the reign of Claudius, the house underwent several changes. Room [10] was built, which enlarged the eastern wing. A new room [3] was created, important enough in the eyes of the proprietor to sacrifice part of one of the porticos to fit it in. In the same period, the spaces between the columns were partly closed, while the courtyard was connected to a water supply network. The paintings were freshened up, and the house doubtless had a second floor. In this last phase, however, the house did not last long. It was destroyed at the beginning of the reign of Vespasian, and the site then remained vacant at least until the middle of the fourth century and probably into the fifth. In this final, Claudian phase, the courtyard represented more than 57 percent of the area. It enjoyed running water, which was not present in the houses of the Verbe incarnéquarter in Lugdunumat the same period. A wooden pipe, of which only the negative imprint can be seen, crossed the courtyard and porticos obliquely. A drain from room [5] was connected to it. The basin of a fountain that has disappeared was placed on the axis of room [9]; it was definitely there in the second phase and possibly in the first, though that has not been demonstrated.
The ground of the central part of the courtyard was topsoil and earth coming from under the porticos. Three samples have been studied palynolocially. The results leave no doubt that a garden grew in the center. We quote the abstract of the publication. “The pollen content is relatively poor, and the counts have been made for each sample separately. The spectrum of pollens includes a rather wide diversity of herbaceous plants of which certain families can include ornamental plants such as the tubuliflorous composites and the Caryophyllaceae (pink family). Ruderal plants, that is, those that grow in sites much transformed by man such as clearings or waste places near habitations, predominate: Chenopodiaceae (such as spinach, beets and their relatives –Tr.), gramineous plants, and the following genera: nettles, arnois (artemesia, tarragon –Tr.), and plantain (Plantago lanceolata). This last is often associated with the cultivation of cereals. There were also species of ferns. Walnuts (Juglans) and grapes (Vitis) may have been cultivated around the site. Finally, pine (Pinus) is relatively well represented, but the very high rate of pollenization of the pine and its capacity for dispersion of its pollens often lead to an over-representation of these species. Thus, this courtyard could have been cultivated as an ornamental garden.” (E. Delaval et al., p. 89).
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  E. Delaval, C. Bellon, J. Chastel, E. Plassot, L. Tranoy, Vaise, un quartier de Lyon antique, Document d’archéologie en Rhône-Alpes n° 5, Lyon, 1995. E. Plassot, Le quartier Saint-Pierre, la maison aux xenia, p. 71-129. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 167717
TGN ID 6003548
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 04 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Masks (Maison aux Masques)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/house_of_the_masks_maison_aux_masques/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/house_of_the_masks_maison_aux_masques/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location LUGDUNUM (Lyon, France)
LUGDUNUM (Pleiades)
Garden House of the Masks (Maison aux Masques)
Keywords  peristyle opus stigninumboth porticoes stylobate plynth pilasters  Garden Description The two known wings of the house were organized around a peristyle (8x 12 m), probably in a U, though the west wall has not been found but has been drawn on the accompanying plan by extension of wall further south. Two of the three galleries were open. The open area of the peristyle court was ornamented by a rectangular pool (5.4 x 2.6 m) covered with opus signinumboth inside and outside; it had a drain in the northeast corner. The surface of the water in the pool would have been above the level of pounded earth floor of the courtyard. Porticoes 2.8 meters wide around three sides of the courtyard also had pounded earth floors; the stylobate was blocks of limestone while the columns were of circular brick covered with plaster painted red in the lower part, white in the upper, and touched with green highlights. The porticoes were terminated at the west end by engaged columns. The painted plaster is preserved in place in the southwest corner of the peristyle. A red plinth sets off tuffs of green foliage; above are black panels bordered with decorative strings. At a later phase, a wall was built between the last two columns of the of the portico; in the space thus created were found bases for shelves. Near the peristyle were found little theatrical masks in terra cotta which had served as oscilla. An ostrich egg, an exotic import, was perhaps also hung in the peristyle. Onto the south portico opened a reception room [B 20] (8.6 x 6.2 m) rhythmically divided by four pilasters and two columns. Onto the east portico opened an even larger room [B 12] (10.5 x 6.5 m). Both reception rooms had concrete floors with limestone accents. There were also two small courtyards &amp;ndash;one in the south wing, one in the east &amp;ndash;both indicated on the plan.
Maps Not Available
Plans Not Available
Images   perspective drawing of porticoes   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  A. Desbat, Les fouilles de la rue des Farges à Lyon, Groupe lyonnais de recherche en archéologie gallo-romaine, Lyon, 1984, p. 45-49 (worldcat) A. Desbat, Jadis, rue des Farges, archéologie d’un quartier de Lyon antique, exposition au Musée de la Civilisation Gallo-Romaine de Lyon, 1985. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 167717
TGN ID 6003548
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 16 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House with Pilasters (Clos du Verbe Incarné)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/house-with-pilasters-clos-du-verbe-incarne%CC%81/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/house-with-pilasters-clos-du-verbe-incarne%CC%81/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location LUGDUNUM (Lyon, France)
LUGDUNUM (Pleiades)
Garden House with Pilasters (Clos du Verbe Incarné)
Keywords  insula / insulae atrium Domus  Garden Description The insula VII of the Clos du Verbe Incarné, excavated from 1977 to 1987, lies on the western slope of a little dip (71 x 34 m) in the upper town, about 160 meters northwest of the center of the top of the theater. In this insula, begun between 40 and 20 BC, one can follow the evolution of this quarter up to the end of the third century. To the north, the insula was bordered by the street called du Capitol and to the west by the street called de Cybèle. The subdivision of the insula was put in place from 15–10 BC. The house occupied 400 square meters, and was organized on an italic plan around a traditional atrium followed by a tablinum[1]. The house of seven or eight rooms did not have a peristyle but did, no doubt, include a hortus[2] (15 x 5 m) at the back of the lot.
The house was originally constructed of adobe on a floor and gutter of granite masonry. Later, in Tibero-Claudian times, a wooden section was added, which facilitated the creation of an upper story on the western part, which also included on the ground level some isolated shops occupying 100 square meters. The neighbor to the north was another small, 315-square-meter house, the Domus with the Mosaic Emblema, which was organized around a four-column atrium, but had no garden. In fact, the House with Pilasters was the only one in the insula to have, without doubt, a little green space. In the southern part of the insula, there were three combinations of house and shop, and another small, 310-square-meter house called the Domus with Lararium.
LUG 1. 1. House with Pilasters. On the rectangle surrounding the word &amp;ldquo;Garden?&amp;rdquo; in the upper left corner is the &amp;ldquo;House with Pilasters.&amp;rdquo; Source, Maison 1996, p.134.
Plans   LUG 1. 1. House with Pilasters. On the rectangle surrounding the word &amp;#34;Garden?&amp;#34; in the upper left corner is the &amp;#34;House with Pilasters.&amp;#34; Source, Maison 1996, p.134.   Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  E. Delaval, “Un îlot d’habitations romaines à Lyon (Ier siècle av.-IIIe siècle ap.J.C.),Clos du Verbe Incarné,colline de Fourvière,” Actes du Ier Congrès Méditerranéen d’ethnologie historique, Lisbonne 4-8 nov. 1991,in Mediterraneo, 4, 1994, p.203-229. E. Delaval,“Espace urbain et habitat privé à Lyon,un îlot de la ville haute au cœur d’une opération d’urbanisme au milieu du Ier siècle,” in Maison 1996, t.I,p. 128-37, planp.134.  Pleiades ID 167717
TGN ID 6002234
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 15 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>