<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/conimbriga/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/conimbriga/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>House of the Cantaber</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/conimbriga/lusitania_house-of-the-cantaber_xw/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/conimbriga/lusitania_house-of-the-cantaber_xw/</guid>
      <description>Province Lusitania Lusitania (Pleiades)
Province Description Despite the prior existence of urban centers like Metellinum, the capital of Lusitania was a new foundation, the Colonia Augusta Emerita (Mérida), which would also serve as the capital of one of the smaller juridical units (conventus) and would be the scene of flourishing activity in the succeeding centuries, its prosperity lasting until the late Roman and Visigothic era. Subsequently, a series of well-known Roman cities were built in what was then Lusitania but is now partly in Portugal and partly in Spain. As well as the capital, there were Conimbriga, Salmantica, Evora, Olisipo (now Lisbon), Pax Iulia (now Beja), and Metallium Viscascense (Aljustrel), this last recognized as the capital of an important mining area. The series of wealthy villae, such as that of La Cocosa, Milreu or San Cucufate are particularly noteworthy. Another of the important elements of the Roman era is the series of still visible ways of communication, of which the Vía de la Plata has most remaining, especially in the sections of Baños de Montemayor in Cáceres or the bridges that cross the rivers, such as that of San Pedro de Alcántara, or of Mérida.
Location Conimbriga
Conimbriga (Pleiades)
Location Description The pre-Roman oppidum of Conimbriga was made the capital of a civitas in the Augustan period and, thereafter, a forum, a public bath-house, an aqueduct and city walls were constructed. During the Flavian period, the city was made a municipium with ius Latii. At the end of the third or beginning of the fourth century AD, new fortification walls considerably reduced the area occupied by the city. In the time of the Suevi it was an Episcopal See, which was then transferred to Aeminium (the present day Coimbra) around A. D. 585, when the kingdom of the Suevi was conquered by the Visigoths. Further reduced in area and impoverished, the city survived until 986, at which date, according to Arab sources, it was destroyed by the great Muslim chief Almansor. In addition to the Augustan forum, which was completely rebuilt on a new ground plan under the Flavians, four bath houses have been excavated, and preliminary trial trenches established the plan of the amphitheater. Four domus have been excavated, three of which were left outside the wall built under the late empire. It is in these houses, all built around peristyles, that we find the gardens of Conimbriga.
Garden House of the Cantaber
Keywords  statuettes (free-standing sculpture) peristyles (columnades)  Garden Description Hidacio, bishop of Chaves and a chronicler of his age, records that the Suevi sacked Conimbriga in 465 and 468 A.D. and that in the second year “the most noble Cantaber” was killed and his family sold into slavery. This house is by far the finest inside the city walls, so it is reasonably guessed to be that of Cantaber. It is larger than the House of the Fountains with an area of more than 3,300 square meters. The garden is similar, although it is less elaborate, has slightly different proportions, and has no fountains. Although the house underwent structural alterations, the peristyle is part of the original plan, which does not appear to date from much later than the Flavian era.
Originally, a large area at the south end was a garden occupying nearly a third of the area of the house. It was later sacrificed to become baths, so it is tinted slightly green on the plan in Figure 1.
The large dimensions of this house required further open spaces for light and air. Two of these had flower beds, although on a much smaller scale.
South of the central peristyle was a large room that centered on the garden, and on the east side of it a large doorway opened open on a large pool with eight columns around the eastern half of the pool. Along the sides were masonry planters projecting a foot or so into the pool. They must certainly have been filled with earth where plants or flowers must have been grown. The boxes covered in pink mortar are clearly visible in the foreground in Figure 3. Traces of plinths in the spaces between the columns suggest that there may have been small statuettes there.
The other garden area was slightly farther south and against the east wall of the house. A portico ran around three sides but required only three columns, all on the west side. The rectangular pool (6.5 x2.5 m) had three basically square flower beds aligned in it. The two end squares, however, had semicircular niches cut out of the center of each side, while the center square had a circle cut out of its center and connected to the surrounding water. As in the House of the Fountains, flower beds in the pool appeared like islands in a lake (Fig. 4). One can imagine that this secluded spot was a favorite of the most noble Cantaber.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: House of Cantaber. Adapted from Hipólito Correia.   Images   Fig. 2: Main peristyle.     Fig. 3: Pool with pink planters.     Fig. 4: Secluded, three-column portico. Photo S.A.J. 1969.   Pleiades ID 236443
Publication date 20 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Fountains</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/conimbriga/lusitania_house-of-the-fountains_xw/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/conimbriga/lusitania_house-of-the-fountains_xw/</guid>
      <description>Province Lusitania Lusitania (Pleiades)
Province Description Despite the prior existence of urban centers like Metellinum, the capital of Lusitania was a new foundation, the Colonia Augusta Emerita (Mérida), which would also serve as the capital of one of the smaller juridical units (conventus) and would be the scene of flourishing activity in the succeeding centuries, its prosperity lasting until the late Roman and Visigothic era. Subsequently, a series of well-known Roman cities were built in what was then Lusitania but is now partly in Portugal and partly in Spain. As well as the capital, there were Conimbriga, Salmantica, Evora, Olisipo (now Lisbon), Pax Iulia (now Beja), and Metallium Viscascense (Aljustrel), this last recognized as the capital of an important mining area. The series of wealthy villae, such as that of La Cocosa, Milreu or San Cucufate are particularly noteworthy. Another of the important elements of the Roman era is the series of still visible ways of communication, of which the Vía de la Plata has most remaining, especially in the sections of Baños de Montemayor in Cáceres or the bridges that cross the rivers, such as that of San Pedro de Alcántara, or of Mérida.
Location Conimbriga
Conimbriga (Pleiades)
Location Description The pre-Roman oppidum of Conimbriga was made the capital of a civitas in the Augustan period and, thereafter, a forum, a public bath-house, an aqueduct and city walls were constructed. During the Flavian period, the city was made a municipium with ius Latii. At the end of the third or beginning of the fourth century AD, new fortification walls considerably reduced the area occupied by the city. In the time of the Suevi it was an Episcopal See, which was then transferred to Aeminium (the present day Coimbra) around A. D. 585, when the kingdom of the Suevi was conquered by the Visigoths. Further reduced in area and impoverished, the city survived until 986, at which date, according to Arab sources, it was destroyed by the great Muslim chief Almansor. In addition to the Augustan forum, which was completely rebuilt on a new ground plan under the Flavians, four bath houses have been excavated, and preliminary trial trenches established the plan of the amphitheater. Four domus have been excavated, three of which were left outside the wall built under the late empire. It is in these houses, all built around peristyles, that we find the gardens of Conimbriga.
Garden House of the Fountains
Keywords  mosaics (visual works) peristyles (columnades)  Garden Description This house is almost entirely excavated, the exception being its north facade, which is still covered by a local lane. It occupies an area of almost 3400 square meters. Its mosaics, published in their entirety, date from the second half of the second century A.D, or the Severan era. The construction of the house dates to between 150 and 175 AD. The house has a central peristyle with twenty-six columns. The area of the large open part (12m x 26m) is completely filled with a pool with a maximum depth of 0.90 meters, inside of which the architect installed six very formal flower-beds. On the edges of these, more than 500 water-jets played continually. The unusual design of this peristyle has its only parallel in the Domus Augustana built in Rome for the emperor Domitian by the architect Rabirius. This parallel, pointed out by L. Cremain 1959 in his L’architettura, has been related by other writers, none of whom has found anything similar in Roman domestic architecture in any part of the Empire.
The house has recently been the subject of a monograph by Isabelle Morand in which she undertakes to recover the geometrical and numerical principles used by the architect and to identify astronomical and astrological allusions in the house.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the House of the Fountains. Adapted from I. Morand.   Images   Fig. 2: Photo of the House of the Fountain in 2007 with the new roof.   Bibliography  Morand, I., La Maison aux jets d&amp;rsquo;eau de Conimbriga (Boccard, Paris, 2005). (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 236443
TGN ID 7031751
Publication date 20 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Skeletons</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/conimbriga/lusitania_house-of-skeletons_xw/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/conimbriga/lusitania_house-of-skeletons_xw/</guid>
      <description>Province Lusitania Lusitania (Pleiades)
Province Description Despite the prior existence of urban centers like Metellinum, the capital of Lusitania was a new foundation, the Colonia Augusta Emerita (Mérida), which would also serve as the capital of one of the smaller juridical units (conventus) and would be the scene of flourishing activity in the succeeding centuries, its prosperity lasting until the late Roman and Visigothic era. Subsequently, a series of well-known Roman cities were built in what was then Lusitania but is now partly in Portugal and partly in Spain. As well as the capital, there were Conimbriga, Salmantica, Evora, Olisipo (now Lisbon), Pax Iulia (now Beja), and Metallium Viscascense (Aljustrel), this last recognized as the capital of an important mining area. The series of wealthy villae, such as that of La Cocosa, Milreu or San Cucufate are particularly noteworthy. Another of the important elements of the Roman era is the series of still visible ways of communication, of which the Vía de la Plata has most remaining, especially in the sections of Baños de Montemayor in Cáceres or the bridges that cross the rivers, such as that of San Pedro de Alcántara, or of Mérida.
Location Conimbriga
Conimbriga (Pleiades)
Location Description The pre-Roman oppidum of Conimbriga was made the capital of a civitas in the Augustan period and, thereafter, a forum, a public bath-house, an aqueduct and city walls were constructed. During the Flavian period, the city was made a municipium with ius Latii. At the end of the third or beginning of the fourth century AD, new fortification walls considerably reduced the area occupied by the city. In the time of the Suevi it was an Episcopal See, which was then transferred to Aeminium (the present day Coimbra) around A. D. 585, when the kingdom of the Suevi was conquered by the Visigoths. Further reduced in area and impoverished, the city survived until 986, at which date, according to Arab sources, it was destroyed by the great Muslim chief Almansor. In addition to the Augustan forum, which was completely rebuilt on a new ground plan under the Flavians, four bath houses have been excavated, and preliminary trial trenches established the plan of the amphitheater. Four domus have been excavated, three of which were left outside the wall built under the late empire. It is in these houses, all built around peristyles, that we find the gardens of Conimbriga.
Garden House of the Skeletons
Keywords  mosaics (visual works) peristyles (Roman courtyards) axial plan  Garden Description The peristyle garden of the fourth domus follows a different pattern. In contrast to the House of the Swastika Mosaic, this house is very squarely centered on the garden. The axis of the entrance bisects the garden and the triclinium on the other side. A shallow rill with a small exedra on this axis winds around the peristyle, leaving a cultivated rectangle in the center. In front of the triclinium there is a square pool, also shallow, lined with slabs of limestone and set into the cultivated area but not joined to the rill.
The large mosaic of the bedroom (Fig. 1, C) was restored in the 1950&amp;rsquo;s; but even originally it was in relatively good condition. Elsewhere in the house, however, there are only a few patches of mosaic owing to the area have been used as a necropolis in the late empire, a use that gave the house the name by which it is now called.
The houses were excavated around 1940, at a time when there was no thought of recovering micro-remains from the soil of the flower-beds, which could have allowed the identification of the vegetal species present in these gardens. There is therefore no evidence as to what was planted. There is also no mention of sculptural elements, which may or may not have been present.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the House of the Skeletons.   Images   Fig. 2: Photo of peristyle at the House of the Skeleton.     Fig. 3: Photo showing the relation of the garden to other rooms of house.   Bibliography  J. Alarcão and R. Etienne, “Les jardins a Conimbriga (Portugal)” in Ancient Roman Gardens, Dumbarton Oaks Colloquium on the History of Landscape Architecture,no. 7. 1979, E. B. MacDougall and W. F. Jashemski eds. Washington, D. C., 1981, pp. 67-80. (worldcat) V. Hipólito Carreia, Conimbriga, Guide to the Ruins, Instituto Portugués de Museus, 2006. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 236443
Publication date 20 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Swastika Mosaic</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/conimbriga/lusitania_house-of-swastika-mosaic_xw/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/lusitania/conimbriga/lusitania_house-of-swastika-mosaic_xw/</guid>
      <description>Province Lusitania Lusitania (Pleiades)
Province Description Despite the prior existence of urban centers like Metellinum, the capital of Lusitania was a new foundation, the Colonia Augusta Emerita (Mérida), which would also serve as the capital of one of the smaller juridical units (conventus) and would be the scene of flourishing activity in the succeeding centuries, its prosperity lasting until the late Roman and Visigothic era. Subsequently, a series of well-known Roman cities were built in what was then Lusitania but is now partly in Portugal and partly in Spain. As well as the capital, there were Conimbriga, Salmantica, Evora, Olisipo (now Lisbon), Pax Iulia (now Beja), and Metallium Viscascense (Aljustrel), this last recognized as the capital of an important mining area. The series of wealthy villae, such as that of La Cocosa, Milreu or San Cucufate are particularly noteworthy. Another of the important elements of the Roman era is the series of still visible ways of communication, of which the Vía de la Plata has most remaining, especially in the sections of Baños de Montemayor in Cáceres or the bridges that cross the rivers, such as that of San Pedro de Alcántara, or of Mérida.
Location Conimbriga
Conimbriga (Pleiades)
Location Description The pre-Roman oppidum of Conimbriga was made the capital of a civitas in the Augustan period and, thereafter, a forum, a public bath-house, an aqueduct and city walls were constructed. During the Flavian period, the city was made a municipium with ius Latii. At the end of the third or beginning of the fourth century AD, new fortification walls considerably reduced the area occupied by the city. In the time of the Suevi it was an Episcopal See, which was then transferred to Aeminium (the present day Coimbra) around A. D. 585, when the kingdom of the Suevi was conquered by the Visigoths. Further reduced in area and impoverished, the city survived until 986, at which date, according to Arab sources, it was destroyed by the great Muslim chief Almansor. In addition to the Augustan forum, which was completely rebuilt on a new ground plan under the Flavians, four bath houses have been excavated, and preliminary trial trenches established the plan of the amphitheater. Four domus have been excavated, three of which were left outside the wall built under the late empire. It is in these houses, all built around peristyles, that we find the gardens of Conimbriga.
Garden House of the Swastika Mosaic
Keywords  mosaics (visual works)  Garden Description Far more modest than the House of Cantaber but following the same general ideas of garden design, this house was left outside the new city wall built during the late empire. The mosaics, now in excellent condition after modern restoration, can be dated to the mid third century A.D., but the house is the result of several successive transformations. Presumably that history explains why the main room with the mosaic with many swastikas is not aligned with the axis of the garden, though two of its three doorways offered views of it.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: House of Swastika Mosaic.   Images   Fig. 2: Looking west over swastika mosaic to garden.   Pleiades ID 236443
Publication date 20 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
