<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>pollen on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/pollen/</link>
    <description>Recent content in pollen on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 00:10:10 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/pollen/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa del Larario Fiorito (II.ix.4)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_ix/casa_del_larario_fiorito/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_ix/casa_del_larario_fiorito/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region II
Insula Insula IX
Keywords  [ambulatione] triclinia charcoal] pollen  Garden Description Excavated in the later 1980s, (Fig. 76) this property features a garden, described by Ciarallo as “laid out in eight ground strips bordered by furrows.” She interprets this layout as a plant nursery, also taking into account that the root cavities throughout were small, 4-8 c. in diameter, with two larger cavities of 20 and 40 cm. The larger cavities flank the axis that divides the garden in half. (Fig. 77) Gardens excavated recently shed light on the layout, which might, alternatively, be seen to comprise two slightly wider beds and two narrow ones that run alongside ambulationes, providing a modest strolling garden adjacent to the triclinium. Elsewhere, gardens of the time of the eruption freatured a variety of plants along these rows that would have been observed and presumably admired by the stroller, either for their exotic origin or for skill in creating new varieties of unusual shapes of familiar plants. The team made 160 casts in this garden. Pollen and charcoal were also collected and indicate the presence of grape (Vitis), hazelnut (Corylus), Prunus, Oak (Quercus), and beech (Fagus). Beech and Oak are also seen in the pollen samples. Tree roots were interpreted as pine (Pinus) and olive (Olea).
Plans   Fig. 75, Plan of Region II, insula ix   Need Fig. 76
Images Need Fig. 77
Pleiades ID 456321707
TGN ID 7004658
Excavation Dates later 1980s
Bibliography  Ciarallo, Le problematiche botaniche dell’area archeologica Vesuviana, in M. Mastroroberto,ed. Archeologia e Botania: Atto del convegno di studi sul contributo della botanica alla conoscenza e alla conservazione delle aree archeologiche vesuviane, Pompei 7-9 aprile 1989, L&amp;rsquo;Erma di Bretschneider, 1990, 17-32. (worldcat)  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 10 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>