<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>court on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/court/</link>
    <description>Recent content in court on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/court/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>House with Aquatic Décor</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-with-aquatic-de%CC%81cor_y.sun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-with-aquatic-de%CC%81cor_y.sun/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania (Pleiades)
Location AUGUSTORITUM - Limoges
Augustoritum (Pleiades)
Location Description The earliest traces of settlement in this area are at the oppidum of Villejoubert 25 kilometers east of the city. The Roman settlement of Limoges proper dates from about 15-10 B.C. and was named Augustoritum (Augustus’s ford) in honor of the emperor. It covered some 65 to 100 hectares and was laid out in a regular rectangular grid. The ancient wall dates from the end of the third century. The town took water from several sources, including the aqueduct of Aigoulène; there were drains for waste water disposal. There were several public fountains and baths, a theater, an arena, and temples. The city declined in the fourth century. Its Roman name was replaced by the Celtic name of the local people; and its regular street pattern, almost totally lost.
Garden House with Aquatic Décor
Keywords  court planting  Garden Description Discovered during excavation of Boulevard Gambetta, this house, in its original stage, had a central room with a painted décor of dolphins and aquatic motifs. In a second stage, towards the middle of the second century, this room [1] was transformed into a light well. It was a court open to the sky, though somewhat protected by the projection of a roof. One band of the former floor was kept; all the rest was covered by hauled-in earth, perhaps for planting. In the northwest corner of the court were found two vats for crushing lime.
Dates The second stage towards the middle of the second century.
Bibliography  J.P. Loustaud. Limoges antique, Travaux d’Archéologie Limousine, supplément 5, 2000, p. 211, plan p. 211. (with a bibliography of earlier works) (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 138203
TGN ID 7030318 7008410
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>