<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>House on rue de la Fraternité on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/house-on-rue-de-la-fraternit%C3%A9/</link>
    <description>Recent content in House on rue de la Fraternité on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/house-on-rue-de-la-fraternit%C3%A9/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>House on rue de la Fraternité</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/house_on_rue_de_la_fraternite%CC%81/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/house_on_rue_de_la_fraternite%CC%81/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location NEMETACUM (Arras, France)
NEMETACUM (Pleiades)
Garden House on rue de la Fraternité
Keywords  mosiacs peristyles  Garden Description Excavated in 1875-79 in the eastern suburbs of the city by A. Ternick, this large house has been uncovered in a roughly elliptical area with axes of 40 and 20 meters. The chronology is uncertain. It was perhaps destroyed by a violent fire (of which there are traces elsewhere in the city) in the second century and not reconstructed. Some walls were decoratively painted; most floors were concrete, but there is some evidence of mosaics. The floor of room [5] (just below room [1] in the plan) had a large slab of black marble in the center in frame with smaller slabs in the corners. The southwest corner of a peristyle and 12 meters along the west side and 10 meters along the south side have been excavated. The galleries had concrete floors and slender Tuscan columns 20 centimeters in diameter and 1.2 meters apart. The walls were painted red. In the center of the peristyle court was a masonry construction considered as an “impluvium” at the time of excavation, but it was quite possibly a pool. If it were a pool, then the area was almost surely in a garden. The house had another interior open court and possible garden [17] of about 6 x 7 meters near a well [25].
Maps    Arras (Pas de Calais), France. Excavations on the House on rue de la Fraternité. 1875-1879.   Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Alain Jacques, Georges Jelski, “Arras antique, bilan et perspective” in Les villes de la Gaule Belgique au Haut-Empire, Actes du colloque tenu à Saint-Riquier (somme) le 22-23-24 octobre 1982, Revue achéologique de Picardie, p. 124-5. (worldcat) Delmaire et al., Le Nord-Pas- de-Calais, 62/1, CAG, p. 145-147, fig. 46, plan p. 145; H. Stern I, 1 p. 101-102.   Pleiades ID 109194
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>