<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/xue_xia/karthago/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 10:39:31 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/xue_xia/karthago/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>House of Dionysos</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/xue_xia/karthago/house-of-dionysos/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/xue_xia/karthago/house-of-dionysos/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa Proconsularis Africa proconsularis (Pleiades)
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location Karthago
Karthago (Pleiades)
Location Description Founded by Tyrians from Phoenicia, Carthage became the capital of a powerful empire that came into conflict with the expanding power of Rome. In 146 BC Carthage was completely destroyed and re-founded as a Roman colony by Augustus who completed Cesar’s initial project. Augustus expanded the new city and encouraged settlements of veterans and civilians. The kingdom of Numidia was transformed into a province and Carthage was raised to the rank of capital. The city not only became the major port through which the wealth of the province flowed to Rome but also became a cultural capital that introduced the African elite to the rest of the empire, making it one of the wealthiest and most cosmopolitan cities in the Mediterranean world. Of the Roman period, the city plan is clearly recognizable. The plan takes as its central axis the summit of the acropolis of Byrsa that divided the city into four quarters of equal size except for the one situated to the northwest. The most remarkable monuments found in Carthage are the Baths of Antonius situated on the seashore at the foot of the hill of Borj Jedid and the villas that stretched along the Odeon’s hill. From the Christian era, several basilicas were found. The necropolis that surrounded the city has also provided important information on the city.
Garden House of Dionysos
Keywords  porticoes columns (architectural elements) basins (vessels)  Garden Description In this very damaged house, a portico on four sides (IV-VII) enclosed a court (VIII) (8 x 11.10 m), which was planted during the building’s second phase dated at the fourth/early fifth century. The northeast and southwest porticos had four columns and the northwest and southeast had five columns.
A low wall was added in between the columns that enclosed the garden. A semi-circular basin attached to a rectangular one oriented northeast/southwest (IX) was placed at the northeast end of the garden. (Plan view, Fig. 1). The house dates from the III-V c.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the House of Dionysos. (Rights statement)   Images Dates The house dates from the III-V c.
Bibliography  CMT, KARTHAGO, Carthage, Les mosaïques du Parc archéologique des Thermes d’Anthonin, INA, Tunis,1999, 46-51, plan 5. (worldcat) Bullo, S. and F. Ghedini, Amplissimae atque ornatissimae domus: l&amp;rsquo;edilizia residenziale nelle citta della Tunisia roman, Rome: Edizioni Quasar, 2003, p. 143-144. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 314921
TGN ID 7016143
Contributor Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Aviary (Maison de la Volière)</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/xue_xia/karthago/house-of-the-aviary/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/xue_xia/karthago/house-of-the-aviary/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa Proconsularis Africa proconsularis (Pleiades)
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location Karthago
Karthago (Pleiades)
Location Description Founded by Tyrians from Phoenicia, Carthage became the capital of a powerful empire that came into conflict with the expanding power of Rome. In 146 BC Carthage was completely destroyed and re-founded as a Roman colony by Augustus who completed Cesar’s initial project. Augustus expanded the new city and encouraged settlements of veterans and civilians. The kingdom of Numidia was transformed into a province and Carthage was raised to the rank of capital. The city not only became the major port through which the wealth of the province flowed to Rome but also became a cultural capital that introduced the African elite to the rest of the empire, making it one of the wealthiest and most cosmopolitan cities in the Mediterranean world. Of the Roman period, the city plan is clearly recognizable. The plan takes as its central axis the summit of the acropolis of Byrsa that divided the city into four quarters of equal size except for the one situated to the northwest. The most remarkable monuments found in Carthage are the Baths of Antonius situated on the seashore at the foot of the hill of Borj Jedid and the villas that stretched along the Odeon’s hill. From the Christian era, several basilicas were found. The necropolis that surrounded the city has also provided important information on the city.
Garden House of the Aviary (Maison de la Volière)
Keywords  peristyles (columnades) peristyles (Roman courtyards) mosaics (visual works) cisterns (plumbing components) oeci  Garden Description Located on a hill overlooking Carthage, the house of the aviary is divided into two parts: the unit centered on the peristyle in the west, and the ensemble with the reception room in the east (Plan view, Fig. 1).
In the center of the peristyle in the western part of the house was an octagonal area enclosed by a low wall 50 cm high. P. Gauckler, the original excavator, recognized the area as a viridarium. The Aviary mosaic covers the floor space between the portico and the octagonal garden. In the center of each corner of the mosaic was a deep cavity in which a tree was planted. There was a cistern beneath the peristyle.
In the eastern part of the house, a low wall with six semi-circular niches that alternated with five square-shaped niches faced the oecus bordered by a portico. On the wall was laid out a large pool with small niches bordered on each side by two planters. On a higher level of the pool and the planters were three small cascades decorated with parietal mosaics and paintings depicting hunting and fishing scenes. Water coming from the huge cistern complex on the top of the hill ran through the cascades and fell into the pool. This arrangement can be compared to theater decor where nature is displayed. Hence, the oecus bordered by a portico was facing a frons scaenae composed by a pulpitum behind which were lined up the pool and two planters that could be compared to a proscaenium. The house dates from the end of the IInd-IVth century.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the House the Aviary. (Rights statement)   Images Dates The house dates from the end of the IInd-IVth century.
Bibliography  A. Ennabli, “La Maison de la Volière à Carthage: L’Architecture&amp;quot;, p. 132, in Mosaïque, Recueil d’hommage à Henri Stern, Paris, 1983. (worldcat) W. Ben Osman, “Etude des pavements de la Villa de la Volière”, p. 147, in Mosaïque, Recueil d’hommage à Henri Stern, Paris, 1983. (worldcat) Bullo, S. and F. Ghedini, Amplissimae atque ornatissimae domus: l&amp;rsquo;edilizia residenziale nelle citta della Tunisia roman, Rome: Edizioni Quasar, 2003, p. 125-128. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 314921
TGN ID 7016143
Contributor Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Bassilica (Maison de la Bassilica)</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/xue_xia/karthago/house-of-the-bassilica/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/xue_xia/karthago/house-of-the-bassilica/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa Proconsularis Africa proconsularis (Pleiades)
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location Karthago
Karthago (Pleiades)
Location Description Founded by Tyrians from Phoenicia, Carthage became the capital of a powerful empire that came into conflict with the expanding power of Rome. In 146 BC Carthage was completely destroyed and re-founded as a Roman colony by Augustus who completed Cesar’s initial project. Augustus expanded the new city and encouraged settlements of veterans and civilians. The kingdom of Numidia was transformed into a province and Carthage was raised to the rank of capital. The city not only became the major port through which the wealth of the province flowed to Rome but also became a cultural capital that introduced the African elite to the rest of the empire, making it one of the wealthiest and most cosmopolitan cities in the Mediterranean world. Of the Roman period, the city plan is clearly recognizable. The plan takes as its central axis the summit of the acropolis of Byrsa that divided the city into four quarters of equal size except for the one situated to the northwest. The most remarkable monuments found in Carthage are the Baths of Antonius situated on the seashore at the foot of the hill of Borj Jedid and the villas that stretched along the Odeon’s hill. From the Christian era, several basilicas were found. The necropolis that surrounded the city has also provided important information on the city.
Garden House of the Bassilica (Maison de la Bassilica)
Keywords  peristyles (columnades) peristyles (Roman courtyards) alleys (streets) exedrae (site elements) mosaics (visual works)  Garden Description The house was located in the insula delimited by the Decumani North V-VI and the Kardines East VIII-IX and neighboring to the North West the Villa of the Aviary. Unfortunately, the house was badly preserved when Gauckler the excavator discovered it (Plan view, Fig. 1). The peristyle was bounded by four porticoes, which were supported by twelve columns. The courtyard had a central alley that was limited on its two sides by colonnaded low walls that formed a circular exedra on one side and a rectangular exedra on the opposite side facing each other. P. Gauckler mentions that the exedrae were paved with mosaic figures of seashore landscapes, as well as the West portico that welcomed the visitor just after the vestibule. Only small fragments of the mosaics have survived. The central alley of the courtyard was on axis with the oecus.
1-	The North and the East portico lead to an open area that Gauckler identifies as a garden of at least 250m2. The house dates from the IVth. c.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the House of the Bassilica. (Rights statement)   Images Dates The house dates from the IVth. c.
Bibliography  P. Gauckler, Marche du service en 1903, Tunis, p. 16-17 (worldcat) W. Ben Osman, Catalogue des mosaïques de Carthage, Musée du Bardo, Musée des Thermes d&amp;rsquo;Antonin; quartier de Dermech, quartier de l&amp;rsquo;Odéon., p. 577-587. (worldcat) Bullo, S. and F. Ghedini, Amplissimae atque ornatissimae domus: l&amp;rsquo;edilizia residenziale nelle citta della Tunisia roman, Rome: Edizioni Quasar, 2003, p.123-124. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 314921
TGN ID 7016143
Contributor Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Cryptoporticus (Maison du Cryptoportique)</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/xue_xia/karthago/house-of-the-cryptoporticus/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/xue_xia/karthago/house-of-the-cryptoporticus/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa Proconsularis Africa proconsularis (Pleiades)
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location Karthago
Karthago (Pleiades)
Location Description Founded by Tyrians from Phoenicia, Carthage became the capital of a powerful empire that came into conflict with the expanding power of Rome. In 146 BC Carthage was completely destroyed and re-founded as a Roman colony by Augustus who completed Cesar’s initial project. Augustus expanded the new city and encouraged settlements of veterans and civilians. The kingdom of Numidia was transformed into a province and Carthage was raised to the rank of capital. The city not only became the major port through which the wealth of the province flowed to Rome but also became a cultural capital that introduced the African elite to the rest of the empire, making it one of the wealthiest and most cosmopolitan cities in the Mediterranean world. Of the Roman period, the city plan is clearly recognizable. The plan takes as its central axis the summit of the acropolis of Byrsa that divided the city into four quarters of equal size except for the one situated to the northwest. The most remarkable monuments found in Carthage are the Baths of Antonius situated on the seashore at the foot of the hill of Borj Jedid and the villas that stretched along the Odeon’s hill. From the Christian era, several basilicas were found. The necropolis that surrounded the city has also provided important information on the city.
Garden House of the Cryptoporticus (Maison du Cryptoportique)
Keywords  peristyles (columnades) peristyles (Roman courtyards) oeci opus sectile (visual works)  Garden Description The house of the Cryptoporticus occupies the hill of the Odeon on the insula that is located between the decumani N IV and V and the kardines E IX and X.
The house is organized around a peristyle garden with a grand oecus of 200m2 paved with opus sectile opening into it (Plan view, Fig. 1). The house dates from the I-Vth c.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the House of the Cryptoportique. (Rights statement)   Images Dates The house dates from the I-Vth c.
Bibliography  Collective publication (CTEMA, Tunis and CNRS,URA 375,1, Paris), Recherches sur les pavements de la &amp;ldquo;maison du cryptoportique&amp;rdquo; à Carthage, 113e Conrgrés National des Sociétés savantes, Strasbourg 1988, IV Colloqsue sur l&amp;rsquo;histoire et l&amp;rsquo;archéologie de l&amp;rsquo;Afrique du Nord, t..I, p 157-173. Bullo, S. and F. Ghedini, Amplissimae atque ornatissimae domus: l&amp;rsquo;edilizia residenziale nelle citta della Tunisia roman, Rome: Edizioni Quasar, 2003, p.132-134. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 314921
TGN ID 7016143
Contributor Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
