<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>tufa on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/tufa/</link>
    <description>Recent content in tufa on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 13:03:42 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/tufa/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>I.iii.3</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_3/i.iii.3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 13:03:42 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_3/i.iii.3/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 3
Garden I.iii.3
Keywords  alleys (streets) archaeological garden exedrae (site elements) gutters (building drainage components) hearths lararia peristyles (columnades) pilasters porticoes puteal tufa  Garden Description The front of this house excavated in 1869 had an unusual design in that it was set back some distance from the street. The peristyle garden was entered at the end of the entranceway at the rear of a long angiprotus (alleyway). Rooms of the house were located at the right and rear of the garden. The peristyle had undergone various changes and was supported on the east and north by tall tufa columns. The portico roof on the west was supported by two low brick columns and two pilasters surmounted by arches. A low wall enclosed the garden, joining the columns either side of the entrance between the two columns to the west. A terra-cotta puteal was adjacent to the west wall along with a hearth covered with a small vault decorated with a rough, bearded head supposed to be Vulcan. A large window on the south wall gave a view from the exedra (b) into the garden. The east peristyle wall contained a lararium niche and a gutter ran along the north, east, and west edges of the garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1869
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 24, no. 22. Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 72. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., pp. 52-53.(worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 1 (1868-69), cols. 300-301. Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 26. (worldcat) Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 78. Pernice, p. 34. Warscher, “Codex.” photos nos. 16-21.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 28 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Epidius Fortunatus (I.iii.3)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_3/house_of_epidius_fortunatus_i.iii.3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 19:24:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_3/house_of_epidius_fortunatus_i.iii.3/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 3
Garden House of Epidius Fortunatus (I.iii.3)
Keywords  archaeological garden aqueducts basins (vessels) gutters (building drainage components) peristyles (columnades) podiums (building divisions) porticoes puteal tablina tufa  Garden Description On the right of the tablinum were ten steps that led to the peristyle garden (a). A portico enclosed the garden on the west, north and east sides. This was supported by ten columns and two engaged columns which were stuccoed brick painted red. The north, east, and west edges of the garden had a gutter. There were two cistern openings, according to Mau, one located in the northeast corner of the garden with a tufa puteal and the other in the corresponding corner of the portico. Water emptied at the northeast corner from the gutter into the cistern and into the street at the southeast and southwest corners. An aqueduct pipe came out of the first column, (counting from the south, on the west portico), and ran between the gutter and the portico. The pipe rose, supported from the second column on the west side, to spurt a jet of water in the gutter. Flanking the west and the north porticos, it disappeared going to the northwest. On the west side it was possible in two places to let water flow into the gutter by a widening of the pipe. The gutter had openings to the gardens at these two points to serve as watering outlets. There were keys before and after the widen pipe sections to control the flow of water. Two branches of this pipe entered a room (b) off the northwest corner of the peristyle where there was a basin.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2 : Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Scavi, pp. 70-71. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., pp.50-51.(worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 26. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 181-182. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 77. Pernice, p. 14. Warscher, “Codex.” photos nos. 4, 6-10a.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 27 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa Della Grata Metallica; Casa Dell’Atrio Tetra-Stilo (I.ii.28)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_28/casa_della_grata_metallica_i.ii.28/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 15:01:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_28/casa_della_grata_metallica_i.ii.28/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 28
Garden Casa Della Grata Metallica; Casa Dell’Atrio Tetra-Stilo (I.ii.28)
Keywords  altars (religious fixtures) archaeological garden cisterns (plumbing components) peristyles (columnades) podiums (building divisions) porticoes tables (support furniture) tablina triclinia tufa  Garden Description At the rear of the house there was a peristyle garden (a) with a portico along the east side and part of the south. The excavation took place in 1873-74. A low wall joined three stuccoed brick columns and two engaged ones which supported the portico. There was an entrance to the garden on the south side opposite the door from the tablinium (b) and another on the east opposite the kitchen door (c), which was closed later according to Mau. The columns were white above the height of the wall and red below. Water was carried to the cistern by a wide gutter on the south and east edges of the garden, and Mau found some evidence of aqueduct water. There was a masonry triclinium (l.medius, 5.30 m.; l.imus, 3.85 m.; l.summus, 2.70 m.) with a circular table (dia. of support, 0.70 m. ) built against the west wall. Inside of each couch there were four niches (0.19 m. wide). The last niche in the south couch was larger in size and separated from the other three by the mouth of the cistern. There was a small masonry podium on the north wall with steps for access. A round tufa altar was located opposite the lectus summus (Fig. 3).
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I.ii.28; 10.11.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation dates 1873-1874
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Descr., p. 48. (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), col. 60. Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 25. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 250-252. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 77. Soprano, p. 293, no. 2 and figs. 28.6 and 29. Viola, “Scavi” p. 14. (worldcat) Warscher, “Codex.” photo no. 54-57.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 27 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.ii.3</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_3/i.ii.3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2020 16:14:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_3/i.ii.3/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 3
Garden I.ii.3
Keywords  archaeological garden tufa vestibules viridarium  Garden Description The small viridarium (a) at the rear of the house had narrow, slightly raised beds along the walls on the north and east side. These beds were for the cultivation of flowers, according to Fiorelli. A small vestibule on the north side of the garden was decorated with remnants of tufa columns brought from another site.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Descr., p. 37. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 21. (worldcat) Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. Gen.,” p. 76. Viola, “Scavi,” p 10. (worldcat) Warscher, “Codex,” photo, no. 12.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 23 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>