<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/annette_guan/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 24 Oct 2020 18:23:32 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/annette_guan/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Chaldaios</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/annette_guan/tomb-garden-of-chaldaios/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Oct 2020 18:23:32 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/annette_guan/tomb-garden-of-chaldaios/</guid>
      <description>Province Asia
Province Description The region of what is now modern Turkey became a part of the Roman Empire in 133 BCE, when king Attalos III of Pergamum bequeathed his kingdom to the Roman people. The province included the heartland of the Pergamene kingdom as well as the territories of Mysia, Lydia, Ionia, Caria, western Phrygia and the eastern Aegean islands. Under Augustus in 27 BCE Asia was declared a senatorial province and the governance of a proconsul. The capital of the province was Ephesos, although Pergamon may have fulfilled this role initially. Under Diocletian (284-305 CE) the province was subdivided into smaller administrative units: Hellespontus, Asia, Lydia, Caria, Phrygia I and Phrygia II. Due to its excellent harbors on the west coast and its many navigable rivers, Asia’s water-borne trade with the rest of the Mediterranean flourished. In the second century CE Asia experienced great prosperity, to which the growth and architectural aggrandizement of many of its cities attest. In the area of Kibyra, bordering the regions of Lycia, Caria, Phrygia and Pisidia, numerous inscriptions refer to the large imperial estates of Roman families. Woolen textiles, marble, and timber constituted a significant part of the commodities exported from the province.
While the Romans might have looked to the Greeks for inspiration in philosophy, architecture, sculpture, and the fine arts, the non-Greek peoples of the eastern Mediterranean are their inspiration for luxury, fine-living, and the status conferred by displays of individual wealth (Ath. Deip. 15.690). Asia was a center for such splendor, first in the kingdoms of Lydia, Phrygia, and Lycia, and then continued by the Persian satraps, and later the Hellenistic kings. The Persian paradeisos is particularly well attested in literature referencing Asia. That these gardens are known primarily from Roman-period literary sources indicates their continuing influence. For example, long after the gold of Lydia’s Pactolus River had disappeared, Lydia remained a literary topos, not only for copious wealth, but for a life of luxury set in a landscape of natural abundance. Athenaeus (Deip. 12.515d-f) wrote in the second century CE that
 &amp;quot;The Lydians in their luxury planned parks and made them like gardens and so kept in the shade. For they thought it more dainty not to have the sun’s rays touch them at all&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;
 Other districts of Asia captured the Roman imagination: Pliny the Elder writes of an ancient plane tree (Sycamorus orientalis) in Lycia with a girth of sufficient circumference to house a grotto in its hollow trunk, ornamented with pumice and moss with provisions for 18 people to dine there (Plin. HN 12.5).
The paradeisoi of the Persian satraps are of particular influence on the introduction of horti and gardens of Rome. The paradeisos, from the Persian, paira daeza, or “enclosed place,” is a term that had evolved by the Hellenistic period to mean a large enclosed park with luxurious gardens as well as orchards, collections of trees, crops, and hunting areas. It was at Sardis that the Greek Lysander visited Cyrus the Younger, a visit recorded by Klearchos and retold by Xenophon. It is an essential moment in garden history recounted for the Romans by Cicero (Sen. 59). These paradeisoi, in the sense of luxurious orchards, are said by the Romans to have been brought to Greece by Kimon (Aristotole apud Plut. Cim. 10; cf. Cic. de Off. 2.64), and were adopted by Hellenistic kings throughout Greece and southern Italy during the late Hellenistic period. The hunting parks at Daskyleion and Celenae are also vividly described by Xenophon (see An. 1.2.7, 2.4.14 and Oec. 4.13). Xenophon also describes how paradeisoi were occupied or cut down by armies during the fourth and third centuries BCE. Appreciation for these parks apparently continued, and Seleucus of Syria took over the royal paradeisos at Sardis (Plut. Dem. 50). Years of instability followed, so it is difficult to know what the Romans themselves thought of paradeisoi in Asia in the second and first centuries BCE. Notable examples of paradeisoi, in some form, may have been visible to Romans visiting Asia, as well. For example, the Mausoleum at Halicarnassus is now thought by its excavators to have been set in a grove or park.
Thus, the paradeisos, the alsos, the gymnasium, and the quadriporticus are not forms the Romans suddenly “discovered.” They had had a long influence and were integrated into the Hellenistic architectural forms of the Italic landscape. In the second century BCE, however, when the Roman generals began to define themselves as rulers of an empire, they turned directly to the palaces and paradeisoi of the Hellenistic monarchs to establish their power, to display spoils of war, and to create the luxurious setting for life in Rome. They further adapted the evolving quadriporticus form for display to the public
Despite the importance of Asia Minor in the history of the Roman landscape, archaeological evidence is scant. The excavators contacted for the gardens of this region indicated that parks, gardens, and other planted areas have yet to become a subject of research design for the region and finds appear to be few — primarily inscriptions and wall paintings. Most of the smaller domestic courtyards — often the most manageable to investigate — are paved. The larger palaestrae, gymnasia, and enclosed open spaces have not been investigated for landscape architectural and planting features, although recently an important campaign of work in the South Agora at Aphrodisias is setting an important precedent (CROSS-REF). The gardens included in this province include areas with dirt and incomplete paved surfaces, as well as sites where the excavators have some level of optimism that future study may yet reveal more about gardens. The subject of designed landscapes, gardens, and planted areas in Asia Minor remains in its archaeological infancy.
Location Thyateira
Thyateira (Pleiades)
Garden Tomb Garden of Chaldaios
Keywords  periboloi inscription tombs [tomb garden] Athenaeus Pliny the Elder Cicero Aristotle Plutarch quadriportici palaestrae gymnasiums  Garden Description According to a marble plaque of Trajanic or Hadrianic date found near Akhisar, “Fabius Zosimus, prepared a sarcophagus for himself and his dearest wife Aurelia Pontiana and put it in a place free of graves in front of the city on the side of the shrine of Sambatha [a local Sibyl] in the garden (περιβόλωι) of Chaldaeus (or “the Chaldaean”) beside the public road.&amp;rdquo; (Φάβιος Ζώσιμοϲ κατασκευάσαϲ σορὸν ἔθετο ἐπὶ τόπου καθαροῦ, ὄντοϲ πρὸ τῆσ πόλεωϲ πρὸϲ τῶι Σαμβαθείωι ἐν τῶι Χαλδαίου περιβόλωι παρὰ τὴν δημοσίαν ὅδον ἑαυτῶι, ἑφ’ ὧι τεθῇ, καὶ τῆι γλυκυτάτηι αὐτοῦ Αὐρηλίᾳ Ποντιανῆι, IGRP 4.1281.1-2) Here, as often elsewhere in central and western Anatolia, a tomb garden seems to be referred to metonymically by reference to its perimeter wall. The establishment of a tomb monument in a garden belonging to an extraneous party is found elsewhere in Asia Minor at Hierapolis in the complex of M. Aurelius Valerianus and Cl(audius) [N]ausimachus. The date and location of Fabius’s funerary disposition is confirmed by a subscription to his declaration, carved on another face of the stone, which places it &amp;ldquo;in the most splendid city of Thyateira during the consulship [probably the first consulship] of L. Catilius Severus&amp;rdquo; (ἐν τῇ λαμπροτάτῃ Θυατειρηνῶν πόλει, ἀνθυπάτωι Κατιλλίωι Σεβήρωι, IGRP 4.1281.5-6), who held the office twice, in 110 and 120 CE.
Maps Plans Images Dates After 110 CE
Bibliography  R. Cagnat and G. Lafaye, Inscriptiones Graecae ad res Romanas pertinentes. Paris, 1906-1927, IV, 1281 (worldcat) P. Herrmann, Tituli Lydiae linguis Graeca et Latina conscripti (Tituli Asiae Minoris V, 2). Vienna, 1989, 1142.(worldcat)  Pleiades ID 550924
TGN ID 7002627
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 9 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Theodoros</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/annette_guan/tomb-garden-of-theodoros/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Oct 2020 17:36:32 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/annette_guan/tomb-garden-of-theodoros/</guid>
      <description>Province Asia
Province Description The region of what is now modern Turkey became a part of the Roman Empire in 133 BCE, when king Attalos III of Pergamum bequeathed his kingdom to the Roman people. The province included the heartland of the Pergamene kingdom as well as the territories of Mysia, Lydia, Ionia, Caria, western Phrygia and the eastern Aegean islands. Under Augustus in 27 BCE Asia was declared a senatorial province and the governance of a proconsul. The capital of the province was Ephesos, although Pergamon may have fulfilled this role initially. Under Diocletian (284-305 CE) the province was subdivided into smaller administrative units: Hellespontus, Asia, Lydia, Caria, Phrygia I and Phrygia II. Due to its excellent harbors on the west coast and its many navigable rivers, Asia’s water-borne trade with the rest of the Mediterranean flourished. In the second century CE Asia experienced great prosperity, to which the growth and architectural aggrandizement of many of its cities attest. In the area of Kibyra, bordering the regions of Lycia, Caria, Phrygia and Pisidia, numerous inscriptions refer to the large imperial estates of Roman families. Woolen textiles, marble, and timber constituted a significant part of the commodities exported from the province.
While the Romans might have looked to the Greeks for inspiration in philosophy, architecture, sculpture, and the fine arts, the non-Greek peoples of the eastern Mediterranean are their inspiration for luxury, fine-living, and the status conferred by displays of individual wealth (Ath. Deip. 15.690). Asia was a center for such splendor, first in the kingdoms of Lydia, Phrygia, and Lycia, and then continued by the Persian satraps, and later the Hellenistic kings. The Persian paradeisos is particularly well attested in literature referencing Asia. That these gardens are known primarily from Roman-period literary sources indicates their continuing influence. For example, long after the gold of Lydia’s Pactolus River had disappeared, Lydia remained a literary topos, not only for copious wealth, but for a life of luxury set in a landscape of natural abundance. Athenaeus (Deip. 12.515d-f) wrote in the second century CE that
 &amp;quot;The Lydians in their luxury planned parks and made them like gardens and so kept in the shade. For they thought it more dainty not to have the sun’s rays touch them at all&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;
 Other districts of Asia captured the Roman imagination: Pliny the Elder writes of an ancient plane tree (Sycamorus orientalis) in Lycia with a girth of sufficient circumference to house a grotto in its hollow trunk, ornamented with pumice and moss with provisions for 18 people to dine there (Plin. HN 12.5).
The paradeisoi of the Persian satraps are of particular influence on the introduction of horti and gardens of Rome. The paradeisos, from the Persian, paira daeza, or “enclosed place,” is a term that had evolved by the Hellenistic period to mean a large enclosed park with luxurious gardens as well as orchards, collections of trees, crops, and hunting areas. It was at Sardis that the Greek Lysander visited Cyrus the Younger, a visit recorded by Klearchos and retold by Xenophon. It is an essential moment in garden history recounted for the Romans by Cicero (Sen. 59). These paradeisoi, in the sense of luxurious orchards, are said by the Romans to have been brought to Greece by Kimon (Aristotole apud Plut. Cim. 10; cf. Cic. de Off. 2.64), and were adopted by Hellenistic kings throughout Greece and southern Italy during the late Hellenistic period. The hunting parks at Daskyleion and Celenae are also vividly described by Xenophon (see An. 1.2.7, 2.4.14 and Oec. 4.13). Xenophon also describes how paradeisoi were occupied or cut down by armies during the fourth and third centuries BCE. Appreciation for these parks apparently continued, and Seleucus of Syria took over the royal paradeisos at Sardis (Plut. Dem. 50). Years of instability followed, so it is difficult to know what the Romans themselves thought of paradeisoi in Asia in the second and first centuries BCE. Notable examples of paradeisoi, in some form, may have been visible to Romans visiting Asia, as well. For example, the Mausoleum at Halicarnassus is now thought by its excavators to have been set in a grove or park.
Thus, the paradeisos, the alsos, the gymnasium, and the quadriporticus are not forms the Romans suddenly “discovered.” They had had a long influence and were integrated into the Hellenistic architectural forms of the Italic landscape. In the second century BCE, however, when the Roman generals began to define themselves as rulers of an empire, they turned directly to the palaces and paradeisoi of the Hellenistic monarchs to establish their power, to display spoils of war, and to create the luxurious setting for life in Rome. They further adapted the evolving quadriporticus form for display to the public
Despite the importance of Asia Minor in the history of the Roman landscape, archaeological evidence is scant. The excavators contacted for the gardens of this region indicated that parks, gardens, and other planted areas have yet to become a subject of research design for the region and finds appear to be few — primarily inscriptions and wall paintings. Most of the smaller domestic courtyards — often the most manageable to investigate — are paved. The larger palaestrae, gymnasia, and enclosed open spaces have not been investigated for landscape architectural and planting features, although recently an important campaign of work in the South Agora at Aphrodisias is setting an important precedent (CROSS-REF). The gardens included in this province include areas with dirt and incomplete paved surfaces, as well as sites where the excavators have some level of optimism that future study may yet reveal more about gardens. The subject of designed landscapes, gardens, and planted areas in Asia Minor remains in its archaeological infancy.
Location Smyrna (İzmir, Turkey)
Smyrna (Pleiades)
Location Description On the Aegean coast of Anatolia, Smyrna was rebuilt after an earthquake in the 2nd century AD atop the area of the city first established after the conquest of Alexander the Great on the slopes of Mt. Pagos (Kadifekale). An inscription suggests the presence of a palm grove that was an elaborately decorated park, as noted at Aphrodisias. (Robert, &amp;hellip;Ét. Anat. 526; n. 5 on IBR IV, 1431.)
Garden Tomb Garden of Theodoros
Keywords  inscription Athenaeus Pliny the Elder Cicero Aristotle Plutarch quadriportici palaestrae gymnasiums  Garden Description A reused rectangular marble block from Smyrna housed since the middle of the eighteenth century in the Ashmolean Museum at Oxford records, in a secondary text carved lengthwise on the underside of the stone, the funerary donation of a garden (kepos) by a notary (sumbolaiographon) Ioannes, the son of Rufinus, from Smyrna, to his grandson Theodorus. The text, which is framed by Christian crosses, evidently dates from the period after Constantine, probably to the fourth or fifth century A.D.
Maps Plans Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  L. Robert. Études Anatoliennes, Sur des inscriptions de l&amp;rsquo;Asie Mineure, 1937. (worldcat) C. Roueché and J.M. Reynolds, Aphrodisias in late antiquity: the late Roman and Byzantine Inscriptions including texts from the excavations conducted at Aphrodisias by Kenan T. Erim. London: Society for the Promotion of Roman Studies, 1989, Pp. 70. (worldcat) R. Chandler, Marmora Oxoniensia. Oxford, 1763, II 39,2 (worldcat) G. Petzl, Die Inschriften von Smyrna. Teil 1: Grabinschriften, postume Ehrungen, Grabepigramme. Bonn, 1982, p. 267, no. 563 and Pl. 40. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 550771
TGN ID 7002543
Contributor # (ORCID: #)
Publication date 15 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rhodes, Groves on the Acropolis</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/annette_guan/rhodes-groves-on-the-acropolis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2020 11:18:32 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/annette_guan/rhodes-groves-on-the-acropolis/</guid>
      <description>Province Asia
Province Description The region of what is now modern Turkey became a part of the Roman Empire in 133 BCE, when king Attalos III of Pergamum bequeathed his kingdom to the Roman people. The province included the heartland of the Pergamene kingdom as well as the territories of Mysia, Lydia, Ionia, Caria, western Phrygia and the eastern Aegean islands. Under Augustus in 27 BCE Asia was declared a senatorial province and the governance of a proconsul. The capital of the province was Ephesos, although Pergamon may have fulfilled this role initially. Under Diocletian (284-305 CE) the province was subdivided into smaller administrative units: Hellespontus, Asia, Lydia, Caria, Phrygia I and Phrygia II. Due to its excellent harbors on the west coast and its many navigable rivers, Asia’s water-borne trade with the rest of the Mediterranean flourished. In the second century CE Asia experienced great prosperity, to which the growth and architectural aggrandizement of many of its cities attest. In the area of Kibyra, bordering the regions of Lycia, Caria, Phrygia and Pisidia, numerous inscriptions refer to the large imperial estates of Roman families. Woolen textiles, marble, and timber constituted a significant part of the commodities exported from the province.
While the Romans might have looked to the Greeks for inspiration in philosophy, architecture, sculpture, and the fine arts, the non-Greek peoples of the eastern Mediterranean are their inspiration for luxury, fine-living, and the status conferred by displays of individual wealth (Ath. Deip. 15.690). Asia was a center for such splendor, first in the kingdoms of Lydia, Phrygia, and Lycia, and then continued by the Persian satraps, and later the Hellenistic kings. The Persian paradeisos is particularly well attested in literature referencing Asia. That these gardens are known primarily from Roman-period literary sources indicates their continuing influence. For example, long after the gold of Lydia’s Pactolus River had disappeared, Lydia remained a literary topos, not only for copious wealth, but for a life of luxury set in a landscape of natural abundance. Athenaeus (Deip. 12.515d-f) wrote in the second century CE that
 &amp;quot;The Lydians in their luxury planned parks and made them like gardens and so kept in the shade. For they thought it more dainty not to have the sun’s rays touch them at all&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;
 Other districts of Asia captured the Roman imagination: Pliny the Elder writes of an ancient plane tree (Sycamorus orientalis) in Lycia with a girth of sufficient circumference to house a grotto in its hollow trunk, ornamented with pumice and moss with provisions for 18 people to dine there (Plin. HN 12.5).
The paradeisoi of the Persian satraps are of particular influence on the introduction of horti and gardens of Rome. The paradeisos, from the Persian, paira daeza, or “enclosed place,” is a term that had evolved by the Hellenistic period to mean a large enclosed park with luxurious gardens as well as orchards, collections of trees, crops, and hunting areas. It was at Sardis that the Greek Lysander visited Cyrus the Younger, a visit recorded by Klearchos and retold by Xenophon. It is an essential moment in garden history recounted for the Romans by Cicero (Sen. 59). These paradeisoi, in the sense of luxurious orchards, are said by the Romans to have been brought to Greece by Kimon (Aristotole apud Plut. Cim. 10; cf. Cic. de Off. 2.64), and were adopted by Hellenistic kings throughout Greece and southern Italy during the late Hellenistic period. The hunting parks at Daskyleion and Celenae are also vividly described by Xenophon (see An. 1.2.7, 2.4.14 and Oec. 4.13). Xenophon also describes how paradeisoi were occupied or cut down by armies during the fourth and third centuries BCE. Appreciation for these parks apparently continued, and Seleucus of Syria took over the royal paradeisos at Sardis (Plut. Dem. 50). Years of instability followed, so it is difficult to know what the Romans themselves thought of paradeisoi in Asia in the second and first centuries BCE. Notable examples of paradeisoi, in some form, may have been visible to Romans visiting Asia, as well. For example, the Mausoleum at Halicarnassus is now thought by its excavators to have been set in a grove or park.
Thus, the paradeisos, the alsos, the gymnasium, and the quadriporticus are not forms the Romans suddenly “discovered.” They had had a long influence and were integrated into the Hellenistic architectural forms of the Italic landscape. In the second century BCE, however, when the Roman generals began to define themselves as rulers of an empire, they turned directly to the palaces and paradeisoi of the Hellenistic monarchs to establish their power, to display spoils of war, and to create the luxurious setting for life in Rome. They further adapted the evolving quadriporticus form for display to the public
Despite the importance of Asia Minor in the history of the Roman landscape, archaeological evidence is scant. The excavators contacted for the gardens of this region indicated that parks, gardens, and other planted areas have yet to become a subject of research design for the region and finds appear to be few — primarily inscriptions and wall paintings. Most of the smaller domestic courtyards — often the most manageable to investigate — are paved. The larger palaestrae, gymnasia, and enclosed open spaces have not been investigated for landscape architectural and planting features, although recently an important campaign of work in the South Agora at Aphrodisias is setting an important precedent (CROSS-REF). The gardens included in this province include areas with dirt and incomplete paved surfaces, as well as sites where the excavators have some level of optimism that future study may yet reveal more about gardens. The subject of designed landscapes, gardens, and planted areas in Asia Minor remains in its archaeological infancy.
Location Rhodes
Rhodes (Pleiades)
Garden Rhodes, Groves on the Acropolis
Keywords  sacred groves gymnasium Athenaeus Pliny the Elder Cicero Aristotle Plutarch quadriportici palaestrae gymnasiums  Garden Description Aelius Aristides (25.6) referred in the second century A.D. to the parks and groves in the acropolis district of the city. According to Philostratos, writing in the late second and early third century A.D., this area in the western part of the city had many sanctuaries, groves and gymnasia (Life of Apollonius 5.22). Archaeological exploration of the acropolis sector has confirmed the existence of temples to Zeus and to Apollo, a gymnasium with a stadium and several sacred caves of the nymphs (nymphaia) near the temple of Zeus. These artificial caves were carved out of the rock and had water basins and niches for statues. No trace of any gardens or groves survives, but these would not have been out of place in the context of sanctuaries and gymnasia.
Maps Plans Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  W. Hoepfner et al, Haus und Stadt im klassischen Griechenland. Wohnen in der klassischen Polis 1, 2nd Edition, Berlin, 1994, pp. 65-66, fig. 41 (worldcat) M. Carroll-Spillecke and J.M. Carreté i Nadal, Κήπος: Der antike griechische Garten. Wohnen in der klassischen Polis 3, Munich, 1989, pp. 86, 94, fig. 12.(worldcat)  Pleiades ID 590031
TGN ID 7011266
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 15 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rhodes, Palatial House</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/annette_guan/palatial-house/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2020 11:18:32 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/annette_guan/palatial-house/</guid>
      <description>Province Asia
Province Description The region of what is now modern Turkey became a part of the Roman Empire in 133 BCE, when king Attalos III of Pergamum bequeathed his kingdom to the Roman people. The province included the heartland of the Pergamene kingdom as well as the territories of Mysia, Lydia, Ionia, Caria, western Phrygia and the eastern Aegean islands. Under Augustus in 27 BCE Asia was declared a senatorial province and the governance of a proconsul. The capital of the province was Ephesos, although Pergamon may have fulfilled this role initially. Under Diocletian (284-305 CE) the province was subdivided into smaller administrative units: Hellespontus, Asia, Lydia, Caria, Phrygia I and Phrygia II. Due to its excellent harbors on the west coast and its many navigable rivers, Asia’s water-borne trade with the rest of the Mediterranean flourished. In the second century CE Asia experienced great prosperity, to which the growth and architectural aggrandizement of many of its cities attest. In the area of Kibyra, bordering the regions of Lycia, Caria, Phrygia and Pisidia, numerous inscriptions refer to the large imperial estates of Roman families. Woolen textiles, marble, and timber constituted a significant part of the commodities exported from the province.
While the Romans might have looked to the Greeks for inspiration in philosophy, architecture, sculpture, and the fine arts, the non-Greek peoples of the eastern Mediterranean are their inspiration for luxury, fine-living, and the status conferred by displays of individual wealth (Ath. Deip. 15.690). Asia was a center for such splendor, first in the kingdoms of Lydia, Phrygia, and Lycia, and then continued by the Persian satraps, and later the Hellenistic kings. The Persian paradeisos is particularly well attested in literature referencing Asia. That these gardens are known primarily from Roman-period literary sources indicates their continuing influence. For example, long after the gold of Lydia’s Pactolus River had disappeared, Lydia remained a literary topos, not only for copious wealth, but for a life of luxury set in a landscape of natural abundance. Athenaeus (Deip. 12.515d-f) wrote in the second century CE that
 &amp;quot;The Lydians in their luxury planned parks and made them like gardens and so kept in the shade. For they thought it more dainty not to have the sun’s rays touch them at all&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;
 Other districts of Asia captured the Roman imagination: Pliny the Elder writes of an ancient plane tree (Sycamorus orientalis) in Lycia with a girth of sufficient circumference to house a grotto in its hollow trunk, ornamented with pumice and moss with provisions for 18 people to dine there (Plin. HN 12.5).
The paradeisoi of the Persian satraps are of particular influence on the introduction of horti and gardens of Rome. The paradeisos, from the Persian, paira daeza, or “enclosed place,” is a term that had evolved by the Hellenistic period to mean a large enclosed park with luxurious gardens as well as orchards, collections of trees, crops, and hunting areas. It was at Sardis that the Greek Lysander visited Cyrus the Younger, a visit recorded by Klearchos and retold by Xenophon. It is an essential moment in garden history recounted for the Romans by Cicero (Sen. 59). These paradeisoi, in the sense of luxurious orchards, are said by the Romans to have been brought to Greece by Kimon (Aristotole apud Plut. Cim. 10; cf. Cic. de Off. 2.64), and were adopted by Hellenistic kings throughout Greece and southern Italy during the late Hellenistic period. The hunting parks at Daskyleion and Celenae are also vividly described by Xenophon (see An. 1.2.7, 2.4.14 and Oec. 4.13). Xenophon also describes how paradeisoi were occupied or cut down by armies during the fourth and third centuries BCE. Appreciation for these parks apparently continued, and Seleucus of Syria took over the royal paradeisos at Sardis (Plut. Dem. 50). Years of instability followed, so it is difficult to know what the Romans themselves thought of paradeisoi in Asia in the second and first centuries BCE. Notable examples of paradeisoi, in some form, may have been visible to Romans visiting Asia, as well. For example, the Mausoleum at Halicarnassus is now thought by its excavators to have been set in a grove or park.
Thus, the paradeisos, the alsos, the gymnasium, and the quadriporticus are not forms the Romans suddenly “discovered.” They had had a long influence and were integrated into the Hellenistic architectural forms of the Italic landscape. In the second century BCE, however, when the Roman generals began to define themselves as rulers of an empire, they turned directly to the palaces and paradeisoi of the Hellenistic monarchs to establish their power, to display spoils of war, and to create the luxurious setting for life in Rome. They further adapted the evolving quadriporticus form for display to the public
Despite the importance of Asia Minor in the history of the Roman landscape, archaeological evidence is scant. The excavators contacted for the gardens of this region indicated that parks, gardens, and other planted areas have yet to become a subject of research design for the region and finds appear to be few — primarily inscriptions and wall paintings. Most of the smaller domestic courtyards — often the most manageable to investigate — are paved. The larger palaestrae, gymnasia, and enclosed open spaces have not been investigated for landscape architectural and planting features, although recently an important campaign of work in the South Agora at Aphrodisias is setting an important precedent (CROSS-REF). The gardens included in this province include areas with dirt and incomplete paved surfaces, as well as sites where the excavators have some level of optimism that future study may yet reveal more about gardens. The subject of designed landscapes, gardens, and planted areas in Asia Minor remains in its archaeological infancy.
Location Rhodes
Rhodes (Pleiades)
Garden Rhodes, Palatial House
Keywords  pools (bodies of water) courtyards Athenaeus Pliny the Elder Cicero Aristotle Plutarch quadriportici palaestrae gymnasiums  Garden Description At the foot of the acropolis in Rhodes stood a late Hellenistic building that occupied an entire insula. Unfortunately, the building is poorly preserved. Because of the size of the building and its provision with luxurious reception rooms and a large bath suite, the excavators proposed that this was not simply a private house, but that it had some other special function.
The building had three courtyards in the eastern sector, and a large open area with a semi-circular pool (15.30 x 17.30 m) in the western part. Various renovations were carried out before the late second century A.D. These included the addition of decorative pools in two of the courtyards and an alteration to the semi-circular pool in the western part of the building. No trace of any pavement was found in this area. The natural rocky ground of the site was left unaltered at the northern end of this pool, giving the whole area a rusticated appearance. Various fragments of sculpture, including a herm, a dog and a marble vessel (louterion), were found on site. The excavators have reconstructed this part of the building as a landscaped garden adorned with plantings, the pool and sculpture.
Maps Plans Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  D. Dreliossi-Herakleidou, “Späthellenistische palastartige Gebäude in der Nähe der Akropolis von Rhodos,” in W. Hoepfner and G. Brands, eds., Basileia. Die Paläste der hellenistischen Könige, Berlin, 1996, pp. 182-192, figs. 7-8. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 590031
TGN ID 7011266
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 15 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Temple Grove of Nikephorion</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/annette_guan/temple-grove-of-nikephorion/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2020 10:37:32 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/annette_guan/temple-grove-of-nikephorion/</guid>
      <description>Province Asia
Province Description The region of what is now modern Turkey became a part of the Roman Empire in 133 BCE, when king Attalos III of Pergamum bequeathed his kingdom to the Roman people. The province included the heartland of the Pergamene kingdom as well as the territories of Mysia, Lydia, Ionia, Caria, western Phrygia and the eastern Aegean islands. Under Augustus in 27 BCE Asia was declared a senatorial province and the governance of a proconsul. The capital of the province was Ephesos, although Pergamon may have fulfilled this role initially. Under Diocletian (284-305 CE) the province was subdivided into smaller administrative units: Hellespontus, Asia, Lydia, Caria, Phrygia I and Phrygia II. Due to its excellent harbors on the west coast and its many navigable rivers, Asia’s water-borne trade with the rest of the Mediterranean flourished. In the second century CE Asia experienced great prosperity, to which the growth and architectural aggrandizement of many of its cities attest. In the area of Kibyra, bordering the regions of Lycia, Caria, Phrygia and Pisidia, numerous inscriptions refer to the large imperial estates of Roman families. Woolen textiles, marble, and timber constituted a significant part of the commodities exported from the province.
While the Romans might have looked to the Greeks for inspiration in philosophy, architecture, sculpture, and the fine arts, the non-Greek peoples of the eastern Mediterranean are their inspiration for luxury, fine-living, and the status conferred by displays of individual wealth (Ath. Deip. 15.690). Asia was a center for such splendor, first in the kingdoms of Lydia, Phrygia, and Lycia, and then continued by the Persian satraps, and later the Hellenistic kings. The Persian paradeisos is particularly well attested in literature referencing Asia. That these gardens are known primarily from Roman-period literary sources indicates their continuing influence. For example, long after the gold of Lydia’s Pactolus River had disappeared, Lydia remained a literary topos, not only for copious wealth, but for a life of luxury set in a landscape of natural abundance. Athenaeus (Deip. 12.515d-f) wrote in the second century CE that
 &amp;quot;The Lydians in their luxury planned parks and made them like gardens and so kept in the shade. For they thought it more dainty not to have the sun’s rays touch them at all&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;
 Other districts of Asia captured the Roman imagination: Pliny the Elder writes of an ancient plane tree (Sycamorus orientalis) in Lycia with a girth of sufficient circumference to house a grotto in its hollow trunk, ornamented with pumice and moss with provisions for 18 people to dine there (Plin. HN 12.5).
The paradeisoi of the Persian satraps are of particular influence on the introduction of horti and gardens of Rome. The paradeisos, from the Persian, paira daeza, or “enclosed place,” is a term that had evolved by the Hellenistic period to mean a large enclosed park with luxurious gardens as well as orchards, collections of trees, crops, and hunting areas. It was at Sardis that the Greek Lysander visited Cyrus the Younger, a visit recorded by Klearchos and retold by Xenophon. It is an essential moment in garden history recounted for the Romans by Cicero (Sen. 59). These paradeisoi, in the sense of luxurious orchards, are said by the Romans to have been brought to Greece by Kimon (Aristotole apud Plut. Cim. 10; cf. Cic. de Off. 2.64), and were adopted by Hellenistic kings throughout Greece and southern Italy during the late Hellenistic period. The hunting parks at Daskyleion and Celenae are also vividly described by Xenophon (see An. 1.2.7, 2.4.14 and Oec. 4.13). Xenophon also describes how paradeisoi were occupied or cut down by armies during the fourth and third centuries BCE. Appreciation for these parks apparently continued, and Seleucus of Syria took over the royal paradeisos at Sardis (Plut. Dem. 50). Years of instability followed, so it is difficult to know what the Romans themselves thought of paradeisoi in Asia in the second and first centuries BCE. Notable examples of paradeisoi, in some form, may have been visible to Romans visiting Asia, as well. For example, the Mausoleum at Halicarnassus is now thought by its excavators to have been set in a grove or park.
Thus, the paradeisos, the alsos, the gymnasium, and the quadriporticus are not forms the Romans suddenly “discovered.” They had had a long influence and were integrated into the Hellenistic architectural forms of the Italic landscape. In the second century BCE, however, when the Roman generals began to define themselves as rulers of an empire, they turned directly to the palaces and paradeisoi of the Hellenistic monarchs to establish their power, to display spoils of war, and to create the luxurious setting for life in Rome. They further adapted the evolving quadriporticus form for display to the public
Despite the importance of Asia Minor in the history of the Roman landscape, archaeological evidence is scant. The excavators contacted for the gardens of this region indicated that parks, gardens, and other planted areas have yet to become a subject of research design for the region and finds appear to be few — primarily inscriptions and wall paintings. Most of the smaller domestic courtyards — often the most manageable to investigate — are paved. The larger palaestrae, gymnasia, and enclosed open spaces have not been investigated for landscape architectural and planting features, although recently an important campaign of work in the South Agora at Aphrodisias is setting an important precedent (CROSS-REF). The gardens included in this province include areas with dirt and incomplete paved surfaces, as well as sites where the excavators have some level of optimism that future study may yet reveal more about gardens. The subject of designed landscapes, gardens, and planted areas in Asia Minor remains in its archaeological infancy.
Location Pergamum (Pergamon; Bergama, Turkey)
Pergamum (Pleiades)
Location Description Pergamum, a fortress site in Mysia near the Aegean coast, was transformed into an architectural center under the Attalid dynasty (282-133 B.C.). Attalus the III wrote treatises on gardens, raised poisonous plants, made wax models (Plut. Demet. 20.2), and upon his death, left the kingdom of Mysia to the Romans. It became one of the most important Roman cities of Asia, and current scholarship has revealed its significance as an influence on the art and architecture of Rome. The range of designed open spaces includes sanctuaries, gymnasia, palaestra, and agoras, all of which were renovated during the Roman period. No archaeological remains of planting features have been reported, but an inscription records a law prohibiting the deliberate planting of trees near walls (SEG XIII 521.11.158-61).
Garden Temple Grove of Nikephorion
Keywords  groves (plant communities) sanctuary centers (religious centers) inscription Athenaeus Pliny the Elder Cicero Aristotle Plutarch quadriportici palaestrae gymnasiums  Garden Description King Eumenes II of Pergamum employed a gardener to plant new trees and nurse damaged ones back to health in the grove of the Nikephorion, following an attack on the city by Philip V of Macedon in 201 B.C., during which Philip V ordered his troops to cut down trees in the sanctuary (Polybios 16.1.6).
Maps Plans Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  M. Carroll-Spillecke, “The Gardens of Greece from Homeric to Roman Times,” Journal of Garden History 12, 1992: 84-101 (Taylor &amp;amp; Francis Online) A. Kuttner, “Republican Rome looks at Pergamon,&amp;rdquo; Harvard Studies in Classical Philology vol. 97, Greece in Rome: Influence, Interaction, Resistance, ed. C.P.Jones, R. Thomas, 1997, pp.157-178 (worldcat) C. Ratte, “Pergamon,” Oxford Encyclopedia of Near Eastern Archaeology, 1997, 261-262 (worldcat) I. Nielsen, Hellenistic Palaces. Aarhus, 1994, p. 107, catalog no. 15.(worldcat)  Pleiades ID 550812
TGN ID 7016140
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032) Kathryn Gleason (ORCID: 0000-0001-6260-8378)
Publication date 15 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lindos, Grove on the Acropolis</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/annette_guan/lindos-grove-on-the-acropolis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Oct 2020 02:45:32 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/annette_guan/lindos-grove-on-the-acropolis/</guid>
      <description>Province Asia
Province Description The region of what is now modern Turkey became a part of the Roman Empire in 133 BCE, when king Attalos III of Pergamum bequeathed his kingdom to the Roman people. The province included the heartland of the Pergamene kingdom as well as the territories of Mysia, Lydia, Ionia, Caria, western Phrygia and the eastern Aegean islands. Under Augustus in 27 BCE Asia was declared a senatorial province and the governance of a proconsul. The capital of the province was Ephesos, although Pergamon may have fulfilled this role initially. Under Diocletian (284-305 CE) the province was subdivided into smaller administrative units: Hellespontus, Asia, Lydia, Caria, Phrygia I and Phrygia II. Due to its excellent harbors on the west coast and its many navigable rivers, Asia’s water-borne trade with the rest of the Mediterranean flourished. In the second century CE Asia experienced great prosperity, to which the growth and architectural aggrandizement of many of its cities attest. In the area of Kibyra, bordering the regions of Lycia, Caria, Phrygia and Pisidia, numerous inscriptions refer to the large imperial estates of Roman families. Woolen textiles, marble, and timber constituted a significant part of the commodities exported from the province.
While the Romans might have looked to the Greeks for inspiration in philosophy, architecture, sculpture, and the fine arts, the non-Greek peoples of the eastern Mediterranean are their inspiration for luxury, fine-living, and the status conferred by displays of individual wealth (Ath. Deip. 15.690). Asia was a center for such splendor, first in the kingdoms of Lydia, Phrygia, and Lycia, and then continued by the Persian satraps, and later the Hellenistic kings. The Persian paradeisos is particularly well attested in literature referencing Asia. That these gardens are known primarily from Roman-period literary sources indicates their continuing influence. For example, long after the gold of Lydia’s Pactolus River had disappeared, Lydia remained a literary topos, not only for copious wealth, but for a life of luxury set in a landscape of natural abundance. Athenaeus (Deip. 12.515d-f) wrote in the second century CE that
 &amp;quot;The Lydians in their luxury planned parks and made them like gardens and so kept in the shade. For they thought it more dainty not to have the sun’s rays touch them at all&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;
 Other districts of Asia captured the Roman imagination: Pliny the Elder writes of an ancient plane tree (Sycamorus orientalis) in Lycia with a girth of sufficient circumference to house a grotto in its hollow trunk, ornamented with pumice and moss with provisions for 18 people to dine there (Plin. HN 12.5).
The paradeisoi of the Persian satraps are of particular influence on the introduction of horti and gardens of Rome. The paradeisos, from the Persian, paira daeza, or “enclosed place,” is a term that had evolved by the Hellenistic period to mean a large enclosed park with luxurious gardens as well as orchards, collections of trees, crops, and hunting areas. It was at Sardis that the Greek Lysander visited Cyrus the Younger, a visit recorded by Klearchos and retold by Xenophon. It is an essential moment in garden history recounted for the Romans by Cicero (Sen. 59). These paradeisoi, in the sense of luxurious orchards, are said by the Romans to have been brought to Greece by Kimon (Aristotole apud Plut. Cim. 10; cf. Cic. de Off. 2.64), and were adopted by Hellenistic kings throughout Greece and southern Italy during the late Hellenistic period. The hunting parks at Daskyleion and Celenae are also vividly described by Xenophon (see An. 1.2.7, 2.4.14 and Oec. 4.13). Xenophon also describes how paradeisoi were occupied or cut down by armies during the fourth and third centuries BCE. Appreciation for these parks apparently continued, and Seleucus of Syria took over the royal paradeisos at Sardis (Plut. Dem. 50). Years of instability followed, so it is difficult to know what the Romans themselves thought of paradeisoi in Asia in the second and first centuries BCE. Notable examples of paradeisoi, in some form, may have been visible to Romans visiting Asia, as well. For example, the Mausoleum at Halicarnassus is now thought by its excavators to have been set in a grove or park.
Thus, the paradeisos, the alsos, the gymnasium, and the quadriporticus are not forms the Romans suddenly “discovered.” They had had a long influence and were integrated into the Hellenistic architectural forms of the Italic landscape. In the second century BCE, however, when the Roman generals began to define themselves as rulers of an empire, they turned directly to the palaces and paradeisoi of the Hellenistic monarchs to establish their power, to display spoils of war, and to create the luxurious setting for life in Rome. They further adapted the evolving quadriporticus form for display to the public
Despite the importance of Asia Minor in the history of the Roman landscape, archaeological evidence is scant. The excavators contacted for the gardens of this region indicated that parks, gardens, and other planted areas have yet to become a subject of research design for the region and finds appear to be few — primarily inscriptions and wall paintings. Most of the smaller domestic courtyards — often the most manageable to investigate — are paved. The larger palaestrae, gymnasia, and enclosed open spaces have not been investigated for landscape architectural and planting features, although recently an important campaign of work in the South Agora at Aphrodisias is setting an important precedent (CROSS-REF). The gardens included in this province include areas with dirt and incomplete paved surfaces, as well as sites where the excavators have some level of optimism that future study may yet reveal more about gardens. The subject of designed landscapes, gardens, and planted areas in Asia Minor remains in its archaeological infancy.
Location Rhodes
Rhodes (Pleiades)
Garden Lindos, Grove on the Acropolis
Keywords  sacred groves Olea europaea (species) inscription Athenaeus Pliny the Elder Cicero Aristotle Plutarch quadriportici palaestrae gymnasiums  Garden Description There is no archaeological evidence for a sacred grove on the acropolis of the Rhodian town of Lindos. Roman inscriptions, however, record the existence of olive trees in a religious context. The names of several priests who made a gift of olive trees are preserved in a text dating to ca. 50 A.D. These were priests of Athena, Apollo and Sarapis, each of them donating 10 or 20 trees, but also of Dionysos; the number of trees the latter donated is not given. Other inscriptions of the third century A.D. name Aglochartos as a generous donor of olive trees to Athena that were meant for her precinct on the acropolis at Lindos (IG XII.1.781-783).
Maps Plans Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  J. Bousquet, “Les oliviers de Lindos,” Recueil Plassart, Paris, 1976, pp. 10, 12 (worldcat) D.E. Birge, Sacred Groves in the Ancient Greek World. PhD thesis, University of California, Berkeley, 1982, pp. 183-184. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 590031
TGN ID 7011266
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 15 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Estates</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/annette_guan/rural-estates/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 18:21:32 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/annette_guan/rural-estates/</guid>
      <description>Province Asia
Province Description The region of what is now modern Turkey became a part of the Roman Empire in 133 BCE, when king Attalos III of Pergamum bequeathed his kingdom to the Roman people. The province included the heartland of the Pergamene kingdom as well as the territories of Mysia, Lydia, Ionia, Caria, western Phrygia and the eastern Aegean islands. Under Augustus in 27 BCE Asia was declared a senatorial province and the governance of a proconsul. The capital of the province was Ephesos, although Pergamon may have fulfilled this role initially. Under Diocletian (284-305 CE) the province was subdivided into smaller administrative units: Hellespontus, Asia, Lydia, Caria, Phrygia I and Phrygia II. Due to its excellent harbors on the west coast and its many navigable rivers, Asia’s water-borne trade with the rest of the Mediterranean flourished. In the second century CE Asia experienced great prosperity, to which the growth and architectural aggrandizement of many of its cities attest. In the area of Kibyra, bordering the regions of Lycia, Caria, Phrygia and Pisidia, numerous inscriptions refer to the large imperial estates of Roman families. Woolen textiles, marble, and timber constituted a significant part of the commodities exported from the province.
While the Romans might have looked to the Greeks for inspiration in philosophy, architecture, sculpture, and the fine arts, the non-Greek peoples of the eastern Mediterranean are their inspiration for luxury, fine-living, and the status conferred by displays of individual wealth (Ath. Deip. 15.690). Asia was a center for such splendor, first in the kingdoms of Lydia, Phrygia, and Lycia, and then continued by the Persian satraps, and later the Hellenistic kings. The Persian paradeisos is particularly well attested in literature referencing Asia. That these gardens are known primarily from Roman-period literary sources indicates their continuing influence. For example, long after the gold of Lydia’s Pactolus River had disappeared, Lydia remained a literary topos, not only for copious wealth, but for a life of luxury set in a landscape of natural abundance. Athenaeus (Deip. 12.515d-f) wrote in the second century CE that
 &amp;quot;The Lydians in their luxury planned parks and made them like gardens and so kept in the shade. For they thought it more dainty not to have the sun’s rays touch them at all&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;
 Other districts of Asia captured the Roman imagination: Pliny the Elder writes of an ancient plane tree (Sycamorus orientalis) in Lycia with a girth of sufficient circumference to house a grotto in its hollow trunk, ornamented with pumice and moss with provisions for 18 people to dine there (Plin. HN 12.5).
The paradeisoi of the Persian satraps are of particular influence on the introduction of horti and gardens of Rome. The paradeisos, from the Persian, paira daeza, or “enclosed place,” is a term that had evolved by the Hellenistic period to mean a large enclosed park with luxurious gardens as well as orchards, collections of trees, crops, and hunting areas. It was at Sardis that the Greek Lysander visited Cyrus the Younger, a visit recorded by Klearchos and retold by Xenophon. It is an essential moment in garden history recounted for the Romans by Cicero (Sen. 59). These paradeisoi, in the sense of luxurious orchards, are said by the Romans to have been brought to Greece by Kimon (Aristotole apud Plut. Cim. 10; cf. Cic. de Off. 2.64), and were adopted by Hellenistic kings throughout Greece and southern Italy during the late Hellenistic period. The hunting parks at Daskyleion and Celenae are also vividly described by Xenophon (see An. 1.2.7, 2.4.14 and Oec. 4.13). Xenophon also describes how paradeisoi were occupied or cut down by armies during the fourth and third centuries BCE. Appreciation for these parks apparently continued, and Seleucus of Syria took over the royal paradeisos at Sardis (Plut. Dem. 50). Years of instability followed, so it is difficult to know what the Romans themselves thought of paradeisoi in Asia in the second and first centuries BCE. Notable examples of paradeisoi, in some form, may have been visible to Romans visiting Asia, as well. For example, the Mausoleum at Halicarnassus is now thought by its excavators to have been set in a grove or park.
Thus, the paradeisos, the alsos, the gymnasium, and the quadriporticus are not forms the Romans suddenly “discovered.” They had had a long influence and were integrated into the Hellenistic architectural forms of the Italic landscape. In the second century BCE, however, when the Roman generals began to define themselves as rulers of an empire, they turned directly to the palaces and paradeisoi of the Hellenistic monarchs to establish their power, to display spoils of war, and to create the luxurious setting for life in Rome. They further adapted the evolving quadriporticus form for display to the public
Despite the importance of Asia Minor in the history of the Roman landscape, archaeological evidence is scant. The excavators contacted for the gardens of this region indicated that parks, gardens, and other planted areas have yet to become a subject of research design for the region and finds appear to be few — primarily inscriptions and wall paintings. Most of the smaller domestic courtyards — often the most manageable to investigate — are paved. The larger palaestrae, gymnasia, and enclosed open spaces have not been investigated for landscape architectural and planting features, although recently an important campaign of work in the South Agora at Aphrodisias is setting an important precedent (CROSS-REF). The gardens included in this province include areas with dirt and incomplete paved surfaces, as well as sites where the excavators have some level of optimism that future study may yet reveal more about gardens. The subject of designed landscapes, gardens, and planted areas in Asia Minor remains in its archaeological infancy.
Location Mytilene
Mytilene (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Estates
Keywords  vineyards groves (plant communities) inscription Athenaeus Pliny the Elder Cicero Aristotle Plutarch quadriportici palaestrae gymnasiums  Garden Description The city of Mytilene was located on the island of Lesbos lying off the west coast of Asia Minor. Gardens, vineyards and olive groves in the territory of Mytilene are known from a list on a Roman marble inscription that has survived in several fragments (IG XII.2 76-80). The inscription records an apparent census of property taken at an unknown date. Although vineyards and olive groves are the dominant type of rural property, several gardens are listed in Fragment 78b, some of them recorded as being near a house, or located in a particular spot, or as belonging to a named individual.
Maps Plans Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  IG XII.2 76-80 worldcat  Pleiades ID 550763
TGN ID Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 9 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Temple Garden, Sanctuary of Asklepios</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/annette_guan/temple-garden-sanctuary-of-asklepios/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 18:00:32 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/annette_guan/temple-garden-sanctuary-of-asklepios/</guid>
      <description>Province Asia
Province Description The region of what is now modern Turkey became a part of the Roman Empire in 133 BCE, when king Attalos III of Pergamum bequeathed his kingdom to the Roman people. The province included the heartland of the Pergamene kingdom as well as the territories of Mysia, Lydia, Ionia, Caria, western Phrygia and the eastern Aegean islands. Under Augustus in 27 BCE Asia was declared a senatorial province and the governance of a proconsul. The capital of the province was Ephesos, although Pergamon may have fulfilled this role initially. Under Diocletian (284-305 CE) the province was subdivided into smaller administrative units: Hellespontus, Asia, Lydia, Caria, Phrygia I and Phrygia II. Due to its excellent harbors on the west coast and its many navigable rivers, Asia’s water-borne trade with the rest of the Mediterranean flourished. In the second century CE Asia experienced great prosperity, to which the growth and architectural aggrandizement of many of its cities attest. In the area of Kibyra, bordering the regions of Lycia, Caria, Phrygia and Pisidia, numerous inscriptions refer to the large imperial estates of Roman families. Woolen textiles, marble, and timber constituted a significant part of the commodities exported from the province.
While the Romans might have looked to the Greeks for inspiration in philosophy, architecture, sculpture, and the fine arts, the non-Greek peoples of the eastern Mediterranean are their inspiration for luxury, fine-living, and the status conferred by displays of individual wealth (Ath. Deip. 15.690). Asia was a center for such splendor, first in the kingdoms of Lydia, Phrygia, and Lycia, and then continued by the Persian satraps, and later the Hellenistic kings. The Persian paradeisos is particularly well attested in literature referencing Asia. That these gardens are known primarily from Roman-period literary sources indicates their continuing influence. For example, long after the gold of Lydia’s Pactolus River had disappeared, Lydia remained a literary topos, not only for copious wealth, but for a life of luxury set in a landscape of natural abundance. Athenaeus (Deip. 12.515d-f) wrote in the second century CE that
 &amp;quot;The Lydians in their luxury planned parks and made them like gardens and so kept in the shade. For they thought it more dainty not to have the sun’s rays touch them at all&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;
 Other districts of Asia captured the Roman imagination: Pliny the Elder writes of an ancient plane tree (Sycamorus orientalis) in Lycia with a girth of sufficient circumference to house a grotto in its hollow trunk, ornamented with pumice and moss with provisions for 18 people to dine there (Plin. HN 12.5).
The paradeisoi of the Persian satraps are of particular influence on the introduction of horti and gardens of Rome. The paradeisos, from the Persian, paira daeza, or “enclosed place,” is a term that had evolved by the Hellenistic period to mean a large enclosed park with luxurious gardens as well as orchards, collections of trees, crops, and hunting areas. It was at Sardis that the Greek Lysander visited Cyrus the Younger, a visit recorded by Klearchos and retold by Xenophon. It is an essential moment in garden history recounted for the Romans by Cicero (Sen. 59). These paradeisoi, in the sense of luxurious orchards, are said by the Romans to have been brought to Greece by Kimon (Aristotole apud Plut. Cim. 10; cf. Cic. de Off. 2.64), and were adopted by Hellenistic kings throughout Greece and southern Italy during the late Hellenistic period. The hunting parks at Daskyleion and Celenae are also vividly described by Xenophon (see An. 1.2.7, 2.4.14 and Oec. 4.13). Xenophon also describes how paradeisoi were occupied or cut down by armies during the fourth and third centuries BCE. Appreciation for these parks apparently continued, and Seleucus of Syria took over the royal paradeisos at Sardis (Plut. Dem. 50). Years of instability followed, so it is difficult to know what the Romans themselves thought of paradeisoi in Asia in the second and first centuries BCE. Notable examples of paradeisoi, in some form, may have been visible to Romans visiting Asia, as well. For example, the Mausoleum at Halicarnassus is now thought by its excavators to have been set in a grove or park.
Thus, the paradeisos, the alsos, the gymnasium, and the quadriporticus are not forms the Romans suddenly “discovered.” They had had a long influence and were integrated into the Hellenistic architectural forms of the Italic landscape. In the second century BCE, however, when the Roman generals began to define themselves as rulers of an empire, they turned directly to the palaces and paradeisoi of the Hellenistic monarchs to establish their power, to display spoils of war, and to create the luxurious setting for life in Rome. They further adapted the evolving quadriporticus form for display to the public
Despite the importance of Asia Minor in the history of the Roman landscape, archaeological evidence is scant. The excavators contacted for the gardens of this region indicated that parks, gardens, and other planted areas have yet to become a subject of research design for the region and finds appear to be few — primarily inscriptions and wall paintings. Most of the smaller domestic courtyards — often the most manageable to investigate — are paved. The larger palaestrae, gymnasia, and enclosed open spaces have not been investigated for landscape architectural and planting features, although recently an important campaign of work in the South Agora at Aphrodisias is setting an important precedent (CROSS-REF). The gardens included in this province include areas with dirt and incomplete paved surfaces, as well as sites where the excavators have some level of optimism that future study may yet reveal more about gardens. The subject of designed landscapes, gardens, and planted areas in Asia Minor remains in its archaeological infancy.
Location Kos
Kos (Pleiades)
Garden Temple Garden, Sanctuary of Asklepios
Keywords  sacred groves sanctuary centers (religious centers) inscription Athenaeus Pliny the Elder Cicero Aristotle Plutarch quadriportici palaestrae gymnasiums  Garden Description Inscriptions of the fifth and fourth centuries B.C. record certain regulations for the maintenance of a sacred grove belonging to Asklepios on the island of Kos. Cypress trees are specifically mentioned, and it was unlawful to cut them down or remove wood from the sanctuary. In the mid-first century B.C., however, a Roman prefect by the name of Turullius felled trees in the sanctuary to acquire timber for building ships. Caesar had him executed for this offence (Cassius Dio 51.8.3; Valerius Maximus 1.1.19).
Maps Plans Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  R. Herzog, Heilige Gesetze von Kos, Berlin, 1928, pp. 32-33. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 599728
TGN ID 7012054
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 9 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of C. Octabios Eutyches and Munatios Dionysios</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/annette_guan/tomb-garden-of-c.-octabios-eutyches-and-munatios-dionysios/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 17:46:32 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/annette_guan/tomb-garden-of-c.-octabios-eutyches-and-munatios-dionysios/</guid>
      <description>Province Asia
Province Description The region of what is now modern Turkey became a part of the Roman Empire in 133 BCE, when king Attalos III of Pergamum bequeathed his kingdom to the Roman people. The province included the heartland of the Pergamene kingdom as well as the territories of Mysia, Lydia, Ionia, Caria, western Phrygia and the eastern Aegean islands. Under Augustus in 27 BCE Asia was declared a senatorial province and the governance of a proconsul. The capital of the province was Ephesos, although Pergamon may have fulfilled this role initially. Under Diocletian (284-305 CE) the province was subdivided into smaller administrative units: Hellespontus, Asia, Lydia, Caria, Phrygia I and Phrygia II. Due to its excellent harbors on the west coast and its many navigable rivers, Asia’s water-borne trade with the rest of the Mediterranean flourished. In the second century CE Asia experienced great prosperity, to which the growth and architectural aggrandizement of many of its cities attest. In the area of Kibyra, bordering the regions of Lycia, Caria, Phrygia and Pisidia, numerous inscriptions refer to the large imperial estates of Roman families. Woolen textiles, marble, and timber constituted a significant part of the commodities exported from the province.
While the Romans might have looked to the Greeks for inspiration in philosophy, architecture, sculpture, and the fine arts, the non-Greek peoples of the eastern Mediterranean are their inspiration for luxury, fine-living, and the status conferred by displays of individual wealth (Ath. Deip. 15.690). Asia was a center for such splendor, first in the kingdoms of Lydia, Phrygia, and Lycia, and then continued by the Persian satraps, and later the Hellenistic kings. The Persian paradeisos is particularly well attested in literature referencing Asia. That these gardens are known primarily from Roman-period literary sources indicates their continuing influence. For example, long after the gold of Lydia’s Pactolus River had disappeared, Lydia remained a literary topos, not only for copious wealth, but for a life of luxury set in a landscape of natural abundance. Athenaeus (Deip. 12.515d-f) wrote in the second century CE that
 &amp;quot;The Lydians in their luxury planned parks and made them like gardens and so kept in the shade. For they thought it more dainty not to have the sun’s rays touch them at all&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;
 Other districts of Asia captured the Roman imagination: Pliny the Elder writes of an ancient plane tree (Sycamorus orientalis) in Lycia with a girth of sufficient circumference to house a grotto in its hollow trunk, ornamented with pumice and moss with provisions for 18 people to dine there (Plin. HN 12.5).
The paradeisoi of the Persian satraps are of particular influence on the introduction of horti and gardens of Rome. The paradeisos, from the Persian, paira daeza, or “enclosed place,” is a term that had evolved by the Hellenistic period to mean a large enclosed park with luxurious gardens as well as orchards, collections of trees, crops, and hunting areas. It was at Sardis that the Greek Lysander visited Cyrus the Younger, a visit recorded by Klearchos and retold by Xenophon. It is an essential moment in garden history recounted for the Romans by Cicero (Sen. 59). These paradeisoi, in the sense of luxurious orchards, are said by the Romans to have been brought to Greece by Kimon (Aristotole apud Plut. Cim. 10; cf. Cic. de Off. 2.64), and were adopted by Hellenistic kings throughout Greece and southern Italy during the late Hellenistic period. The hunting parks at Daskyleion and Celenae are also vividly described by Xenophon (see An. 1.2.7, 2.4.14 and Oec. 4.13). Xenophon also describes how paradeisoi were occupied or cut down by armies during the fourth and third centuries BCE. Appreciation for these parks apparently continued, and Seleucus of Syria took over the royal paradeisos at Sardis (Plut. Dem. 50). Years of instability followed, so it is difficult to know what the Romans themselves thought of paradeisoi in Asia in the second and first centuries BCE. Notable examples of paradeisoi, in some form, may have been visible to Romans visiting Asia, as well. For example, the Mausoleum at Halicarnassus is now thought by its excavators to have been set in a grove or park.
Thus, the paradeisos, the alsos, the gymnasium, and the quadriporticus are not forms the Romans suddenly “discovered.” They had had a long influence and were integrated into the Hellenistic architectural forms of the Italic landscape. In the second century BCE, however, when the Roman generals began to define themselves as rulers of an empire, they turned directly to the palaces and paradeisoi of the Hellenistic monarchs to establish their power, to display spoils of war, and to create the luxurious setting for life in Rome. They further adapted the evolving quadriporticus form for display to the public
Despite the importance of Asia Minor in the history of the Roman landscape, archaeological evidence is scant. The excavators contacted for the gardens of this region indicated that parks, gardens, and other planted areas have yet to become a subject of research design for the region and finds appear to be few — primarily inscriptions and wall paintings. Most of the smaller domestic courtyards — often the most manageable to investigate — are paved. The larger palaestrae, gymnasia, and enclosed open spaces have not been investigated for landscape architectural and planting features, although recently an important campaign of work in the South Agora at Aphrodisias is setting an important precedent (CROSS-REF). The gardens included in this province include areas with dirt and incomplete paved surfaces, as well as sites where the excavators have some level of optimism that future study may yet reveal more about gardens. The subject of designed landscapes, gardens, and planted areas in Asia Minor remains in its archaeological infancy.
Location Hypaipa
Hypaipa (Pleiades)
Garden Tomb Garden of C. Octabios Eutyches and Munatios Dionysios
Keywords  stelae periboloi plantation orchard inscription tombs [tomb garden] Athenaeus Pliny the Elder Cicero Aristotle Plutarch quadriportici palaestrae gymnasiums  Garden Description A grave stele set up at Hypaipa by C. Octabios (Octavius) Eutyches from Ephesos, Munatius Dionysius, and several others, sometime probably in the first or second century, declares that “they built this tomb with the garden (peribolos) and its trees around the tomb&amp;rdquo; (lines 1-2: τοῦτο τὸ ἡρῶον κατεσκεύσα[ν] σὺν καὶ τῶ περιβόλω | καὶ τοῖς δένδρεσιν αὐτοῦ τοῖς περὶ τὸ ἡρῶον). Here, as regularly in Lydia and often elsewhere in Asia Minor, the garden itself (in this case perhaps a plantation or orchard) is referred to metonymically by its perimeter wall (peribolos).
Maps Plans Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  PJ. Keil and A. von Premerstein, Bericht über eine dritte Reise in Lydien. Vienna, 1914, no. 108 (worldcat) J. Kubińska, Les monuments funéraires dans les inscriptions grecques de l’Asie Mineure. Warsaw, 1968, p. 146. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 550585
TGN ID 5004366
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 9 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>