<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/hispania_tarraconensis/sagunto/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/hispania_tarraconensis/sagunto/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Tomb garden and baths of P. Caecil(ius) Rufus and Valeria </title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/hispania_tarraconensis/sagunto/hispania_tomb-garden_xw/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/hispania_tarraconensis/sagunto/hispania_tomb-garden_xw/</guid>
      <description>Province Sagunto Sagunto (Pleiades)
Location Saguntum
Saguntum/Arse (Pleiades)
Garden Tomb garden and baths of P. Caecil(ius) Rufus and Valeria
Keywords  tombs  Garden Description A marble slab found at Puçol (Puzol) near Saguntum, now lost, but originally preserving an epitaph of the late first or early second century set up by P. Caecil(ius) Rufus for himself and his wife Valeria, records that they purchased an area (locus) vaulted over with walls, baths (a notable amenity at a tomb), and gardens and constructed a monument there for themselves and their daughters, to the end that their ashes be mingled with those of their ancestors (se vivis compararunt locum uti est concameratum parietib(us), balneis, hortis; monumentum construxerunt sibi et filiabus donec avitis cineribus immisceantur). For the identification of the couple and the approximate date, see Alföldy in CIL.
Maps Plans Images Bibliography  H. von Hesberg, “Römische Grabbauten in den hispanischen Provinzen” in W. Trimllmich et al., eds., Hispania Antiqua. Denkmäler der Römerzeit (Mainz 1993) XXX; EDH HD026300. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 266021
Publication date 20 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
