<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Le Mans on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/categories/le-mans/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Le Mans on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/categories/le-mans/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>House on the Place des Halles (La maison des Halles)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/house_on_the_place_des_halles_la_maison_des_halles/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/house_on_the_place_des_halles_la_maison_des_halles/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location &amp;ndash; missing in Pleiades &amp;ndash; VINDINUM a.k.a. Subdinnum (Le Mans, France)
VINDINUM a.k.a. Subdinnum (Pleiades)
Sublocation Description On the left bank of the Sarthe, where it is joined by the Isaac creek, the Roman town was the successor to a Celtic oppidum. A wall of the late empire enclosed nine hectares.
Garden House on the Place des Halles (La maison des Halles)
Keywords  domus courtyard  Garden Description LUG 6.1.1: Le Mans. House on the Place des Halles. From CAG.
This domus was on the Place des Halles, the former site of the covered market place. It was excavated in 1987-88 south of the principal street. In a part of the ancient city inhabited since the first century, the house occupied a surface (33 x 54 m) of 1782 square meters. Two-story wings of the house surround on three sides a courtyard [1] that may have been a garden. The residential wing, to the south, of careful construction, had four principal rooms with floors of smooth concrete. The existence of a second court farther south, on the other façade of the residential wing has been supposed, but its nature is unknown.
Maps Plans   Restored section of the entire domus by P. André   Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Service Régional de l’Archéologie des Pays de la Loire, La Sarthe, 72, CAG p. 318-319, plan p. 318. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 109236
TGN ID 6003548
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
