<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/aferica_proconsularis/xue_xia/sufetula/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 10:39:31 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/aferica_proconsularis/xue_xia/sufetula/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Seasons (La maison des Saisons)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/aferica_proconsularis/xue_xia/sufetula/house-of-the-seasons/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/aferica_proconsularis/xue_xia/sufetula/house-of-the-seasons/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa Proconsularis
Location Sufetula
Sufetula (Pleiades)
Location Description Sufetula founded under Vespasian was a center of oil production. Excavations have shown that the city was laid out on a grid plan that was not strictly followed. Numerous buildings have been uncovered among them the forum, the capitol, the triumphal gateway dedicated to Antonius Pius, a triumphal arc of the Tetrarchy, the Great baths, the theater and the episcopal group that comprised two large basilicas called Vitalis and Bellator, which are separated from each other by the Jucundus Chapel. Annexes, among them, small baths and probably the dwellings of the clergy, surround this complex.
Garden House of the Seasons
Keywords  oeci peristyles (columnades) peristyles (Roman courtyards)  Garden Description This house, known for its majestic and richly decorated oecus, is laidout around a peristyle courtyard that was probably planted. The house is dated to the late IVth. early Vth. Century (Plan view, Fig. 1).
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the House of the Seasons. (Rights statement)   Images Dates The house is dated to the late IVth. early Vth. Century
Bibliography  D. Parrish, &amp;ldquo;The Mosaic of Xenophon from Sbeitla&amp;rdquo;, Mosaïque, Recueil d’hommages à Henri Stern, Paris, 1982, pp. 297-306, pl. CXCV. 1. (worldcat) A.Merlin in BCTH, 1910, p. CXCVI-CXCVII. (worldcat) N. Duval, F. Baratte, Les ruines de Sufetula Sbeïtla, Tunis, 1973, p. 65-69, fig. 44. (worldcat) D. Parrish, The Seasons mosaics of Roman North Africa, Rome, 1984, p. 215-218. (worldcat) Bullo, S. and F. Ghedini, Amplissimae atque ornatissimae domus: l&amp;rsquo;edilizia residenziale nelle citta della Tunisia roman, Rome: Edizioni Quasar, 2003, p. 201-202. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 324816
TGN ID 7001754
Contributor Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>