<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>villa on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/villa/</link>
    <description>Recent content in villa on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/villa/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Funerary Chamber of Manlia Felicitas</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_appia/funerary_chamber_of_manlia_felicitas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_appia/funerary_chamber_of_manlia_felicitas/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location VIA APPIA Funerary Chamber of Manlia Felicitas
Sublocation Via Appia
Sublocation Description An early Roman road (via publica) originating at Rome and terminating at Brundisium, the Via Appia was begun in the fourth century B.C. by the censor Appius Claudius Caecus. The Latin author Statius described the Via Appia as &amp;ldquo;queen of the long roads&amp;rdquo;.
Garden Funerary Chamber of Manlia Felicitas
Keywords  villa tombs funerary buildings  Garden Description In 1937 a French student, Louis Vignon, searching for new catacombs around the third mile of the Via Appia near the tomb of Caecilia Metella, discovered a subterranean funerary chamber accessible via a descending stair that ended at a landing which opened perpendicularly into the middle of one of its walls. Each of the other three walls contained an arcosolium decorated with frescoes depicting animal and vegetal life against a background of herbs and flowers beneath hanging garlands punctuated by aquatic fowl, doves, and the heads of youths; beneath the frescoes the lower walls were paneled in polychrome marble. The figured scenes—at the back, opposite the entrance, a pair of peacocks flanking a niche; to the left a pair of Cupids draping a gazelle in a long ribbon; to the right a pair of gazelles on either side of a twisted tree—belong to a stock of Hellenistic motifs evocative of the gardens of the blessed popular at Rome during the Julio-Claudian period and, especially, the reign of Augustus, to which Wuillemier thought the monument belonged. When Vignon returned to the site thirteen years later, the underground chamber could not be located, but at the edge of the site, near an ancient aedicula fronting the Via Appia, he found a marble funerary inscription in a pile of broken stones evidently recovered from a second subterranean room beneath the aedicula. Underground galleries extending off the subterranean room and from the intersection at the entrance to the tomb chamber seemed to Vignon to join the two structures to each other in a large subterranean complex (Fig. XXX). The inscription (AE 1952, 35)—an epitaph to a freedwoman Manlia Felicitas set up by her fellow freedman and husband of thirty-five years, P. Manlius Epigonus, her daughter Manlia Flora, and her daughter’s husband L. Calpurnius Servatus—declares that the “twenty-fourth part” (pars semunciaria) (either of the entire estate or of an acre, about 40 meters square) “in these gardens of the Manlii” (in his hortis Manlianis) entrusted by Manlia Salvilla (evidently the patroness of Epigonus and Felicitas) to Epigonus for him to hand over to Felicitas, Felicitas had wanted to belong to their daughter Flora. It is uncertain whether “these Manlian gardens” refer to a tomb garden proper or to a suburban estate (horti): both are well attested in conjunction with suburban tombs (see vol. 1, 208). Reference to a “twenty-fourth part”, the (indirect) involvement of the patroness Salvilla, and the early imperial fashion of styling suburban estates as “gardens” named after their owners (regularly expressed in adjectival form) here favor the latter. Whether the inscription, which in form and formula appears not later than the second century, can be put into any direct relation with the subterranean chamber with arcosoli, a tomb type more characteristic of the fourth century, remains doubtful. But the discovery of both on the same property perhaps suggests a continuous use of the site as a funerary space for two centuries.
Dates 130CE
Bibliography   J. Bodel, Roman Tomb Gardens, Cambridge University Press, 2018, p. 208-209. link
  P. Wuilleumier , Sur la Voie Appienne: Les horti Manliani, Comptes rendus des séances de l&amp;rsquo;Académie des Inscriptions et Belles-Lettres,1951, 34-41; Archaiologike Ephemeris, 1952, 35; Quilici 1977: 39 (horti Manliani) worldcat
  G.-L. Gregori , Horti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, Bullettino della Commissione Archeologica Comunale di Roma BCom 92 (1987-88) [1989]: 180 n. 35, 185. worldcat
  Pleiades ID 990721366
Contributor John Bodel
Publication date 01 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Temple Tomb Garden of Q. Haterius Tychicus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_labicana/temple_tomb_garden_of_q._haterius_tychicus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_labicana/temple_tomb_garden_of_q._haterius_tychicus/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Via Labicana Temple Tomb Garden of Q. Haterius Tychicus
Sublocation Via Labicana
Sublocation Description An ancient Roman road connecting Rome and Labicum.
Garden Temple Tomb Garden of Q. Haterius Tychicus
Keywords  funerary buildings sepulchral monuments tombs villa garden pavilions  Garden Description One of the well-known reliefs from the tomb monument of the Haterii found in 1848 at a villa site after the fourth mile of the Via Labicana and depicting the temple tomb they adorned seems to represent schematically a garden and ornamental pavilion (diaeta) enclosed by a perimeter wall or fence in front of the tomb (Fig. XXX). The property evidently belonged to a building contractor, probably the redemptor Q. Haterius Tychicus (CIL 6.607, perhaps a freedman of Q. Haterius Antoninus, the consul of 53 CE), who participated in several prominent public building projects during the Flavian era and who erected his monument (to judge from the style of the relief decoration) during the Trajanic period. The tomb itself, built on an inset tufa base c. 3.5 meters square, partly out of peperino blocks, partly in reticulate work, and partly with brickwork, is almost wholly destroyed. In 1970, about ten meters from the tomb, new excavations at the site unearthed a dedication to Silvanus set up by two Q. Haterii (AE 1982, 78), probably at the boundary of the funerary garden represented in the relief by the enclosed pavilion. In the same garden was found the so-called urn of the Haterii, in all likelihood an elaborately sculpted fountain base.
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  G.-L. Gregori, Horti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, Bullettino della Commissione Archeologica Comunale di Roma worldcat  -F. Sinn and K. S. Freyberger, Vatikansiche Museen: Museo Gregorio Profano ex Lateranense: Dir Grabdenkmäler 2: Die Ausstatung des Hateriusgrabes, (Mainz 1996) 45-51, no. 5 (pl. 7, figs. 8-10). worldcat
Pleiades ID 229438406
Contributor John Bodel
Publication date 01 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Garden restaurant in market garden or workshop (II.iii.7/9) . </title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_iii/house7_9/ii.iii.7_9/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_iii/house7_9/ii.iii.7_9/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region II
House Market garden or workshop in Pompeii Region II (II.iii.7/9) (https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/243620947)
Garden Garden restaurant in market garden or workshop (II.iii.7/9)
Keywords  tables (support furniture) villa  Garden Description This garden restaurant was strategically located across from the Palaestra. It occupied most of the southern part of this insula and had a masonry triclinium (l. medius, 4.90 m.; l. imus and summus 4.50 m.), a round table 1.00 m. in dia. and a square table 0.90 x 0.90.
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography   Jashemski, Wilhelmina F, The Gardens of Pompeii, Herculaneum, and the Villas Destroyed by Vesuvius, New Rochelle: Aristide D. Caratzas, 1979. Print , 1:176; worldcat
  Idem, The Gardens of Pompeii, Herculaneum, and the Villas Destroyed by Vesuvius,, vol.II, p. 85. worldcat
  Della, Corte M. Case Ed Abitanti Di Pompei. Pompei-scavi: M. Della Corte, 1954. Print. worldcat
  Pleiades ID 243620947
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 2 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Venus Marina; Casa Della Venere in Conchiglia (II.iii.3)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_iii/house_3/ii.iii.3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_iii/house_3/ii.iii.3/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region II
House Casa della Venere in conchiglia; House of Venus Marina(II.iii.3)
Garden Peristyle Garden
Keywords  architectural paintings villa peristyles (Roman courtyards)  Garden Description Redecorating had been just completed to this site at the time of the eruption and here was found the best preserved garden paintings in Pompeii. Nine stuccoed columns, gold below, fluted white above, supported a portico on the west, north and part of the east sides of this peristyle garden (a) at the rear of the house. A gutter ran along the portico at the edge of the garden. Fig. 9, 50.35.64 Garden paintings decorated the outside walls of the sitting room (diaeta) (b), the small room (c) extending into the garden on the east, and the little room in the southeast corner of the garden. The long rear wall was in full view of the grand triclinium and so the paintings here were the focal point of the garden. Yellow bands separate the wall into three panels and a golden lattice fence on a black background extends across the base. On the left panel a poorly rendered statue of Mars stands on a pedestal in front of the fence. The garden painting behind this is painted on a blue background with an ivy garland framing the top and sides. The left side of the panel shows an oleander with pink blossoms, a myrtle with white blossoms and a heron (Ardea cinerea L.) standing on the fence. Then comes a slender and tall tree-like bush with a large yellow bird, perhaps an oriole, perched within, followed by another oleander in bloom, a pine with a song thrush (Turdus philomelos C.L.Brehm) eating a berry and another bird flying overhead. There is an oleander behind the statue of Mars, to the right a myrtle, a tall slender tree with yellow fruit, more oleanders, and another heron standing in front of an unidentified plant. Three more birds are painted, one hanging upside down like a titmouse to reach some berries (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, figs., 1, 103, 204, on pp. ii, 64 and 129). There is a mask at the center of the top (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, figs. 1, 101 and 204 on pp. ii, 62 and 129). Fig. 10, 18.36.59 Venus is featured on the large central panel floating on a seashell and accompanied by two amorini, one of which is riding a dolphin (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, figs. 101 and 203 on pp. 62 and 128). A narrow brown band runs around the side and top of this panel which dominates the garden. The right side panel is similar to the left one with a blue background, ivy garlands, and a mask in the center at the top (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, fig. 102 on p. 63). The images counted from the left are as follows; a myrtle bush with white flowers and a large bird above it, a clump of ivy in front of this with white flowers, then a tall slender oleander in bloom and another large bird perched on it, next a myrtle with a heron in front standing on the fence, a plant with fern-like foliage and finally a rosebush in bloom. The center of the panel features a basin-shaped, footed fountain on a pedestal in front of the fence. Water is spouting from the center and a bird is perched drinking on the left side rim with a pigeon on the opposing rim. Far into the background behind the fountain is a tree with graceful branches. A myrtle and an oleander with a gray shrike perched on it are painted to the right of the fountain along with another heron walking on the fence, a tall slender apple tree with yellow fruit, and a myrtle with a clump of ivy in front. Inserted into the border of the right panel is a small niche lararium decorated with green plants. Fig.11, 17.19.59, Fig. 12, 50.26.64, Fig. 13, 54.3.64 The outside walls of the small room which extends into the southeast corner of the garden are golden yellow with a red-brown border. The top had an ivy garland, the center caught up with a shield on the south wall and with a helmet on the east. The south wall painting features a two handled, footed egg-shaped fountain standing on a pedestal in front of the fence. It is decorated with three standing figures in high relief, and has a water jet in the center. Directly behind the fountain in back of the fence are a tall slender bush in bloom and a rose bush in flower to the left. There is a bird perching in this bush and a song thrush flying to the right towards a low shrub-like tree with fruit (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, fig. 104 on p. 65). The east wall painting is located to the left of the door with the main feature being a graceful two-handled crater fountain standing on a rectangular pedestal in front of the lattice fence (Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, fig. 104 on p. 64). Behind the jetting fountain and the fence is a pine tree (Pinus sp.) with a large wood pigeon (Columba palumbus L.) perched on the top and a large bird flying towards the tree from either side. Low bushes fill the background. A soft green background is used in the garden paintings on the outside walls of the sitting room and the adjacent small room projecting into the garden on the east. The lattice fence is painted along the base and the panel is outlined with bands of red-brown. A bird perches on the right side of a footed, bowl-shaped, square rimmed fountain in the only portion of the south wall painting that remains. Fig. 14, 51.35.64 The fountain stands behind the lattice fence in the center of the panel and to the left just above are some yellow-orange flowers, difficult to identify, with oleanders and some other badly damaged flowers in the background. Daisies are painted to the left of the fountain and part of a tall bush with a little bird survived on the right edge of the panel. A belvedere window that looks out into the garden from the sitting room interrupts two of the panels on the east wall. Both panels have lost the top portion while little remains of the left panel. All that can be discerned here is a footed, bowl-shaped fountain with a bird on the right rim standing behind the fence in a garden of unidentified plants. On the right side panel an elaborate bowl-shaped fountain spouts water behind the fence with two birds perched on the rim, a brown bird on the left and a lighter colored one on the right. The garden behind the fence has a small tree with apple-like fruits on the left and a pomegranate tree directly behind the fountain. To the right is a myrtle in bloom and them one more tall bush (Jashemski, Gardens¸vol. 1, fig. 106 on p. 66). In the foreground are several roses and an ivy mound to the left of the fountain and what could have been another ivy bush to the right. Fig. 15, 22.15.66
Plans   garden paintings detail 1.     garden paintings detail - bird and plant.     overview garden paintings 1.     overview garden paintings 2.     overview garden paintings 3.     painting remains.     painting of garden.   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography   Jashemski, Wilhelmina F, The Gardens of Pompeii, Herculaneum, and the Villas Destroyed by Vesuvius, New Rochelle: Aristide D. Caratzas, 1979. Print , 1:63-66, 128-129 and fig. 1 on p. ii, figs. 101-106 on pp. 62-66, figs. 203 and 204 on pp. 128, 129; worldcat
  Jashemski, Wilhelmina F, and Stanley A. Jashemski, The Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the Villas Destroyed by Vesuvius. New Rochelle, NY: Caratzas, 1993. Print. pp. 84, 330-331worldcat
  Maiuri, Pompei, Roma: Roma, 1986. Print. p. 83-84worldcat
  Maiuri, Rome Painting,, pp. 7, 125;worldcat
  Michel, Dorothea, Pompejanische Gartenmalereien, Mainz am Rhein: P. von Zabern, 1978. Print. pp. 7, 125; worldcat
  Orr, David G.Roman Domestic Religion: A Study of the Roman Household Deities and Their Shrines at Pompeii and Herculaneum, Ann Arbor, Mich: UMI, 1999. Print.pp. 399-400;worldcat
  Schefold, Karl.Wände Pompejis: Topographisches Verzeichnis Der Bildmotive. Berlin: Gruyter, Walter de, &amp;amp; Co, 1957. Print. worldcat
  Pleiades ID 425769173
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 2 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Large Garden in House 4-6 in Pompeii Region II (II.iii.4-6)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_iii/house4_6/ii.iii.4-6b/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_iii/house4_6/ii.iii.4-6b/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region II
House House 4-6 in Pompeii Region II
Garden Large Garden in House 4-6 in Pompeii Region II (II.iii.4-6)
Keywords  villa courtyards  Garden Description B. The small garden to the rear of house 4 had an entrance into this large open area (b) which had been planted at the time of the eruption. There was a second entrance (6) from the side street. At the time of excavation a cistern was noted in the southwest corner, a basin along the south wall just before the jog, and the presence of seven root cavities. Jashemski found a few other scattered root cavities later, but too much damage had occurred from new growth to determine the original planting plan. At the east end of the north wall a door opened to a small sacellum with an aedicula lararium on a small podium on the rear wall and a small masonry. Fig.16, 17.18.59
Plans   garden paintings detail 1.   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography   Jashemski, Wilhelmina F, and Stanley A. Jashemski, The Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the Villas Destroyed by Vesuvius. New Rochelle, NY: Caratzas, 1993. Print. pp. 84-85 worldcat
  Orr, David G.Roman Domestic Religion: A Study of the Roman Household Deities and Their Shrines at Pompeii and Herculaneum, Ann Arbor, Mich: UMI, 1999. Print.pp. 399-400;worldcat
  Pleiades ID 998787235
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 2 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Narrow garden in the house of Messius Ampliatus (II.ii.4)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_ii/house_4/ii.ii.4b/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_ii/house_4/ii.ii.4b/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region II
House House of Messius Ampliatus(II.ii.4))
Garden Narrow garden in the house of Messius Ampliatus (II.ii.4)
Keywords  villa courtyards  Garden Description B. The east portico gave access to the narrow garden (b) to the back of the house.
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography   Jashemski, Wilhelmina F, ‘The Garden of Hercules at Pompeii’ (II.viii.6): The Discovery of a Commercial Flower Garden.,American Journal of Archaeology, vol. 83, no. 4, 1979, pp. 403–411. [link](https://www.jstor.org/stable/504139. Accessed 2 Dec. 2020.)
  Spinazzola, Vittorio, and Salvatore Aurigemma, Pompei Alla Luce Degli Scavi Nuovi Di Via Dell&amp;rsquo;abbondanza (anni 1910-1923), Roma: Libreria dello Stato, 1953. Print. map after p. 376 where this garden is labeled hortus.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 433204
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 4 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Peristyle garden in house of Messius Ampliatus (II.ii.4) </title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_ii/house_4/ii.ii.4a/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_ii/house_4/ii.ii.4a/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region II
House House of Messius Ampliatus(II.ii.4))
Garden Peristyle garden in house of Messius Ampliatus (II.ii.4)
Keywords  villa courtyards  Garden Description A. The portico which bordered the peristyle garden (a) on the north and east side was accessed from the entrance hall. This site had been extensively damaged prior to excavation.
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography   Della, Corte M, Case Ed Abitanti Di Pompei, Pompei-scavi: M. Della Corte, 1954. Print. worldcat
  Jashemski, Wilhelmina F, ‘The Garden of Hercules at Pompeii’ (II.viii.6): The Discovery of a Commercial Flower Garden.,American Journal of Archaeology, vol. 83, no. 4, 1979, pp. 403–411. [link](https://www.jstor.org/stable/504139. Accessed 2 Dec. 2020.)
  Pleiades ID 634179974
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 2 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Small Garden House 4-6 in Pompeii Region II (II.iii.4-6). </title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_iii/house4_6/ii.iii.4-6a/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_iii/house4_6/ii.iii.4-6a/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region II
House House 4-6 in Pompeii Region II
Garden Small Garden House 4-6 in Pompeii Region II
Keywords  statuettes (free-standing sculpture) tufa villa  Garden Description A. A small garden (a) at the rear of this connected house and caupona may have originally contained the two small statuettes found at this site in 1953. The two pieces were a headless ithyphallic tufa statuette (0.33 m. high with base; Pompeii inv. no. 10017) and a marble statuette of Venus (0.51 m. high without base; Pompeii inv. no. 9926) with much of the red color preserved in the drapery. The Inventory Books list this house as II.vi.4.
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Jashemski, Wilhelmina F, and Stanley A. Jashemski, The Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the Villas Destroyed by Vesuvius. New Rochelle, NY: Caratzas, 1993. Print. pp. 84 worldcat  Pleiades ID 998787235
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 2 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Gardens of Sperlonga. The peristyle garden </title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/sperlonga/the-cryptoporticus-and-the-terrace/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/sperlonga/the-cryptoporticus-and-the-terrace/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Italia Villa Tiberii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Sperlonga
Sublocation Description Sperlonga is a maritime villa built at the end of the Roman Republic. It probably belonged to some very rich piscinarius, one of those extremely wealthy Roman patricians who took delight in creating their own fish ponds. The purpose might have been to always find fresh fish at their disposal, or, at least, so they said. Actually those Tritones piscinarum, as Cicero called them (CIC. Att. 2.1.6; 2.9.1), considered their piscinae more a status symbol than an industrial operation, and cherished their fishes more as pets than as tasty tidbits (VARR. r. r. 3.17.3). Sperlonga, with its lavish decoration and its luxurious setting, was built by one of these tycoons. Built, yes, but by whom? When, in the middle of the last century, this villa was discovered, some scholars decided that it must have been Tiberius. Actually the only connection we could establish between the ancient emperor and this place is the fact that he nearly died while dining in the villa&amp;rsquo;s colossal nymphaeum. At this time he was traveling from Capri to Rome and stopped at Sperlonga to rest. We read that he was there, on a small island set at the center of the fishpond, laying with his friends on mattresses placed around an elegant water triclinium (Fig. 91, A) set on a small island at the center of the fishpond. They were drinking, chatting and enjoying the splendid view of the statuary groups displayed in the nymphaeum when the entrance of the grotto crashed down in a historical landslide reported by both Suetonius (Tib. 39) and Tacitus (ann. 4.59) (Fig. 92). I can&amp;rsquo;t imagine how this unfortunate dinner could place Tiberius as the owner and the creator of the spectacular grotto. However this is what some scholars assert and they still believe it. I can&amp;rsquo;t agree. For one thing we know that Tiberius disapproved of luxury. In Tacitus (TACITUS) we find the transcription of some of his speeches to the senate and we notice how harshly he attacked all the people who built luxurious villas and bought expensive statues to put in them. How could Tiberius censor his fellows countrymen for purchasing some marble copies of goddesses and heroes, while he himself was importing from Greece those monumental Hellenistic groups, and setting them in the seaside grotto of a more than sumptuous maritime residence? It was not logical, and for this reason we feel quite certain that Tiberius had no part in creating the Sperlongan art display. However, are we sure that the villa didn&amp;rsquo;t belong to the imperial praedia? No, we can&amp;rsquo;t even deny this: Sperlonga could have entered Augustus&amp;rsquo; estate through a legacy. As a matter of fact we know that, on their death, many rich men used to leave their property to the emperor. Some of these tycoons and also some relatives of the Julio-Claudian family could easily have done this. We can&amp;rsquo;t even forget that - as reported by Cicero (CIC. I cent. B.C.) - Philip, Augustus&amp;rsquo; stepfather, was one of the most important and rich piscinarii of the I cent B.C. Apart from this we can&amp;rsquo;t say anything more.
Garden The villa has three gardens: one peristyle garden, one cryptoporticus and the terrace on the sea, one nymphaeum.
Keywords  villa courtyards terrace gardens  Garden Description These parts of the villa have been relatively spared and they are among the best features of this maritime residence (SALZA PRINA RICOTTI 2002). As a matter of fact, also when the peristyle garden was flourishing, it could never have been as impressive as this imposing cryptoporticus and its underlying terrace (Fig. 93, B), beautiful places to stroll and admire the glorious sunset. The combination of a cryptoporticus and a terrace to create a new kind of garden, was already present in Roman architecture. We can see it depicted in the Pompeian frescoes and we find it in other seaside villas. For instance this kind of open-air arrangement was extensively described in a letter in which Pliny the Younger pointed out the highlights of his cherished Laurentine villa to one of his friend (PLIN. epist. 2.17). In Sperlonga as in Pliny&amp;rsquo;s terrace, a narrow border of flowering plants was set against a low masonry wall, a parapet which was necessary to protect the vegetation from the salty sea breezes (Fig. 94). Today, the fact that bunches of blossoms existed there is confirmed by the presence of a watering system which started from some spring set high on the overhanging hill. We can follow the trace of a groove cut in the rock coming down to the fishpond&amp;rsquo;s northeastern bank. From the piscina side, through a canal (Figs. 91, S; 96), the water was led up to the low parapet of the terrace (Fig. 97), and here, turning at a right angle, it ran all along it. At regular intervals, a series of drain wells helped to draw the water and irrigate the plants. Their presence confirm that a flowerbed existed there and that it was set against the wall.
Plans   the plan of Sperlonga&amp;#39;s Villa.   Images   the general garden plan of Sperlonga.     The landslide.     Cryptoporch and terrace.     Terrace&amp;#39;s parapet.   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography -B. ANDREAE, A. CONTICELLO, H. SCHROTELER, D. WUNDERLICH, Abformung der Polyphemgruppe von Sperlonga, in GfK nach einem neuen Verfahren, Der Präparaator 16, 1-2 (1970), pp. 1-000 worldcat
-F. COARELLI, Sperlonga e Tiberio, DArch 7 (1973), pp. 97-122 worldcat
-A. CONTICELLO, B. ANDREAE, Die Skulpturen von Sperlonga, Antike Plastik 14, Berlin 1974, pp. 000-000 worldcat
-G. JACOPI, L’antro di Tiberio a Sperlonga (Istituto di Studi Romani), Roma 1963 worldcat
-SALZA PRINA RICOTTI, Il gruppo di Polifemo a Sperlonga - Problemi di sistemazione, RendPontAcc 42 (1968-1970), pp. 118-134, tavv. 1-3, figg. 5-9 [worldcat]http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/849270161
-SALZA PRINA RICOTTI, The Importance of Water in Roman Garden Triclinia,in Ancient Roman Villa Gardens (Dumbarton Oaks Research Library and Collection), Dumbarton Oaks 1987, pp. 137-184 [worldcat]http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/715121487
-SALZA PRINA RICOTTI, Sistemazione paesaggistica del fronte a mare e giardini nelle ville marittime di epoca romana, in Giornate di studio in occasione del 250º anniversario degli Scavi di Stabia (in print), pp. 137-169. worldcat
Pleiades ID 433204
TGN ID Contributor EUGENIA SALZA PRINA RICOTTI
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Gardens of Sperlonga. The peristyle garden </title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/sperlonga/the-gardens-of-sperlonga.-the-peristyle-garden/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/sperlonga/the-gardens-of-sperlonga.-the-peristyle-garden/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Italia
Villa Tiberii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Sperlonga
Sublocation Description Sperlonga is a maritime villa built at the end of the Roman Republic. It probably belonged to some very rich piscinarius, one of those extremely wealthy Roman patricians who took delight in creating their own fish ponds. The purpose might have been to always find fresh fish at their disposal, or, at least, so they said. Actually those Tritones piscinarum, as Cicero called them (CIC. Att. 2.1.6; 2.9.1), considered their piscinae more a status symbol than an industrial operation, and cherished their fishes more as pets than as tasty tidbits (VARR. r. r. 3.17.3). Sperlonga, with its lavish decoration and its luxurious setting, was built by one of these tycoons. Built, yes, but by whom? When, in the middle of the last century, this villa was discovered, some scholars decided that it must have been Tiberius. Actually the only connection we could establish between the ancient emperor and this place is the fact that he nearly died while dining in the villa&amp;rsquo;s colossal nymphaeum. At this time he was traveling from Capri to Rome and stopped at Sperlonga to rest. We read that he was there, on a small island set at the center of the fishpond, laying with his friends on mattresses placed around an elegant water triclinium (Fig. 91, A) set on a small island at the center of the fishpond. They were drinking, chatting and enjoying the splendid view of the statuary groups displayed in the nymphaeum when the entrance of the grotto crashed down in a historical landslide reported by both Suetonius (Tib. 39) and Tacitus (ann. 4.59) (Fig. 92). I can&amp;rsquo;t imagine how this unfortunate dinner could place Tiberius as the owner and the creator of the spectacular grotto. However this is what some scholars assert and they still believe it. I can&amp;rsquo;t agree. For one thing we know that Tiberius disapproved of luxury. In Tacitus (TACITUS) we find the transcription of some of his speeches to the senate and we notice how harshly he attacked all the people who built luxurious villas and bought expensive statues to put in them. How could Tiberius censor his fellows countrymen for purchasing some marble copies of goddesses and heroes, while he himself was importing from Greece those monumental Hellenistic groups, and setting them in the seaside grotto of a more than sumptuous maritime residence? It was not logical, and for this reason we feel quite certain that Tiberius had no part in creating the Sperlongan art display. However, are we sure that the villa didn&amp;rsquo;t belong to the imperial praedia? No, we can&amp;rsquo;t even deny this: Sperlonga could have entered Augustus&amp;rsquo; estate through a legacy. As a matter of fact we know that, on their death, many rich men used to leave their property to the emperor. Some of these tycoons and also some relatives of the Julio-Claudian family could easily have done this. We can&amp;rsquo;t even forget that - as reported by Cicero (CIC. I cent. B.C.) - Philip, Augustus&amp;rsquo; stepfather, was one of the most important and rich piscinarii of the I cent B.C. Apart from this we can&amp;rsquo;t say anything more.
Garden The villa has three gardens: one peristyle garden, one cryptoporticus and the terrace on the sea, one nymphaeum.
Keywords  villa courtyards peristyles (Roman courtyards)  Garden Description In the villa there are three different garden arrangements (SALZA PRINA RICOTTI 1990). Unluckily (Fig. 93) all its quarters have been badly damaged by a colony of monks who, probably toward 800 A.D., established themselves and their peasants there. All this people excavated a well in the peristyle, created a tank to wash their linens, moved and demolished many of the portico&amp;rsquo;s columns, and set mangers for the animals in the elegant rooms of the villa. Moreover the family of peasants who tilled the monastery&amp;rsquo;s fields divided this lordly mansion in 8 lodgings. Due to these transformations, today it is nearly impossible to find how the original peristyle looked at its heydays. We can only see the bases of the portico&amp;rsquo;s columns and the remains of what probably was a nice nymphaeum, which, set on the north-eastern part of the courtyard (Fig. 93, N), occupied a large hall, 9 m long and 4.5 m wide, with a semicircular absid at the end. A square basin, 2 x 2 m, stood near the entrance. Apart from this there is nothing else left.
Maps Plans   the plan of Sperlonga&amp;#39;s Villa.   Images   the general garden plan of Sperlonga.     The landslide.   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography -B. ANDREAE, A. CONTICELLO, H. SCHROTELER, D. WUNDERLICH, Abformung der Polyphemgruppe von Sperlonga, in GfK nach einem neuen Verfahren, Der Präparaator 16, 1-2 (1970), pp. 1-000 worldcat
-F. COARELLI, Sperlonga e Tiberio, DArch 7 (1973), pp. 97-122 worldcat
-A. CONTICELLO, B. ANDREAE, Die Skulpturen von Sperlonga, Antike Plastik 14, Berlin 1974, pp. 000-000 worldcat
-G. JACOPI, L’antro di Tiberio a Sperlonga (Istituto di Studi Romani), Roma 1963 worldcat
-SALZA PRINA RICOTTI, Il gruppo di Polifemo a Sperlonga - Problemi di sistemazione, RendPontAcc 42 (1968-1970), pp. 118-134, tavv. 1-3, figg. 5-9 [worldcat]http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/849270161
-SALZA PRINA RICOTTI, The Importance of Water in Roman Garden Triclinia,in Ancient Roman Villa Gardens (Dumbarton Oaks Research Library and Collection), Dumbarton Oaks 1987, pp. 137-184 [worldcat]http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/715121487
-SALZA PRINA RICOTTI, Sistemazione paesaggistica del fronte a mare e giardini nelle ville marittime di epoca romana, in Giornate di studio in occasione del 250º anniversario degli Scavi di Stabia (in print), pp. 137-169. worldcat
Pleiades ID 433204
Contributor EUGENIA SALZA PRINA RICOTTI
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Gardens of Sperlonga. The peristyle garden </title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/sperlonga/the-nymphaeum/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/sperlonga/the-nymphaeum/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Italia Villa Tiberii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Sperlonga
Sublocation Description Sperlonga is a maritime villa built at the end of the Roman Republic. It probably belonged to some very rich piscinarius, one of those extremely wealthy Roman patricians who took delight in creating their own fish ponds. The purpose might have been to always find fresh fish at their disposal, or, at least, so they said. Actually those Tritones piscinarum, as Cicero called them (CIC. Att. 2.1.6; 2.9.1), considered their piscinae more a status symbol than an industrial operation, and cherished their fishes more as pets than as tasty tidbits (VARR. r. r. 3.17.3). Sperlonga, with its lavish decoration and its luxurious setting, was built by one of these tycoons. Built, yes, but by whom? When, in the middle of the last century, this villa was discovered, some scholars decided that it must have been Tiberius. Actually the only connection we could establish between the ancient emperor and this place is the fact that he nearly died while dining in the villa&amp;rsquo;s colossal nymphaeum. At this time he was traveling from Capri to Rome and stopped at Sperlonga to rest. We read that he was there, on a small island set at the center of the fishpond, laying with his friends on mattresses placed around an elegant water triclinium (Fig. 91, A) set on a small island at the center of the fishpond. They were drinking, chatting and enjoying the splendid view of the statuary groups displayed in the nymphaeum when the entrance of the grotto crashed down in a historical landslide reported by both Suetonius (Tib. 39) and Tacitus (ann. 4.59) (Fig. 92). I can&amp;rsquo;t imagine how this unfortunate dinner could place Tiberius as the owner and the creator of the spectacular grotto. However this is what some scholars assert and they still believe it. I can&amp;rsquo;t agree. For one thing we know that Tiberius disapproved of luxury. In Tacitus (TACITUS) we find the transcription of some of his speeches to the senate and we notice how harshly he attacked all the people who built luxurious villas and bought expensive statues to put in them. How could Tiberius censor his fellows countrymen for purchasing some marble copies of goddesses and heroes, while he himself was importing from Greece those monumental Hellenistic groups, and setting them in the seaside grotto of a more than sumptuous maritime residence? It was not logical, and for this reason we feel quite certain that Tiberius had no part in creating the Sperlongan art display. However, are we sure that the villa didn&amp;rsquo;t belong to the imperial praedia? No, we can&amp;rsquo;t even deny this: Sperlonga could have entered Augustus&amp;rsquo; estate through a legacy. As a matter of fact we know that, on their death, many rich men used to leave their property to the emperor. Some of these tycoons and also some relatives of the Julio-Claudian family could easily have done this. We can&amp;rsquo;t even forget that - as reported by Cicero (CIC. I cent. B.C.) - Philip, Augustus&amp;rsquo; stepfather, was one of the most important and rich piscinarii of the I cent B.C. Apart from this we can&amp;rsquo;t say anything more.
Garden The villa has three gardens: one peristyle garden, one cryptoporticus and the terrace on the sea, one nymphaeum.
Keywords  villa courtyards terrace gardens  Garden Description These parts of the villa have been relatively spared and they are among the best features of this maritime residence (SALZA PRINA RICOTTI 2002). As a matter of fact, also when the peristyle garden was flourishing, it could never have been as impressive as this imposing cryptoporticus and its underlying terrace (Fig. 93, B), beautiful places to stroll and admire the glorious sunset. The combination of a cryptoporticus and a terrace to create a new kind of garden, was already present in Roman architecture. We can see it depicted in the Pompeian frescoes and we find it in other seaside villas. For instance this kind of open-air arrangement was extensively described in a letter in which Pliny the Younger pointed out the highlights of his cherished Laurentine villa to one of his friend (PLIN. epist. 2.17). In Sperlonga as in Pliny&amp;rsquo;s terrace, a narrow border of flowering plants was set against a low masonry wall, a parapet which was necessary to protect the vegetation from the salty sea breezes (Fig. 94). Today, the fact that bunches of blossoms existed there is confirmed by the presence of a watering system which started from some spring set high on the overhanging hill. We can follow the trace of a groove cut in the rock coming down to the fishpond&amp;rsquo;s northeastern bank. From the piscina side, through a canal (Figs. 91, S; 96), the water was led up to the low parapet of the terrace (Fig. 97), and here, turning at a right angle, it ran all along it. At regular intervals, a series of drain wells helped to draw the water and irrigate the plants. Their presence confirm that a flowerbed existed there and that it was set against the wall.
Maps Plans   the plan of Sperlonga&amp;#39;s Villa.   Images   the general garden plan of Sperlonga.     The landslide.     Cryptoporch and terrace.     The irrigation canal.     Terrace&amp;#39;s parapet.     Not founded Wall.   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography -B. ANDREAE, A. CONTICELLO, H. SCHROTELER, D. WUNDERLICH, Abformung der Polyphemgruppe von Sperlonga, in GfK nach einem neuen Verfahren, Der Präparaator 16, 1-2 (1970), pp. 1-000 worldcat
-F. COARELLI, Sperlonga e Tiberio, DArch 7 (1973), pp. 97-122 worldcat
-A. CONTICELLO, B. ANDREAE, Die Skulpturen von Sperlonga, Antike Plastik 14, Berlin 1974, pp. 000-000 worldcat
-G. JACOPI, L’antro di Tiberio a Sperlonga (Istituto di Studi Romani), Roma 1963 worldcat
-SALZA PRINA RICOTTI, Il gruppo di Polifemo a Sperlonga - Problemi di sistemazione, RendPontAcc 42 (1968-1970), pp. 118-134, tavv. 1-3, figg. 5-9 [worldcat]http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/849270161
-SALZA PRINA RICOTTI, The Importance of Water in Roman Garden Triclinia,in Ancient Roman Villa Gardens (Dumbarton Oaks Research Library and Collection), Dumbarton Oaks 1987, pp. 137-184 [worldcat]http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/715121487
-SALZA PRINA RICOTTI, Sistemazione paesaggistica del fronte a mare e giardini nelle ville marittime di epoca romana, in Giornate di studio in occasione del 250º anniversario degli Scavi di Stabia (in print), pp. 137-169. worldcat
Pleiades ID 433204
TGN ID Contributor EUGENIA SALZA PRINA RICOTTI
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The garden on the back</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/laurentinum/the-garden-on-the-back/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/laurentinum/the-garden-on-the-back/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Laurentes (Pleiades)
Sublocation laurentinum
Sublocation Description The discovery of the Laurentinum
The Laurentinum was a villa belonging to Pliny the Younger (PLIN. epist. 2.17). It was described in a letter directed to one of his friends, a certain Gallo, whom he invited there to spend some time together. In this letter Pliny described accurately his Laurentine maritime residence. Throughout the centuries, having read this letter, many architects and scholars tried their hand at reconstructing its plan. I did one myself, which - as I discovered later on - was not exactly right, but at least it proved to be as good an approximation as it could be expected. Knowing of this reconstruction, Prof. Antonio Maria Colini, who in 1935 had excavated the so-called Pliny&amp;rsquo;s Villa of Castel Fusano (COLINI 1985), asked me if it was possible to confront it with the plan of the Castel Fusano excavation. He wanted to check if there was any chance that, also if greatly modified during the centuries, this one could be the real Laurentinum. Lanciani, at least, had so declared and, after his statement, the fact was not discussed any more. It did not take too long to decide that the Castel Fusano Villa had nothing in common with the Laurentinum and that no transformation brought to it throughout the centuries could ever made it look as it looked. At this moment to locate the real Laurentinum was a challenge one couldn&amp;rsquo;t resist. With all that had been discovered and all the elements that were now at hand, finding it couldn&amp;rsquo;t really pose great problems. In fact Pliny gave its topographical localization quite clearly. First of all he told his friend that his residence was situated 17 miles from Rome and that it could be reached by two roads: the Laurentina and the Ostiensis. After 11 mile one had to leave the Ostiensis and take a dirt track; as for the Laurentina, after 14 mile one would find another dirt track leading to Pliny’s villa. This meant two things: first of all that the trip would have had the same length through the two itineraries, and second that the villa was placed on the stretch of coast which was limited by the two roads. Only in this case one could have used both for getting there. Pliny told also something else that was very important: he told his friend that his villa was the second one starting from a village which was in this area, but he didn&amp;rsquo;t say if it was towards Ostia or towards Antium. At the end of the XIX century the village was found. As the Municipality of Rome had bought the property of the Chigi family at Castel Fusano, where a villa - the second one towards Ostia starting from the village - had been found, it was decided to excavate it. As we have just seen it proved not to be Pliny&amp;rsquo;s one. So I concluded that the Laurentinum had to be the second one toward Antium, the so-called Villa Magna (SALZA PRINA RICOTTI 1984; SALZA PRINA RICOTTI 1987, pp. 182-184, figs. 35-37). Proofs of this were gathered. First of all topographical ones. We knew the layout of the ancient Ostiensis and Laurentina roads. Thus one could easily mark on a map the place where these roads had to be left. It is evident that these places could be considered two points of a triangulation. At this moment one had only to take a compass, point it on the spots where to leave the Ostiensis and take an opening corresponding to six mile. After this do the same for the Laurentina with an opening of three miles and trace the two arches. They would cross on the spot were Pliny&amp;rsquo;s Villa had been. When I did it the arches crossed just on the Villa Magna. A survey proved that everything Pliny had depicted in his letter tallied with the remains of the villa, and also the description of his gardens (SALZA PRINA RICOTTI 1985; SALZA PRINA RICOTTI 1987a).
Garden The garden on the back
Keywords  villa courtyards  Garden Description Excavating the garden of the Laurentinum would have been very interesting, but there was not the time, nor the money. However we found where it was: a rectangular area free from masonry set, as the letter said, on the back of the famous cryptoporticus, one of the principal highlights of the Laurentine. Pliny told us that a long vine trellis ran along this building and that mulberry trees and figs grew in the garden. Thus the place, with its fruit trees, must have been pleasingly rustic. There was also a long hedge of box trees. Rosemary took the place of buxum every time the bushes had to be exposed to the sea winds. As Pliny explained, buxum couldn&amp;rsquo;t stand the salt and, when exposed to it, it quickly dried up and died, while rosemary thrived on the coast. This description we just reported was the one that Pliny gave us. From what we see now, it appears that, after Pliny&amp;rsquo;s death and the selling of his maritime residence, the new owners brought many changes to it. Today high heaps of soil surround the garden&amp;rsquo;s area and, even though this part has not been excavated, it is evident that some masonry structure must be buried under it. It is highly probable that the vine trellises, and the rustic enclosures of Pliny&amp;rsquo;s times, were substituted by a marble portico which transformed the simple garden in a more elegant peristyle one. Evidently at this moment mulberry trees and figs must have been quickly replaced by less useful but more decorative plants.
Plans   102 - Pliny times     1103 - Laurentinum in Severian times     104 - Excavations and survey of the Cryptoporch and the Severian changes   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography   COLINI 1985 = A. M. COLINI., Tra Castel Fusano e Capocotta: il vicus Augustanus e le ville di Ortensio e di Plinio il Giovane, Sin AA. VV., Capocotta ultima spiaggia. Proposta per il parco naturalistico-archeologico del litorale romano, Roma 1985, pp. 79-87. worldcat
  SALZA PRINA RICOTTI 1984 = E. SALZA PRINA RICOTTI, , La c.d. Villa Magna: il Laurentinum di Plinio il Giovane, RendLinc 39 (1984), pp. 339-358 worldcat
  SALZA PRINA RICOTTI 1985 = E. SALZA PRINA RICOTTI, , La Villa Magna a Grotte di Piastra, in Castelporziano I. Iª Campagna di scavo e di restauro 1984, Roma 1985, pp. 53-66 worldcat
  SALZA PRINA RICOTTI 1987 = E. SALZA PRINA RICOTTI, , The Importance of Water in Roman Garden Triclinia,in Ancient Roman Villa Gardens (Dumbarton Oaks Research Library and Collection), Dumbarton Oaks 1987, pp. 137-184 worldcat
  SALZA PRINA RICOTTI 1987a = rrE. SALZA PRINA RICOTTI, , La Villa Magna a Grotte di Piastra,in Castelporziano II. Campagna di scavo e di restauro 1985 – 1986, Roma 1987, pp. 45-66 worldcat
  Pleiades ID 422959
Contributor SALZA PRINA RICOTTI
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The terrance</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/laurentinum/the-terrance/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/laurentinum/the-terrance/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Laurentes (Pleiades)
Sublocation laurentinum
Sublocation Description The discovery of the Laurentinum
The Laurentinum was a villa belonging to Pliny the Younger (PLIN. epist. 2.17). It was described in a letter directed to one of his friends, a certain Gallo, whom he invited there to spend some time together. In this letter Pliny described accurately his Laurentine maritime residence. Throughout the centuries, having read this letter, many architects and scholars tried their hand at reconstructing its plan. I did one myself, which - as I discovered later on - was not exactly right, but at least it proved to be as good an approximation as it could be expected. Knowing of this reconstruction, Prof. Antonio Maria Colini, who in 1935 had excavated the so-called Pliny&amp;rsquo;s Villa of Castel Fusano (COLINI 1985), asked me if it was possible to confront it with the plan of the Castel Fusano excavation. He wanted to check if there was any chance that, also if greatly modified during the centuries, this one could be the real Laurentinum. Lanciani, at least, had so declared and, after his statement, the fact was not discussed any more. It did not take too long to decide that the Castel Fusano Villa had nothing in common with the Laurentinum and that no transformation brought to it throughout the centuries could ever made it look as it looked. At this moment to locate the real Laurentinum was a challenge one couldn&amp;rsquo;t resist. With all that had been discovered and all the elements that were now at hand, finding it couldn&amp;rsquo;t really pose great problems. In fact Pliny gave its topographical localization quite clearly. First of all he told his friend that his residence was situated 17 miles from Rome and that it could be reached by two roads: the Laurentina and the Ostiensis. After 11 mile one had to leave the Ostiensis and take a dirt track; as for the Laurentina, after 14 mile one would find another dirt track leading to Pliny’s villa. This meant two things: first of all that the trip would have had the same length through the two itineraries, and second that the villa was placed on the stretch of coast which was limited by the two roads. Only in this case one could have used both for getting there. Pliny told also something else that was very important: he told his friend that his villa was the second one starting from a village which was in this area, but he didn&amp;rsquo;t say if it was towards Ostia or towards Antium. At the end of the XIX century the village was found. As the Municipality of Rome had bought the property of the Chigi family at Castel Fusano, where a villa - the second one towards Ostia starting from the village - had been found, it was decided to excavate it. As we have just seen it proved not to be Pliny&amp;rsquo;s one. So I concluded that the Laurentinum had to be the second one toward Antium, the so-called Villa Magna (SALZA PRINA RICOTTI 1984; SALZA PRINA RICOTTI 1987, pp. 182-184, figs. 35-37). Proofs of this were gathered. First of all topographical ones. We knew the layout of the ancient Ostiensis and Laurentina roads. Thus one could easily mark on a map the place where these roads had to be left. It is evident that these places could be considered two points of a triangulation. At this moment one had only to take a compass, point it on the spots where to leave the Ostiensis and take an opening corresponding to six mile. After this do the same for the Laurentina with an opening of three miles and trace the two arches. They would cross on the spot were Pliny&amp;rsquo;s Villa had been. When I did it the arches crossed just on the Villa Magna. A survey proved that everything Pliny had depicted in his letter tallied with the remains of the villa, and also the description of his gardens (SALZA PRINA RICOTTI 1985; SALZA PRINA RICOTTI 1987a).
Garden The garden on the back
Keywords  villa  Garden Description However the most enticing garden of the Laurentinum was the terrace, so well described by Pliny the Younger (SALZA PRINA RICOTTI 1989; SALZA PRINA RICOTTI in print). It was set in front of the luminous cryptoporticus with all its windows open toward the Tyrrenian Sea. The two elements ran parallel to the coast. Only the terrace&amp;rsquo;s low wall protected them from the sand that the southwest wind and the frequent winter&amp;rsquo;s gales piled up against the villa. Sheltered by the masonry, masses of perfumed violets grew all along this parapet. Today only few remains of the terrace are still to be seen. The place had been changed in Severian times (Fig. 103). Part of the terrace was covered and joined to the famous cryptoporticus. A simple transfer brought the ancient seaside wall with its extra large windows on what once was the terrace&amp;rsquo;s parapet and pillars took the places of the windows in the ancient cryptoporticus, creating either a covered double portico or a large hall (Fig. 104). A small private bath was erected directly on the beach and was attached to this hall. Probably it took the place of Pliny&amp;rsquo;s Heliocaminus, a solarium which Pliny described. In this part the terrace was quite completely obliterated. Luckily a small part of it was preserved, and here we still find the low parapet against which the violets were and a stele (Fig 104, D) with an epigraph giving us the name of the family that bought the house after Pliny&amp;rsquo;s death. Also in this reduced state, the remains still retain the poetry of Pliny&amp;rsquo;s description. However it is always possible, basing ourselves on these remains and on Pliny&amp;rsquo;s letter, to reconstruct how the cryptoporticus and the terrace were at his times. For one thing the cryptoporticus described by Pliny is still saved and intact with delicate frescoes on its wall and an Augustan mosaic on its floor. Moreover it is still on the same line with his beloved pavilions, just as he described it in his letter, when he wrote that from the pavilion door he could overview all the length of the monumental cryptoporticus. Also the terrace is in line with it. Thus, omitting the Severian additions and destruction, we can redesign the plan of this part of the house with the garden, the cryptoporticus and the terrace set how they were once (Fig. 102).
Maps Plans   102 - Pliny times     1103 - Laurentinum in Severian times     104 - Excavations and survey of the Cryptoporch and the Severian changes   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography   COLINI 1985 = A. M. COLINI., Tra Castel Fusano e Capocotta: il vicus Augustanus e le ville di Ortensio e di Plinio il Giovane, Sin AA. VV., Capocotta ultima spiaggia. Proposta per il parco naturalistico-archeologico del litorale romano, Roma 1985, pp. 79-87. worldcat
  SALZA PRINA RICOTTI 1984 = E. SALZA PRINA RICOTTI, , La c.d. Villa Magna: il Laurentinum di Plinio il Giovane, RendLinc 39 (1984), pp. 339-358 worldcat
  SALZA PRINA RICOTTI 1985 = E. SALZA PRINA RICOTTI, , La Villa Magna a Grotte di Piastra, in Castelporziano I. Iª Campagna di scavo e di restauro 1984, Roma 1985, pp. 53-66 worldcat
  SALZA PRINA RICOTTI 1987 = E. SALZA PRINA RICOTTI, , The Importance of Water in Roman Garden Triclinia,in Ancient Roman Villa Gardens (Dumbarton Oaks Research Library and Collection), Dumbarton Oaks 1987, pp. 137-184 worldcat
  SALZA PRINA RICOTTI 1987a = E. SALZA PRINA RICOTTI, , La Villa Magna a Grotte di Piastra,in Castelporziano II. Campagna di scavo e di restauro 1985 – 1986, Roma 1987, pp. 45-66 worldcat
  SALZA PRINA RICOTTI 1989 = E. SALZA PRINA RICOTTI, , Sul terrazzo odoroso di viole: la scoperta della villa di Plinio il Giovane,Archeo 54 (agosto 1989), pp. 34-43 [worldcat] (https://www.worldcat.org/title/archeo/oclc/920385284/editions?referer=di&amp;amp;editionsView=true)
  SALZA PRINA RICOTTI 2002 = E. SALZA PRINA RICOTTI, , Sistemazione paesaggistica del fronte a mare e giardini nelle ville marittime di epoca romana,in Giornate di studio in occasione del 250º anniversario degli Scavi di Stabia (in print), pp. 137-169 worldcat
  Pleiades ID 4229596
Contributor SALZA PRINA RICOTTI
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>