<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/nerac/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:07:01 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/nerac/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa of La Garenne, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/nerac/gallia-aquitania_villa-of-la-garenne_j.zhou/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:07:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/nerac/gallia-aquitania_villa-of-la-garenne_j.zhou/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_Aquitania Gallia_Aquitania (Pleiades)
Province Description A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location Nérac
Nérac (Pleiades)
House Villa of La Garenne
House Description Despite its inauspicious entry into the rolls of archaeological sites, the villa remains truly a large and richly ornamented mansion. There were numerous pavements in polychrome opus tesselatum; much white and colored marble was used in the decoration. There were works in opus sectile and composite capitals with leafy swirls on their corners. There was a sculpture collection including a marble portrait of Marcus Aurelius and several mythological subjects.
Garden Keywords  statues reception rooms  Garden Description The villa was in two distinct parts. A bath complex and nymphaeum ran along the river bank. Some eighty meters back from the water and on a terrace was an enormous reception complex. In the center of it was a circular room about ten meters in diameter and on each side was a huge reception area about nine meters wide and 27 meters long with an apse at the end near the center. Between these two complexes was a large area divided by walls into three roughly rectangular areas. It appears possible that this walled-in area between the luxurious reception area and the river would have been developed as a garden. It is noteworthy that it is not a peristyle garden.
There were two phase of construction. The first seems to go back to the early empire. The second, which realigned slightly the upper complex, is dated by Balmelle to the early 5th century.
Plans Dates 1st Part: Early Empire 2nd Part: Early 5th Century CE
Excavation Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Catherine Balmelle, Les demeures aristocratiques d&amp;rsquo;Aquitaine, societe et culture de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquite tardive dans le sou-ouest de la Gaule, Ausonius, supple. d&amp;rsquo;Aquitania 10, Bordeaux 2001, p. 390-3. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505
TGN ID Contributor Clopper Almon
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>