<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>trellises on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/trellises/</link>
    <description>Recent content in trellises on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/trellises/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Large vineyard.</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/region_ii_2/insula_v/house/ii.v/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/region_ii_2/insula_v/house/ii.v/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region II
House Large vineyard in Pompeii
Garden Large vineyard
Keywords   amphitheaters
  trellises
  triclinia (couches)
  vineyards
  Garden Description Located north of the amphitheater, this site was initially identified as the Foro Boario or Cattle Market. A small amount of excavation was started in 1755, but in 1814 the entrance and south wall were excavated. Most of the excavation was completed in the 1950s except the northeastern section. In 1966 Jashemski undertook preliminary sub-soil excavations and proved that the area had been under cultivation. Work continued through 1968 and 1970 removing some undisturbed lapilli and consequently 2,014 vine root cavities were recorded with an equal number of stakes in that section. It was noted that ninety percent of the root cavities had a diameter ranging from 2 to 5.5 cm. with the average being just under 4 cm. The total range of size was from 1 cm. to 8.5 cm. The vines were spaced four Roman feet apart, trained on a rectangular framed trellis (vitus compluviata) and each vine had three or four depressions for watering at the base. Also discovered were two well preserved examples of propagation by layering. A north-south path starting from the entrance divided the vineyard into equal halves. An east-west path crossed this leading to the outdoor triclinium and two rooms where the wine was made. A third path was discovered in 1970 running parallel to the north wall. Fifteen coins were found on the third path, (for identification of these coins see Table E). The paths ran under arbors and usually two root cavities were found by each of the posts that supported the arbor. Rows of trees were planted at the edge of the vineyard between the second and third row of vines, widely spaced trees grew along the paths between the first and second row of vines on each side of the paths, and other trees were scattered randomly in the rest of the vineyard. In all, fifty-eight tree cavities were found, their ground level dimension ranging from 3.5 to 40 cm. Two carbonized olives were found as well as one bean which could indicate that vegetables were also grown under the vines. The entrance directly across from the amphitheater was designed to be an architectural part of the masonry triclinium (l. medius, 4.85 m.; l. imus and l. summus 4.50 m.; table 0.60 x 1.30m.). The entrance pillar matched the extension of the lectus imus across from it in length and width and a low masonry pedestal that was in line with the other entrance pillar shared the same dimensions. The pedestal could have held a lamp or statuette, and the extension of the lectus summus would have been used as a table. A second triclinium (l. medius, 4.60 m.; l. imus and l. summus 4.00 m.) was unique for the pergola posts were supported by a row of amphoras broken off at the top and bottom and buried in the ground along the outside edge of the lectus summus, close to the wall of the wine making building. The entrance triclinium, and perhaps the second one where the wine was made, would have been used to serve those attending games at the amphitheater. Fifty–two bones were found here, (see Jashemski, Gardens, 1:216-218 and Table A on p. 217) with evidence that they were the remains of meals. Serving meals would have been a source of additional revenue for the wine makers. Wine would also have been sold at the shop with the ¬portico that faced the Via dell’Abbondanza that was part of this property.
Plans   site overview 1     excavation detail 1     excavation work     one excavation site     the excavated bones     the excavated holes     excavated root cavities     work on the excavation     trees in the site     large excavated site     large excavated site with the arranged stones     excavation on one site     one hole work     hole and remains     a line of holes     archeologist     fragments     part of site overview     one hole     three holes     a line-shape hole     stone remains 1     stone remains detail      site view      excavation work      site view     site with wild flowers      line holes      three holes details      holes details      holes details      works on the hole      one view of the site      people discussion      hole finding      hole work     hole fix      excavation work      the excavation    Dates Unspecified
Bibliography   Giornale di scavo sistematico eseguito nell’area del Foro Boario da 1º Decembre, 1954 al 31 Maggio 1955 (unpublished);
  Jashemski,Excavations in the‘Foro Borario’at Pompeii: A Preliminary Report, AJA 72 (1968): 69-73, ills. 1-3 and figs. 1-7
  Idem,University of Maryland Excavations at Pompeii, 1968, AJA 74 (1970): 63-70, ills. 1-5 and figs. 1-15
  Idem,The Discovery of a Large Vineyard at Pompeii: University of Maryland Excavations, 1970, AJA 77 (1973): 27-41, ills. 1-5 and figs, 1-7; )
  Idem, Large Vineyard Discovered in Ancient Pompeii, Science 180 (1973): 821-830 and figs. 1-8
  Idem, Gardens, 1:201-218 and figs. 293-317
  Idem, Gardens, vol.II, p.89-90
  Maiuri, Pompeii (Novara, 1928), p. 43: “scavato parzialmente nel 1755 e poi ricolmato” worldcat
  Meyer, Frederick G,Carbonized Food Plants of Pompeii, Herculaneum, and the Villa at Torre Annunziata, Economic Botany. 34.4 (1980): 401-437. Print p.418 worldcat
  Pleiades ID 444848573
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 2 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Great Palestra (Insula or. II.4)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/insula_or._ii/great_palestra/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/insula_or._ii/great_palestra/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Insula Insula Orientalis II
House Thermea
Garden Great Palestra
Keywords  shrine fountains trellises  Garden Description The Palaestra was crossed by Burbon tunnels in 1756-1760 and partially excavated from 1933 to 1954. Carbonized remains of large tree trunks found in the southwest corner and along the north side against the portico where they were swept by the volcanic flow indicated to Maiuri that the central area had been planted with trees similar to the central area of the Great Palestra at Pompeii. The soil was compacted, as typical of athletic fields, and no evidence of paths or beds have yet been found. A large cruciform pool occupied the center of the area. The north-south arm is 55.00 m. long, the east-west arm is 31.50 m. long, each arm is 5.80 wide and the depth is 1.00-1.10 m. at the center. A masonry base 0.95 m. square and 1.14 m. high stood at the center of the intersection and presumably held the monumental bronze fountain sculpture found in 1952 at the bottom of the pool. The statue is a five-headed serpent 2.45 m. high coiled around a tree with water jetting from the mouth of each head. On the west end of the pool there is a pilaster with a smaller jet. Two meters from the front of the enclosed portico on the north side there is a rectangular pool 3.00 x 30.00 m.; 2.35 m. deep which was proportioned the same as a swimming pool, but had been abandoned before the eruption. Close to the bottom of the pool thirty five amphoras were installed in the walls, with openings ranging from 20 to 30 cm. in diameter. These provided shelter and spawning areas for fish.
Plans   Plan of the new excavations of Herculaneum (Maiuri, Herculaneum)     Herculaneum - Garden at rear of Casa del Rilievo di Telefo.   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, 1:162-163, n. 94 on p. 348 and fig. 247 on p. 163(worldcat) Maiuri, Herculaneum, pp. 55-56 (worldcat) Maiuri, “Fontana monumentale in bronzo nei nuovi scavi di Ercolano,” BdA (1954), pp. 193-199(worldcat) Maiuri, Ercolano, pp. 136-137 and fig. 91 (plan) on p. 114 (see pp. 189-190, nn. 58 and 59 for reports of Ruggiero on the Burbon excavations(worldcat)  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 20 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sacred Area Outside the South Walls</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/sacred_area/sacred_area_outside_the_south_walls/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/sacred_area/sacred_area_outside_the_south_walls/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Keywords  parapets podium shrine woven rim trellises  Garden Description The southern edge of town was against a sharp drop to the sea. A terrace located on this drop held two shrines (a) and (b) and a series of rooms for cult activities. All of these faced on a long garden (c) 6.85 x 22.60 m. where the fragments of two large marble fountain basins were found when this area was excavated in 1939 to 1958. On the south end of the garden a parapet had a podium which could have been used as a garden seat. Garden paintings decorated the interior walls of shrine (b). The fragments that survived were enough to give an idea of what the original effect must have been. The lower part of the panel to the left of the entrance on the south is the best preserved. The base of the wall was painted with hart’s-tongue ferns, each plant separated by a trellis that was identical to the woven fence just above which must have encircled the entire room. A garden extended behind the fence and on the south wall a marble basin supported by three legs was graced by three doves perched on the rim to drink. A small date palm and flowers are nearby, including a corn poppy on the left with carefully executed foliage and flowers, two in profile and the others drawn open faced. A young palm tree and a plant with daisy-like flowers comes next and to the right of the basin there is a rosebush with blossoms very similar to the ones painted in the garden rooms of I.ix.5. The east wall appears to have had a crater-shaped fountain, and on the north wall above the large podium altar three panels each contained a garden painting. The side panels each had a young palm tree as the dominant feature in the middle, but the center panel was too damaged to determine what it contained.
Plans   Plan of the new excavations of Herculaneum (Maiuri, Herculaneum)     Plan of the Sacred Area (Maiuri, Herculaneum)   Images   Sacred Area Outside the South Walls (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates Unspecified
Excavation Date 1939 to 1958
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, 1:158-160 (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 371 (worldcat) Maiuri, Ercolano, pp. 181-182 and fig. 143 (plan) opposite p. 176 (worldcat) Michel, p. 386  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 20 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
