<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/friedberg-pfingstweide/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 18:12:31 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/friedberg-pfingstweide/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Friedberg Pfingstweide</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/friedberg-pfingstweide/friedberg-pfingstweide_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 18:12:31 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/friedberg-pfingstweide/friedberg-pfingstweide_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Friedberg Pfingstweide
Friedberg Pfingstweide (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Friedberg Pfingstweide
Keywords  archaeological garden bathhouses (water recreation structures) villae rusticae  Garden Description This villa rustica was situated on the northern slope of a valley through which a stream ran. The enclosed area of the farm occupied an area of 3.4 hectares (180 x 190 meters), and it was divided into a residential part (pars urbana) and a service area (pars rustica) by a road running east-west (Fig. 1). The front of the house (H in Fig. 1) faced north and had a view of the valley and the lower lying service area of the farm.
Built in the early 2nd century, the house was of the winged corridor type with a large open courtyard enclosed by the protruding wings of the house. The courtyard was divided into two zones that were possibly gardens (G in Fig. 1) and have been reconstructed as such. The farm was destroyed by fire in the first half of the 3rd century.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the villa (H) with a bath building (B) and with two possible garden enclosures (G) joined to the house at the north. Adapted from Baatz and Herrmann 1989, fig. 246.   Dates Early 2nd century - first half of 3rd century
Bibliography  D. Baatz and F.-R. Herrmann, eds., Die Römer in Hessen, 2nd ed., Stuttgart, 1989, pp. 307-309, fig. 246. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981525
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 16 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
