<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>insulae on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/insulae/</link>
    <description>Recent content in insulae on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 10:24:03 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/insulae/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>House in Insula 16 in Aventicum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_house_in_insula_16/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 10:24:03 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_house_in_insula_16/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Province Description Location Aventicum
Aventicum (Pleiades)
Location Description The town was established in the Augustan period as the civitas capital of the Helvetii. At this time the orthogonal street grid was laid out. Most probably in AD 71, it became Colonia Pia Flavia Constans Emerita Helvetiorum Foederata. The town was destroyed or badly damaged around AD 260, and it was progressively abandoned thereafter.
Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden House in Insula 16 in Aventicum
Keywords colonnades
insulae
peristyles (Roman courtyards)
Garden Description In Insula 16 East, northeast of the forum, were small shops and houses belonging to three different owners. These were demolished when the town was promoted to the status of colonia by Vespasian. The new house occupied the whole insula and was entered on the northeast.
In the middle of the insula was a large peristyle courtyard which may have been planted (G in Fig. 1). In the southwestern part of the building complex taverns and shops opened onto the colonnaded street.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House in Insula 13 in Aventicum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_house_in_insula_13/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 10:06:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_house_in_insula_13/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Province Description Location Aventicum
Aventicum (Pleiades)
Location Description The town was established in the Augustan period as the civitas capital of the Helvetii. At this time the orthogonal street grid was laid out. Most probably in AD 71, it became Colonia Pia Flavia Constans Emerita Helvetiorum Foederata. The town was destroyed or badly damaged around AD 260, and it was progressively abandoned thereafter.
Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden House in Insula 13 in Aventicum
Keywords archaeological garden
bathhouses (water recreation structures)
corridors
fountains
garden pavilions
gutters (building drainage components)
insulae
peristyles (Roman courtyards)
piscinae
reception rooms
Garden Description Recent excavations in Insula 13 on the northwestern edge of the town have uncovered the remains of two large and luxurious houses separated from each other by a narrow corridor. They date to the late 1st century and were occupied until the middle of the 3rd century. Both buildings had a length of 60 meters, spanning the length of the insula.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House in Insula 30 in Augusta Raurica</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ausgusta_raurica/augusta_raurica_house_in_insula_30/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 10:02:05 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ausgusta_raurica/augusta_raurica_house_in_insula_30/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Province Description Location Augusta Raurica
Augusta Raurica (Pleiades)
Location Description The town on the Rhine River possessed colonial status since the late 1st century BC. The street grid, as well as many public and residential buildings, are well known from excavations.
Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden House in Insula 30 in Augusta Raurica
Keywords barrier walls
colonnades
corridors
insulae
peristyles (Roman courtyards)
triclinia
vestibules
water wells
Garden Description Insula 30, east of the central baths, was taken up by a single house built around 200 AD. This replaced several earlier structures on the site. The insula, including the street colonnades, had an overall area of ca. 48 x 60 meters.
The house had a peristyle courtyard of rectangular shape which was surrounded on three sides by a low wall supporting stone columns. The courtyard was unpaved and almost certainly planted (G in Fig. 1). Entering the house from the east, one passed through a vestibule before arriving in the peristyle corridor around the courtyard.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House in Insula 1 and 2 in Augusta Raurica</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ausgusta_raurica/augusta_raurica_house_in_insula_1_and_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 17:34:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ausgusta_raurica/augusta_raurica_house_in_insula_1_and_2/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Province Description Location Augusta Raurica
Augusta Raurica (Pleiades)
Location Description The town on the Rhine River possessed colonial status since the late 1st century BC. The street grid, as well as many public and residential buildings, are well known from excavations.
Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden House in Insula 1 and 2 in Augusta Raurica
Keywords archaeological garden
barrier walls
insulae
peristyles (Roman courtyards)
porticoes
terrace gardens
Garden Description This house, built on sloping terrain on the northern edge of the city around AD 150, was enlarged twenty years later to incorporate at least two certain gardens (Fig. 1). It bordered north and south on streets and was flanked on the east and west by other houses. In this last phase after ca. 170, the house covered an area of about 2000 square meters. In the center of the building was an irregular peristyle courtyard, at the north end of which was a private bath complex.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Houses of Insula 7 in Colonia Ulpia Traiana</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/colonia_ulpia_xanten/colonia_xanten_insula7/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/colonia_ulpia_xanten/colonia_xanten_insula7/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Xanten
Xanten (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Industrial quarter
Sublocation Description This insula southeast of the forum is commonly referred to as an industrial quarter (Plan 1). It was divided into several long, narrow plots on which were houses, shops and workshops.
Garden The houses of Insula 7 in Colonia Ulpia Traiana (Xanten)
Keywords insulae
kitchen gardens
courtyards
Garden Description Between the buildings were open areas, some paved and equipped with ovens and pottery kilns, wells and latrines, others unpaved. Some of the small courtyards have been reconstructed by the excavators as kitchen gardens and shrine gardens (Image 1). Organic material from a well in this insula included the remains of peas, beans, lentils, apples, pears and herbs. These fruits and vegetables may have grown in kitchen gardens in the insula, but they may, on the other hand, have been brought into the city from nearby farms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Dionyius</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_dionysius/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 20:22:59 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_dionysius/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden House of Dionysius (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords urban villas
villae urbanae
triclinia
insulae
peristyles (Roman courtyards)
apsed pools
axial plan
piscinae
Garden Description The largest urban villa excavated thus far in Cologne is the House of Dionysos (3400 sq. m.), named after the early 3rd century mosaic floor decorated with Dionysiac motifs in the triclinium (Image 1??). The house occupies part of an insula in the northeastern corner of the city, bordered on the south by a street leading to the harbor.
The original house, erected after A.D. 50, was rebuilt under Vespasian and included a peristyle garden courtyard measuring 23 x 27 m.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>