<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/aquileia/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2020 12:00:02 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/aquileia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Funerary Grove of Q. Cervonius Chryseros</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/aquileia/funerary_grove_of_q.-cervonius_chryseros/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_x/aquileia/funerary_grove_of_q.-cervonius_chryseros/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Aquileia
Aquileia (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region X
Garden Funerary Grove of Q. Cervonius Chryseros
Keywords  tombs stelae grove (sacred grove) altars (religious fixtures)  Garden Description A small inscribed altar of (probably) the Julio-Claudian era found by Mommsen among the stones of Aquileia and now lost records on its left and right sides dedications to Dis Pater and (H)era respectively and, on its front, the name of the dedicant, a consul’s aide (acc(ensus) co(n)s(ularis)) and local sevir at Florentia, Q. Cervonius Chryseros, who built “the grove, the enclosure wall, the altars, the mound (? molem), and the seats” (lucum, maceriem, aras, molem, [s]edilia). The dedication to Dis Pater suggests a funerary context, which leads Chioffi to identify the molis as a tomb monument of some ill-defined type (perhaps an irregular mound?). A Roman soldier serving in lower Germany at Carvium (Herwen) was buried by his two heirs ad molem, “near (or at) the mound” (AE 1939, 130). The same Chryseros perhaps appears as the owner of a slave, Fausta, who in fulfillment of a vow dedicated another monument to Dis Pater at Aquileia (CIL 5.35*).
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date unspecified
Bibliography  G. B. Brusin, Inscriptiones Aquileiae, Udine 1991-1993, no. 192.(worldcat) S. Panciera, Libitina e dintorni : Libitina e i luci sepolcrali, Rome 2004, nn. 17-31. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 187290
TGN ID 7005553
Contributor Sean Gillies (https://pleiades.stoa.org/author/sgillies)
Publication date 15 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
