<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/aulis/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 09:50:12 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/aulis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Sanctuary of Artemis</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/aulis/aulis_sanctuary_of_artemis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 09:50:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/aulis/aulis_sanctuary_of_artemis/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands.
The provincial capital was Corinth. Under Nero in the mid-1st century A.D. Epirus became a separate province, and in the mid-2nd century Thessaly was detached and added to the province of Macedonia. Under Roman domination many cities such as Athens, Sparta, Patras, and Corinth grew in size and prominence, the latter two partly owing to their importance as ports. After an initial decline in the number of rural sites in the early Empire, by the late Roman period the countryside was densely settled with farms and villas, due to changing landholding patterns and Roman improvements in agricultural and irrigation technology. The main exports from Achaea were wine, particularly from the northern Peloponnese, as well as olive oil and honey, linen and woollen textiles and marbles.
Location Aulis
Aulis (Pleiades)
Garden Sancturary of Artemis
Keywords Literary
grove (sacred grove)
Pausanias
Garden Description The shrine of Artemis at Aulis in Boeotia was visited by Pausanias (9.19.6-8). The Greeks in Homer’s Iliad had sacrificed to Artemis in Aulis in hope for favorable winds to carry them from Greek shores to Troy (Iliad 2.305-310). The late 5th century Athenian playwright, Euripides, made reference to the grove of Artemis in his Iphigenia in Aulis (185-186, 1543-1549). Here in the 2nd century A.D. Pausanias noted white stone statues (presumably marble) of Artemis and saw palm trees growing in the sanctuary. According to him, the fruit was not all edible, as it was in Palestine, but he remarked that the fruit ripened better than the dates in Ionia.
Dates Bibliography Pleiades ID Aulis (Pleiades)
TGN ID 5004252
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 16 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>