<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vi/house_11/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2020 09:50:25 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vi/house_11/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa Dei Quadretti Teatralli; House of the Calavii (I.vi.11)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vi/house_11/casa_dei_quadretti_teatralli/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2020 09:50:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_vi/house_11/casa_dei_quadretti_teatralli/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VI
House House 11
Garden Casa Dei Quadretti Teatralli; House of the Calavii (I.vi.11)
Keywords  archaeological garden cisterns (plumbing components) columns (architectural elements) mural paintings (visual works) porticoes puteal wine cellars  Garden Description A partially completed wall joined the columns supporting the portico at the rear of this house. Next to this was a small garden (a) which was in an extreme state of ruin at the time of excavation due to the weakening of the wine cellar vaults below. The vaults had openings to admit light and air for the wine aging and a cistern was also located under the garden. On the portico to the east there was a large terra-cotta puteal. Fig. 3. A room on the south end of the east portico contains a garden representation on the west wall. Barely a third of the representation survived and what remains is extremely faded. It is painted in yellow on a small dark green panel in the center of a red wall and shows a pergola with a lattice fence extending from both sides and a section of fence in front. Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula vi, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 9, p. 34; *NSc* (1929), pl 18; Spinnazola, *Scavi nuovi*, vol. 1, after p. 679; Ibid., vol. 2, after p. 1027 (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I. vi. 13.9.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 36. (worldcat) Idem, Gardens, vol.II, p. 395. (worldcat) Maiuri, NSc (1929), pp. 414-415 and fig. 26 (plan) on p. 401.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 07 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>