<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>mural paintings on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/mural-paintings/</link>
    <description>Recent content in mural paintings on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 15:31:46 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/mural-paintings/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Capella (I.iii.24)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_24/house_of_capella/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 15:31:46 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_24/house_of_capella/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 24
Garden House of Capella (I.iii.24)
Keywords  archaeological garden lararia mural paintings (visual works) peristyles (columnades) porticoes triclinia  Garden Description At the rear of the house, excavated in 1868, there was a peristyle garden (a) with a portico supported by three brick columns on the east and north sides. The south wall had a lararium painting and a crude animal painting on one corner of the south garden wall. This had been executed in the manner of a topiary painting according to the excavators, who reported a lion consuming a deer, below which there was a dog pouncing on a hare. A good view of the garden was obtained through the triclinium (b) on the north.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1868
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 24, no. 261. Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 74, p. 150, no. 456 . (worldcat) Idem, Desc., pp. 56-57.(worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 28. (worldcat) Idem, Gardens, vol.II, p. 313. (worldcat) Matz, BdI (1869), pp. 239-240. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 78. Schefold, WändP, p. 13 . Sogliano, “Pitture,” p. 225, no. 705.  Warscher, “Codex,” photo no. 54.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 29 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Actius Anicetus (I.iii.23)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_23/house_of_actius_anicetus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 12:55:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_23/house_of_actius_anicetus/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 23
Garden I.iii.20/22
Keywords  archaeological garden cisterns (plumbing components) gutters (building drainage components) mural paintings (visual works) peristyles (columnades) porticoes puteal  Garden Description This site was excavated in 1868 revealing a peristyle garden (a) at the rear of the house. A portico on the east and north side was supported by five columns connected by a low wall. There was an opening to the garden on the north. The middle of the garden had two cistern puteals. The west wall of the garden held the famous painting depicting the battle between the Nucerians and the Pompeians in the ampitheator (1.60 m. high by a little less than 2.00 m. wide; Mus. Naz. Inv. No. 112 222; Ruesch no. 1344). This event was recorded by Tacitus (Annals 14.17). A gutter went along the east, south, and north edges of the garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1868
Bibliography  DePetra, GiornSc, n.s., 1 (1865-1869), cols. 185-187 (where the address is given as I.ii). Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 74 and pp. 145-146, no. 401. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., pp. 52-53.(worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 27. (worldcat) Matz, BdI (1869), pp. 240-241. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 78. Niccolini, Case, vol. 4, “Supplemento,” p1. 32. Maiuri, NSc (1939), pp. 168-169. Schefold, WändP, p.12. Sogliano, “Pitture,” p. 204, no.604. Warscher, “Codex.” photos nos. 44-50.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 29 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.ii.17 B</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_17/i.ii.17_b/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2020 15:01:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_17/i.ii.17_b/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 17
Garden I.ii.17 B
Keywords  archaeological garden atriums mural paintings (visual works) peristyles (columnades) pillars porticoes statues statuettes (free-standing sculpture) tablina  Garden Description The peristyle garden to the east of the atrium was excavated in 1873. It had a portico on the north and west supported by two pillars, one at the northwest corner and the other in the middle of the north side. A gutter sloped towards the southeast corner as it went around the east, north, and west edges of the garden. A shrine-like structure was built against the east wall with the marble veneered façade above the level of the floor of the niche. The niche contained a marble statuette of Venus, her left arm supported by a statuette (1.04 m. high; Mus Naz. inv. no. 109 608; Ruesch no. 1325). The wall behind the statue was painted to represent blue drapery and the ceiling had a shell-like fluting. Two small marble statuettes of toads (Mus. Nac. inv. no. 109 609, 109 610) found in the garden and probably the one of two doves (Mus. Naz. inv. no. 120 407) found in the tablinum decorated the flowerbeds. There was also a marble head of a man identified as Agrippa, found cemented in a cup (total height 0.285 m.; Mus. Nac. inv. no. 109 611; Reusch no. 1081). The marble statuette of Hercules wrapped in a lion skin (0.70 m. high; Mus. Nac. inv. no. 109 677) found in the atrium was probably a garden decoration. The large room on the north had a fine view of the garden and the east and south walls of the garden were decorated with garden paintings. These were separated by narrow panels with a painting of a candelabrum, according to Mau, and each painting featured a fence with an amphora upon it. Behind this there was a thicket with birds. On either side of the amphora there was an ibis, and a pheasant in the center. Fiorelli mentioned observing animals in the paintings. Jashemski notes that no trace of the paintings remained when she examined the site, and further, she has never seen a pheasant represented in any garden paintings. Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation dates 1873
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 22, no. 10. de Franciscis, Ritratto, p. 25 and figs. 10-11. (worldcat) Döhl, p.1. Dwyer, Pomp. Sculpture, pp. 124, 12. (worldcat) Fiorelli, Descr., p. 44. (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), cols. 46-47, 48, 55. Grimal, p. 445, no. 1.  Jashemski, Gardens, 1::124-125. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, pp. 23-24. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 313. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 233-235. Ibid. (1874), pp. 265-266. Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 265-266.  Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 76. Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “L’arte,” p. 6 and pl. 14 (Venus). Schefold, WandP, p. 10. (worldcat)  Sogliano, “Pitture,” p. 223, no. 691. (worldcat)  Sogliano, “Scavi,” p. 310. (worldcat) Viola, “Scavi” pp. 12 and 76, no. 1, p.77, nos. 5, 12, p.79, nos. 45, 46. (worldcat) Warscher, “Codex,” photo no. 32.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.ii.17 A</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_17/i.ii.17_a/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2020 15:00:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_17/i.ii.17_a/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 17
Garden I.ii.17 A
Keywords  archaeological garden mural paintings (visual works) piscinae tablina  Garden Description At the rear of the house was a very small garden entered from the tablinum. Excavated in 1872, much of the garden was occupied by two small raised pools, according to Mau. (Fig. 3) Attached to the west wall was a masonry pool 0.58 m. deep on the inside and 0.73 m. high on the outside. The other pool was to the south and there was a garden painting on the rear wall.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, *Scavi*, pl. 1; Niccolini, *Case*, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I.ii.17; 10.13.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation dates 1872
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Descr., p. 44. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 23. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 264-265. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. Gen.,” p. 76. Viola, “Scavi” p. 12. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 25 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of L. Vousius Faustus and M. Vousius Faustus (I.ii.10)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_10/house_of_l._vousius_faustus_and_m._volusius_faustus-i.ii.10/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2020 18:18:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_10/house_of_l._vousius_faustus_and_m._volusius_faustus-i.ii.10/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 10
Garden House of L. Vousius Faustus and M. Vousius Faustus (I.ii.10)
Keywords  aedicules archaeological garden biclinia drains lararia mural paintings (visual works) piscinae triclinia  Garden Description The garden at the rear of the house, excavated in 1873, is almost totally destroyed. According to Mau, most of the garden was occupied by a large pool (5.40 X 2.90 m.) which was sloped toward the west from where it drained into the street through a pipe. The pool was surrounded by a low wall about 0.55 m. high leaving only a narrow space between the pool and the walls. In the northwest corner were the two beds of a masonry biclinium which sloped toward the wall, as was customary. Rainwater falling on them was carried away by a terra-cotta drain which emptied into the pool. A square niche under the north couch provided a storage space. On the wall above this couch was a rectangular niche lararium with a roughly made aedicula facade (Fig. 3, 2.19.72). At the east end of this couch was a masonry table. Fiorelli reports a planting bed attached to the rear (east) wall. There was a view from the triclinium through the large window in the east wall, across the pool to the garden painting on the rear wall.
Garden Painting
When this garden was excavated in 1873, the excavators reported three panels on the east wall with garden paintings. The center panel had a body of water with swimming fish with assorted animals in the background that included a grazing deer and a springing leopard. The two panels on either side each had a large crater-shaped fountain surrounded by thick growth. Large red flowers and yellow apples could be identified to the left of each fountain and the right, pomegranates (Punica granatum L.). Jashemski examined this painting in 1964 to find it had been covered by a growth of ivy which had destroyed most of the painting. A section of a large pomegranate bush was all that was left intact at the time. She describes the leaves, painted in blue-green with darker shading and a few yellow leaves and the fruit, deep yellow with reddish-orange shading, as being rendered in an impressionistic manner. At the right of the entrance to the garden area was a cistern opening. Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I.ii.10; 2.19.72, S. A. Jashemski.   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1873
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 22, no. 6. Fiorelli, Descr., p. 42. (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), col. 57.  Jashemski, Gardens, 1:1 10-1 1 1. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 22. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 313. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 197-198. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. Gen.,” p. 76. Schefold, WandP, p. 9 (describes this painting as a paradeisos, with sea, deer, panther, and nymphaeum). (worldcat)  Sogliano, “Pitture,” p. 224, no. 694. (worldcat)  Soprano, p.305, no. 23. Viola, “Scavi” p. 11. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 24 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban House on Lungenstrasse</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_lungenstrasse/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:53:55 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_lungenstrasse/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Garden Urban house on Lungenstrasse (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords  peristyles (Roman courtyards) mural paintings (visual works)  Garden Description In the second half of the 1st century A.D. a large peristyle house was constructed on the western fringe of the city, built on the remains of abandoned pottery kilns. The peristyle courtyard of the house was at least 13 x 21 m. in size, but the structural remains were badly damaged when a temple complex was erected on the site around the middle of the 2nd century Neither the complete ground plan nor the extent of the building could be determined.
In the leveled remains of the 1st century house were fragments of painted wall plaster, including fragments of scenes depicting gardens (Image 1). These show trees against a sky-blue background. It is uncertain which rooms of the house were decorated in this way.
Maps Images   Fragments of garden paintings from the peristyle courtyard house on Lungengasse (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium). Photo courtesy of M. Carroll.   Dates mid-first to mid-second century CE
Bibliography None
Pleiades ID 108751
TGN ID 7004446
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 13 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban House on Wolfsstrasse</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_wolfsstrasse/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:52:13 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_wolfsstrasse/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Garden Urban house on Wolfsstrasse (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords  urban villas villae urbanae colonnades peristyles (Roman courtyards) mural paintings (visual works)  Garden Description Only a fraction of this house in the immediate vicinity of the House on Gertrudenstraße was excavated. Enough was salvaged, however, to be able to recognize that the house was of the peristyle type (Plan 1). The house was built after the middle of the 1st century A.D. By the mid-4th century the building was ruinous and the stones of most of the walls were robbed for reuse elsewhere.
The peristyle courtyard was ca. 7 m. wide and 11.30 m. long. Both faces of the wall surrounding it were plastered and painted red. Presumably the wall was several courses high, much like a balustrade, with columns on top. There was a doorway or monumental entrance, 3.50 m. wide, to the courtyard at the southeast. The corridor around the garden was 3.10 m. wide and had a beaten earth floor resurfaced more than once. Most of the original earth in the courtyard had been disturbed or removed in post-Roman times, but there was clearly no sign of a paved surface or beaten earth floors that had been trodden in the courtyard, so that one might postulate the existence of loose garden soil here during the occupation of the house (G on Plan 1). In the northern part of the courtyard was a deep, circular shaft which may have been a well (W on Plan 1), the stone courses of which had been robbed out.
Maps Plans   Plan 1: Plan of the partially excavated courtyard house with a possible garden (G) containing a well (W) on Wolfsstraße. Adapted from Carroll-Spillecke 1997, fig. 7. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Middle of the first century CE until the fourth century CE
Bibliography  M. Carroll-Spillecke, “Ausgrabungen in einem römischen Wohnviertel in der Wolfsstraße/Richmodstraße in Köln,” Kölner Jahrbuch 30 (1997): 415-31. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108751
TGN ID 7004446
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 12 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>