<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>mural paintings on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/mural-paintings/</link>
    <description>Recent content in mural paintings on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 12:00:02 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/mural-paintings/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Grotto of catullus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/region_x/sirmio/grotto_of_catullus/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/region_x/sirmio/grotto_of_catullus/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Sirmio
Sirmio (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region X
Garden House of Grotto of Aatullus
Keywords  insulae cryptoportici vestibules piscinae peristyles (columnades) porticoes bathhouses (water recreation structures) atriums ditches water supply systems water baths gutters (building drainage components) drains loam basins (vessels) statues cisterns (plumbing components) terrazzo water wells orchards presence chambers fences (site elements) exedrae (site elements) garden pavilions reception rooms terrazzo  Garden Description Sirmio is known from a citation in Catullus’ XXXI° poem (paene insularum, Sirmio, insularumque ocelle &amp;hellip;) and in later road itineraries as a staging post (Sermione mansio) along the road between Verona and Brixia (Brescia), which passed to the south of the peninsula, forming part of the erritory of Verona. In several areas along this ancient coastline remains have been brought to light of large and sumptuous villas built on the coast, in large coves or high places, with beautiful panoramas.The remains of a villa, called by fifteenth-century visitors to the site “Grotte di Catullo”, after Verona’s poet Catullus, are situated at the northern tip of the Sirmione peninsula, on the southern bank of the Benacus(Lake Garda), the largest of the pre-alpine lakes (Fig.1). As one of the most interesting examples of Roman residential architecture in northern Italy, this villa deserves the designation of villa maritima, as other similar examples along the Campanium-Latium coast.The villa covers an area of around 20,000 square meters distributed on three terraces, which ascend the slope of the hill on a series of substructures. The building has a rectangular plan (167.5 x 105 meters), with two foreparts; on the S side at the main entrance and on the N side at the tip of the peninsula, towards which the villa faced, so as to be surrounded by the lake on three sides (Fig. 2).On the evidence of recent studies, the villa is dated to the Augustan-Tiberian period (end of the first century B.C. –start of the first century A.D.): it was constructed after the destruction of an earlier building, the existence of which has been documented in a small archaeological excavation beneath the floor of one of the rooms on the southern side of the villa. Modifications to the building, in particular the creation of the large baths area, date to the end of the first –second century A.D. The destruction of the villa came quickly, with all probability around the 3rd century: at that time the functioning of the villa seems to have stopped and no later maintenance or building interventions have been identified; a differing situation as regards the other villas in the lake Garda area, which had a continued life, with phases of great importance, up to the first half of the fifth century.The building, constructed as a whole and with axial and symmetrical criteria, is characterized by long terraces on the eastern, western and northern sides: these connect directly with the large terrace on the northern forepart, which was shaded by a veiled covering, as demonstrated by the characteristic elements which supported the posts found in this area. By the side of the terraces were long porticoes: the western one built over a double-nave cryptoporticus, which acted as a substructure, the eastern for the main part built directly on the natural bedrock. The residential rooms were distributed in the northern and southern areas, the western part of the latter being occupied by the baths complex (Fig. 3-4).While the substructures are well-preserved, the residential floor, situated on the higher level, has been subject to greater destruction over the course of the centuries, due to the systematic robbing of building materials, already started in ancient times, the collapse of part of the wall on the eastern side along the hill-side, and in the agricultural use of the land, presently occupied by a vast olive grove (Fig. 5). The villa has been excavated on several occasions from the start of the 19th century and subsequently backfilled, so that the plan and hypotheses for the reconstruction for a large part of the residential level, which has not been the object of new research in recent years, are based on the notes and drawings of the 19th century, not always reliable. Other excavations were conducted between 1941 and 1965; research aimed at defining the chronology of the building and resolving problems in the plan of several rooms in the southern area were undertaken between 1984 and 1994.The events endured by the structure render difficult and at times impossible, at present, to hypothesize the functions and characteristics of many of the residential rooms, as also with the various open spaces present within the building. Undoubtedly, other than the large peristyle (C), which occupied the central area of the building, other open spaces, now buried (courtyards or gardens), were to be found along the central N-S axis. In the southern part there was an open space (N), situated between the western part of the villa, destined as the baths complex, and the eastern part containing the living rooms. In this case, according to the interpretation of the director of the first excavations and more recently, the area functioned as a courtyard giving access and light to the rooms on its E, S and W sides. A wall divided the courtyard from the S side of the peristyle, to which direct access was possible by one or more entrances. Another hypothesis suggests that access between the two courtyards was not axial but by a side corridor, while a wall with windows would have permitted a view of the internal garden.Of the other open space (O), situated to the N, there is uncertainty as to its function. One can hypothesize, on the basis of the 19th century plans, an open space with porticoes on all four sides: perhaps another small peristyle. An element which would confirm its use as a courtyard or garden is the presence of a stone-built rainwater drain, still present in the 19th century and illustrated by Orti Manara in his publication on Sirmione. Some parts of this drain have been re-used in the walls of the Early Medieval church of San Salvatore in Sirmione. There are no precise indications for external gardens and it is only possible to hypothesize the natural setting in which the villa was situated. However it must be stated that artificial terraces had been made on the eastern side of the building, or more precisely the areas which corresponded to the N-E and S-E corners, formed by the two foreparts of the villa. In the first (H) the bedrock has been cut to a depth of around 4 meters to create a large terrace, which occupied the whole area as far as the drop in level towards the lake (Fig.6). It is interesting that the second artificial terrace (I), of more limited extension, at around 10 meters below the residential level of the villa and reached by a flight of steps, was still known in the 19th century, by ancient tradition and without apparent justification, as “the garden.”The large central open space (C), beginning from the 19th century, was identified as a courtyard-viridarium. It is formed by an area of around 4000 square meters, equivalent to about one fifth of the whole area of the villa (Fig.7). Both the 19th century excavations and more recent trenches have failed to locate the presence of structures or floors, and it is therefore possible to hypothesize that the area functioned as a garden, probably surrounded on all four sides by porticoes as indicated in the 19th century plans and supported by recent research.The present land use, with many trees, and the thin soil cover in respect to the original ground surface, no longer permit the acquisition of data to allow a more precise reconstruction of the ancient garden, its internal sub-divisions, the types of vegetation, the possible ornamentation. On the S side of the peristyle is located a large perfectly preserved underground cistern (66), of a length corresponding to the width of the peristyle (42.60 x 2.40 meters). It is covered by a herringbone floor in small bricks, 6 meters wide and around 50 meters long (fig.8). Rainwater, collected in this part of the building, flowed into the cistern through a series of lead fistulae which entered the S-E and S-W corners, as is demonstrated by holes in the floor created by the robbing of the lead pipes, of which fortunately a small part is still preserved in the S-W corner, where it enters the cistern. The floor of the cistern has a slope of 7-8% from S to N: on the northern side four channels collected rain water and allowed it to flow in an organized manner towards the garden, with a slope of 6% (fig.9). The channel was formed in the initial part by a prolongation of the herringbone brick floor, which with its tapering form towards the external area helped the entry of rainwater into the channel, which flowed beneath the ancient ground surface (Fig. 10). The channels, lined with hydraulic mortar, were excavated in the bedrock, which outcropped on the eastern side and were covered with thin stone slabs. On the opposite side they were constructed in the earth and only their lower parts are preserved, the covering and the ancient floor shaving been robbed. Given the slope of the channels, their conformation and number, it is to be excluded that they had the sole function of draining the rainwater from the brick floor, and it may be hypothesized that they also served the function of directing to the garden the water which was extracted from the cistern, perhaps for irrigation.Water was drawn from the cistern by one or more wells: in the 19th century a well-curb, which was said to have come from the area of cistern, was still preserved in Sirmione. By the side of the cut which housed one of the well-curbs, two square holes had been cut into the floor in ancient times. It is hypothesized that they held the posts for the structure supporting the ropes and vessel used to extract water from the cistern (girgillus).There are no other elements to help describe the form of the large peristyle. Two pieces which may have formed part of the decoration of the garden are composed of sculptural fragments: a head dating to the second century A.D., found in the soil inside the cistern (66), and a sundial, presently lost, but fortunately represented by a drawing. Given the location, the head must have come from the peristyle, and can be hypothesized as belonging to the statue of a Dioscuros (fig. 11). In Greek marble, it is broken at the level of the chin. The head is covered by a pilos, from which issue locks of hair, curling on the forehead and sides of the face.There are no useful clues to help reconstruct the vegetation, which may have been present in and around the villa.The climate of Lake Garda is sub-Mediterranean, determined by the notably large mass of water which tends to maintain a constant temperature, much milder than the rest of the cisalpine area. The cultivation of olives already existed in Roman times, as documented by botanical evidence from recent excavations at Sirmione and the strong spread of the plant both in the locality and the whole area around Lake Garda in the Early Medieval period. In the same manner grapes were probably also cultivated, indirectly represented by an inscription found near Sirmione (fig. 12). Probably also common in the Roman period were the native species, shrubs such as oleander and rosemary and trees such as cypress, bay, ash and several species of oak, documented in the last two examples by botanic remains found at Sirmione, recently analyzed by the Archaeobiological Laboratory of the Civic Museums of Como.
Plans {&amp;lt; figure src=&amp;rdquo;../images/sirmio-2.png&amp;rdquo; alt=&amp;quot;Fig. 2: Plan of House of Grotto of Catullus.&amp;rdquo; title=&amp;quot;Fig. 2: Plan of House of Grotto of Catullus&amp;rdquo; &amp;gt;}}
  Fig. 3: Plan of the residential rooms     Fig. 5: Aerial view of vast olive grove     Fig. 7: Aerial view of courtyard-viridarium     Fig. 11: statue of a Dioscuros     Fig. 12: Figure of Plant fossils   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1801
Bibliography  G.G. Orti Manara, La penisola di Sirmione sul lago di Garda, Verona 1856.(worldcat) N. Degrassi, Le Grotte di Catullo, Taranto 1956. (worldcat) M. MirabellaRoberti, La villa romana di Sirmione, Milano 1958, pp.157-162.(worldcat) T.P.Wiseman, Le Grotte di Catullo. Una villa romana e i suoi proprietari, Brescia 1990. (worldcat) E. Roffia, Sirmione, le “grotte di Catullo”, in Ville romane sul lago di Garda, a cura di E.Roffia, Brescia 1997, pp.141-169. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 870993210
TGN ID 7005771
Contributor Tom Elliott (https://pleiades.stoa.org/author/thomase)
Publication date 15 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb garden of A. Coelius C. f.</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/region_x/patavium/tomb_garden_of_a_coelius_c_f/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/region_x/patavium/tomb_garden_of_a_coelius_c_f/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Patavium
Patavium (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region X
Garden Tomb garden of A. Coelius C. f.
Keywords  tombs epitaphs stelae mausoleums  Garden Description A broken marble slab immured in the cathedral at Padua since the seventeenth century records the epitaph of A. Coelius C. f., who some time in the first or second century dedicated to the divine spirits (Dis Manibus) and to himself in perpetuity a garden that had once, it seems, belonged to an Arius (hortum… Arianum). Whether it had always been a tomb garden or was only then being converted to a funerary use is uncertain.
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date unspecified
Bibliography  CIL 5.2935  Pleiades ID 393473
TGN ID 77003085
Contributor Brady Kiesling (https://pleiades.stoa.org/author/bkiesling)
Publication date 15 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of L. Ogius Patroclus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/region_x/altinum/tomb_garden_of_l.-ogius_patroclus/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/region_x/altinum/tomb_garden_of_l.-ogius_patroclus/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location ALTINUM
ALTINUM (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region X
Garden Tomb Garden of L. Ogius Patroclus
Keywords  tombs epitaphs stelae grove (sacred grove) vegetable gardens  Garden Description A marble slab reported at Altinum in the sixteenth century and now in Venice records, above a depiction of an axe, a plumb-line, and a tree with birds, the epitaph of L. Ogius Patroclus, who some time (probably) in the late first or second century, “following the tradition of dutiful respect maintained by the corporation of firemen, donated while still living the gardens with building adjoining the tomb, so that from their revenue roses and food would be supplied generously for his patron and, eventually, for himself” (secutus pietatem col(legii) cent(onariorum) hortos cum aedificio huic sepult(urae) {a} iunctos vivos donavit, ut ex reditu eor(um) largius rosae et esce patrono suo et quandoque sibi ponerentur). The pairing of roses for the dead and food for the living (rosae et escae) was common in Roman funerary celebrations at the grave site, which perhaps suggests that mixed planting of flowers and vegetables was common in Roman tomb gardens as well (cf. ILS 6711, 8371).
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 16th century
Bibliography  CIL 5.2176 ILS 8369  Pleiades ID 197110
TGN ID 4000603
Contributor Sean Gillies (https://pleiades.stoa.org/author/sgillies)
Publication date 15 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb garden of T. Vettius Hermes</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/region_ix/vardagate/tomb_garden_of_t.-vettius_hermes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/region_ix/vardagate/tomb_garden_of_t.-vettius_hermes/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Vardagate
Vardagate (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region IX
Garden Tomb garden of T. Vettius Hermes
Keywords  tombs epitaphs stelae  Garden Description A marble stele now in a church at Grazzano records the epitaph of T. Vettius Hermes, a freedman ointment dealer (seplasiarius). After a gnomic sentiment about chthonic birthand reunion (mater genuit materq(ue) recepiit), Hermes goes on to declare that “these gardens, as great and excellent as they are, (will) serve my ashes, for I shall appoint caretakers to dine on the proceeds from them on my birthday and on the day of roses, in perpetuity” (hi horti ita uti o(ptimi) m(aximi)/que sunt cineribus seruite(!) meis nam curatores substituam uti uescantur ex horum hortorum reditu natale meo et per rosam in perpetuo).
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date unspecified
Bibliography  CIL5.7454, cf. p. 7454 ILS8342  Pleiades ID 383809
TGN ID unspecified
Contributor Sean Gillies (https://pleiades.stoa.org/author/sgillies)
Publication date 15 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa at Pola&#34;</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/region_x/barbariga/villa_at_pola/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/region_x/barbariga/villa_at_pola/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location BARBARIGA
BARBARIGA (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region X
Garden Villa at Pola
Keywords  mosaics (visual works) cryptoportici gutters (building drainage components) podiums (building divisions) peristyles (columnades) porticoes tesserae villae urbanae reception rooms atrium houses mural paintings (visual works) presence chambers  Garden Description This large maritime villa consisted of two parts, labeled “summer villa” and “winter villa”. The “summer” quarters unfold around a U-shaped peristyle, open on the sea-side, with central garden measuring 31.8 x 26.2 m. (fig. 2: 4). No traces of a pool or fountain were found in the center of the garden. The portico, 2.40 m wide, had a mosaic floor in black tesserae with a white border. Many rooms looked into the peristyle, with the main one probably being a triclinium (Fig. 1). On the two opposite corners of this side of the courtyard were also service rooms: Room 6 was the kitchen, 15 maybe a storeroom (many amphorae were recovered, but the room had a mosaic floor). Of the rooms around the peristyle, Room 31 was the most lavishly decorated. The back wall presented a semicircular niche with a statue-base, the floor had an elaborate polychrome mosaic, and the walls were covered with marble slabs. South of the “summer villa” was a long cryptoportico, flanking a garden, no longer preserved, but known from nineteenth century archival documents. The villa was built in the first century A.D. and, at least in part, was used down to the sixth century A.D.
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1801
Bibliography  M. De Franceschini, 1998, Le ville romane della X regio: Venetia et Histria. Catalogo e carta archeologica dell’insediamento romano nel territorio, dall’età repubblicana al tardo impero, Roma.(worldcat)  Pleiades ID 870993210
TGN ID 7005771
Contributor Tom Elliott (https://pleiades.stoa.org/author/thomase)
Publication date 15 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa of the Bath</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/region_x/tergeste/villa_of_the_bath/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/region_x/tergeste/villa_of_the_bath/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Tergeste
Tergeste (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region X
Garden Villa of the Bath
Keywords  archaeological garden cisterns (plumbing components) gutters (building drainage components) villae urbanae peristyles (columnades) porticoes bathhouses (water recreation structures) water baths courtyards atrium houses corridors  Garden Description Remains discovered in 1888 revealed a large semicircular garden (Fig. 1: c) enclosed by a portico (b), into which opened a series of rooms (d to p). A corridor (a) connected this garden to a bath quarter that boasted a nymphaeum (t) and a panoramic view onto the sea. A similar semicircular portico and garden was in the villa of Anguillara Sabatia, but the radial disposition of the rooms of the ‘Villa della Terma’s’ pars urbana is unusual, revealing a desire to lend each room a view onto the garden. The preservation of this villa is poor because for centuries it was scavenged for building material. Dated material ranges from the first century B.C. (brick stamps) to the early fifth century A.D. (coins). It is possible that these remains were part of the nearby “Villa della Statua.”
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1888
Bibliography  M. De Franceschini, 1998, Le ville romane della X regio: Venetia et Histria. Catalogo e carta archeologica dell’insediamento romano nel territorio, dall’età repubblicana al tardo impero, Roma.(worldcat)  Pleiades ID 187578
TGN ID 7005539
Contributor Brady Kiesling
Publication date 15 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa of the Statue (I.iii.23)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/region_x/tergeste/villa_of_the_statue/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/region_x/tergeste/villa_of_the_statue/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Tergeste
Tergeste (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region X
Garden Villa of the Statue
Keywords  archaeological garden cisterns (plumbing components) gutters (building drainage components) mural paintings (visual works) peristyles (columnades) porticoes mosaic pergolas bathhouses (water recreation structures) water baths atrium houses atriums nymphaea (garden structures) tesserae ceramic tile opus sectile (visual works) opus signinum garden pavilions [apsed triclinium] [archaeological garden]  Garden Description A villa dating from the first century B.C. to at least the time of Marcus Aurelius was discovered near the modern via Miramare in Barcola. It overlooked the sea to the west and had a portico at the south (Fig. 1: B), with rooms opening onto it. The main nucleus of the villa unfolded around a rectangular garden surrounded by porticoes on all four sides (the long sides measure 24.5 m.; the short ones 15.2; Fig. 1: U). A rectangular brick pool with a black mosaic pavement was in the north-east portion of the garden (Fig. 1: a). It pre-dates the portico, since it was partly destroyed by the paving of the north-east portico. A terminus post quem for the construction of the portico was determined by a coin of Nero, found inside the pool.
During nineteenth century excavations, fragments of two superimposed wall paintings were recovered in Room C. The outer layer is not well enough preserved to identify any subject, but the preserved fragments beneath show branches and leaves with colored backgrounds of light blue, red, yellow and white. It is, therefore, possible that this cycle of painting depicted a garden, echoing the view of the real plantings visible through the doorway.
North of the peristyle was the bath quarter (Fig. 1: G, H, I, M, P), but it is not completely clear how the two parts of the villa were connected. In a partially excavated Tuscan type atrium (G) with an impluvium, several fragments of a marble torso were recovered, possible from a copy of the Polykleitan Doryphoros or Diadumenos. On the west side of the villa facing the sea was a porticoed garden (Z) and large semicircular exedra (24 m in diameter). Under the mosaic floor of this exedra are traces of an earlier room (Fig. 1: a) with a mosaic floor. On axis with the center of the exedra and garden was a triclinium (6.2 x 12 m) with a black-and-white mosaic floor. Another exedra (7.5 x 15 m), with a black-and-white mosaic floor, had large windows looking to the sea, and beside it a staircase leading to the water’s edge and to a dock.
Dates 100 B.C.
Excavation Date 19th century
Bibliography  M. De Franceschini, 1998, Le ville romane della X regio: Venetia et Histria. Catalogo e carta archeologica dell’insediamento romano nel territorio, dall’età repubblicana al tardo impero, Roma.(worldcat)  Pleiades ID 187578
TGN ID 7005539
Contributor Brady Kiesling
Publication date 15 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb garden of T. Vettius Hermes (I.iii.23)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/region_xi/vardagate/tomb_garden_of_t.-vettius_hermes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/region_xi/vardagate/tomb_garden_of_t.-vettius_hermes/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Vardagate
Vardagate (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region IX
Garden Tomb garden of T. Vettius Hermes
Keywords  tombs epitaphs stelae  Garden Description A marble stele now in a church at Grazzano records the epitaph of T. Vettius Hermes, a freedman ointment dealer (seplasiarius). After a gnomic sentiment about chthonic birthand reunion (mater genuit materq(ue) recepiit), Hermes goes on to declare that “these gardens, as great and excellent as they are, (will) serve my ashes, for I shall appoint caretakers to dine on the proceeds from them on my birthday and on the day of roses, in perpetuity” (hi horti ita uti o(ptimi) m(aximi)/que sunt cineribus seruite(!) meis nam curatores substituam uti uescantur ex horum hortorum reditu natale meo et per rosam in perpetuo).
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date unspecified
Bibliography  CIL5.7454, cf. p. 7454 ILS8342  Pleiades ID 383809
TGN ID unspecified
Contributor Sean Gillies (https://pleiades.stoa.org/author/sgillies)
Publication date 25 Oct 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Funerary Grove of Q. Cervonius Chryseros</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/region_x/aquileia/funerary_grove_of_q.-cervonius_chryseros/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/region_x/aquileia/funerary_grove_of_q.-cervonius_chryseros/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Aquileia
Aquileia (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region X
Garden Funerary Grove of Q. Cervonius Chryseros
Keywords  tombs stelae grove (sacred grove) altars (religious fixtures)  Garden Description A small inscribed altar of (probably) the Julio-Claudian era found by Mommsen among the stones of Aquileia and now lost records on its left and right sides dedications to Dis Pater and (H)era respectively and, on its front, the name of the dedicant, a consul’s aide (acc(ensus) co(n)s(ularis)) and local sevir at Florentia, Q. Cervonius Chryseros, who built “the grove, the enclosure wall, the altars, the mound (? molem), and the seats” (lucum, maceriem, aras, molem, [s]edilia). The dedication to Dis Pater suggests a funerary context, which leads Chioffi to identify the molis as a tomb monument of some ill-defined type (perhaps an irregular mound?). A Roman soldier serving in lower Germany at Carvium (Herwen) was buried by his two heirs ad molem, “near (or at) the mound” (AE 1939, 130). The same Chryseros perhaps appears as the owner of a slave, Fausta, who in fulfillment of a vow dedicated another monument to Dis Pater at Aquileia (CIL 5.35*).
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date unspecified
Bibliography  G. B. Brusin, Inscriptiones Aquileiae, Udine 1991-1993, no. 192.(worldcat) S. Panciera, Libitina e dintorni : Libitina e i luci sepolcrali, Rome 2004, nn. 17-31. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 187290
TGN ID 7005553
Contributor Sean Gillies (https://pleiades.stoa.org/author/sgillies)
Publication date 15 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban House on Lungenstrasse</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_lungenstrasse/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:53:55 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_lungenstrasse/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Garden Urban house on Lungenstrasse (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords  peristyles (Roman courtyards) mural paintings (visual works)  Garden Description In the second half of the 1st century A.D. a large peristyle house was constructed on the western fringe of the city, built on the remains of abandoned pottery kilns. The peristyle courtyard of the house was at least 13 x 21 m. in size, but the structural remains were badly damaged when a temple complex was erected on the site around the middle of the 2nd century Neither the complete ground plan nor the extent of the building could be determined.
In the leveled remains of the 1st century house were fragments of painted wall plaster, including fragments of scenes depicting gardens (Image 1). These show trees against a sky-blue background. It is uncertain which rooms of the house were decorated in this way.
Maps Images   Fragments of garden paintings from the peristyle courtyard house on Lungengasse (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium). Photo courtesy of M. Carroll.   Dates mid-first to mid-second century CE
Bibliography None
Pleiades ID 108751
TGN ID 7004446
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 13 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban House on Wolfsstrasse</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_wolfsstrasse/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:52:13 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_wolfsstrasse/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Garden Urban house on Wolfsstrasse (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords  urban villas villae urbanae colonnades peristyles (Roman courtyards) mural paintings (visual works)  Garden Description Only a fraction of this house in the immediate vicinity of the House on Gertrudenstraße was excavated. Enough was salvaged, however, to be able to recognize that the house was of the peristyle type (Plan 1). The house was built after the middle of the 1st century A.D. By the mid-4th century the building was ruinous and the stones of most of the walls were robbed for reuse elsewhere.
The peristyle courtyard was ca. 7 m. wide and 11.30 m. long. Both faces of the wall surrounding it were plastered and painted red. Presumably the wall was several courses high, much like a balustrade, with columns on top. There was a doorway or monumental entrance, 3.50 m. wide, to the courtyard at the southeast. The corridor around the garden was 3.10 m. wide and had a beaten earth floor resurfaced more than once. Most of the original earth in the courtyard had been disturbed or removed in post-Roman times, but there was clearly no sign of a paved surface or beaten earth floors that had been trodden in the courtyard, so that one might postulate the existence of loose garden soil here during the occupation of the house (G on Plan 1). In the northern part of the courtyard was a deep, circular shaft which may have been a well (W on Plan 1), the stone courses of which had been robbed out.
Maps Plans   Plan 1: Plan of the partially excavated courtyard house with a possible garden (G) containing a well (W) on Wolfsstraße. Adapted from Carroll-Spillecke 1997, fig. 7. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Middle of the first century CE until the fourth century CE
Bibliography  M. Carroll-Spillecke, “Ausgrabungen in einem römischen Wohnviertel in der Wolfsstraße/Richmodstraße in Köln,” Kölner Jahrbuch 30 (1997): 415-31. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108751
TGN ID 7004446
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 12 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
