<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>mural paintings on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/mural-paintings/</link>
    <description>Recent content in mural paintings on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:53:55 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/mural-paintings/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban House on Lungenstrasse</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_lungenstrasse/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:53:55 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_lungenstrasse/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Urban house on Lungenstrasse (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords peristyles (Roman courtyards)
mural paintings (visual works)
Garden Description In the second half of the 1st century A.D. a large peristyle house was constructed on the western fringe of the city, built on the remains of abandoned pottery kilns. The peristyle courtyard of the house was at least 13 x 21 m. in size, but the structural remains were badly damaged when a temple complex was erected on the site around the middle of the 2nd century Neither the complete ground plan nor the extent of the building could be determined.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban House on Wolfsstrasse</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_wolfsstrasse/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:52:13 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_wolfsstrasse/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Urban house on Wolfsstrasse (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords urban villas
villae urbanae
colonnades
peristyles (Roman courtyards)
mural paintings (visual works)
Garden Description Only a fraction of this house in the immediate vicinity of the House on Gertrudenstraße was excavated. Enough was salvaged, however, to be able to recognize that the house was of the peristyle type (Plan 1). The house was built after the middle of the 1st century A.D. By the mid-4th century the building was ruinous and the stones of most of the walls were robbed for reuse elsewhere.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>