<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>fences on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/fences/</link>
    <description>Recent content in fences on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2020 17:12:15 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/fences/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa in Vallon (Sur Dompierre, Canton de Fribourg, Switzerland)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vallon/vallon_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2020 17:12:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vallon/vallon_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Vallon
Vallon (Pleiades)
Garden Villa in Vallon (Sur Dompierre, Canton de Fribourg, Switzerland)
Keywords  arbors barns cisterns (plumbing components) ceramic tile ditches fences (site elements) hearths horrea kitchen gardens mosaics (visual works) orchards pedestals pillars piscinae porticoes sherds tesserae villae rusticae water supply systems  Garden Description Located 6km south-east of Avenches/ Aventicum, the capital of the Helvetian tribe, this site is situated on a small alluvial terrace at the bottom of a hillside. The area is bordered by a stream, the Laret, characterized by a flow, sometimes torrential, that has fluctuated during the past centuries. To the west, on the right bank, stands the rocky spur of Carignan (Fig. 1). Due to the relatively restrictive topography, human settlements favoured the left bank until the Middle Ages.
On the spur east of the stream, a building made of a light structure, apparently isolated, is constructed at the beginning of the 1st c. CE; it is bordered on its southern and northern sides by two roads. During the years 30/40 CE, a peripheral gallery on wooden pillars is placed around it. Its layout rather suggests an annex of a villa rustica or perhaps even a simple house in an urban context. Between 50 and 70 CE, it is surrounded by two other constructions, which together with the first building take on the characteristic shape of an “L”. The northern house is made of several habitation rooms; as it is bordered by a portico, it recalls the dwelling places of the medium-sized villae rusticae discovered in Switzerland. The southern building, surrounded by galleries, is laid out around a 100 m2 large kitchen, containing a large central hearth, which separates, to the south, the rooms designed for habitation, and the areas, to the north, apparently dedicated to utilitarian activities. At the back of the southern construction, a fourth building was erected, a barn (horreum) recognizable because of the network of pillars that supported an elevated floor.
A wall section, placed under a later separating wall, already indicates the existence of a division of the area between the northern and southern parts of the garden. The occupation layer is marked by a number of undated hollow structures. A ditch, boarded on the east by two big oval pits, distinguishes itself by its orientation which is parallel to the front of the central building, but its function still remains unknown: could it be an early garden arrangement? The only palynological analysis undertaken in a trench opened in the north building, suggest a tree canopy composed of a mixture of oaks, birches and hazel trees, in the second half of the 1st century CE; alders and willow trees could be found along the stream banks. An abundance of ferns and conifers grew in the surrounding areas. Herbaceous vegetation was intermingled with cereals. The information in our possession is too scarce to allow us to interpret it as a garden. Traces of equidistant posts or peg holes appear to form the outline of structures that are still difficult to explain (light arbour-like construction?). This open space is confined by a small bank to the south. Below it, the area is crossed by two long perpendicular depressions that could have a natural origin (paleochannel?), re-used as rubbish disposals at the beginning of our era. The south-east oriented channel, originally interpreted as a clay extraction pit, was cleared over a distance of approximately thirty meters. It was seven to eight meters wide, 1,2 meters deep and contained, in its lower part, several conduits made from pine trees (fig. 3). These timber elements were not assembled but stored in a humid environment before being used. The preparation and preservation of wood for plumbing systems, suggests the existence, from the first Antique settlements, of a very elaborate running water supply system, its use in domestic and/or handicraft or farming activities still needs to be clarified. Dendrochronology reveals two time series, dated to the autumn/winter 3/4 CE and 32/33 CE. These dates, that are contemporary with the first building stages of the villa, are very early for Switzerland and are close to Avenche’s first dated constructions.
The edges of the channel, which are gradually filled in, are bordered by two small fences in the last quarter of the Ist century; these fittings may be the result of a wish to stabilize the banks of the channel, clearly still under water at that time. Later on, the channel is filled in by a new rubbish disposal that seals the fences. We know nothing about the appearance of the area (courtyard or garden?) which extended between the channel and the southern building.
The profound architectural developments that took place in the three habitation buildings from the years 150/160 CE, had repercussions on the gardens (fig. 2). The occupation layer of the courtyards to the west of the buildings is raised by bringing in a large amount of ballast material. The subdivision of the garden zone is not precisely known. To the west of the constructed area, in the northern area bordered by the waterway, a pedestal indicates the presence of a statuary decoration that will be removed by the next generation. A long masonry wall, decorated with pillars presumably sculpted, is the only partition element brought to light. It marks the boundaries of an area interpreted as an ornamental garden, onto which the northern building and the northern part of the central building open. Divided into two zones, the oriental part of the northern garden is covered with tiles, revealing in its northern corner a fountain; it is replaced, in its western part, by soil around which a fence was probably built. It communicates directly with a second ornamental garden situated on the side of the central building, maybe destined for the private use of the family and close relatives. Here too, the remains are sparse: a patch stretches along the separation wall with the northern garden. A path followed the central building. Others must have crossed beds of plants edged with vertical ceramic elements. In other places, wooden posts formed rows that are still difficult to elucidate but that may indicate the outline of arbours. In the same place were found meander shaped ditches which do not follow the exact same orientation as the buildings (fig. 4). Were they hedges that were part of a vegetal maze? Despite the absence of palynological facts, they can be compared to the ditches excavated in the gardens of the Fishbourne Villa (England) or to those in the pars urbana of Dietikon’s villae (canton of Zurich).
At the end of the first archaeological excavations (1985-2000), we favoured the hypothesis of a subdivision of the area to the west of the buildings into three juxtaposed courtyards which echoed the tripartition of the constructions. They contained two ornamental gardens, in the north and in the center, and a courtyard that sheltered a kitchen garden and an orchard at the front of the southern building, dedicated to utilitarian activities (fig. 5). The recent research does not support a division of the area into three distinctive courtyards (2006/2010). The second garden, which presents a regular incline to the south, does not show any tangible boundary. Did it occupy the whole area in the front of the south building, or were they garden arrangements (hedges) dividing it? (fig. 6) Traces of vegetation being very hard to spot on the surface of the ground of the gardens, no definitive conclusion can be drawn.
The recent discovery of the lower part of a pool in front of the south building has also casts doubts on its utilitarian function. The structure itself, laid on a foundation of stakes made from oak and alder wood dated by dendrochonology to the years after 160 CE, has been almost entirely retrieved. The interpretation of this structure is still under discussion: it could be a cistern but it is more likely to be an ornamental pool that could have been enhanced by a parietal mosaic composed of the many glass tesserae that were found nearby. The structure, standing against the south building, would be oriented not towards the construction itself, but towards the courtyard where no garden arrangement has been uncovered.
Whereas the courtyards have offered very few traces for the Early Roman Period, the Late Antique Period marks a turning point in the history of Vallon’s gardens. Following a fire, the buildings are reorganized and areas dedicated to handicraft activities appear in the porticoes. A new function is attributed to the courtyards. The rubble of the partially demolished north and central buildings is discarded in the northern garden and the northern part of the second courtyard. To the south of themeander shaped ditches, is built a construction consisting of posts and sill plates, equipped with a ground hearth made out of ceramic tiles. The late occupation of the gardens seems to be linked to the salvage and transformation of building materials collected in the edifices. Other post structures (constructions? enclosures?) almost cover the whole area in the front of the southern building. The archaeological objects found (pottery fragments, over a hundred coins) suggest that this occupation partly covers the IVth century and does not go further than the beginning of the Vth century.
After the disappearance of the Antique site, the land continues to be occupied during the Early Middle Ages. The discovery of channels supports the hypothesis that the areas between the new buildings or on their sides, were well enough built to see the creation of an ornamental garden. However, the remains are too disrupted to allow further discussion.
Maps   Fig. 1: Vallon location map. (Rights Statement)     Fig. 2 : map of the habitation zone in the second half of the IInd century of our era.(Rights Statement)   Images   Fig. 3 : pine wood conduits preserved in one of the channels. Photo Fribourg State Archaeological Service. (Rights Statement)     Fig. 4 : ditches uncovered in the courtyard in front of the central building (2006). Photo Fribourg State Archaeological Service. (Rights Statement)     Fig. 5 : scale model of the habitation area in the second half of the IInd century. Built before the research in the gardens was resumed, it presents a considerable partitioning of the various open spaces. Photo Fribourg State Archaeological Service. (Rights Statement)     Fig. 6 : watercolour of the habitation area integrating the first results obtained by excavating the gardens. Please note the less significant partition between the different courtyards. The cistern at the front of the south building (to the right) is highly hypothetical; it seems rather to be an ornamental pool. Watercolour: Bernard Reymond, Yverdon-les-Bains (Switzerland). (Rights Statement)   Dates Beginning of the 1st c. CE - beginning of the Vth century
Excavation Dates 1985-2000, 2006/2010
Bibliography No bibliography listed Pleiades ID 981525
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor Michel Fuchs (ORCID: 0000-0001-8176-8393)
Jacques Monnier (ORCID: N/A)
Publication date 18 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Niederzier Hambach 59</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/niederzier-hambach/niederzier-hambach59/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:55:45 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/niederzier-hambach/niederzier-hambach59/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Province Description Location Niederzier-Hambach
Niederzier-Hambach (Pleiades)
Location Description In the Hambacher Forst region, which lies approximately 30-35 km. west of the former capital city Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium (mod. Cologne), a number of modest villae rusticae have been excavated.
Garden Niederzier Hambach 59
Keywords  villae rusticae ditches fences (site elements) hedges water wells orchards cherry (plant)  Garden Description This farm, known as Hambach 59, was built in the late 1st century A.D. and inhabited until its destruction in the 4th century (Plan 1). The farmhouse, 19.50 x 26 m. in size (A on plan), occupied a position in the northern part of the complex, and looked out on the rest of the farm to the south where various outbuildings and stables stood. There was no division between the residential part and the service area of the farm.
The farmyard was enclosed by a hedge (dotted lines on plan) and took up an area of approximately 1.5 hectares. Outside of the enclosed farmyard to the north were four large plots, presumably for orchards and cultivated fields, which were marked off by ditches or fences (outlined in black on plan). Two of these plots were approximately one hectare in size. The reconstruction of the vegetation on the farm is based on the palaeobotanical analysis of deposits from the four wells in front of the house. The material includes charred fruits and seeds as well as unburnt plant remains and pollen. Cherry pits are evidence for sweet cherry trees. Oak pollen, as well as the water-logged remains of the buds and bud scales of the oak tree, suggest that a shady oak may have grown near one of the wells in the courtyard. Walnut pollen was found in such large quantities in the wells, that one can safely assume the presence of walnut trees near the house. The same applies for lime trees attested by their pollen in the sediments. The remains of coriander and linseed in the wells suggest that these plants may have grown in the vegetable garden in the immediate vicinity of the house. The hedge surrounding the farm compound may have consisted of a combination of hazelnut, elderberry, raspberry and brambleberry, which were all present as pollen, shells, and seeds in the sediments. Box is attested by the pollen in the wells, but it is uncertain where this plant grew on the site.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the farm with hedges (dotted lines) and fences (solid lines) enclosing orchards, fields and the farmyard with its house (A). Plan adapted from Gaitzsch 1990, fig. on p. 238. (Rights statement).   Images Dates Late first century CE until the fourth century CE.
Bibliography  W. Gaitzsch, &amp;ldquo;Der römische Gutshof im &amp;lsquo;Gewährhau’ bei Niederzier,&amp;rdquo; in H. Hellenkemper, H. Koschik and B. Trier, eds., Archäologie in Nordrhein-Westfalen, Cologne, 1990, pp. 235-41. worldcat K.-H. Knörzer and J. Meurers-Balke, &amp;ldquo;Die Wirtschafts- und Nutzflächen eines römischen Gutshofes,&amp;rdquo; in H. Hellenkemper, H. Koschick and B.Trier, eds., Archäologie in Nordrhein-Westfalen, pp. 242-46. worldcat W. Gaitzsch, &amp;ldquo;Antikes Landleben im Modell einer villa rustica,&amp;rdquo; Archäologie im Rheinland 1990, Cologne, 1991, pp. 46-49.  Pleiades ID 109210
TGN ID 7128518
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 24 July 2020
Related articles Niederzier-Hambach 69.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Niederzier Hambach 69</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/niederzier-hambach/niederzier-hambach69/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:55:45 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/niederzier-hambach/niederzier-hambach69/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Province Description Location Niederzier-Hambach
Niederzier-Hambach (Pleiades)
Location Description In the Hambacher Forst region, which lies approximately 30-35 km. west of the former capital city Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium (mod. Cologne), a number of modest villae rusticae have been excavated.
Garden Niederzier Hambach 69
Keywords  villae rusticae fences (site elements) ditches hedges kitchen gardens orchards water wells cherry (plant)  Garden Description This villa rustica was situated west of Cologne in the same region as Hambach 59. It was built in the late 1st century A.D. and inhabited until the 4th century (Plan 1). The farm had a calculated overall area, including the cultivated land, of 50 hectares. The farm compound itself was one hectare in size. The modest house (A on plan) stood just inside the western border of the complex. Elsewhere on the property were various stables, barns, a pond and several wells.
To the east of the house was an area marked off by a narrow ditch (B on plan). This was probably a bedding trench for a protective hedge around a vegetable garden (G on plan). Palaeobotanical material, all of it carbonized, from deposits in wells and pits provide information on the field crops. Considerable amounts of charred chaff in a well in the eastern part of the farmyard suggest that a threshing area for the grain grown on the farm may have been situated near the well. The botanical remains indicate that spelt wheat was the main crop, followed by barley. The farmyard has hedge borders, the planting trenches for which were excavated. Within this area, fruit trees, oaks and alders as well as elderberry bushes possibly were planted.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the farm house (A) and the farmyard enclosed by a hedge (grey line). A vegetable garden (G) may have lain within another hedge (B). Adapted from Gaitzsch 1986, fig. 5. (Rights statement).   Dates Late first century CE until the fourth century CE.
Bibliography  K.-H. Knörzer, &amp;ldquo;Veränderungen der Unkrautvegetation auf rheinischen Bauernhöfen seit der Römerzeit,&amp;rdquo; Bonner Jahrbuch 184, 1984: 491-503. worldcat W. Gaitzsch, &amp;ldquo;Grundformen römischer Landsiedlungen im Westen der CCAA,&amp;rdquo; Bonner Jahrbuch 186, 1986: 397-427, fig. 5. worldcat  Pleiades ID 109210
TGN ID 7128518
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 24 July 2020
Related articles Niederzier-Hambach 59.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Byzantine Law Court and Roof Garden</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/judaea/caesarea_maritima/byzantine_law_court_and_roof_garden/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/judaea/caesarea_maritima/byzantine_law_court_and_roof_garden/</guid>
      <description>Province Judaea
Iudaea (province) (Pleiades)
Province Description Judaea, the Roman province, included parts of the areas of the Hasmonean and Herodium kingdoms, notably Biblical Judah, Samaria, and Edom. Its capital was Caesarea Maritima. Roman influence in the region began in 63 CE, when the Roman general Pompey the Great took over Syria from Mithridates and, coming into Jerusalem, occupied the Second Temple. Pompey appointed Antipater, the father of Herod, as the first Roman Procurator. Later these ties allowed Herod to seek backing from Rome against the Hasmoneans in 40 BCE, when the senate recognized him as “king of the Jews.” His territories came to include the regions of Galilee, Gaulanitis (the Golan),Peraea and the Decapolis. Herod balanced his allegiance to Rome with the independence of his kingdom, often employing architectural projects to express his ambitions and control of nature to express his capacity to rule . His many palaces, placed strategically around the kingdom, feature dramatically designed landscapes and gardens. Upon his death, his heirs were unable to maintain order and Judea was annexed to Syria in 6 CE, although it was assigned its own procurator. By the time of Trajan, Judea was reduced in size and the Herodian palaces abandoned, preserving them over the millennia for archaeologists. Hadrian renamed the province Syria Palaestina after the Bar Kochba revolts (132-135) provoked him to erase the name of Judea.
The period for which we have the richest evidence of a garden culture in this region is during the reign of Herod the Great. A client king of Rome, Herod’s relationships with Mark Antony, Cleopatra, Augustus and Marcus Agrippa and other officials have been preserved in the texts of Flavius Josephus. These constitute a rare record of interactions between Rome and its territories, and provide a valuable context for understanding the trends of design in the early imperial period. The proximity of Judea to Alexandria, whose palaces and gardens lie beneath the modern city and its harbors, may also provide a suggestion of the late Hellenistic garden culture that Romans emulated. Evidence of gardens in the Hasmonean winter palaces at Jericho and the palaces of Hyracanus the Tobiad on the other side of the Jordan Valley provide rare cases where texts can illuminate archaeological evidence. These gardens require further investigation and both are threatened by local development. This geography of Judaea comprises a wide variety of biomes, from richly watered plains of the Galilee and the Jordan, to the semi arid Judean Hills, the humid, fertile coastal plain of the Mediterranean, and the deserts of the Dead Sea valley and the Negev.
Location Caesarea Maritima
Caesarea Maritima (Pleiades)
Location Description Ultimately the capital of the Roman provinces of Judaea and Syria Palestina, the city was built by Herod the Great. He acquired the old Hellenistic city of Strato’s Tower from Octavian as part of a territorial expansion after Actium, and turned the modest natural harbor here into a major port city, laid out on an orthogonal urban plan. Reminiscent of the basilaea of Alexandria, the southern area of the city was devoted to Herod’s seaside palace, in its early phase, and to public entertainment facilities by the time of the city’s opening in 12 BC. Josephus describes the port and the features of the city (AJ 15.9.6.331 and BJ 1.21.5. 408) including an “amphitheatron” and theater in the south, where archaeologists have discovered and restored a stadium and a theater. These are in the area of the archaeological remains of a palace, also noted but not located by Josephus. The city was a successful enterprise, and by the second and third centuries CE the stadium functions had moved inland and expansive villas were constructed over the remains of the stadium. By the Byzantine era, these villas were incorporated into a new praetorium. These palaces and villas have gardens, discovered in varying degrees of preservation, supplied with water through water channels, initially from the aqueduct and later from wells. Upon the destruction of this district of the city, the Arab inhabitants developed gardens amidst the ruins, irrigated by wells and water channels.
Garden Royal Garden
Keywords  pleasure garden walled garden  Garden Description Byzantine Law Court and Roof Garden
Architectural analysis and epigraphic finds excavated by Josef Patrich and the Combined Caesarea Excavations suggest that the buildings in the area immediately south of the harbor (Area CC) formed a governmental compound of Roman - Byzantine Caesarea, comprising a Revenue Office (skrinion), a Law Court and adjacent to them an archive or library for judicial and financial records and books. Earlier archaeologists (JECM) had identified this complex as an honorific U-shaped building; however, it is clearly the inverse. Constructed about 200 CE, the Law Court was a vast hall (13 x 18 m.), built on top of four vaults facing west. In the first phase, the hall faced west to the sea and was surrounded on three sides (N, E and S) by a reflection pool. To its east a square fountain was constructed. (Fig.1)
During the second phase, the pool was converted to a roof garden, filled in with the rich, red sandy soil, locally known as hamra (also noted in the upper courtyard at the promontory palace.) The soil was set on a surface of bipedal ceramic tiles (ca. 60 x 50 cm), which in turn were supported on suspensurae of flat sandstone blocks (each 20 x 20 cm and 15 cm thick) supporting the corners of four bipedal tiles. This arrangement formed a separating space between the roof of the vaults and the garden soil, preventing moisture from damaging the ceiling of the vaults (Fig. 2). This arrangement has no known parallels in Israel, but was used over vaults for the gardens of Tiberius on the Palatine in Rome, a form of nemora pensile, or hanging gardens.
During this phase the building looked out over an extended garden on the east side. Here the garden soil (hamra) extended beyond the eastern wall of the former reflection pool to include the square fountain. The garden was irrigated by a water tank (ca. 3 x 3 m.) erected on ground level between the hall and the fountain, the dimensions of which were reduced at this phase. The eastern wall of the reflection pool was partially dismantled to accommodate this tank.
During the third phase, in the 6th century, the entire garden, including the fountain, was covered by a mosaic floor.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the garden area (Combined Caesarea Excavations)   Images   Fig. 2: Reconstructed section of vaults and planting area showing roof garden construction (E. Clemence after J. Patrich)   Dates 324 CE - 638 CE
Bibliography  K.G. Holum, “Inscriptions from the imperial revenue office of Byzantine Caesarea Palaestinae” Journal of Roman Archaeology Supplement 14, 1995: 333-345. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 678401
TGN ID 7001363
Contributor Joseph Patrich ORCID: #
Publication date 09 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Promontory Palace of Herod the Great</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/judaea/caesarea_maritima/promontory_palace_of_herod_the_great/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/judaea/caesarea_maritima/promontory_palace_of_herod_the_great/</guid>
      <description>Province Judaea
Iudaea (province) (Pleiades)
Province Description Judaea, the Roman province, included parts of the areas of the Hasmonean and Herodium kingdoms, notably Biblical Judah, Samaria, and Edom. Its capital was Caesarea Maritima. Roman influence in the region began in 63 CE, when the Roman general Pompey the Great took over Syria from Mithridates and, coming into Jerusalem, occupied the Second Temple. Pompey appointed Antipater, the father of Herod, as the first Roman Procurator. Later these ties allowed Herod to seek backing from Rome against the Hasmoneans in 40 BCE, when the senate recognized him as “king of the Jews.” His territories came to include the regions of Galilee, Gaulanitis (the Golan),Peraea and the Decapolis. Herod balanced his allegiance to Rome with the independence of his kingdom, often employing architectural projects to express his ambitions and control of nature to express his capacity to rule . His many palaces, placed strategically around the kingdom, feature dramatically designed landscapes and gardens. Upon his death, his heirs were unable to maintain order and Judea was annexed to Syria in 6 CE, although it was assigned its own procurator. By the time of Trajan, Judea was reduced in size and the Herodian palaces abandoned, preserving them over the millennia for archaeologists. Hadrian renamed the province Syria Palaestina after the Bar Kochba revolts (132-135) provoked him to erase the name of Judea.
The period for which we have the richest evidence of a garden culture in this region is during the reign of Herod the Great. A client king of Rome, Herod’s relationships with Mark Antony, Cleopatra, Augustus and Marcus Agrippa and other officials have been preserved in the texts of Flavius Josephus. These constitute a rare record of interactions between Rome and its territories, and provide a valuable context for understanding the trends of design in the early imperial period. The proximity of Judea to Alexandria, whose palaces and gardens lie beneath the modern city and its harbors, may also provide a suggestion of the late Hellenistic garden culture that Romans emulated. Evidence of gardens in the Hasmonean winter palaces at Jericho and the palaces of Hyracanus the Tobiad on the other side of the Jordan Valley provide rare cases where texts can illuminate archaeological evidence. These gardens require further investigation and both are threatened by local development. This geography of Judaea comprises a wide variety of biomes, from richly watered plains of the Galilee and the Jordan, to the semi arid Judean Hills, the humid, fertile coastal plain of the Mediterranean, and the deserts of the Dead Sea valley and the Negev.
Location Caesarea Maritima
Caesarea Maritima (Pleiades)
Location Description Ultimately the capital of the Roman provinces of Judaea and Syria Palestina, the city was built by Herod the Great. He acquired the old Hellenistic city of Strato’s Tower from Octavian as part of a territorial expansion after Actium, and turned the modest natural harbor here into a major port city, laid out on an orthogonal urban plan. Reminiscent of the basilaea of Alexandria, the southern area of the city was devoted to Herod’s seaside palace, in its early phase, and to public entertainment facilities by the time of the city’s opening in 12 BC. Josephus describes the port and the features of the city (AJ 15.9.6.331 and BJ 1.21.5. 408) including an “amphitheatron” and theater in the south, where archaeologists have discovered and restored a stadium and a theater. These are in the area of the archaeological remains of a palace, also noted but not located by Josephus. The city was a successful enterprise, and by the second and third centuries CE the stadium functions had moved inland and expansive villas were constructed over the remains of the stadium. By the Byzantine era, these villas were incorporated into a new praetorium. These palaces and villas have gardens, discovered in varying degrees of preservation, supplied with water through water channels, initially from the aqueduct and later from wells. Upon the destruction of this district of the city, the Arab inhabitants developed gardens amidst the ruins, irrigated by wells and water channels.
Garden Royal Garden
Keywords  pleasure garden walled garden  Garden Description Promontory Palace of Herod the Great
A seaside palace west of the theater at Caesarea Maritima has been identified by E. Netzer as the maritime palace Herod the Great built to supervise construction of the great harbor, and, later, to provide reception space for guests at spectacles and official functions. (Fig. 1) The view north from this promontory became increasingly impressive as the harbor was completed and thrived. The palace served as the official praetorium of his heirs and subsequent Roman officials. Lower Promontory Excavations in the 1970s by Netzer and Lee I. Levine in the lower area of the palace revealed a series of luxurious reception rooms and heated chambers centering on a large (35 x 18 m.) rock-cut swimming pool enclosed by a colonnade. Cuttings in the bedrock between the columns suggested to Netzer that planters had been built between the columns, offering a pluteus around the pool, as well as a planting area protected from the salt spray. (Fig. 2) Upper Palace Excavations by K. Gleason and B. Burrell for the University of Pennsylvania Museum (1990-1996), in collaboration with E. Netzer and Hebrew University; and by Y. Porath of the Israel Antiquities Authority (1993-1996), have revealed an upper, more public half of the palace connected to the stadium (also referred to as an amphitheater by Porath following Josephus) and the theater. The upper palace comprised a series of baths and reception rooms facing out onto a quadriportico (42 x 65 m.) Although the courtyard was paved in plastered crushed sandstone in later Roman phases, fragmentary areas of layers of rich red sand (hamra), popular today with gardeners, were used to level many areas of the courtyard and may indicate the presence of vegetation or a gardened area in the first Herodian period and possibly a gardened courtyard in the first phase of the upper palace’s peristyle courtyard, but soil pits and other planting features were not preserved in any detectable pattern. (Fig. 3) Pollen extracted from plaster on the kurkar columns of the surrounding colonnade included taxa likely to have been growing within the courtyard: Cypress (Cupressus&amp;ndash;either juniperus or sempervirens), hazelnut (Corylus, a non-native), and the herbaceous taxa, Brassicacaea, Salvia, and Cistus (Fig. 4). A fourth century AD well briefly supplied water for the courtyard. Curse tablets (defixiones) at the bottom of this well indicate the popular practice of wishing ill, rather than wishing well.
Foundations of garden architecture, water channels and garden soils of the late Byzantine period have also been found, best preserved in the eastern half of the site.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the Promontory Palace (J.H. Williams and A. Iamim): a) first phase (c. 22-15 BC) ; b) second phase (c. 15-4 BC)   Images   Fig. 2:Photograph of cuttings around pool for planters (K. Gleason.     Fig. 3:Photograph of Hamra soil in courtyard (K. Gleason).     Reconstruction drawing of the Promontory upper garden (Y. Korman)   Dates 37 BCE - 135 CE
Bibliography  D. Langgut, K. Gleason, and B. Burrell, “Pollen Analysis as Evidence for Herod’s Royal Garden at the Promontory Palace, Caesarea” Israel Journal of Plant Sciences 62 (2015): 111-121. http://www.tandfonline.com/action/showCitFormats?doi=10.1080/07929978.2014.975560; K. Gleason et al. “The promontory palace at Caesarea Maritima : preliminary evidence for Herod&amp;rsquo;s Praetorium” Journal of Roman Archaeology, 11 (1998) 23-52. (worldcat) B. Burrell, K. Gleason, and E. Netzer, “Uncovering Herod’s Seaside Palace” Biblical Archaeology Review 19.3(1993): 50-57; K. K. Gleason, “Ruler and Spectacle: Herod’s Palace at Caesarea” Caesarea Maritima: a Retrospective after Two Millennia. Eds., A. Raban and K. Holum, Leiden: J. Brill, 1996, pp. 208-27; (worldcat) L.I. Levine, and E. Netzer, Excavations at Caesarea Maritima, Qedem 21, 1986, pp. 158-160; Excavations at Caesarea Maritima (worldcat) E. Netzer, “Herod the Great’s Palace” In Caesarea Maritima: a Retrospective after Two Millennia. Eds. A. Raban and K. Holum, Leiden: J. Brill, 1996, pp. 193-207. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 678401
TGN ID 7001363
Contributor Kathryn L. Gleason ORCID: 0000-0001-6260-8378
Publication date 09 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Latimer</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/latimer/latimer_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/latimer/latimer_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Latimer
Latimer (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Latimer
Keywords archaeological garden \
 fences (site elements) flower gardens orchards rural villas vegetable gardens villae rusticae  Garden Description Excavations at this country house in Buckinghamshire have produced evidence for gardens adjacent to the main residence in its latest phase dating to the beginning of the 4th century (Fig. 1). The house at the west is of the winged corridor type, fronted by a large courtyard bisected by a paved central drive with a banked edge. Between the outer courtyard wall and the house were areas used for gardening (G in Fig. 1). Just inside the outer yard wall on the south side of the drive traces of at least six bedding trenches cut into the natural subsoil and running parallel to each other were followed for at least 5 meters (b in Fig. 1). These have been interpreted by the excavator as the remains of vegetable gardens (Fig. 2). He also attributed a number of stake holes in this area to small fences bounding the vegetable gardens, and suggested the possibility of an orchard on the northern side of the drive as well as a formal flower garden nearer to the house between the projecting wings, for which there is no concrete archaeological evidence. Finally a small pit just inside the courtyard gateway may represent a pit dug to take one of a pair of trees flanking the entrance.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the residential building (A) with excavated bedding trenches (b) in its garden courtyard (G). Adapted from Branigan 1971, fig. 20.(Rights statement)   Images   Fig. 2: Reconstruction of the house and garden. Courtesy of K. Branigan.   Dates Evidence for gardens dating to the beginning of 4th century
Bibliography  K. Branigan, Latimer. Belgic, Roman, Dark Age and Early Modern Farm, Bristol, 1971, pp. 85-86, 184, figs. 14, 20 (worldcat) R.J. Zeepvat, “Roman Gardens in Britain,” in: A.E. Brown, ed., Garden Archaeology. Council for British Archaeology Research Report 78, London, 1991, p. 56, fig. 5.3. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 79555
TGN ID 1029792
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>