<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>brick on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/brick/</link>
    <description>Recent content in brick on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 11:20:32 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/brick/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The House of the Small Viridarium</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_the-house-of-the-small-viridarium_y.sun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_the-house-of-the-small-viridarium_y.sun/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania (Pleiades)
Location AUGUSTORITUM - Limoges
Augustoritum (Pleiades)
Location Description The earliest traces of settlement in this area are at the oppidum of Villejoubert 25 kilometers east of the city. The Roman settlement of Limoges proper dates from about 15-10 B.C. and was named Augustoritum (Augustus’s ford) in honor of the emperor. It covered some 65 to 100 hectares and was laid out in a regular rectangular grid. The ancient wall dates from the end of the third century. The town took water from several sources, including the aqueduct of Aigoulène; there were drains for waste water disposal. There were several public fountains and baths, a theater, an arena, and temples. The city declined in the fourth century. Its Roman name was replaced by the Celtic name of the local people; and its regular street pattern, almost totally lost.
Garden The House of the Small Viridarium
Keywords  brick  Garden Description Discovered in the course of a campaign of excavations in 1928, this house occupies part of insula VI-4 west of the forum. It had a central courtyard [1] with a peristyle of columns of brick. The garden, 11.5 meter long, occupied at least 90 square meters. Though incompletely explored, we know that it had in its center a vat for crushing lime and an area paved with reused marble plates with a molding.
Excavation Dates 1928
Bibliography  J.P. Loustaud. Limoges antique, Travaux d’Archéologie Limousine, supplément 5, 2000, p. 210, plan p. 210. (with a bibliography of earlier works) (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 138203
TGN ID 7030318 7008410
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>