<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Provinces on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Provinces on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 13:58:53 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Achaea</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 13:58:53 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Province Description Roman intervention in Greek political affairs resulted in conflicts that led to the destruction of Corinth in 146 B.C. and the sacking of Athens in 86 B.C. It was not until 27 B.C., however, that Augustus formally organized the Roman province of Achaea. Achaea consisted of the cities and territories of the southern Greek mainland between the Peloponnese and Thessaly, as well as Epirus in the northwest and the Ionian and some of the Aegean islands.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Macedonia</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/macedonia/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 09:34:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/macedonia/</guid>
      <description>Province Province Description Location Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Dates Bibliography Periodo ID Pleiades ID 981531
TGN ID 7001349
Contributor ORCID Publication date 16 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dalmatia</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/dalmatia/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 16:46:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/dalmatia/</guid>
      <description>Province Province Description Introduction Needed
Location Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Dates Bibliography Periodo ID Pleiades ID TGN ID Contributor ORCID Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Germania Superior</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 15:52:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Province Description The regions on the upper Rhine formally became the province of Germania Superior, Upper Germany, during the reign of Domitian, probably around AD 85. Since the Augustan period, they had formed a military zone on the eastern fringes of Gallia Belgica and Gallica Lugdunensis. Moguntiacum (Mainz) at the confluence of the Rhine and Main rivers was the administrative capital and the site of a legionary base.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Germania Inferior</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:26:59 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Province Description The Augustan military zone along the lower Rhine was formally reorganized as the province of Germania Inferior, Lower Germany, during the reign of Domitian around A.D. 85. Until this time, the area had been on the eastern fringe of the province of Gallia Belgica. The provincial capital was Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium (modern Cologne). Numerous legionary and auxiliary bases fortified the lower Rhine frontier throughout its history.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dacia Traiana</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/dacia_traiana/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 19:24:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/dacia_traiana/</guid>
      <description>Province Dacia Traiana
Province Description Dacia occupied the region occupied by today by Romania, Moldava, and parts of Bulgaria, Serbia, Hungary and the Ukraine. Homeland of the Gatae tribe, it was conquered by the Romans under Trajan in 106 CE. After the Romans retreated from this region in 271-275 CE, they renamed an area of Moesia Superior “Dacia Aureliana”. This entry concerns only original province of Dacia.
The area was known to the Romans prior to its conquest, particularly for its position along the Hercynian Forest (Black Forest).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Britannia</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2020 12:53:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description After Caesar’s campaigns in Britain in 55 and 54 BC, the southern part of the island lay within Rome’s sphere of influence. It was not until the Claudian invasion in 43 AD, however, that Britain was annexed as a Roman province, although the ‘conquest’ of Britain in the west and north continued and proceeded slowly in the decades thereafter. Apart from a brief interlude in the mid-2nd century, when the northern border of the province was fixed at the Antonine Wall in Scotland, from the 120&amp;rsquo;s the northern frontier of the island lay on Hadrian’s Wall stretching from the west to the east coast.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>