<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 10:17:25 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Winden Am See</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/winden_am_see/winden_am_see_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 10:17:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/winden_am_see/winden_am_see_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Pannonia
Province Description Location Winden Am See
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Winden Am See
Keywords corridors
rural villas
villae rusticae
Garden Description The modest house of this villa rustica is of the so-called corridor type, a type common in the region and already seen at Carnuntum (Fig. 1). It was built around 100 A.D. and occupied until the 4th century.
On the southeast of the house was a vestibule, from which a central corridor departed at a 90 degree angle.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Iul(ia) Victorin(a) in Scarbantia</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/scarbantia/scarbantia_tomb_garden_of_iulia_victorina/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 10:08:21 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/scarbantia/scarbantia_tomb_garden_of_iulia_victorina/</guid>
      <description>Province Pannonia
Province Description Location Scarbantia
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Tomb Garden of Iul(ia) Victorin(a) in Scarbantia
Keywords epitaphs
stelae
tombs
Garden Description A limestone funerary stele of probably third century date unearthed in 1973 near Scarbantia at Winder am See (Burgenland) and now in the Burgenländische Landesmuseum at Eisenstadt records an epitaph set up by Septimius Alcides, a veteran of the legio XIII Gemina Iulia, for his wife, Iul(ia) Victorin(a), dead at thirty, for whom he built at his own expense a funerary pleasure garden (viridarium).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Fl(avius) Dalmatius in Savaria</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/savaria/savaria_tomb_garden_of_flavius_dalmatius/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 09:49:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/savaria/savaria_tomb_garden_of_flavius_dalmatius/</guid>
      <description>Province Pannonia
Province Description Location Savaria
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Tomb Garden of Fl(avius) Dalmatius in Savaria
Keywords epitaphs
tombs
Garden Description A limestone slab found near the monastery of St. Martin in Szombathely (Savaria), Hungary, in 1845 and subsequently transferred to the National Museum in Budapest records the epitaph of a high ranking equestrian official (vir perfectissimus), Fl(avius) Dalmatius, and his wife Aur(elia) Iulia, who some time during the third or fourth century built a tomb on their villa estate and composed for it a verse inscription in which Dalmatius hopes for commemoration from a future owner of the property: “Whoever will be master of this house and garden after me, gather the nearby roses for me, put out the white lilies which the green garden will grow for me: these are the gifts of the blessed” (Quisquis {h}e(ris) post me d(o)m(inus) Laris huius et (h)orti, / vicinas mihi carpe rosas, mihi lilia pone / [ca]ndeda{s} q(uae) viridis dabit (h)ortulus: ista (sc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Eisenstadt</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/eisenstadt/eisenstadt_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 09:31:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/eisenstadt/eisenstadt_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Pannonia
Province Description Location Eisenstadt
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Eisenstadt
Keywords altars (religious fixtures)
atriums
peristyles (Roman courtyards)
podiums (building divisions)
porticoes rural villas
villae rusticae
Garden Description The residence of this villa rustica was entered on the southeast by a portico (Fig. 1). After passing through a room interpreted as the atrium, one arrived in the open courtyard which had a peristyle on three sides (G on plan).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban Houses in Carnuntum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/carnuntum/carnuntum_urban_houses/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 08:57:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/carnuntum/carnuntum_urban_houses/</guid>
      <description>Province Pannonia
Province Description Location Carnuntum
Location Description The town of Carnuntum on the Danube River, like Aquincum, was promoted to colonial status in 194 A.D., after having been a municipium. Excavations in the modern zoological garden have revealed part of the town plan and its residential district.
Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Urban Houses in Carnuntum
Keywords arcades (structural assemblies) corridors
Garden Description The regional house type found often in Pannonia, the so-called corridor house, is characterized by a vestibule or arcade on its narrow front and a central corridor running the length of the house, separating it into two parts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban House or Schola in Aquincum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/aquincum/aquincum_urban_house_or_schola/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jul 2020 16:44:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/aquincum/aquincum_urban_house_or_schola/</guid>
      <description>Province Pannonia
Province Description Location Aquincum
Location Description This town on the Danube river acquired the rank of municipium under Hadrian in 124 A.D. In the year 194 it was granted colonial status.
Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Urban House or Schola in Aquincum
Keywords bathhouses (water recreation structures)
fountains
peristyles (Roman courtyards) piscinae
Garden Description Very few houses of Mediterranean type have been discovered, and only one can be said with certainty to have had a garden (Fig.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pannonia</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/pannonia/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jul 2020 16:35:11 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/pannonia/</guid>
      <description>Province Pannonia
Province Description The creation of the province of Pannonia can be dated to the years following 9 B.C., after the Pannonian tribes had been defeated by Tiberius. The province occupied the western half of modern Hungary up to the Danube in the north and east. Its western neighboring province was Noricum; to the south lay the Save river, Dalmatia, and the Adriatic coast. Because of its frontier position on the Danube, Pannonia was heavily garrisoned by the Roman army throughout its history.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>