<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>portico on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/portico/</link>
    <description>Recent content in portico on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/portico/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>House in the Rue des Clairettes</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-in-the-rue-des-clairettes_y.sun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-in-the-rue-des-clairettes_y.sun/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania (Pleiades)
Location AUGUSTORITUM - Limoges
Augustoritum (Pleiades)
Location Description The earliest traces of settlement in this area are at the oppidum of Villejoubert 25 kilometers east of the city. The Roman settlement of Limoges proper dates from about 15-10 B.C. and was named Augustoritum (Augustus’s ford) in honor of the emperor. It covered some 65 to 100 hectares and was laid out in a regular rectangular grid. The ancient wall dates from the end of the third century. The town took water from several sources, including the aqueduct of Aigoulène; there were drains for waste water disposal. There were several public fountains and baths, a theater, an arena, and temples. The city declined in the fourth century. Its Roman name was replaced by the Celtic name of the local people; and its regular street pattern, almost totally lost.
Garden House in the Rue des Clairettes
Keywords  pool portico  Garden Description This house was discovered in the excavation of 1998 in the rue des Clairettes. Constructed in the first half of the second century, it dominated the street. Only the wing running east-west is known. A portico must have opened onto a large garden to the north [1]. In the axis of this garden was the central room [2] of the wing with 125 square meters. In the center of this room was a large square pool, several times remodeled. Originally it was paved with marble or limestone and fed by an underground vaulted tunnel that crossed the whole room. To the south opened another portico overlooking a terrace two meters below; the street which defined the southern border was on beyond.
Dates Constructed in the first half of the second century。
Excavation Dates 1998
Bibliography  J.P. Loustaud. Limoges antique, Travaux d’Archéologie Limousine, supplément 5, 2000, p. 208-209, plan p. 208. (with a bibliography of earlier works) (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 138203
TGN ID 7030318 7008410
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Opus Sectile</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-of-the-opus-sectile_y.sun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-of-the-opus-sectile_y.sun/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania (Pleiades)
Location AUGUSTORITUM - Limoges
Augustoritum (Pleiades)
Location Description The earliest traces of settlement in this area are at the oppidum of Villejoubert 25 kilometers east of the city. The Roman settlement of Limoges proper dates from about 15-10 B.C. and was named Augustoritum (Augustus’s ford) in honor of the emperor. It covered some 65 to 100 hectares and was laid out in a regular rectangular grid. The ancient wall dates from the end of the third century. The town took water from several sources, including the aqueduct of Aigoulène; there were drains for waste water disposal. There were several public fountains and baths, a theater, an arena, and temples. The city declined in the fourth century. Its Roman name was replaced by the Celtic name of the local people; and its regular street pattern, almost totally lost.
Garden House of the Opus Sectile
Keywords  portico  Garden Description This house occupied part of insula VI-5, across the street to the west of the forum. Constructed a little after the middle of the first century, it filled a space of 2300 square meters and certainly had an upper story. It consists of a living wing to the north of a garden with porticos [1] of 560 square meters. The south portico has preserved traces of a low wall on which the columns rested ; its inside had a coating painted black. The quality of the main reception room centered on the garden [3] (10 x 5.65 m), one of the most important rooms, is hard to judge because of the modifications in the following stage connected with installation of a hypocaust. The second reception room to the east [2] is ornamented by coatings painted in the Pompeian third style.
Dates Constructed a little after the middle of the first century.
Excavation Dates Bibliography  J.P. Loustaud. Limoges antique, Travaux d’Archéologie Limousine, supplément 5, 2000, p. 196-8, plan p. 196. (with bibliography of earlier works). (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 138203
TGN ID 7030318 7008410
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa dell’Ara Laterizia</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/tiffany_fong/casa_dellara_laterizia/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/tiffany_fong/casa_dellara_laterizia/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Garden Casa dell’Ara Laterizia
##Jashemski Catalogue 539.III.17. 540.III.19-18/1-2
Keywords  sacellum portico opus reticulatum  Garden Description 539.III.17. At the rear of this small house there was a courtyard with an impressive brick altar against the rear wall. Maiuri felt this was probably a roofed area which would have been a sacellum. This area was excavated in 1927-1929 and may have held a few potted plants.
540.III.19-18/1-2 Because it was one of the largest houses in Herculaneum commanding a fine view of the Bay, it was initially thought that this residence was a hotel when it was excavated between the years of 1835 to 1855. The large garden (a) was also mistaken for a poultry yard but the discovery of the carbonized trunk of a pear tree (Pyrus communis L.) would indicate this area could have been planted in fruit trees. A portico surrounded the garden eight steps (1.10) above the garden level while the gutter ran one step below the portico and at each corner there was a shallow square basin for purifying the household water. The gutter conveyed the rain water to a cistern below the two wells, the openings of which were located between the columns in the middle of the east and west walls. A low masonry wall of opus reticulatum which went between the columns was a later addition. The garden was entered by way of masonry steps in the center of the south side.
Plans Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1835-1855
Bibliography  A.C. BdI (1835),p. 129 (worldcat) Maiuri, Herculaneum, pp. 26-27 (worldcat) Trotter, “Identificazione di un tronco d’albero carbonizzato rinvenuto nei recenti scavi di Ercolano,” Annali del Regio Instituto Superiore Agrario di Portici, ser. 3, vol. 5 (1932), pp. 1-6 and pls. 1, 2 (worldcat) Idem, Ercolano, pp. 51, 330-331 and fig. 258 (plan) on p. 474-475 (for reference to Bonucci’s brief and inaccurate account of the excavation of this house, as preserved by Ruggerio) (worldcat)  -
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa dell’Atrio a Mosaico</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/tiffany_fong/casa_dellatrio_a_mosaico/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/tiffany_fong/casa_dellatrio_a_mosaico/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Garden Casa dell’Atrio a Mosaico
##Jashemski Catalogue 541.IV.1-2
Keywords  portico exedra triclinium  Garden Description 541.IV.1-2 A windowed portico surrounded this garden (a) on the north, south and west. The east side was bordered by a narrow corridor which Maiuri proposed had glass in woodenframes set on the outside edge of the low wall. This wall had a planting space 0.16 m. wide in the top next to where the windows were set, creating a greenhouse environment. This luxurious house had an exedra(b) opening onto the center of the corridor and looking into the garden, which was slightly lower. On the oppositeside,the walls, columns, and the door posts were decorated with paintingsof shrubs, grapevines, ivy andoleander in flower as a continuation of the garden proper. A gutter circled the perimeter of the garden except by the entrance on the south, which was directly across from the grand triclinium-oecus(c). A rectangular marble-edged pool in the center of the garden had a water jet which could be viewed from either the exedra or the triclinium. The excavations in this garden in 1929-1930 uncovered a spherical white marble sundial. The triclinium-oecus opened to the south onto a long covered portico with an open terrace (d) beyond that looking out over the Bay. Potted plants most likely were placed here.
Plans Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1929-1930
Bibliography  Gibbs, Greek and Roman sundials, p. 148, no 1031G (worldcat)     Maiuri, Herculaneum, pp. 28-30 (worldcat)     Idem, Ercolano, pp. 290-293, 295, 298, 300 and fig. 223 (plan) on p. 280.(worldcat)  -
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa D’Argo</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/tiffany_fong/casa_dargo/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/tiffany_fong/casa_dargo/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Garden Casa D’Argo
##Jashemski Catalogue 533.II.2. 534.II.2.
Keywords  cisterns (plumbing components) triclinium peristyles porticoes gutters (building drainage components)  Garden Description 533.II.2. A. The earliest excavations of Herculaneum were done with underground tunnels. Several of these crossed this site and were discovered sixty three years later when further excavation of this patrician house was conducted in1828-1835. Eight brick columns and one engaged column stood on each of the long sides of the portico that bounded the large peristyle garden (a) on the east, north, and west sides. The north side was supported by four more columns and at the two front corners there was a pillar with an engaged column on each side. In the center of the north side two smaller pillars with one engaged column each framed a garden view from the triclinium. All the supporting members were coated with fine stucco. Gutters ringing the garden conveyed rain water to the cistern.
534.II.2. B. A second peristyle garden was located to the west of the first, but has only been partially excavated. It has stuccoed columns and pillars joined by a wall 0.4 m. high painted with plants and flowers.
Plans   Casa D’Argo   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1828-1835
Bibliography  A.C. BdI (1835),p. 130 (worldcat) Bonucci, BdI (1830), p.121 (worldcat) Bonucci, Le due Sicilie: Ercolano, fig. 11 (plan) and p. 37 (worldcat) Breton,Pompeia p. 519 (worldcat) Maiuri, Herculaneum, p. 24 (worldcat) Idem,Ercolano, pp. 367-368 and fig. 293 (plan) on p. 362 (worldcat) Niccolini,Real museo borbonico, vol. 7, fig. 59 (plan), description by Bechi, pp. 19-21 (worldcat)     Ruggiero, Ercolano, pp. 541-545 (contains the detailed reports of Bonucci)(worldcat)     -      Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casadetta del Genio</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/tiffany_fong/casadetta_del_genio/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/tiffany_fong/casadetta_del_genio/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Garden Casadetta del Genio
##Jashemski Catalogue 535.II.3.
Keywords  porticoes  Garden Description This house was partially excavated in 1829-1830 and again in 1850. The portico had a floor on the east slightly lower than the sections on the north and south. A pool (a) was located in the center of the garden with a semi-circular extension on the east end and two small marble posts which probably held herms. The pool measured 2.35 m. wide, 0.87 m. deep and was only excavated to a length of 6.50 m.
Plans   Casadetta del Genio   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897 Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1829-1830; 1850
Bibliography    Maiuri, Herculaneum, p. 25 (worldcat)   Idem, Ercolano, pp. 375-377 and fig. 307 (plan) on p. 376 (worldcat)     Ruggiero, Ercolano, pp. 562, 566, 574 (worldcat)      Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>