<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/numidia/thamugadi/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/numidia/thamugadi/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Hermaphrodite House (Maison de l&#39;Hermaphrodite)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/numidia/thamugadi/hermaphrodite_house/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/numidia/thamugadi/hermaphrodite_house/</guid>
      <description>Province Numidia Numidia (Pleiades)
Province Description The frontier between Numidia and Mauretania fluctuated during early the African kingdoms. It was fixed at the river of Ampsaga during Caesar’s reign when he rewarded his ally King Bocchus, giving him part of the Numidian kingdom. By 31 BCE, Numidia (also known as Africa Nova) was under direct Roman control, becoming attached to the province of Africa Proconsularis. Toward 194 CE, Septimus Severus detached most of the Numidia territory from the province of Africa Proconsularis, forming a special province governed from Cirta by a procurator, subordinate to the imperial legate. With the Diocletian reforms, the whole of Roman Africa (with exception of Mauretania Tingitana) constituted a single diocese subdivided into six provinces, including Numidia Cirtensis with Cirta as capital.
Location Thamugadi
Thamugadi (Pleiades)
Location Description Thamugadi, now known as Timgad, was founded as a colony during by Emperor Trajan around 100 CE. The city had a checker-board plan, measuring approximately 11 hectares (27 acres) total, containing a forum with Curia, an imperial temple, and a basilica. Between the second and fourth centuries, the city expanded from its original layout. Additional temples and baths were built, and the center of the city was expanded with the construction of luxurious houses, a library, and a new market. At the end of the fourth century, bishop Optatus of Timgad, a prominent member of the Donatist church, constructed the great west basilica. During the Byzantine conquest, a fortress was erected on the water sanctuary; the original site dating to the third or fourth century.
Garden Hermaphrodite House (Maison de l&amp;rsquo;Hermaphrodite)
Keywords  peristyles (columnades) peristyles (Roman courtyards) triclinia  Garden Description The large house was laid out around a large peristyle of 22 columns. In the axis of the triclinium was a rectangular pool. The courtyard may have been planted (Plan view, Fig. 1).
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the Hermaphrodite House. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  A. Ballu, Les ruines de Timgad, Paris, 1903, p. 90-94. (worldcat) S. Germain, Les mosaïques de Timgad, Paris, 1969, p. 65, fig. 7. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 334636
TGN ID 7001328
Contributor Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House at the W of the Filadelfes (Maison à l&#39;Ouest des Bains des Filadelfes)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/numidia/thamugadi/house_at_the_w_of_the_filadelfes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/numidia/thamugadi/house_at_the_w_of_the_filadelfes/</guid>
      <description>Province Numidia Numidia (Pleiades)
Province Description The frontier between Numidia and Mauretania fluctuated during early the African kingdoms. It was fixed at the river of Ampsaga during Caesar’s reign when he rewarded his ally King Bocchus, giving him part of the Numidian kingdom. By 31 BCE, Numidia (also known as Africa Nova) was under direct Roman control, becoming attached to the province of Africa Proconsularis. Toward 194 CE, Septimus Severus detached most of the Numidia territory from the province of Africa Proconsularis, forming a special province governed from Cirta by a procurator, subordinate to the imperial legate. With the Diocletian reforms, the whole of Roman Africa (with exception of Mauretania Tingitana) constituted a single diocese subdivided into six provinces, including Numidia Cirtensis with Cirta as capital.
Location Thamugadi
Thamugadi (Pleiades)
Location Description Thamugadi, now known as Timgad, was founded as a colony during by Emperor Trajan around 100 CE. The city had a checker-board plan, measuring approximately 11 hectares (27 acres) total, containing a forum with Curia, an imperial temple, and a basilica. Between the second and fourth centuries, the city expanded from its original layout. Additional temples and baths were built, and the center of the city was expanded with the construction of luxurious houses, a library, and a new market. At the end of the fourth century, bishop Optatus of Timgad, a prominent member of the Donatist church, constructed the great west basilica. During the Byzantine conquest, a fortress was erected on the water sanctuary; the original site dating to the third or fourth century.
Garden House at the W of the Filadelfes (Maison à l&amp;rsquo;Ouest des Bains des Filadelfes)
Keywords  peristyles (columnades) peristyles (Roman courtyards)  Garden Description This large house (2500m2) was laid out around two peristyles. The E peristyle had 12 columns onto which at least three rooms opened. The large peristyle on the W, was bordered by three porticos, its large courtyard may have been planted. Between the peristyles was placed a reception room that opened into each of them.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the House at the W of the Philadelphes Baths. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Ballu A., Rapport, 1922, p. 47-53. (worldcat) Ballu A., Rapport 1923, p. 45-47: plan dépliant. (worldcat) S. Germain, Les mosaïques de Timgad, Paris, 1969, p 81, fig. 10. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 334636
TGN ID 7001328
Contributor Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Sertius (Maison de Sertius)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/numidia/thamugadi/house_of_sertius/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/numidia/thamugadi/house_of_sertius/</guid>
      <description>Province Numidia Numidia (Pleiades)
Province Description The frontier between Numidia and Mauretania fluctuated during early the African kingdoms. It was fixed at the river of Ampsaga during Caesar’s reign when he rewarded his ally King Bocchus, giving him part of the Numidian kingdom. By 31 BCE, Numidia (also known as Africa Nova) was under direct Roman control, becoming attached to the province of Africa Proconsularis. Toward 194 CE, Septimus Severus detached most of the Numidia territory from the province of Africa Proconsularis, forming a special province governed from Cirta by a procurator, subordinate to the imperial legate. With the Diocletian reforms, the whole of Roman Africa (with exception of Mauretania Tingitana) constituted a single diocese subdivided into six provinces, including Numidia Cirtensis with Cirta as capital.
Location Thamugadi
Thamugadi (Pleiades)
Location Description Thamugadi, now known as Timgad, was founded as a colony during by Emperor Trajan around 100 CE. The city had a checker-board plan, measuring approximately 11 hectares (27 acres) total, containing a forum with Curia, an imperial temple, and a basilica. Between the second and fourth centuries, the city expanded from its original layout. Additional temples and baths were built, and the center of the city was expanded with the construction of luxurious houses, a library, and a new market. At the end of the fourth century, bishop Optatus of Timgad, a prominent member of the Donatist church, constructed the great west basilica. During the Byzantine conquest, a fortress was erected on the water sanctuary; the original site dating to the third or fourth century.
Garden House of Sertius (Maison de Sertius)
Keywords  peristyles (columnades) peristyles (Roman courtyards) basins (vessels) triclinia  Garden Description This large domus the result of the combining of two houses, is located at the periphery of the center of the city. The domus is laid out around two peristyles. The first, near the vestibule had a long rectangular basin placed in the axis of the triclinium, the two strips that bordered the pool may have been planted. The second peristyle with 8 columns had a semi-circular basin (Plan view Fi.1).
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the House of Sertius. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  E. Boeswillwald, R. Cagnat, A. Ballu, Timgad une cité africaine sous l’Empire romain, Paris, 1905; p. 326-333, plan fig. 152. (worldcat) Courtois, C., Timgad, antique Thamugadi, Paris, 1951, p 53, plan with scale. (worldcat) S. Germain, Les mosaïques de Timgad, Paris, 1969, p. 59. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 334636
TGN ID 7001328
Contributor Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Planters (Maison aux jardinières)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/numidia/thamugadi/house_of_the_planters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/numidia/thamugadi/house_of_the_planters/</guid>
      <description>Province Numidia Numidia (Pleiades)
Province Description The frontier between Numidia and Mauretania fluctuated during early the African kingdoms. It was fixed at the river of Ampsaga during Caesar’s reign when he rewarded his ally King Bocchus, giving him part of the Numidian kingdom. By 31 BCE, Numidia (also known as Africa Nova) was under direct Roman control, becoming attached to the province of Africa Proconsularis. Toward 194 CE, Septimus Severus detached most of the Numidia territory from the province of Africa Proconsularis, forming a special province governed from Cirta by a procurator, subordinate to the imperial legate. With the Diocletian reforms, the whole of Roman Africa (with exception of Mauretania Tingitana) constituted a single diocese subdivided into six provinces, including Numidia Cirtensis with Cirta as capital.
Location Thamugadi
Thamugadi (Pleiades)
Location Description Thamugadi, now known as Timgad, was founded as a colony during by Emperor Trajan around 100 CE. The city had a checker-board plan, measuring approximately 11 hectares (27 acres) total, containing a forum with Curia, an imperial temple, and a basilica. Between the second and fourth centuries, the city expanded from its original layout. Additional temples and baths were built, and the center of the city was expanded with the construction of luxurious houses, a library, and a new market. At the end of the fourth century, bishop Optatus of Timgad, a prominent member of the Donatist church, constructed the great west basilica. During the Byzantine conquest, a fortress was erected on the water sanctuary; the original site dating to the third or fourth century.
Garden House of the Planters (Maison aux jardinières)
Keywords  peristyles (columnades) peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes water wells  Garden Description Located SW of the Decumanus and NE of the forum, the house of the &amp;ldquo;Jardinières&amp;rdquo; almost square shaped, was laid out around a peristyle of 10 columns. Along the three porticoes and the angles of the fourth were arranged planters (10,50 x10,50 m) whose contours are curved. Double herm-heads or two sided-plaque with masks were found, they may have surmounted the corner pilasters of the courtyard. In the middle was a well. Facing the entrance and opening towards the courtyard, a large reception room was surrounded on its two sides by a vestibule leading to a room. (Plan view Fig.1; Fig.2)
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the House of the Planters. (Rights statement)   Images   Fig. 2: Drawing by A Ballu of the courtyard of the House of the Planters (Rights statement)     Fig. 3 Photographic view of the courtyard of the House of the Planters (WFJ). (Rights statement)   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  A. Ballu, Les ruines de Timgad (Antique Thamugadi), Paris, 1897, p. 224-226, plan fig. 36. S. (worldcat) S. Germain, Les mosaïques de Timgad, Paris, 1969, p. 37. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 334636
TGN ID 7001328
Contributor Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Warehouse (Maison de l&#39;entrepôt)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/numidia/thamugadi/house_of_the_warehouse/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/numidia/thamugadi/house_of_the_warehouse/</guid>
      <description>Province Numidia Numidia (Pleiades)
Province Description The frontier between Numidia and Mauretania fluctuated during early the African kingdoms. It was fixed at the river of Ampsaga during Caesar’s reign when he rewarded his ally King Bocchus, giving him part of the Numidian kingdom. By 31 BCE, Numidia (also known as Africa Nova) was under direct Roman control, becoming attached to the province of Africa Proconsularis. Toward 194 CE, Septimus Severus detached most of the Numidia territory from the province of Africa Proconsularis, forming a special province governed from Cirta by a procurator, subordinate to the imperial legate. With the Diocletian reforms, the whole of Roman Africa (with exception of Mauretania Tingitana) constituted a single diocese subdivided into six provinces, including Numidia Cirtensis with Cirta as capital.
Location Thamugadi
Thamugadi (Pleiades)
Location Description Thamugadi, now known as Timgad, was founded as a colony during by Emperor Trajan around 100 CE. The city had a checker-board plan, measuring approximately 11 hectares (27 acres) total, containing a forum with Curia, an imperial temple, and a basilica. Between the second and fourth centuries, the city expanded from its original layout. Additional temples and baths were built, and the center of the city was expanded with the construction of luxurious houses, a library, and a new market. At the end of the fourth century, bishop Optatus of Timgad, a prominent member of the Donatist church, constructed the great west basilica. During the Byzantine conquest, a fortress was erected on the water sanctuary; the original site dating to the third or fourth century.
Garden House of the Warehouse (Maison de l&amp;rsquo;entrepôt)
Keywords  peristyles (columnades) peristyles (Roman courtyards) basins (vessels)  Garden Description This large house was laid out around two peristyles (A,B) arranged along the N S axis. The plan presents a complex layout notably in the southern part of the domus upon which the excavators did not comment thoroughly (Plan view, Fig. 1).
The S part of the domus was probably added in a latter period. It presents a peristyle (B) on which a reception room (C) projected and a series of galleries terminating with an apsidal form. The N peristyle (A) had four porticoes, the S gallery was a continuous colonnade that crossed the W and E porticoes. On the N and W, a vestibule and reception rooms opened towards the peristyle (A). A large rectangular basin oriented NS was placed on the axis of the vestibule, which projected into the courtyard. It seems that the S reception room (C) opened also toward the N peristyle (A). Along the NS axis a semi-circular basin projecting into the peristyle (B) and facing a reception room was placed in between the fourth and the fifth columns. The courtyards of the peristyles may have been planted.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the House of the Warehouse. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  A. Ballu, Les ruines de Timgad, Sept années de découvertes, Paris, 1911, p. 49-53,120, plan p. 51. (worldcat) S. Germain, Les mosaïques de Timgad, Paris, 1969, p. 88, fig. 12. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 334636
TGN ID 7001328
Contributor Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Water Sanctuary Aqua Eptimania Felix (Sanctuaire des eaux)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/numidia/thamugadi/water_sanctuary_aqua_eptimania_felix/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/numidia/thamugadi/water_sanctuary_aqua_eptimania_felix/</guid>
      <description>Province Numidia Numidia (Pleiades)
Province Description Thamugadi, now known as Timgad, was founded as a colony during by Emperor Trajan around 100 CE. The city had a checker-board plan, measuring approximately 11 hectares (27 acres) total, containing a forum with Curia, an imperial temple, and a basilica. Between the second and fourth centuries, the city expanded from its original layout. Additional temples and baths were built, and the center of the city was expanded with the construction of luxurious houses, a library, and a new market. At the end of the fourth century, bishop Optatus of Timgad, a prominent member of the Donatist church, constructed the great west basilica. During the Byzantine conquest, a fortress was erected on the water sanctuary; the original site dating to the third or fourth century.
Location Thamugadi
Thamugadi (Pleiades)
Location Description Timgad, ancient Thamugadi was founded as a colony under Trajan. The city had a checker board plan, that measured 11ha. In the center was the forum with its Curia, an imperial temple and the basilica. Between the IInd and the IVth century the city expanded out of its original layout. Temples, baths and a market were built and the center of the city was renovated with the construction of the library, the market and luxurious houses. At the end of the IVth century the bishop Optatus of Timgad a prominent member of the donatist church constructed the great west basilica. During the Byzantine conquest a fortress was erected on the water sanctuary dating to the IIIrd and IVth century.
Garden Water Sanctuary Aqua Eptimania Felix (Sanctuaire des eaux)
Keywords  mural paintings (visual works) porticoes viridarium  Garden Description The water sanctuary lies beneath the Byzantine fort in the Northern suburbs of the city. An inscription that was discovered during the Byzantine fort excavations enumerates the embellishments that were undertaken in 213 by the city of Timgad for the sanctuary, Aqua Septimania Felix: one of which, a bronze balustrade surrounding the spring (a pool with marble slabs of 3,6 m x 13, 60 m) and a viridarium surrounded by porticoes decorated with paintings (porticus virdiari (sic) picturis ornatas). But the central space of the vast porticoed monument discovered to the North of the fort is paved, this has lead L. Leschi, in order to explain the viridarium designation, to consider that the paintings of the porticoes were garden paintings.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan view of the city. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  L. LESCHI, Découvertes récentes à Timgad: Aqua Septimania Felix, CRAI, 1947, p. 87-99. (worldcat) L. LESCHI, Etudes d&amp;rsquo;épigraphie, d&amp;rsquo;archéologie et d&amp;rsquo;histoire africaines, Paris, 1957, pp. 240-45, ici p. 242. (worldcat) J. LASSUS, La forteresse byzantine de Thamugadi, Fouilles à Timgad, 1938-1956, Paris, 1981, plan p. 25, fig. 9, pp. 215-17, fig. 174-76. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 334636
TGN ID 7001328
Contributor Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
