<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ix/house_3/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 17:59:16 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ix/house_3/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Successus (I.ix.3)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ix/house_3/house_of_successus/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 17:59:16 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ix/house_3/house_of_successus/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula IX
House House 3
Garden House of Successus (I.ix.3)
Keywords  archaeological garden atriums cubicula (domestic spaces) graffiti (casual notations) inscription mural paintings (visual works) porticoes statues statuettes (free-standing sculpture) tables (support furniture)  Garden Description A portrait of a little boy painted on the north wall of the cubiculum, to the left of the atrium, with the graffito PVER/SUCCUSSVS (CIL IV. 9992a) gave this house its name. Excavated in 1952, the garden (a) at the rear of the house had a portico, and a table base carved as a statuette of a small boy with a dove (Pompeii inv. no. 20395) was discovered in the north portico. Fig. 3, Fig. 4. The room in the southwest corner of the garden (b) had a garden representation on the large white middle panel on the south wall of the room. It was framed by a narrow reddish-brown border and painted in shades of brown and white on a light blue-green background. Two gardens enclosed by a wooden fence contained an open apse-shaped area in between them with a round pool. A jet in the center jetted water which descended in two separate streams. The gardens on the side were cut off by the frame. A figure across the front of the painting was perhaps a fence defining a passageway.Fig. 5.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ix, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 12, p. 44 (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: 18.15.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).     Fig. 4: 18.16.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).     Fig. 5: 18.22.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1952
Bibliography  Della Corte, Case, p. 339, no. 723a. Jashemski, Gardens, vol. 1, fig. 160 on p. 102 (for the portrait). (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, pp. 44; 395. (worldcat) Maiuri, Pompeii, p. 82. (worldcat) Schefold, WandP, p. 38.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 09 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>