<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/saint-cricq-villeneuve_landes/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:07:01 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/saint-cricq-villeneuve_landes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa at Glesia, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/saint-cricq-villeneuve_landes/gallia-aquitania_villa-at-glesia_j.zhou/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:07:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/saint-cricq-villeneuve_landes/gallia-aquitania_villa-at-glesia_j.zhou/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_Aquitania Gallia_Aquitania (Pleiades)
Province Description A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location Saint-Cricq-Villeneuve
Saint-Cricq-Villeneuve, Landes (Pleiades)
House Villa at Glesia
House Description On the right bank of the Midou, there was discovered in 1868 a large villa with much marble and numerous mosaics. A salvage excavation in 1976 only glimpsed the remains, and they are now known unfortunately only from a very schematic plan and sketchy descriptions.
Garden Keywords  mosaics (visual works) reception rooms  Garden Description The villa was built around a large courtyard (88.6 by 31.6 as read from the plan), which may have been a garden. It does not seem to have been surrounded in the usual way by porticoes, but one should not put much trust in the very simplified plan. There are, however, façade galleries on several sides. The separate baths, situated below the house near the river, were connected to the villa a series of flights of steps with landings between them. Along the southeast two-thirds of the southwest façade, a gallery runs between two reception rooms, a feature shared with the villa de Baptest at Moncrabeau, though in the present case, the gallery seems to have been double. Moreover, according to the descriptions of the excavations, each end of the exterior gallery (65 x 3.78 m) was terminated by an apse, a form found in other plans in this region and elsewhere. At the southeast end, in a feature characteristic of late antiquity, a trilobed room opened off of the reception room and extended beyond the basic rectangle of the house, as if to allow the enjoyment of the surrounding grounds.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the Villa at Glesia. Adapted from Dufourcet et al., 1890.   Dates 1868CE
Excavation Dates 1976CE
Bibliography  J. Quicherat, Rapport sur diverses communications concernant des mosaïques trouvées à Saint-Cricq (Landes, Revue des Sociétés Savantes, 5e série, I, 1870, p. 116-119. (worldcat) E. Morvillez, Forme et évolution des salles de réception des grandes demeures tardives du bassin Méditerranéen occidental, 1993, t. 1, p. 179-185.(worldcat) Catherine Balmelle, Les demeures aristocratiques d&amp;rsquo;Aquitaine, societe et culture de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquite tardive dans le sou-ouest de la Gaule, Ausonius, supple. d&amp;rsquo;Aquitania 10, Bordeaux 2001, p. 401-403, 445. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 249916
TGN ID Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>