<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>PROCONSULARIS on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/categories/proconsularis/</link>
    <description>Recent content in PROCONSULARIS on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 07:38:05 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/categories/proconsularis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>House of the Fishing Scene</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/althiburos/house_of_the_fishing_scene/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 07:38:05 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/althiburos/house_of_the_fishing_scene/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa proconsularis(Pleiades)
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location ALTHIBUROS (Médeïna) Tunisia(Pleiades)
Location Description This town is located on the road between Carthage and Theveste near the border of Proconsularis and Byzacena 35 km west of Mactar. Under the Roman Empire it remained an indigenous civitas until it was raised to the status of a municipium by Hadrian: municipium aelium hadrianum augustum althiburitanum and later was granted the ius Italicum.
The trade of agricultural products and craftsmanship made Althiburos a prosperous city, particularly, the fabrication and the commerce of aromatics. The development of the city reached its peak under the Antonian and Severian dynasties. It is difficult to follow the history of Althiburos during the third century when the province of Africa underwent the severe crisis of 238. The city was abandoned just before the Arab conquest. Excavations have brought to light the forum, the capitol, the Hadrianic triumphal arch and two temples. At the east corner of the forum, near one of the temples, was a complex of houses and a building with a rotonda to the south of which stood a monumental fountain. Outside the excavated center are other monuments, among them the theater and a triumphal arch.
Garden House of the Fishing Scene (Maison de la scène de pêche)
Keywords  peristyles (colonnades)  Garden Description The house stands on the other side of the Wadi Oum El Abid, on the left bank, 120 meters to the north of the capitol. The badly damaged rooms are arranged around a peristyle whose porticoes are paved with mosaics (Plan view, Fig.1). A long basin bisected the garden that was enclosed by a balustrade running in between the columns. One of the rooms to the north of the peristyle has two symmetrical apses at each end and is paved with a famous mosaic representing a fishing scene with the head of Oceanus depicted at either end.
Maps Images   Fig. 1: House of the Fishing Scene. Photo courtesy of Amina-Aïcha Malek.(Rights statement)   Dates Severian period (IIIrd c.)
Bibliography  R. Rebuffat, 1969, Althiburos 3 ; M. Ennaifer, La cité d’Althiburos et l’édifice des Asclepieia, INA, Tunis, 1976, p. 58-63, plan pl. XXXIII, *   Bullo, S. and F. Ghedini,. Amplissimae atque ornatissimae domus: l&amp;rsquo;edilizia residenziale nelle citta della Tunisia roman, Rome: Edizioni Quasar, 2003,p.30-31. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 324664
TGN ID 5003658
Contributor Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X
Publication date 13 November 2020
Related articles House of the Muses (Maison des Muses) Asclepeia Building (Edifice des Asclepeia)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House H (Maison H)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/utica/house_h/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 09:49:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/utica/house_h/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa proconsularis(Pleiades)
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location UTICA (Utique) Tunisia(Pleiades)
Location Description Her geographic situation made of Utica one of the oldest and well-known Phoenician settlements. In 146 B.C, Utica became the capital of the newly created province of Africa and the residence of the governor. With the triumph of Caesar and the resurgence of Carthage, Utica&amp;rsquo;s supremacy would gradually decline under the empire. In 36 B.C. it became a municipium and a colony under Hadrian.
The city was laid out on a grid plan. Numerous buildings have been uncovered, among them the forum, several temples and baths, an amphitheater, a circus, and opulent houses. Many of these buildings of the Republican period were, during the imperial era, replaced by others larger and more luxurious. This explains the existence of two theaters for example, the one fitted into the side of the hill, the other built in open country. Enormous cisterns were constructed, fed by an aqueduct. Still extant on the summit of the acropolis overlooking the town, is a quadrangular edifice habitually referred to as “the citadel,” which could perhaps be simply a water tower.
Garden House H (Maison H)
Keywords  semicircular mosaics  Garden Description This house, the largest in insula III (lots 2,3,4,9,10), rivals the House of the Cascade in size and richness of mosaics (Plan view, Fig.1). A semicircular basin extended into the garden on the S and E sides, each decorated with a marine scene.
Images   Fig.1: Plan of the House H. Photo courtesy of Wilhelmina F. Jashemski.   Dates the I-III century.
Bibliography  CMT, Utique, Les Mosaïque in situ en dehors des insulae I-II-III, INA, Tunis, 1974, pp.121-128. (worldcat) Bullo, S. and F. Ghedini,. Amplissimae atque ornatissimae domus: l&amp;rsquo;edilizia residenziale nelle citta della Tunisia roman, Rome: Edizioni Quasar, 2003, p.346-347. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 315248
TGN ID 7018163
Contributor Wilhelmina F. Jashemski (WorldCat Identities: lccn-n80037970 Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X
Publication date 13 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Africa (Maison de l&#39;Afrique)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/thysdrus/house_of_africa/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 09:49:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/thysdrus/house_of_africa/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa proconsularis(Pleiades)
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location THYSDRUS (El Jem) Tunisia(Pleiades)
Location Description Thysdrus is located on the western border of the Sahel at 60 km S of Hadrumetum on the road leading to Sfax. The development, from the end of the 2d c., of its olive plantations and its trade in oil made the fortune of the city.
The name appeared for the first time in the period of Caesar&amp;rsquo;s African campaign when the city, at the time a small town, took side with the Pompeian and Juba against Ceasar. Towards the end of the 2d c. it became a municipium, competing with Hadrumetum for the second place in the province. The decline of Thysdrus began when, involved in a political crisis, the city choose the side of Gordian proconsul of Africa against the Emperor Maximianus. The joint effects of the political disgrace and the economic crisis, which resulted from it, brought an end to its development. By the end of the IVth century it was scarcely mentioned by the Catholic and Donatist bishops.
Among the most remarkable monuments of the ancient city are the best preserved large amphitheater in Africa, the small amphitheater located some 7.20 m to the S of the large one, the circus better visible on an aerial photography, the baths covering a surface of 2400 sq., and the residential district bounded on the S by a necropolis and to the E by a fine street.
Garden House of Africa (Maison de l&amp;rsquo;Afrique) (New plan and reconstruction) cf V.B.Bijon
Keywords  peristyle semicircular  Garden Description This vast house (3000 m2) was laid out around a peristyle garden (Plan view, Fig.1). The sunken garden was enclosed by a low wall that curved to form a semi-circular basin in-between the third and fourth column to which was adjoined a euripus at the end of which a rectangular platform supported either a sculpture or a fountain.
Dates the beginning of the IIIrd century.
Bibliography  H. Slim, CMGR VII-1, 1999, pp. 137-38, Archéologia, Avril 2000, n° 366. (worldcat) Bullo, S. and F. Ghedini, Amplissimae atque ornatissimae domus: l’edilizia residenziale nelle citta della Tunisia roman, Rome: Edizioni Quasar, 2003, p.123-124. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 324835
TGN ID 7017557
Contributor Wilhelmina F. Jashemski (WorldCat Identities: lccn-n80037970 Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X
Publication date 13 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Baklouti (Maison de Baklouti)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/uthina/house_of_baklouti/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 09:49:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/uthina/house_of_baklouti/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa proconsularis(Pleiades)
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location UTHINA (Oudna) Tunisia(Pleiades)
Location Description Uthina was a town in the province of Africa Proconsularis, now northern Tunisia. Uthina became a Roman colony of veterans of Legio XIII Gemina during the reign of Emperor Augustus. Hence, it was mentioned by Ptolemy (IV, 3, 34), Pliny the Elder, and the Tabula Peutingeriana.
From the accounts given by geographers the site seems to be the ruins that form the archeological site of Oudna, near a station on the railway from Tunis to Kef and not far from what was the World War II Oudna Airfield. These ruins occupy a surface nearly three miles in circumference, covering a hilly plateau, and commanding the left bank of the Milian wady; there are remains of a fortress, cisterns, an aqueduct, a triumphal arch, a theatre, an amphitheater, a basilica with a circular crypt, and a bridge. Many mosaics are to be found there as well.
Garden House of Baklouti (Maison de Baklouti)
Keywords  peristyle niches  Garden Description The peristyle garden enclosed by a portico on four sides had a long basin, which was concave at one end, and had semicircular and rectangular niches. It occupied the central axis of the garden. The bottom was paved with mosaic. The semicircular pool extending into the garden on the E side was also decorated with niches.
Dates the II-III century.
Bibliography  H. Baklouti, &amp;ldquo;Une fouille à Uthina, rapport préliminaire&amp;rdquo;, in REPPAL, 1997, 10, p. 17-34. (worldcat) Bullo, S. and F. Ghedini,. Amplissimae atque ornatissimae domus: l&amp;rsquo;edilizia residenziale nelle citta della Tunisia roman, Rome: Edizioni Quasar, 2003, p.333-334. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 315247
TGN ID 7024022
Contributor Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X
Publication date 13 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Icarios (Maison d&#39;Icarios)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/uthina/house_of_icarios/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 09:49:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/uthina/house_of_icarios/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa proconsularis(Pleiades)
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location UTHINA (Oudna) Tunisia(Pleiades)
Location Description Uthina was a town in the province of Africa Proconsularis, now northern Tunisia. Uthina became a Roman colony of veterans of Legio XIII Gemina during the reign of Emperor Augustus. Hence, it was mentioned by Ptolemy (IV, 3, 34), Pliny the Elder, and the Tabula Peutingeriana.
From the accounts given by geographers the site seems to be the ruins that form the archeological site of Oudna, near a station on the railway from Tunis to Kef and not far from what was the World War II Oudna Airfield. These ruins occupy a surface nearly three miles in circumference, covering a hilly plateau, and commanding the left bank of the Milian wady; there are remains of a fortress, cisterns, an aqueduct, a triumphal arch, a theatre, an amphitheater, a basilica with a circular crypt, and a bridge. Many mosaics are to be found there as well.
Garden   Fig. 1: Plan view of the House of Icarios. Photo courtesy of Amina-Aïcha Malek.(Rights statement)   Keywords  domus triclinium vaults vestibule cistern  Garden Description This richly decorated house is considered as one of the most remarkable domus of Africa (Plan view, Fig.1). Twenty-four Corinthian columns that may have reached 3m high, supported a portico on four sides. On the North, the South and the West, the peristyle is surrounded by rooms and apartments, some with their own colonnaded courtyards paved with mosaics (pseudo-atria). The Eastern portico, because of the declivity of the land was constructed on vaults. It probably opened on the exterior by a colonnade that allowed the visitor to admire the sea, the mountains and the valley of Oued Zaghouan. A small wooden fence enclosed the garden except in front of the vestibule and the oecus, from the vestibule one could traverse the garden and enter the oecus, without having to use the porticoes. At a later phase these entries were closed by a basin and cistern. The garden had in its center a rectangular basin, of which only the foundation was found.
Maps Images   Fig.1: Plan of the House of Icarios. Photo courtesy of Amina-Aïcha Malek.(Rights statement)   Dates the II-III century.
Bibliography  P. Gauckler in MonPiot 2(1896) 177-229; P. Quoniam in MelRome 60(1948) pp. 35-54; H. Ben Hassen, L. Maurin, Oudna (Uthina) La découverte d’une ville antique de Tunisie, Paris, 1998; Tomei, Antenor, 3, 2002. (worldcat) Bullo, S. and F. Ghedini,. Amplissimae atque ornatissimae domus: l&amp;rsquo;edilizia residenziale nelle citta della Tunisia roman, Rome: Edizioni Quasar, 2003,p.325-329. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 315247
TGN ID 7024022
Contributor Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X
Publication date 13 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Icarios (Maison d&#39;Icarios)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/uthina/house_of_industrius/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 09:49:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/uthina/house_of_industrius/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa proconsularis(Pleiades)
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location UTHINA (Oudna) Tunisia(Pleiades)
Location Description Located to the Southeast of the amphitheater, this house was laid out around a peristyle garden of 10 columns that connected by a low wall. A semicircular basin extended into the garden on the NE facing the reception room.
Garden House of Icarios (Maison d&amp;rsquo;Icarios)
Keywords  colonnade vestibule cistern  Garden Description This richly decorated house is considered as one of the most remarkable domus of Africa (Plan view, Fig.1). Twenty-four Corinthian columns that may have reached 3m high, supported a portico on four sides. On the North, the South and the West, the peristyle is surrounded by rooms and apartments, some with their own colonnaded courtyards paved with mosaics (pseudo-atria). The Eastern portico, because of the declivity of the land was constructed on vaults. It probably opened on the exterior by a colonnade that allowed the visitor to admire the sea, the mountains and the valley of Oued Zaghouan. A small wooden fence enclosed the garden except in front of the vestibule and the oecus, from the vestibule one could traverse the garden and enter the oecus, without having to use the porticoes. At a later phase these entries were closed by a basin and cistern. The garden had in its center a rectangular basin, of which only the foundation was found.
Maps Dates the II-III century.
Bibliography  H. Ben Hassen, L. Maurin, Oudna (Uthina) La découverte d’une ville antique de Tunisie, Paris, 1998.(worldcat) Bullo, S. and F. Ghedini,. Amplissimae atque ornatissimae domus: l&amp;rsquo;edilizia residenziale nelle citta della Tunisia roman, Rome: Edizioni Quasar, 2003, p.330-332. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 315247
TGN ID 7024022
Contributor Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X
Publication date 13 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Cascade (Maison de la Cascade)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/utica/house_of_the_cascade/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 09:49:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/utica/house_of_the_cascade/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa proconsularis(Pleiades)
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location UTICA (Utique) Tunisia(Pleiades)
Location Description Her geographic situation made of Utica one of the oldest and well-known Phoenician settlements. In 146 B.C, Utica became the capital of the newly created province of Africa and the residence of the governor. With the triumph of Caesar and the resurgence of Carthage, Utica&amp;rsquo;s supremacy would gradually decline under the empire. In 36 B.C. it became a municipium and a colony under Hadrian.
The city was laid out on a grid plan. Numerous buildings have been uncovered, among them the forum, several temples and baths, an amphitheater, a circus, and opulent houses. Many of these buildings of the Republican period were, during the imperial era, replaced by others larger and more luxurious. This explains the existence of two theaters for example, the one fitted into the side of the hill, the other built in open country. Enormous cisterns were constructed, fed by an aqueduct. Still extant on the summit of the acropolis overlooking the town, is a quadrangular edifice habitually referred to as “the citadel,” which could perhaps be simply a water tower.
Garden House of the Cascade (Maison de la Cascade)
Keywords  masonry triclinium baroque cascade  Garden Description This house, the largest in the insula II (lots 2,3,8,9,10), was given its present form in the second century. A large peristyle with elaborate viridarium dominated the S part of the house (Plan view, Fig.1). The large shallow pool in the center of the garden occupied a rectangular area that was largely filled by a huge marble-faced masonry construction with semicircular and rectangular niches that gave the pool a baroque shape. The marble-faced construction probably held an important sculpture. Water from the fountain jet spilled from the marble-lined channel cut into the base and then spilled into the pool. The sundial, today at the edge of the base of the pool, is not in its original position.
Extending into the garden from the two central columns on the N was a semicircular pool (which faced the large room (XXXIV), decorated with a well preserved mosaic showing an Eros fishing from a boat, surrounded by fish and other sea animals. A wide entrance on the E side of the garden led through the portico to the handsome triclinium, by far the largest room in the house.
Opening off of the triclinium to the S was a smaller area enclosed by a portico on three sides. The dominant feature was the shallow square basin (1.92x 1.2 m) decorated with a fish mosaic and the adjacent mosaic panel from which the house is named. In the cascade panel, two fishermen are pulling in a vast net full of fish and sea animals. The soil on each side of the cascade was probably planted.
Maps Images   Fig. 1: Plan of the House of the Cascade. Photo courtesy of Wilhelmina F. Jashemski for House of the Cascade.(Rights statement)   Dates the I-II century.
Bibliography  CMT, Utique, insulae, I-II-III, INA, Tunis, 1973, pp. 19-56, plan 5,7 and plates 8, 9, 25, 63. [(WorldCat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/61828622) P.-A. Février, &amp;ldquo;Image, imaginaire et symbolisme. A propos de deux maisons du Maghreb antique&amp;rdquo;, in Mosaïque, Recueil d&amp;rsquo;hommages à Henri Stern, Paris,1983, p. 159-162. (worldcat) Bullo, S. and F. Ghedini,. Amplissimae atque ornatissimae domus: l&amp;rsquo;edilizia residenziale nelle citta della Tunisia roman, Rome: Edizioni Quasar, 2003, p.351-354. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 315248
TGN ID 7018163
Contributor Wilhelmina F. Jashemski (WorldCat Identities: lccn-n80037970 Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X
Publication date 13 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Dolphins (Maison des dauphins)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/thysdrus/house_of_lucius_verus/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 09:49:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/thysdrus/house_of_lucius_verus/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa proconsularis(Pleiades)
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location THYSDRUS (El Jem) Tunisia(Pleiades)
Location Description Thysdrus is located on the western border of the Sahel at 60 km S of Hadrumetum on the road leading to Sfax. The development, from the end of the 2d c., of its olive plantations and its trade in oil made the fortune of the city.
The name appeared for the first time in the period of Caesar&amp;rsquo;s African campaign when the city, at the time a small town, took side with the Pompeian and Juba against Ceasar. Towards the end of the 2d c. it became a municipium, competing with Hadrumetum for the second place in the province. The decline of Thysdrus began when, involved in a political crisis, the city choose the side of Gordian proconsul of Africa against the Emperor Maximianus. The joint effects of the political disgrace and the economic crisis, which resulted from it, brought an end to its development. By the end of the IVth century it was scarcely mentioned by the Catholic and Donatist bishops.
Among the most remarkable monuments of the ancient city are the best preserved large amphitheater in Africa, the small amphitheater located some 7.20 m to the S of the large one, the circus better visible on an aerial photography, the baths covering a surface of 2400 sq., and the residential district bounded on the S by a necropolis and to the E by a fine street.
Garden House of the Dolphins (Maison des dauphins)
Keywords  peristyle  Garden Description The house was laid out around a large persityle garden of twenty-two columns (20 x15.5 m) that had a euripus and a semicircular basin facing a large reception room (Plan view, Fig.1)
Maps Images   Fig. 1: Plan of the House of Lucius Verus. Photo courtesy of Wilhelmina F. Jashemski.(Rights statement)   Dates the beginning of the IIIrd century.
Bibliography  H. SLIM, &amp;ldquo;Thysdrus, une des plus grarndes villes romaines d&amp;rsquo;Afrique&amp;rdquo;, in Dossiers archéologiques, 69, 1983, p. 52-61; &amp;ldquo;La maison du portrait de Lucius Verus à El Jem,&amp;rdquo; BSAF, 1990, p.87-88; (worldcat) &amp;ldquo;Le modèle urbain romain et le problème de l&amp;rsquo;eau dans les confins Sahel et de la Basse Steppe&amp;rdquo;, in *Afrique dans l&amp;rsquo;Occident romain (1er Siècle av. J.-C.- IV siècls ap. J.-C.) *Actes du Colloque, Rome, décembre 1987, Rome, 1990, p. 190-192; El Jem, Ancient Thrysdrus, Tunis, 1996, p. 75-76; (worldcat) Commission d&amp;rsquo;Afrique du Nord 2/2/90 BCTH(worldcat) Bullo, S. and F. Ghedini,. Amplissimae atque ornatissimae domus: l&amp;rsquo;edilizia residenziale nelle citta della Tunisia roman, Rome: Edizioni Quasar, 2003,p.309-312. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 324835
TGN ID 7017557
Contributor Wilhelmina F. Jashemski (WorldCat Identities: lccn-n80037970 Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X
Publication date 13 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Dolphins (Maison des dauphins)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/thysdrus/house_of_the_dolphins/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 09:49:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/thysdrus/house_of_the_dolphins/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa proconsularis(Pleiades)
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location THYSDRUS (El Jem) Tunisia(Pleiades)
Location Description Thysdrus is located on the western border of the Sahel at 60 km S of Hadrumetum on the road leading to Sfax. The development, from the end of the 2d c., of its olive plantations and its trade in oil made the fortune of the city.
The name appeared for the first time in the period of Caesar&amp;rsquo;s African campaign when the city, at the time a small town, took side with the Pompeian and Juba against Ceasar. Towards the end of the 2d c. it became a municipium, competing with Hadrumetum for the second place in the province. The decline of Thysdrus began when, involved in a political crisis, the city choose the side of Gordian proconsul of Africa against the Emperor Maximianus. The joint effects of the political disgrace and the economic crisis, which resulted from it, brought an end to its development. By the end of the IVth century it was scarcely mentioned by the Catholic and Donatist bishops.
Among the most remarkable monuments of the ancient city are the best preserved large amphitheater in Africa, the small amphitheater located some 7.20 m to the S of the large one, the circus better visible on an aerial photography, the baths covering a surface of 2400 sq., and the residential district bounded on the S by a necropolis and to the E by a fine street.
Garden House of the Dolphins (Maison des dauphins)
Keywords  column porticos aedicula  Garden Description The vast house (3000-3500 m2) is laid out around a large peristyle garden (Plan view, Fig.1). The large sunken garden (X, 16 x 16.25 m) was enclosed by a low wall (0.70 m high) and had a large semicircular basin (dia. 3.10 m) between the fifth and the sixth column facing a reception room (XXV). A rectangular aedicula with four columns facing the oecus (XXXVII) extended in the garden on the W.
Two lararia (32 B, XXXV) open off of porticos XI and XIII respectively. Images   Fig. 1: House of the Dolphins. Photo courtesy of Wilhelmina F. Jashemski for House of the Dolphins.(Rights statement)   Dates the beginning of the IIIrd century.
Bibliography  CMT, Thysdrus, El Jem, Quartier Sud-Ouest, INA, Tunis, 1996, pp. 67-75, plans 5-6. (worldcat) Bullo, S. and F. Ghedini,. Amplissimae atque ornatissimae domus: l&amp;rsquo;edilizia residenziale nelle citta della Tunisia roman, Rome: Edizioni Quasar, 2003,p.309-312. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 324835
TGN ID 7017557
Contributor Wilhelmina F. Jashemski (WorldCat Identities: lccn-n80037970 Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X
Publication date 13 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Figured Basins (Maison aux bassins figurés)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/utica/house_of_the_figured_basins/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 09:49:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/utica/house_of_the_figured_basins/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa proconsularis(Pleiades)
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location UTICA (Utique) Tunisia(Pleiades)
Location Description Her geographic situation made of Utica one of the oldest and well-known Phoenician settlements. In 146 B.C, Utica became the capital of the newly created province of Africa and the residence of the governor. With the triumph of Caesar and the resurgence of Carthage, Utica&amp;rsquo;s supremacy would gradually decline under the empire. In 36 B.C. it became a municipium and a colony under Hadrian.
The city was laid out on a grid plan. Numerous buildings have been uncovered, among them the forum, several temples and baths, an amphitheater, a circus, and opulent houses. Many of these buildings of the Republican period were, during the imperial era, replaced by others larger and more luxurious. This explains the existence of two theaters for example, the one fitted into the side of the hill, the other built in open country. Enormous cisterns were constructed, fed by an aqueduct. Still extant on the summit of the acropolis overlooking the town, is a quadrangular edifice habitually referred to as “the citadel,” which could perhaps be simply a water tower.
Garden House of the Figured Basins (Maison aux bassins figurés)
Keywords  semicircular geometric brim  Garden Description The house was located in the insula III. The rectangular courtyard, in the SW corner on the axis of the great hall (XI), paved during the last period may have been a garden earlier (Plan view, Fig.1). It had a semicircular basin with a geometric design in the bottom. The wall and the brim were figured.
Maps Images   Fig. 1: Plan view of the House of the Figured Basins. Photo courtesy of Wilhelmina F. Jashemski.   Dates the II-IV century.
Bibliography  CMT. Utique, insulae, I-II-III, INA, Tunis, 1973, pp. 121, 126-128, plan 23. (worldcat) Bullo, S. and F. Ghedini,. Amplissimae atque ornatissimae domus: l&amp;rsquo;edilizia residenziale nelle citta della Tunisia roman, Rome: Edizioni Quasar, 2003,p.344-345. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 315248
TGN ID 7018163
Contributor Wilhelmina F. Jashemski (WorldCat Identities: lccn-n80037970 Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X
Publication date 2 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Grand Oecus (Maison du grand oecus)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/utica/house_of_the_grand_oecus/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 09:49:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/utica/house_of_the_grand_oecus/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa proconsularis(Pleiades)
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location UTICA (Utique) Tunisia(Pleiades)
Location Description Her geographic situation made of Utica one of the oldest and well-known Phoenician settlements. In 146 B.C, Utica became the capital of the newly created province of Africa and the residence of the governor. With the triumph of Caesar and the resurgence of Carthage, Utica&amp;rsquo;s supremacy would gradually decline under the empire. In 36 B.C. it became a municipium and a colony under Hadrian.
The city was laid out on a grid plan. Numerous buildings have been uncovered, among them the forum, several temples and baths, an amphitheater, a circus, and opulent houses. Many of these buildings of the Republican period were, during the imperial era, replaced by others larger and more luxurious. This explains the existence of two theaters for example, the one fitted into the side of the hill, the other built in open country. Enormous cisterns were constructed, fed by an aqueduct. Still extant on the summit of the acropolis overlooking the town, is a quadrangular edifice habitually referred to as “the citadel,” which could perhaps be simply a water tower.
Garden House of the Grand Oecus (Maison du grand oecus)
Keywords  peristyle portico concave mosaic  Garden Description This house is the most important dwelling discovered to date at Utica. The large peristyle garden (XXVII), enclosed by a portico on four sides (XXVIII-XXX) had a long basin concave at each end down the center of the garden (Plan view, Fig. 1). The bottom was paved with a simple mosaic. The semicircular pool extending into the garden on the N side was also paved with a simple mosaic.
Maps Images   Fig.1: Plan of the House of the Grand Oecus. Photo courtesy of Wilhelmina F. Jashemski.   Dates the I-II century.
Bibliography  CMT, Utique, Les Mosaïque in situ en dehors des insulae I-II-III, INA, Tunis, 1974, pp. 1-18, plans 1, 2. (worldcat) Bullo, S. and F. Ghedini,. Amplissimae atque ornatissimae domus: l&amp;rsquo;edilizia residenziale nelle citta della Tunisia roman, Rome: Edizioni Quasar, 2003, p.341-343. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 315248
TGN ID 7018163
Contributor Wilhelmina F. Jashemski (WorldCat Identities: lccn-n80037970 Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X
Publication date 13 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Peacock (Maison du Paon)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/thysdrus/house_of_the_peacock/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 09:49:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/thysdrus/house_of_the_peacock/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa proconsularis(Pleiades)
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location THYSDRUS (El Jem) Tunisia(Pleiades)
Location Description Thysdrus is located on the western border of the Sahel at 60 km S of Hadrumetum on the road leading to Sfax. The development, from the end of the 2d c., of its olive plantations and its trade in oil made the fortune of the city.
The name appeared for the first time in the period of Caesar&amp;rsquo;s African campaign when the city, at the time a small town, took side with the Pompeian and Juba against Ceasar. Towards the end of the 2d c. it became a municipium, competing with Hadrumetum for the second place in the province. The decline of Thysdrus began when, involved in a political crisis, the city choose the side of Gordian proconsul of Africa against the Emperor Maximianus. The joint effects of the political disgrace and the economic crisis, which resulted from it, brought an end to its development. By the end of the IVth century it was scarcely mentioned by the Catholic and Donatist bishops.
Among the most remarkable monuments of the ancient city are the best preserved large amphitheater in Africa, the small amphitheater located some 7.20 m to the S of the large one, the circus better visible on an aerial photography, the baths covering a surface of 2400 sq., and the residential district bounded on the S by a necropolis and to the E by a fine street.
Garden House of the Peacock (Maison du Paon)
Keywords  semicircular domus  Garden Description This large house (1800 m2) adjacent to the domus of Sollertiana on the N had a large peristyle garden (XIII, 10.50 x 13.20 m) enclosed on four sides by a portico (XIV-XVII) of 18 columns that were connected by a low wall (Plan view, Fig.1). A semicircular basin facing the large oecus on the N, extended into the garden 30 cm lower than the level of the portico. To the N a small courtyard garden (XXXII, 2.70 x 3.70 m) 40cm lower than the level of the portico had 2 two semicircular pools that occupied most of the space, each facing a reception room (XXXI, XXXIII).
The light well (XXVII, 8.45 x 2.75 m) to the W of the oecus was also planted.
Images   Fig. 1: Plan of the House of the Peacock. Photo courtesy of Wilhelmina F. Jashemski for House of the Peacock.(Rights statement)   Dates the beginning of the IIIrd century.
Bibliography  CMT, Thysdrus, El Jem, Quartier Sud-Ouest, INA, Tunis, 1996, pp. 31-66, plans 3-4.(worldcat) Bullo, S. and F. Ghedini,. Amplissimae atque ornatissimae domus: l&amp;rsquo;edilizia residenziale nelle citta della Tunisia roman, Rome: Edizioni Quasar, 2003, p.266-267.p.313-316. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 324835
TGN ID 7017557
Contributor Wilhelmina F. Jashemski (WorldCat Identities: lccn-n80037970 Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X
Publication date 13 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Treasure (Maison au trésor)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/utica/house_of_the_treasure/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 09:49:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/utica/house_of_the_treasure/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa proconsularis(Pleiades)
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location UTICA (Utique) Tunisia(Pleiades)
Location Description Her geographic situation made of Utica one of the oldest and well-known Phoenician settlements. In 146 B.C, Utica became the capital of the newly created province of Africa and the residence of the governor. With the triumph of Caesar and the resurgence of Carthage, Utica&amp;rsquo;s supremacy would gradually decline under the empire. In 36 B.C. it became a municipium and a colony under Hadrian.
The city was laid out on a grid plan. Numerous buildings have been uncovered, among them the forum, several temples and baths, an amphitheater, a circus, and opulent houses. Many of these buildings of the Republican period were, during the imperial era, replaced by others larger and more luxurious. This explains the existence of two theaters for example, the one fitted into the side of the hill, the other built in open country. Enormous cisterns were constructed, fed by an aqueduct. Still extant on the summit of the acropolis overlooking the town, is a quadrangular edifice habitually referred to as “the citadel,” which could perhaps be simply a water tower.
Garden House of the Treasure (Maison au trésor)
Keywords  semicircular triclinium oecus  Garden Description The House is located in the insula II (Lots 1,7). The peristyle garden had a semicircular basin extending from the two middle columns on the S side, facing the triclinium (XVII) during the first century AD (Plan view, Fig.1). When the house was substantially altered in the second century the enlargement of the curb on the adjoining well destroyed half of the basin. At the same time the oecus was subdivided into several rooms, courtyard was paved.
Maps Images   Fig.1: Plan of the House of the Treasure. Photo courtesy of Wilhelmina F. Jashemski.   Dates the I-IV century.
Bibliography  CMT, Utique, Les Mosaïque in situ en dehors des insulae I-II-III, INA, Tunis, 1974, pp.11-18, plans 3,4.(worldcat) Bullo, S. and F. Ghedini,. Amplissimae atque ornatissimae domus: l&amp;rsquo;edilizia residenziale nelle citta della Tunisia roman, Rome: Edizioni Quasar, 2003, p.348-349. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 315248
TGN ID 7018163
Contributor Wilhelmina F. Jashemski (WorldCat Identities: lccn-n80037970 Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X
Publication date 13 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Triumph of Neptune (Maison du Triomphe de Neptune)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/althiburos/asclepeia_building/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 09:49:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/althiburos/asclepeia_building/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa proconsularis(Pleiades)
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location ALTHIBUROS (Médeïna) Tunisia(Pleiades)
Location Description This town is located on the road between Carthage and Theveste near the border of Proconsularis and Byzacena 35 km west of Mactar. Under the Roman Empire it remained an indigenous civitas until it was raised to the status of a municipium by Hadrian: municipium aelium hadrianum augustum althiburitanum and later was granted the ius Italicum.
The trade of agricultural products and craftsmanship made Althiburos a prosperous city, particularly, the fabrication and the commerce of aromatics. The development of the city reached its peak under the Antonian and Severian dynasties. It is difficult to follow the history of Althiburos during the third century when the province of Africa underwent the severe crisis of 238. The city was abandoned just before the Arab conquest. Excavations have brought to light the forum, the capitol, the Hadrianic triumphal arch and two temples. At the east corner of the forum, near one of the temples, was a complex of houses and a building with a rotonda to the south of which stood a monumental fountain. Outside the excavated center are other monuments, among them the theater and a triumphal arch.
Garden Asclepeia Building (Edifice des Asclepeia)
Keywords  Il Portico triclinium lararium foliage  Garden Description The Asklepeia monument, so-called from a mosaic inscription, is located to the northeast of the House of the Muses. (Plan view, Fig. 1)
This building is divided into three sections: the central building, the northeast sector and the private baths. The central building, probably a house, presents an architectural arrangement unusual in Africa. Strictly symmetrical in plan, the monument has a long gallery terminating at either end in two corner turrets. The facade has several windows on either side of an impressive entrance. This corridor opens onto a large square room flanked on either side by a square-shaped basin with a passageway running around it. This great vestibule views onto a peristyle garden (20.33x17.5m) equipped with a complete hydraulic system in the garden (167m2). Two large symmetrical oeci, along with their adjoining apartments, frame both sides of this peristyle.
The garden gradually changed during three phases of building renovation.
During the first phase, in the beginning of the third century, the garden was bordered by twenty columns and had a well (f) and two square shaped enclosures (e, h) from which water jets came out. One jetted towards the reception room (4) located near the entrance on the south and the other jetted symmetrically towards the reception room (23) on the north.
During the second phase, in the mid third century, the garden was enclosed by a balustrade and several water features were added: two semi-circular basins (c, d) symmetrical in shape and size – with a rectangular shape on the outside and semi-circular on the inside, each facing a reception room (28, 16). A shallow round pool that had the shape of a daisy with 49 petals was placed inside the N square enclosure (h) from which water was jetting. The well was later filled with soil and not used.
During this phase, a long rectangular basin was laid in front of the entrance of the house. The basin may have been bordered by a garden.
During the third stage dated to the beginning of the second half of the fourth century, the water features were modified and a large basin was added. Niches were added inside the semi-circular basins. In the center of the garden, a rectangular basin (g) (6.20x4.20m) that protruded onto the square basin (h) and enclosed a small rectangular basin (g) (0.15x0.15m) was added.
Maps Images   Fig. 1: Plan of the Asclepeia Building. Photo courtesy of Amina-Aïcha Malek.(Rights statement)   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  M. Ennaifer, La cité d’Althiburos et l’édifice des Asclepeia, Ministère des Affaires Culturelles, Tunis, 1976, pp. 71-152, plan III-IV.(worldcat) Bullo, S. and F. Ghedini,. Amplissimae atque ornatissimae domus: l&amp;rsquo;edilizia residenziale nelle citta della Tunisia roman, Rome: Edizioni Quasar, 2003,p.21-26. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 324653
TGN ID 6000082
Contributor Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X
Publication date 13 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Triumph of Neptune (Maison du Triomphe de Neptune)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/althiburos/house_of_the_muses/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 09:49:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/althiburos/house_of_the_muses/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa proconsularis(Pleiades)
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location ALTHIBUROS (Médeïna) Tunisia(Pleiades)
Location Description This town is located on the road between Carthage and Theveste near the border of Proconsularis and Byzacena 35 km west of Mactar. Under the Roman Empire it remained an indigenous civitas until it was raised to the status of a municipium by Hadrian: municipium aelium hadrianum augustum althiburitanum and later was granted the ius Italicum.
The trade of agricultural products and craftsmanship made Althiburos a prosperous city, particularly, the fabrication and the commerce of aromatics. The development of the city reached its peak under the Antonian and Severian dynasties. It is difficult to follow the history of Althiburos during the third century when the province of Africa underwent the severe crisis of 238. The city was abandoned just before the Arab conquest. Excavations have brought to light the forum, the capitol, the Hadrianic triumphal arch and two temples. At the east corner of the forum, near one of the temples, was a complex of houses and a building with a rotonda to the south of which stood a monumental fountain. Outside the excavated center are other monuments, among them the theater and a triumphal arch.
Garden House of the Fishing Scene (Maison de la scène de pêche)
Keywords  Il Portico triclinium lararium foliage  Garden Description The house, noteworthy for its many and varied mosaic floors, is located on the right side of Oum El Abid river in a residential neighborhood. This vast domus is laid out around a peristyle onto which the rooms open. The courtyard (6.50 x 6.50 m) may have been planted (Plan view, Fig. 1). A long basin (4.15x 1.85; D. 0,72m.) was placed on the axis of the triclinium (G). Each end of the basin is curved to form a semi-circular pool.
The triclinium was bordered on two sides by two apartments that each had rooms and a corridor. The rooms to the north of the triclinium have an additional non-paved courtyard (L) enclosed by a colonnade closed by a balustrade. This lightwell may have been a small garden.
Maps Images   Fig. 1: Plan of the House of the Muses. Photo courtesy of Amina-Aïcha Malek.(Rights statement)   Dates Antonian and Severian period (II-III c.)
Bibliography  R. Rebuffat, 1969, Althiburos 2; M. Ennaifer, La cité d’Althiburos et l’édifice des Asclepieia, INA, Tunis, 1976, p. 64-70, plan II.(worldcat) Bullo, S. and F. Ghedini,. Amplissimae atque ornatissimae domus: l&amp;rsquo;edilizia residenziale nelle citta della Tunisia roman, Rome: Edizioni Quasar, 2003,p.27-29. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 324653
TGN ID 6000082
Contributor Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X
Publication date 13 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the West (Maison de l&#39;est)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/utica/house_of_the_west/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 09:49:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/utica/house_of_the_west/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa proconsularis
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location UTICA (Utique) Tunisia
Location Description Her geographic situation made of Utica one of the oldest and well-known Phoenician settlements. In 146 B.C, Utica became the capital of the newly created province of Africa and the residence of the governor. With the triumph of Caesar and the resurgence of Carthage, Utica&amp;rsquo;s supremacy would gradually decline under the empire. In 36 B.C. it became a municipium and a colony under Hadrian.
The city was laid out on a grid plan. Numerous buildings have been uncovered, among them the forum, several temples and baths, an amphitheater, a circus, and opulent houses. Many of these buildings of the Republican period were, during the imperial era, replaced by others larger and more luxurious. This explains the existence of two theaters for example, the one fitted into the side of the hill, the other built in open country. Enormous cisterns were constructed, fed by an aqueduct. Still extant on the summit of the acropolis overlooking the town, is a quadrangular edifice habitually referred to as “the citadel,” which could perhaps be simply a water tower.
Garden House of the West (Maison de l&amp;rsquo;est)
Keywords  column triclinium  Garden Description The peristyle garden (V) has a rectangular basin with curved angles extending from two middle columns on the W side, facing the triclinium (XI) (Plan view, Fig.1). The house is dated to the II c.
Maps Images   Fig.1: Plan of the House of the West. Photo courtesy of Wilhelmina F. Jashemski.   Dates the I-II century.
Bibliography  CMT, Utique, Les Mosaïque in situ en dehors des insulae I-II-III, INA, Tunis, 1974, pp.19-26, plans 4. (worldcat) Bullo, S. and F. Ghedini,. Amplissimae atque ornatissimae domus: l&amp;rsquo;edilizia residenziale nelle citta della Tunisia roman, Rome: Edizioni Quasar, 2003, p.339-340. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 315248
TGN ID 7018163
Contributor Wilhelmina F. Jashemski (WorldCat Identities: lccn-n80037970 Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X
Publication date 13 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the White Mosaic (Maison des mosaïques blanches)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/thysdrus/house_of_the_white_mosaic/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 09:49:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/thysdrus/house_of_the_white_mosaic/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa proconsularis(Pleiades)
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location THYSDRUS (El Jem) Tunisia(Pleiades)
Location Description Thysdrus is located on the western border of the Sahel at 60 km S of Hadrumetum on the road leading to Sfax. The development, from the end of the 2d c., of its olive plantations and its trade in oil made the fortune of the city.
The name appeared for the first time in the period of Caesar&amp;rsquo;s African campaign when the city, at the time a small town, took side with the Pompeian and Juba against Ceasar. Towards the end of the 2d c. it became a municipium, competing with Hadrumetum for the second place in the province. The decline of Thysdrus began when, involved in a political crisis, the city choose the side of Gordian proconsul of Africa against the Emperor Maximianus. The joint effects of the political disgrace and the economic crisis, which resulted from it, brought an end to its development. By the end of the IVth century it was scarcely mentioned by the Catholic and Donatist bishops.
Among the most remarkable monuments of the ancient city are the best preserved large amphitheater in Africa, the small amphitheater located some 7.20 m to the S of the large one, the circus better visible on an aerial photography, the baths covering a surface of 2400 sq., and the residential district bounded on the S by a necropolis and to the E by a fine street.
Garden House of the White Mosaic (Maison des mosaïques blanches)
Keywords  peristyle  Garden Description This house located E of the House of the Dolphins, has a small sunken peristyle garden (VI, 6.35 x 7 m) 60 cm lower than the level of the portico and bordered by a low wall (Plan view, Fig.1).
Maps Images   Fig.1: Plan of the house of the White Mosaic. Photo courtesy of Wilhelmina F. Jashemski.(Rights statement)   Dates the beginning of the IIIrd century.
Bibliography  CMT, Thysdrus, El Jem, Quartier Sud-Ouest, INA, Tunis, 1996, pp. 101-105, plans 7.(worldcat) Bullo, S. and F. Ghedini,. Amplissimae atque ornatissimae domus: l&amp;rsquo;edilizia residenziale nelle citta della Tunisia roman, Rome: Edizioni Quasar, 2003, p.306-308. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 324835
TGN ID 7017557
Contributor Wilhelmina F. Jashemski (WorldCat Identities: lccn-n80037970 Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X
Publication date 13 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Insula II, lot 4</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/utica/insula_ii_lot_4/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 09:49:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/utica/insula_ii_lot_4/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa proconsularis(Pleiades)
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location UTICA (Utique) Tunisia(Pleiades)
Location Description Her geographic situation made of Utica one of the oldest and well-known Phoenician settlements. In 146 B.C, Utica became the capital of the newly created province of Africa and the residence of the governor. With the triumph of Caesar and the resurgence of Carthage, Utica&amp;rsquo;s supremacy would gradually decline under the empire. In 36 B.C. it became a municipium and a colony under Hadrian.
The city was laid out on a grid plan. Numerous buildings have been uncovered, among them the forum, several temples and baths, an amphitheater, a circus, and opulent houses. Many of these buildings of the Republican period were, during the imperial era, replaced by others larger and more luxurious. This explains the existence of two theaters for example, the one fitted into the side of the hill, the other built in open country. Enormous cisterns were constructed, fed by an aqueduct. Still extant on the summit of the acropolis overlooking the town, is a quadrangular edifice habitually referred to as “the citadel,” which could perhaps be simply a water tower.
Garden Insula II, lot 4
Keywords  peristyle  Garden Description The peristyle courtyard is destroyed today, but there is soil in it (View plan, Fig.1). It may have been originally planted.
Maps Plans   Fig.1: Plan of the of the peristyle, Insula II, lot 4. Photo courtesy of Wilhelmina F. Jashemski.   Dates the I-II century.
Bibliography  CMT, Utique, Les Mosaïque in situ en dehors des insulae I-II-III, INA, Tunis, pp. 57-66, plans 8-10. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 315248
TGN ID 7018163
Contributor Wilhelmina F. Jashemski (WorldCat Identities: lccn-n80037970
Publication date 13 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sollertianna Domus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/thysdrus/sollertianna_domus/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 09:49:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/jinyi_yang/thysdrus/sollertianna_domus/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa proconsularis(Pleiades)
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location THYSDRUS (El Jem) Tunisia(Pleiades)
Location Description Thysdrus is located on the western border of the Sahel at 60 km S of Hadrumetum on the road leading to Sfax. The development, from the end of the 2d c., of its olive plantations and its trade in oil made the fortune of the city.
The name appeared for the first time in the period of Caesar&amp;rsquo;s African campaign when the city, at the time a small town, took side with the Pompeian and Juba against Ceasar. Towards the end of the 2d c. it became a municipium, competing with Hadrumetum for the second place in the province. The decline of Thysdrus began when, involved in a political crisis, the city choose the side of Gordian proconsul of Africa against the Emperor Maximianus. The joint effects of the political disgrace and the economic crisis, which resulted from it, brought an end to its development. By the end of the IVth century it was scarcely mentioned by the Catholic and Donatist bishops.
Among the most remarkable monuments of the ancient city are the best preserved large amphitheater in Africa, the small amphitheater located some 7.20 m to the S of the large one, the circus better visible on an aerial photography, the baths covering a surface of 2400 sq., and the residential district bounded on the S by a necropolis and to the E by a fine street.
Garden Sollertianna Domus
Keywords  periphery colonnade  Garden Description This large house (1120 m2) at the periphery of the SW quarter was laid out around a peristyle garden (VII, 8.20x11.30 m) enclosed on four sides by a portico of 14 columns that connected by a low wall (Plan view, Fig.1). A semicircular basin extended into the garden 75cm lower than the level of the portico. The cistern opening in the garden is adjacent to the middle column on the SE side. A large reception room (XVII) had a view onto the basin and the garden, which is planted today. A lararium (XXVII) opened off of portico X.
A small courtyard garden (XX, 5.60 x 3 m) enclosed on its two sides by a colonnade (XXI) brought light and freshness to five rooms (XXII-XXVI). Three trees grow in it today.
Images   Fig. 1: Plan of the Sollertianna Domus. Photo courtesy of Wilhelmina F. Jashemski for Sollertianna Domus.(Rights statement)   Dates the beginning of the IIIrd century.
Bibliography  R. Rebuffat, 1969, Althiburos 2; M. Ennaifer, La cité d’Althiburos et l’édifice des Asclepieia, INA, Tunis, 1976, p. 64-70, plan II.(worldcat) Bullo, S. and F. Ghedini,. Amplissimae atque ornatissimae domus: l&amp;rsquo;edilizia residenziale nelle citta della Tunisia roman, Rome: Edizioni Quasar, 2003, p. 27-29. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 324835
TGN ID 7017557
Contributor Wilhelmina F. Jashemski (WorldCat Identities: lccn-n80037970 Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X
Publication date 13 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
