<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>aedicula lararium on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/aedicula-lararium/</link>
    <description>Recent content in aedicula lararium on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/aedicula-lararium/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Casa del Mobilio Carbonizzato</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tiffany_fong2/casa_del_mobilio_carbonizzato/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tiffany_fong2/casa_del_mobilio_carbonizzato/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Insula V
House 5
Garden Casa del Mobilio Carbonizzato
Keywords  fauces aedicula opus signinum aedicula lararium [lararium]  Garden Description 549.V.5. Visible from the fauces, this little courtyard (a) had an elaborate aedicula shrine which was excavated in 1932-1933. A low double wall with a gutter bordered the courtyard on the west and north sides with a cistern opening located in the center of the west edge of garden. Four small flower beds on the sides and a circular bed in the center had raised borders to retain the water for the plants within, and the remainder of the courtyard was paved in opus signinum. Jashemski commented that the garden had been restored with eleven such small planting beds. The east wall had traces of an animal painting on a blue background by the aedicula lararium. A deer was painted on the right side and several more indistinct animal forms were noted over the lararium. At the south end of this wall there were traces of leaves and a lattice fence suggesting a garden painting may have been located here.
Plans   Plan of Casa dell’Ara Laterizia     Plan of Casa dell’Ara Laterizia   Images   Illustration of Casa dell’Ara Laterizia     Illustration of Casa dell’Ara Laterizia   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1932-1933
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 370-371 Maiuri, Herculaneum,p. 44 Maiuri, Ercolano, pp.260-261 and fig. 203 (plan) on p. 256.  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
