<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/hispania_tarraconensis/soria/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/hispania_tarraconensis/soria/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa los Quintanares</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/hispania_tarraconensis/soria/hispania_villa-quintanares_xw/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/hispania_tarraconensis/soria/hispania_villa-quintanares_xw/</guid>
      <description>Province Soria Soria (Pleiades)
Location Rioseco Di Soria
Rioseco Di Soria (Pleiades)
Location Description This villa is about 600 meters southwest of the town Rioseco di Soria on the right (north) bank of the Sequillo river – here a small stream &amp;ndash; and overlooking its plain. Excavations go back to the early 1970&amp;rsquo;s. In 2007 the site was marked only by mounds of earth over the ruins.
Garden Villa los Quintanares
Keywords  peristyles (Roman courtyards) mosaics (visual works)  Garden Description Built in the second half of the 2nd century CE, it was destroyed during the invasions of the Franks after 256. Following the recovery of the Empire under Claudius II and Aurelian (268 -275), it was rebuilt and enlarged, surviving into the 5th century. Water was brought to the villa by a conduit from 1.5 km further up the Sequillo. The villa is built around two peristyles of similar size. The surrounding rooms featured more than 30 mosaics. The western peristyle (11 x 11 m) was built first, with porticoes on all four sides of its central garden, and, a double gallery on the north side against the summer sun. The later, eastern half had a slightly larger peristyle (12.5 x 21 m), with galleries on three sides of its garden. A large hall extended directly off the fourth side. The peristyle was richly adorned with sculptures, mosaics, and mural paintings.
Maps Plans   Fig.1 Villa los Quintanares, Rioseco de Soria, Soria. Source: Gorges, Planche LIII   Images Bibliography  Teógenes Ortego Frías, La villa romana de Los Quintanares, en el término de Rioseco de Soria, in IX Congreso Nacional de Arqueología. Valladolid. Valladolid, 1965, pp. 341-347. (worldcat) T. Ortego Frías, La villa romana de Los Quintanares, en el término de Rioseco (Soria), in Segovia , Symposium de arqueología romana,. Publicaciones eventuales 27, Universidad de Barcelona, Barcelona, 1977, pp. 285-292. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 614074944
Publication date 20 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>