<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>courtyards on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/courtyards/</link>
    <description>Recent content in courtyards on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/courtyards/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Monumental Tomb Garden Complex</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_labicana/monumental_tomb_garden_complex/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_labicana/monumental_tomb_garden_complex/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Via Labicana Monumental Tomb Garden Complex
Sublocation Via Labicana
Sublocation Description An ancient Roman road connecting Rome and Labicum.
Garden Monumental Tomb Garden Complex
Keywords  courtyards ditches epitaphs funerary buildings sepulchral monuments tombs  Garden Description Two conjoining fragments of a cut marble slab found in the cemetery of Centocelle at the third mile of the Via Labicana, now in the Palazzo Ducale in Urbino, show part of a plan (not drawn to scale) of a large rectangular funerary garden (546 x 524.5 Roman feet, almost exactly 10 iugera, about 5.8 acres, in area) bounded on at least two sides by a private road that branched off near the end of a longer side to intersect a public thoroughfare 1,783 Roman feet (about 1/3rd of a Roman mile) long, beside which several rectangular tomb plots, some marked with border cippi at the (rear?) corners, are marked off in a reed bed. To judge from the stippling on the stone (incompletely marked on the most frequently reproduced drawing of the plan), a second reed bed occupying a triangular plot between the shorter length of private road and a ditch on the opposite side (a subsecivum) extended perpendicularly from the short side of the triangle at the hypotenuse in a narrow band equal in width to that of the reed bed beside the public road and the private road around the perimeter of the enclosure (see the photograph in Luni, fig. 6). De Rossi believed, on no firm evidence, that the property bounded by the public road and reed bed extending off the top of the plan was productive agricultural land attached to the tomb; if so, the territory was perhaps circumscribed by a band of reedbeds and private roads of uniform width bordering the property. But since we know neither the purpose nor the original extent of the plan, the significance of the undifferentiated area outside the enclosed tomb garden remains a matter of speculation: the only features labeled on the plan are the public road, the ditch, and the stippled reedbeds.
The enclosed tomb garden, accessible only by an entranceway at the upper left corner (according to the orientation of the plan) and by a narrow door next to an aedicular structure outside the enclosure in the lower left of the plan, is characterized by a strict formality of design. The garden proper consists of eight rectangular plots marked with stippling, possibly flower beds or lawns, regularly disposed amid perfectly aligned single or triple rows of equidistant circular dots, probably representing trees. A double row of dots separated from the others along the upper perimeter perhaps represents a pergola or elevated walkway. The lower third of the enclosure is dominated by a large tower-tomb monument (perhaps 15 meters square at the base) apparently similar in form to a mausoleum near S. Maria Capua Vetere sketched by Pirro Ligorio and known as “La Conocchia” (“The Distaff”). The tower-tomb sits in the center of a rectangular courtyard bordered by a single row of trees (interrupted by the rear wall of the tomb) that form an ambulatory around the perimeter. The longest side of the courtyard, along the bottom of the plan, gave access to connecting service rooms aligned perpendicularly behind the shorter sides of the courtyard and, in the lower left, a rectangular aedicular building outside the entrance, possibly a funerary shrine or perhaps the custodian’s quarters.
The plan has been dated as early as the Augustan age (by Huelsen, who favored De Rossi’s fanciful attribution of the tomb complex to “Turia”, fragments of whose well known epitaph were found, similarly cut for reuse in covering loculi, in the same cemetery of Centocelle [cf. CIL 6.37053 with 1527, 31670]), but the scale of the complex and the design of the monument seem more compatible with a date later in the first or second century.
The Centocelle plan provides uniquely valuable, if ambiguous, evidence for the arrangement of the planting and the disposition of the monument within a Roman tomb garden (our other surviving plan of a tomb-garden complex [see Claudia Peloris] focuses on the internal articulation of the buildings), but it can hardly be considered typical: not only is the central monument of a form and type not found elsewhere in the region of Rome (the only known parallel is at Capua), but the size of the plot dwarfs all others known in central Italy and is second in area only to the thirty-five iugera (almost twenty acres) of farm land dedicated by a Roman knight at Parma to supporting his funerary celebrations (see C. Praeconius P.f. Ventilius Magnus). If the round dots do indeed represent trees and the stippled areas flower beds, the size of the area laid out primarily, it seems, for amenity (even if the trees bore fruit and the flowers produced garlands and perfume) is far larger than that of other attested funerary gardens in Italy that served primarily a decorative purpose. Productive funerary gardens of comparable and smaller area that we can identify elsewhere in Rome and Italy were normally equipped with work buildings (aedificia) and retail outlets (bars and shops, tabernae) (see vol. 2, XXX). The spaces on the plan flanking the courtyard and identified as storerooms could well have housed farming and gardening tools, but the footprint of the structure in the lower left corner seems ill-suited to the design of a tavern. More probably a collective monument (perhaps of a funerary collegium) than a familial tomb, the complex raises more questions than it resolves about the characteristic form and function of the Roman tomb garden (see no. XXX, funerary collegium of the Cocceii).
Dates The plan was dated as early as the Augustan age, the scale and design seem more later in the frist or second century.
Bibliography   J. Bodel, Roman Tomb Gardens, Cambridge University Press, 2018, pp. 222-224. link
  Ch. Hülsen, Piante iconografiche incise in marmo, BMDAI(R) 5 (1890): 46-63 worldcat
  H. von Hesberg, Römische Grundrissplane auf Marmor, in Bauplanung und Bautheorie der Antike (Berlin 1984) 121-24;worldcat
  M. Luni, Iscrizioni pubbliche ed iscrizioni relative ad edifici, in 1756-1986. Il Museo Archeologico di Urbino I (Urbino 1986) 167 figs. 6-7. worldcat
  R. Volpe,Cento anni a Centocelle: dal volo di Wilbur Wright ai recenti scavi, in Atti del Convegno Nazionale di Archeologia Aerea “100 anni di Archeologia Aerea in Italia&amp;quot; (Roma 15-17 aprile 2009), Archeologia Aerea 4-5, 2010-2011, pp.41-46. Fig. 3 worldcat
  Pleiades ID 811119037
Contributor John Bodel
Publication date 01 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Gardens of Sperlonga. The peristyle garden </title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/sperlonga/the-cryptoporticus-and-the-terrace/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/sperlonga/the-cryptoporticus-and-the-terrace/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Italia Villa Tiberii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Sperlonga
Sublocation Description Sperlonga is a maritime villa built at the end of the Roman Republic. It probably belonged to some very rich piscinarius, one of those extremely wealthy Roman patricians who took delight in creating their own fish ponds. The purpose might have been to always find fresh fish at their disposal, or, at least, so they said. Actually those Tritones piscinarum, as Cicero called them (CIC. Att. 2.1.6; 2.9.1), considered their piscinae more a status symbol than an industrial operation, and cherished their fishes more as pets than as tasty tidbits (VARR. r. r. 3.17.3). Sperlonga, with its lavish decoration and its luxurious setting, was built by one of these tycoons. Built, yes, but by whom? When, in the middle of the last century, this villa was discovered, some scholars decided that it must have been Tiberius. Actually the only connection we could establish between the ancient emperor and this place is the fact that he nearly died while dining in the villa&amp;rsquo;s colossal nymphaeum. At this time he was traveling from Capri to Rome and stopped at Sperlonga to rest. We read that he was there, on a small island set at the center of the fishpond, laying with his friends on mattresses placed around an elegant water triclinium (Fig. 91, A) set on a small island at the center of the fishpond. They were drinking, chatting and enjoying the splendid view of the statuary groups displayed in the nymphaeum when the entrance of the grotto crashed down in a historical landslide reported by both Suetonius (Tib. 39) and Tacitus (ann. 4.59) (Fig. 92). I can&amp;rsquo;t imagine how this unfortunate dinner could place Tiberius as the owner and the creator of the spectacular grotto. However this is what some scholars assert and they still believe it. I can&amp;rsquo;t agree. For one thing we know that Tiberius disapproved of luxury. In Tacitus (TACITUS) we find the transcription of some of his speeches to the senate and we notice how harshly he attacked all the people who built luxurious villas and bought expensive statues to put in them. How could Tiberius censor his fellows countrymen for purchasing some marble copies of goddesses and heroes, while he himself was importing from Greece those monumental Hellenistic groups, and setting them in the seaside grotto of a more than sumptuous maritime residence? It was not logical, and for this reason we feel quite certain that Tiberius had no part in creating the Sperlongan art display. However, are we sure that the villa didn&amp;rsquo;t belong to the imperial praedia? No, we can&amp;rsquo;t even deny this: Sperlonga could have entered Augustus&#39; estate through a legacy. As a matter of fact we know that, on their death, many rich men used to leave their property to the emperor. Some of these tycoons and also some relatives of the Julio-Claudian family could easily have done this. We can&amp;rsquo;t even forget that - as reported by Cicero (CIC. I cent. B.C.) - Philip, Augustus&#39; stepfather, was one of the most important and rich piscinarii of the I cent B.C. Apart from this we can&amp;rsquo;t say anything more.
Garden The villa has three gardens: one peristyle garden, one cryptoporticus and the terrace on the sea, one nymphaeum.
Keywords  villa courtyards terrace gardens  Garden Description These parts of the villa have been relatively spared and they are among the best features of this maritime residence (SALZA PRINA RICOTTI 2002). As a matter of fact, also when the peristyle garden was flourishing, it could never have been as impressive as this imposing cryptoporticus and its underlying terrace (Fig. 93, B), beautiful places to stroll and admire the glorious sunset. The combination of a cryptoporticus and a terrace to create a new kind of garden, was already present in Roman architecture. We can see it depicted in the Pompeian frescoes and we find it in other seaside villas. For instance this kind of open-air arrangement was extensively described in a letter in which Pliny the Younger pointed out the highlights of his cherished Laurentine villa to one of his friend (PLIN. epist. 2.17). In Sperlonga as in Pliny&amp;rsquo;s terrace, a narrow border of flowering plants was set against a low masonry wall, a parapet which was necessary to protect the vegetation from the salty sea breezes (Fig. 94). Today, the fact that bunches of blossoms existed there is confirmed by the presence of a watering system which started from some spring set high on the overhanging hill. We can follow the trace of a groove cut in the rock coming down to the fishpond&amp;rsquo;s northeastern bank. From the piscina side, through a canal (Figs. 91, S; 96), the water was led up to the low parapet of the terrace (Fig. 97), and here, turning at a right angle, it ran all along it. At regular intervals, a series of drain wells helped to draw the water and irrigate the plants. Their presence confirm that a flowerbed existed there and that it was set against the wall.
Plans   the plan of Sperlonga&amp;#39;s Villa.   Images   the general garden plan of Sperlonga.     The landslide.     Cryptoporch and terrace.     Terrace&amp;#39;s parapet.   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography -B. ANDREAE, A. CONTICELLO, H. SCHROTELER, D. WUNDERLICH, Abformung der Polyphemgruppe von Sperlonga, in GfK nach einem neuen Verfahren, Der Präparaator 16, 1-2 (1970), pp. 1-000 worldcat
-F. COARELLI, Sperlonga e Tiberio, DArch 7 (1973), pp. 97-122 worldcat
-A. CONTICELLO, B. ANDREAE, Die Skulpturen von Sperlonga, Antike Plastik 14, Berlin 1974, pp. 000-000 worldcat
-G. JACOPI, L’antro di Tiberio a Sperlonga (Istituto di Studi Romani), Roma 1963 worldcat
-SALZA PRINA RICOTTI, Il gruppo di Polifemo a Sperlonga - Problemi di sistemazione, RendPontAcc 42 (1968-1970), pp. 118-134, tavv. 1-3, figg. 5-9 [worldcat]http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/849270161
-SALZA PRINA RICOTTI, The Importance of Water in Roman Garden Triclinia,in Ancient Roman Villa Gardens (Dumbarton Oaks Research Library and Collection), Dumbarton Oaks 1987, pp. 137-184 [worldcat]http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/715121487
-SALZA PRINA RICOTTI, Sistemazione paesaggistica del fronte a mare e giardini nelle ville marittime di epoca romana, in Giornate di studio in occasione del 250º anniversario degli Scavi di Stabia (in print), pp. 137-169. worldcat
Pleiades ID 433204
TGN ID Contributor EUGENIA SALZA PRINA RICOTTI
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Gardens of Sperlonga. The peristyle garden </title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/sperlonga/the-gardens-of-sperlonga.-the-peristyle-garden/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/sperlonga/the-gardens-of-sperlonga.-the-peristyle-garden/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Italia
Villa Tiberii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Sperlonga
Sublocation Description Sperlonga is a maritime villa built at the end of the Roman Republic. It probably belonged to some very rich piscinarius, one of those extremely wealthy Roman patricians who took delight in creating their own fish ponds. The purpose might have been to always find fresh fish at their disposal, or, at least, so they said. Actually those Tritones piscinarum, as Cicero called them (CIC. Att. 2.1.6; 2.9.1), considered their piscinae more a status symbol than an industrial operation, and cherished their fishes more as pets than as tasty tidbits (VARR. r. r. 3.17.3). Sperlonga, with its lavish decoration and its luxurious setting, was built by one of these tycoons. Built, yes, but by whom? When, in the middle of the last century, this villa was discovered, some scholars decided that it must have been Tiberius. Actually the only connection we could establish between the ancient emperor and this place is the fact that he nearly died while dining in the villa&amp;rsquo;s colossal nymphaeum. At this time he was traveling from Capri to Rome and stopped at Sperlonga to rest. We read that he was there, on a small island set at the center of the fishpond, laying with his friends on mattresses placed around an elegant water triclinium (Fig. 91, A) set on a small island at the center of the fishpond. They were drinking, chatting and enjoying the splendid view of the statuary groups displayed in the nymphaeum when the entrance of the grotto crashed down in a historical landslide reported by both Suetonius (Tib. 39) and Tacitus (ann. 4.59) (Fig. 92). I can&amp;rsquo;t imagine how this unfortunate dinner could place Tiberius as the owner and the creator of the spectacular grotto. However this is what some scholars assert and they still believe it. I can&amp;rsquo;t agree. For one thing we know that Tiberius disapproved of luxury. In Tacitus (TACITUS) we find the transcription of some of his speeches to the senate and we notice how harshly he attacked all the people who built luxurious villas and bought expensive statues to put in them. How could Tiberius censor his fellows countrymen for purchasing some marble copies of goddesses and heroes, while he himself was importing from Greece those monumental Hellenistic groups, and setting them in the seaside grotto of a more than sumptuous maritime residence? It was not logical, and for this reason we feel quite certain that Tiberius had no part in creating the Sperlongan art display. However, are we sure that the villa didn&amp;rsquo;t belong to the imperial praedia? No, we can&amp;rsquo;t even deny this: Sperlonga could have entered Augustus&#39; estate through a legacy. As a matter of fact we know that, on their death, many rich men used to leave their property to the emperor. Some of these tycoons and also some relatives of the Julio-Claudian family could easily have done this. We can&amp;rsquo;t even forget that - as reported by Cicero (CIC. I cent. B.C.) - Philip, Augustus&#39; stepfather, was one of the most important and rich piscinarii of the I cent B.C. Apart from this we can&amp;rsquo;t say anything more.
Garden The villa has three gardens: one peristyle garden, one cryptoporticus and the terrace on the sea, one nymphaeum.
Keywords  villa courtyards peristyles (Roman courtyards)  Garden Description In the villa there are three different garden arrangements (SALZA PRINA RICOTTI 1990). Unluckily (Fig. 93) all its quarters have been badly damaged by a colony of monks who, probably toward 800 A.D., established themselves and their peasants there. All this people excavated a well in the peristyle, created a tank to wash their linens, moved and demolished many of the portico&amp;rsquo;s columns, and set mangers for the animals in the elegant rooms of the villa. Moreover the family of peasants who tilled the monastery&amp;rsquo;s fields divided this lordly mansion in 8 lodgings. Due to these transformations, today it is nearly impossible to find how the original peristyle looked at its heydays. We can only see the bases of the portico&amp;rsquo;s columns and the remains of what probably was a nice nymphaeum, which, set on the north-eastern part of the courtyard (Fig. 93, N), occupied a large hall, 9 m long and 4.5 m wide, with a semicircular absid at the end. A square basin, 2 x 2 m, stood near the entrance. Apart from this there is nothing else left.
Maps Plans   the plan of Sperlonga&amp;#39;s Villa.   Images   the general garden plan of Sperlonga.     The landslide.   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography -B. ANDREAE, A. CONTICELLO, H. SCHROTELER, D. WUNDERLICH, Abformung der Polyphemgruppe von Sperlonga, in GfK nach einem neuen Verfahren, Der Präparaator 16, 1-2 (1970), pp. 1-000 worldcat
-F. COARELLI, Sperlonga e Tiberio, DArch 7 (1973), pp. 97-122 worldcat
-A. CONTICELLO, B. ANDREAE, Die Skulpturen von Sperlonga, Antike Plastik 14, Berlin 1974, pp. 000-000 worldcat
-G. JACOPI, L’antro di Tiberio a Sperlonga (Istituto di Studi Romani), Roma 1963 worldcat
-SALZA PRINA RICOTTI, Il gruppo di Polifemo a Sperlonga - Problemi di sistemazione, RendPontAcc 42 (1968-1970), pp. 118-134, tavv. 1-3, figg. 5-9 [worldcat]http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/849270161
-SALZA PRINA RICOTTI, The Importance of Water in Roman Garden Triclinia,in Ancient Roman Villa Gardens (Dumbarton Oaks Research Library and Collection), Dumbarton Oaks 1987, pp. 137-184 [worldcat]http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/715121487
-SALZA PRINA RICOTTI, Sistemazione paesaggistica del fronte a mare e giardini nelle ville marittime di epoca romana, in Giornate di studio in occasione del 250º anniversario degli Scavi di Stabia (in print), pp. 137-169. worldcat
Pleiades ID 433204
Contributor EUGENIA SALZA PRINA RICOTTI
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Gardens of Sperlonga. The peristyle garden </title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/sperlonga/the-nymphaeum/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/sperlonga/the-nymphaeum/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Italia Villa Tiberii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Sperlonga
Sublocation Description Sperlonga is a maritime villa built at the end of the Roman Republic. It probably belonged to some very rich piscinarius, one of those extremely wealthy Roman patricians who took delight in creating their own fish ponds. The purpose might have been to always find fresh fish at their disposal, or, at least, so they said. Actually those Tritones piscinarum, as Cicero called them (CIC. Att. 2.1.6; 2.9.1), considered their piscinae more a status symbol than an industrial operation, and cherished their fishes more as pets than as tasty tidbits (VARR. r. r. 3.17.3). Sperlonga, with its lavish decoration and its luxurious setting, was built by one of these tycoons. Built, yes, but by whom? When, in the middle of the last century, this villa was discovered, some scholars decided that it must have been Tiberius. Actually the only connection we could establish between the ancient emperor and this place is the fact that he nearly died while dining in the villa&amp;rsquo;s colossal nymphaeum. At this time he was traveling from Capri to Rome and stopped at Sperlonga to rest. We read that he was there, on a small island set at the center of the fishpond, laying with his friends on mattresses placed around an elegant water triclinium (Fig. 91, A) set on a small island at the center of the fishpond. They were drinking, chatting and enjoying the splendid view of the statuary groups displayed in the nymphaeum when the entrance of the grotto crashed down in a historical landslide reported by both Suetonius (Tib. 39) and Tacitus (ann. 4.59) (Fig. 92). I can&amp;rsquo;t imagine how this unfortunate dinner could place Tiberius as the owner and the creator of the spectacular grotto. However this is what some scholars assert and they still believe it. I can&amp;rsquo;t agree. For one thing we know that Tiberius disapproved of luxury. In Tacitus (TACITUS) we find the transcription of some of his speeches to the senate and we notice how harshly he attacked all the people who built luxurious villas and bought expensive statues to put in them. How could Tiberius censor his fellows countrymen for purchasing some marble copies of goddesses and heroes, while he himself was importing from Greece those monumental Hellenistic groups, and setting them in the seaside grotto of a more than sumptuous maritime residence? It was not logical, and for this reason we feel quite certain that Tiberius had no part in creating the Sperlongan art display. However, are we sure that the villa didn&amp;rsquo;t belong to the imperial praedia? No, we can&amp;rsquo;t even deny this: Sperlonga could have entered Augustus&#39; estate through a legacy. As a matter of fact we know that, on their death, many rich men used to leave their property to the emperor. Some of these tycoons and also some relatives of the Julio-Claudian family could easily have done this. We can&amp;rsquo;t even forget that - as reported by Cicero (CIC. I cent. B.C.) - Philip, Augustus&#39; stepfather, was one of the most important and rich piscinarii of the I cent B.C. Apart from this we can&amp;rsquo;t say anything more.
Garden The villa has three gardens: one peristyle garden, one cryptoporticus and the terrace on the sea, one nymphaeum.
Keywords  villa courtyards terrace gardens  Garden Description These parts of the villa have been relatively spared and they are among the best features of this maritime residence (SALZA PRINA RICOTTI 2002). As a matter of fact, also when the peristyle garden was flourishing, it could never have been as impressive as this imposing cryptoporticus and its underlying terrace (Fig. 93, B), beautiful places to stroll and admire the glorious sunset. The combination of a cryptoporticus and a terrace to create a new kind of garden, was already present in Roman architecture. We can see it depicted in the Pompeian frescoes and we find it in other seaside villas. For instance this kind of open-air arrangement was extensively described in a letter in which Pliny the Younger pointed out the highlights of his cherished Laurentine villa to one of his friend (PLIN. epist. 2.17). In Sperlonga as in Pliny&amp;rsquo;s terrace, a narrow border of flowering plants was set against a low masonry wall, a parapet which was necessary to protect the vegetation from the salty sea breezes (Fig. 94). Today, the fact that bunches of blossoms existed there is confirmed by the presence of a watering system which started from some spring set high on the overhanging hill. We can follow the trace of a groove cut in the rock coming down to the fishpond&amp;rsquo;s northeastern bank. From the piscina side, through a canal (Figs. 91, S; 96), the water was led up to the low parapet of the terrace (Fig. 97), and here, turning at a right angle, it ran all along it. At regular intervals, a series of drain wells helped to draw the water and irrigate the plants. Their presence confirm that a flowerbed existed there and that it was set against the wall.
Maps Plans   the plan of Sperlonga&amp;#39;s Villa.   Images   the general garden plan of Sperlonga.     The landslide.     Cryptoporch and terrace.     The irrigation canal.     Terrace&amp;#39;s parapet.     Not founded Wall.   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography -B. ANDREAE, A. CONTICELLO, H. SCHROTELER, D. WUNDERLICH, Abformung der Polyphemgruppe von Sperlonga, in GfK nach einem neuen Verfahren, Der Präparaator 16, 1-2 (1970), pp. 1-000 worldcat
-F. COARELLI, Sperlonga e Tiberio, DArch 7 (1973), pp. 97-122 worldcat
-A. CONTICELLO, B. ANDREAE, Die Skulpturen von Sperlonga, Antike Plastik 14, Berlin 1974, pp. 000-000 worldcat
-G. JACOPI, L’antro di Tiberio a Sperlonga (Istituto di Studi Romani), Roma 1963 worldcat
-SALZA PRINA RICOTTI, Il gruppo di Polifemo a Sperlonga - Problemi di sistemazione, RendPontAcc 42 (1968-1970), pp. 118-134, tavv. 1-3, figg. 5-9 [worldcat]http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/849270161
-SALZA PRINA RICOTTI, The Importance of Water in Roman Garden Triclinia,in Ancient Roman Villa Gardens (Dumbarton Oaks Research Library and Collection), Dumbarton Oaks 1987, pp. 137-184 [worldcat]http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/715121487
-SALZA PRINA RICOTTI, Sistemazione paesaggistica del fronte a mare e giardini nelle ville marittime di epoca romana, in Giornate di studio in occasione del 250º anniversario degli Scavi di Stabia (in print), pp. 137-169. worldcat
Pleiades ID 433204
TGN ID Contributor EUGENIA SALZA PRINA RICOTTI
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>villa at site 10</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/via_gabina/villa_at_site_10/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/via_gabina/villa_at_site_10/</guid>
      <description>Province italia
Location villa at site 10
villa at site 10 (Pleiades)
Sublocation Via Gabina
Sublocation Description For six and a half weeks each summer from 1976 through 1989 Philip Oliver-Smith and the author (both of Rice University) excavated, often to bedrock, two sites fourteen kilometers east of the center of ancient Rome. The team worked from a surface survey conducted by John Ward Perkins and Anne Kahane in 1964, which traced the path of the via Gabina, a road joining Rome and Gabii and supplanted in the 1st century B.C. by the more up-to-date via Praeneste (today the via Praenestina-Fig.1). This same survey established by the collection of surface material thirty-five occupation sites bordering the via Gabina. From these sites we selected three for further investigation, two of which were fully uncovered to reveal the remains of two suburban villas and a late Roman horreum or giant barn. For recording purposes we kept the site designations of Ward Perkins and Kahane. Therefore the discussion here will refer to the villas at Site 10 and Site 11. In 1976, our first season, two trial trenches located structures at Site 13 (another villa?), but no further digging was done here because of problems involving crop rotation (our work was carried out on the land of a still existing farm), time, and money.
Garden Villa at site 10
Keywords  courtyards corridors domus mosaics (visual works) villae suburbanae  Garden Description This large complex villa structure was founded in the Augustan period and was abandoned in the early 3rd century A.D, with evidence from pottery of continued occupation that time. Not even the peristyle core of the plan could be dated to what we call Period 1 (the early occupation period of the Via Gabina sites). Pottery, roof tile stamps, and construction technique (revetted concrete) all give four phases to the villa remains – Augustan, Julio Claudian, Domitianic, and Hadrianic. Reconstructions have been accomplished for all the phases of Period 2, but what interests us here with our focus on gardens is the last or Hadrianic phase (Phase 2 D – Figs. 4 and 5).
The villa had a western enclosed garden area (Figs. 4 and 5) framed on the east by a Doric loggia at least from the time of Domitian. It was then that the owners created an elaborately decorated triclinium (Fig. 4, “35”) overlooking the garden and affording a view back to Rome (thus setting up the contrast of the serenity of the country with the congestion of the city). This was a major addition to the villa/residence. Phase 2D extended the loggia and gave a greater sense of symmetry to the facade. No pool of any depth was possible because the space of the garden overlaid bedrock-cut chambers for the fermentation of wine. Again, there could be no determination of specific planting; not even flotation material was helpful. It was in this western garden area that a huge horreum/barn was constructed in the late 4th or early 5th century C.E.
2.B.	The peristyle garden of Phase 2D (Figs. 4, “B” and 5) dates from the Augustan core of construction (Phase 2A). Overlooking the peristyle center through a wide double doorway was an oecus or reception/dining room (Fig. 4, “2”) with an emblema (59cm x 59cm) at the center of its mosaic floor. The emblema (now on permanent exhibition in the Palazzo Massimo alle Terme di Museo Nazionale Romano) portrays “The Rape of Hylas” (Fig. 6). This depiction was found in situ and oriented to be seen to best advantage from the couch of the padrone or distinguished guest at the back of the room. The location of the couch was indicated in the design of the black and white mosaic surrounding the emblema – unfortunately the Museo Nazionale’s restoration has reversed this relationship by turning the emblema so it would be read in proper perspective from the door of the oecus and not the couch). From bedrock cuts (Fig. 4, “b”) and a nearby well, it would seem the pool and grotto into which Hylas was abducted was emulated in the open area of the peristyle garden. Hence a view from the principal couch first of the graphic depiction of the rape and then a simulation of the place it occurred. The iconography involved in this sequence and subject relates to the agricultural function of the villa itself and its bucolic character. Because the emblema consists of a single tile containing the tiny tesserae (therefore portable) and can be dated to the beginning of the 1st century B.C., it may well be that the emblema was also an embellishment of the Period 1 villa.
These two sites represent a rare glimpse of the transformation of suburban Rome over more than twelve centuries of occupation.
Maps Plans   fig04_recon_phase2d   Images   fig05_recon_phase2d.     The Rape of Hylas.   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  J.B. Ward Perkins and A. Kahane, ed., The Via Gabina, Papers of the British School at Rome, 40 (1972), 91-126. worldcat W. Widrig, Two Sites on the Ancient Via Gabina, British Museum Occasional Paper 24 (1980), 119-141. worldcat W. Widrig, Land Use at the Via Gabina Villas, Ancient Roman Villa Gardens (Dumbarton Oaks, 1987), 225-260. worldcat  Pleiades ID 622606468
TGN ID 7208125
Contributor Walter M Widrig (https://www.worldcat.org/wcidentities/lccn-n2009061717)
Publication date 22 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>villa at site 11</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/via_gabina/villa_at_site_11/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/via_gabina/villa_at_site_11/</guid>
      <description>Province italia
Location villa at site 11
villa at site 11 (Pleiades)
Sublocation Via Gabina
Sublocation Description For six and a half weeks each summer from 1976 through 1989 Philip Oliver-Smith and the author (both of Rice University) excavated, often to bedrock, two sites fourteen kilometers east of the center of ancient Rome. The team worked from a surface survey conducted by John Ward Perkins and Anne Kahane in 1964, which traced the path of the via Gabina, a road joining Rome and Gabii and supplanted in the 1st century B.C. by the more up-to-date via Praeneste (today the via Praenestina-Fig.1). This same survey established by the collection of surface material thirty-five occupation sites bordering the via Gabina. From these sites we selected three for further investigation, two of which were fully uncovered to reveal the remains of two suburban villas and a late Roman horreum or giant barn. For recording purposes we kept the site designations of Ward Perkins and Kahane. Therefore the discussion here will refer to the villas at Site 10 and Site 11. In 1976, our first season, two trial trenches located structures at Site 13 (another villa?), but no further digging was done here because of problems involving crop rotation (our work was carried out on the land of a still existing farm), time, and money.
Garden Villa at site 11
Keywords  barns atrium houses courtyards villae suburbanae  Garden Description This villa at Site 11 was a simple “U” plan farmhouse initiated at the beginning of the 3rd century B.C. (Period 1). In the Augustan Age this farmhouse was transformed into a more luxurious atrium type villa/residence (Period 2 – Figs. 2 and 3). During the reign of Trajan a bath suite was added as well as an outside plunge pool in what seems to have been a western enclosed garden (hortus) from as early as Period 1. Because of the proximity of bedrock and the fact the slight earth cover had been ploughed for centuries, any evidence of what might have been planted in the garden had long since been destroyed. We know, however, that there must have been surrounding olive groves from the press facilities of the villa, also dating from the time of Trajan. All was abandoned in the second or third decade of the 3rd century of the Christian Era.
Maps Plans   Plan at the Villa at site 11.   Images   fig03_the axon of the Villa at site 11.   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  J.B. Ward Perkins and A. Kahane, ed., The Via Gabina, Papers of the British School at Rome, 40 (1972), 91-126. worldcat W. Widrig, Two Sites on the Ancient Via Gabina, British Museum Occasional Paper 24 (1980), 119-141. worldcat W. Widrig, Land Use at the Via Gabina Villas, Ancient Roman Villa Gardens (Dumbarton Oaks, 1987), 225-260. worldcat  Pleiades ID 622606468
TGN ID 7208125
Contributor Walter M Widrig (https://www.worldcat.org/wcidentities/lccn-n2009061717)
Publication date 22 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Terrace House 2</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/shamika_ghate/7._ephesos_terrace_house/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/shamika_ghate/7._ephesos_terrace_house/</guid>
      <description>Province Asia Asia (Pleiades)
Province description The region of what is now modern Turkey became a part of the Roman Empire in 133 B.C. when king Attalos III of Pergamum bequeathed his kingdom to the Roman people. The province included the heartland of the Pergamene kingdom as well as the territories of Mysia, Lydia, Ionia, Caria, western Phrygia and the eastern Aegean islands. Under Augustus in 27 B.C. Asia was declared a senatorial province and the governance of a proconsul. The capital of the province was Ephesos, although Pergamon may have fulfilled this role initially. Under Diocletian (284-305 A.D.) the province was subdivided into smaller administrative units: Hellespontus, Asia, Lydia, Caria, Phrygia I and Phrygia II. Due to its excellent harbors on the west coast and its many navigable rivers, Asia’s water-borne trade with the rest of the Mediterranean flourished. In the second century A.D. Asia experienced great prosperity, to which the growth and architectural aggrandizement of many of its cities attest. In the area of Kibyra, bordering the regions of Lycia, Caria, Phrygia and Pisidia, numerous inscriptions refer to the large imperial estates of Roman families. Woolen textiles, marble, and timber constituted a significant part of the commodities exported from the province.
While the Romans might have looked to the Greeks for inspiration in philosophy, architecture, sculpture, and the fine arts, the non-Greek peoples of the eastern Mediterranean are their inspiration for luxury, fine-living, and the status conferred by displays of individual wealth (Athenaeus Deip. XV.690). Asia was a center for such splendor, first in the kingdoms of Lydia, Phrygia, and Lycia, and then continued by the Persian satraps, and later the Hellenistic kings. The Persian paradeisos is particularly well-attested in literature referencing Asia. That these gardens are known primarily from Roman-period literary sources indicates their continuing influence. For example, long after the gold of Lydia’s Pactolus River had disappeared, Lydia remained a literary topos, not only for copious wealth, but for a life of luxury set in a landscape of natural abundance. Athenaeus (Deipnosophistae 12.515d-f) wrote in the second century A.D. that
&amp;ldquo;The Lydians in their luxury planned parks and made them like gardens and so kept in the shade. For they thought it more dainty not to have the sun’s rays touch them at all…&amp;rdquo;
Other districts of Asia captured the Roman imagination: Pliny the Elder writes of an ancient plane tree (Sycamorus orientalis) in Lycia with a girth of sufficient circumference to house a grotto in its hollow trunk, ornamented with pumice and moss with provisions for 18 people to dine there (Pliny HN 12.9).
The paradeisoi of the Persian satraps are of particular influence on the introduction of horti and gardens of Rome. The paradeisos, from the Persian, paira daeza, or “enclosed place,” is a term that had evolved by the Hellenistic period to mean a large enclosed park with luxurious gardens as well as orchards, collections of trees, crops, and hunting areas (see Sardis below). It was at Sardis that the Greek Lysander visited Cyrus the Younger, a visit recorded by Clearchus and retold by Xenophon. It is an essential moment in garden history recounted for the Romans by Cicero, De Senectute. 17.59. These paradeisoi, in the sense of luxurious orchards, are said by the Romans to have been brought to Greece by Kimon (Aristot. apud Plut. Cim. 10; comp. Cic. de Off. 2.18Plutarch), and were adopted by Hellenistic kings throughout Greece and southern Italy during the late Hellenistic period. The hunting parks at Daskyleion and Celenae are also vividly described by Xenophon (See Anabasis 1.2.7, 2.4.14 and Oeconomicus 4.13). Xenophon also describes how paradeisoi were occupied or cut down by armies during the fourth and third centuries BC. Appreciation for these parks apparently continued, and Seleucus of Syria took over the royal paradeisos at Sardis (Plutarch, Demetrios 50.6). Years of instability followed, so it is difficult to know what the Romans themselves thought of paradeisoi in Asia in the second and first centuries B.C. Notable examples of paradeisoi, in some form, may have been visible to Romans visiting Asia, as well. For example, the Mausoleum at Halicarnassus is now thought by its excavators to have been set in a grove or park.
Thus, the paradeisos, the alsos, the gymnasium, and the quadriporticus are not forms the Romans suddenly “discovered.” They had had a long influence and were integrated into the Hellenistic architectural forms of the Italic landscape. In the second century B.C., however, when the Roman generals began to define themselves as rulers of an empire, they turned directly to the palaces and paradeisoi of the Hellenistic monarchs to establish their power, to display spoils of war, and to create the luxurious setting for life in Rome. They further adapted the evolving quadriporticus form for display to the public Despite the importance of Asia Minor in the history of the Roman landscape, archaeological evidence is scant. The excavators contacted for this essay indicated that parks, gardens, and other planted areas have yet to become a subject of research design for the region and finds appear to be few—primarily inscriptions and wall paintings. Most of the smaller domestic courtyards—often the most manageable to investigate - are paved. The larger palaestrae, gymnasia, and enclosed open spaces have not been investigated for landscape architectural and planting features, although recently an important campaign of work in the South Agora at Aphrodisias is setting an important precedent (see below). This catalog includes areas with dirt and incomplete paved surfaces, and notes sites where the excavators have some level of optimism about fruitful future study. The subject of designed landscapes, gardens, and planted areas in Asia Minor awaits archaeological investigation.
Location EPHESOS (Efes, Turkey) (Pleiades)
Location Description Remains of gardens have yet to be discovered in this city, but an appreciation for garden culture is seen in the Terrace Houses, dating to the second and third centuries A.D., where wall paintings not only depict gardens, but use garden images to create the illustionistic experience of being in the space of garden.
House Terrace House 2
Keywords  courtyard dado peristyle (Roman courtyards) medallion (ornament areas) putto  House Description The most striking remains are in Terrace House 2, in Room 20 (Residence 4), excavated by H. Vetters between 1967-1983. Here, in a space originally designed as a courtyard, the walls are decorated with an elaborate garden scene. Much of the painting is covered by a later painting of marble panels, but on the north and west walls the garden scene has been partially revealed (Figs. 1 and 2). The viewer within the room looks out past a real marble dado on top of which is an illusionistic marble fence with an unusual egg and dart design along the top. Beyond is a garden scene, similar to those seen in Pompeii or the famous garden scene of Livia at Prima Porta. The scene is filled with luxuriant foliage, out of which apple trees rise up against the blue sky bearing apples or quinces. A bird flies over a young juniper or cypress. The illusion of the garden continues without a break around the corners. It allows the viewers to feel present in a garden, while knowing they are in a room looking out at it. The later painting completely destroys both the illusion and any recollection that the space had formerly been an open courtyard.
In the central peristyle of Residence 2 of Terrace House 2, Vetters uncovered a late Imperial mosaic of Dionysius and Ariadne in a niche. The peristyle itself is a paved courtyard, but the mosaic offers the viewer a rich view of a paradisiacal vineyard. A lunette features a mosaic of two peacocks holding a garland over a basket or urn of grapes and fruits, with white geese to each side standing on a green lawn with roses and lilies (Fig. 3). The ceiling of the niche features Dionysias and Ariadne in a central medallion set into a panel of blue, against which is arrayed a vine laden with grapes and doves (Fig. 4). In the upper corner, the vine emerges from the ground, and along the base of the wall, a winged putto leads two harnessed leopards or panthers. The opposite side is not preserved.
Just off the peristyle in Room 17, the walls feature a variety of birds, individually portrayed on white backgrounds either sitting on branches or standing among small plants. In Room 24, the landscape themes continue with a painting of stags in woodland, apparently being chased by a putto. Only a small fragment remains. In Room 14, mythological scenes of Achilles and Skyros (west wall) and Achilles and Priam (south wall) are set in a landscape of rocks and trees (Fig. 6). Bird and plant themes are represented through this house.
Maps Plans   Plan of Ephesos terrace house 2   Images   Garden painting in the North-West corner of the peristyle     Detail of the garden painting in the North-West corner of the peristyle, Photo by N. Blanc     Painting as discovered on the west wall of the terrace house 2     Painting as discovered on the North wall of the terrace house 2   Dates 1st-3rd c. CE
Bibliography  Forschungen in Ephesos Vol. VIII/1, Figs. 207-219 (worldcat) Forschungen in Ephesos Vol. VIII/2 Figs. 109-130 (worldcat) W. Jobst, Romische Mosaiken aus Ephesos I: Die Hanghauser des Embolos,Vienna, 1977 (worldcat) C. Kearns, “Visual representations of gardens: diachronic perspectives on the art of landscape,” In ed. K. Gleason, Cultural History of Gardens, London. 2013. pp. 164-165. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 599612
TGN ID 7002358
Contributor Kathryn Gleason (ORCID: 0000-0001-6260-8378)
Publication date 22 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural villa at Voerendaal</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/voerendaal/voerendaal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:58:07 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/voerendaal/voerendaal/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Province Description Location Voerendaal
Voerendaal (Pleiades)
Garden Rural villa at Voerendaal
Keywords  villae rusticae porticoes piscinae hedges courtyards  Garden Description The stone-built structures of this villa rustica near the Meuse river, the largest excavated thus far in the Netherlands, were erected in the early 2nd century and repeatedly enlarged until the abandonment of the farm around 300 A.D. (Plan 1). The total area of the farm, including the cultivated land, is calculated to have been ca. 150 hectares. The main residence (A on plan) lay in the northern half of the complex which measured 167 x 214 m. (3.5 hectares) in size. The porticoed facade in its final state was 190 m. long.
In front of the house to the south was a large area (17 x 37 m.), enclosed by a stone wall on two sides and villa porticoes on the other sides. This has been interpreted as a formal garden (G on plan) with low plantings, hedges and a pool (P on plan; Image 1 [NO IMAGE INCLUDED]). The main road leading from the gate in the south to the house in the north cut through this enclosed area. The excavators postulate a vegetable garden behind the house for easy, daily access. The boundaries of the farm complex were planted with a row of trees or a hedge, the planting pits of which had survived. The many carbonized grains of wheat and chaff found in and around a large building in the northeastern part of the courtyard enclosure suggest that wheat grown in the fields of the farm was processed here. The main crop at Voerendaal was spelt; very little emmer or bread wheat was present in the organic remains.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the rural villa with a possible walled garden (G) and its pool (P) south of the house (A). Hedges (rows of dots) enclosed the farmyard. Adapted from Willems 1992, Fig. 307. (Rights statement).   Images Dates Early second century CE to ca. 300 CE
Bibliography  W.J.H. Willems, &amp;ldquo;Die kaiserzeitliche Villa von Voerendaal&amp;rdquo;, in Spurensicherung. Archäologische Denkmalpflege in der Euregio Maas-Rhein, Mainz, 1992, pp. 526-534, figs. 307-308. worldcat P. Van Ossel, Établissements ruraux de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquité tardive dans le nord de la Gaule, Paris, 1992, pp. 363-365, fig. 155. worldcat  Pleiades ID 109442
TGN ID 7272601
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Houses of Insula 7 in Colonia Ulpia Traiana</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/colonia_ulpia_xanten/colonia_xanten_insula7/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/colonia_ulpia_xanten/colonia_xanten_insula7/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Xanten
Xanten (Pleiades)
Sublocation Industrial quarter
Sublocation Description This insula southeast of the forum is commonly referred to as an industrial quarter (Plan 1). It was divided into several long, narrow plots on which were houses, shops and workshops.
Garden The houses of Insula 7 in Colonia Ulpia Traiana (Xanten)
Keywords  insulae kitchen gardens courtyards  Garden Description Between the buildings were open areas, some paved and equipped with ovens and pottery kilns, wells and latrines, others unpaved. Some of the small courtyards have been reconstructed by the excavators as kitchen gardens and shrine gardens (Image 1). Organic material from a well in this insula included the remains of peas, beans, lentils, apples, pears and herbs. These fruits and vegetables may have grown in kitchen gardens in the insula, but they may, on the other hand, have been brought into the city from nearby farms.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the houses in *Insula* 7 with paved (stippled) and unpaved courtyards. The black dots are wells. Adapted from Precht and Rüger 1991. Rights statement.   Images   Image 1. Model of the houses in *Insula* 7 with courtyard garden. Photo courtesy of M. Carroll.   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  H.G. Horn, ed., Die Römer in Nordrhein-Westfalen, Stuttgart, 1987, pp. 634-636, fig. 542 (incorrectly labeled as Insula 26). worldcat G. Precht and C.B. Rüger, Archaologischer Stadtplan. Colonia Ulpia Traiana, Cologne, 1991. worldcat  Pleiades ID 108896
TGN ID 7208125
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
