<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>courtyards on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/courtyards/</link>
    <description>Recent content in courtyards on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:58:07 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/courtyards/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural villa at Voerendaal</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/voerendaal/voerendaal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:58:07 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/voerendaal/voerendaal/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Province Description Location Voerendaal
Voerendaal (Pleiades)
Garden Rural villa at Voerendaal
Keywords  villae rusticae porticoes piscinae hedges courtyards  Garden Description The stone-built structures of this villa rustica near the Meuse river, the largest excavated thus far in the Netherlands, were erected in the early 2nd century and repeatedly enlarged until the abandonment of the farm around 300 A.D. (Plan 1). The total area of the farm, including the cultivated land, is calculated to have been ca. 150 hectares. The main residence (A on plan) lay in the northern half of the complex which measured 167 x 214 m. (3.5 hectares) in size. The porticoed facade in its final state was 190 m. long.
In front of the house to the south was a large area (17 x 37 m.), enclosed by a stone wall on two sides and villa porticoes on the other sides. This has been interpreted as a formal garden (G on plan) with low plantings, hedges and a pool (P on plan; Image 1 [NO IMAGE INCLUDED]). The main road leading from the gate in the south to the house in the north cut through this enclosed area. The excavators postulate a vegetable garden behind the house for easy, daily access. The boundaries of the farm complex were planted with a row of trees or a hedge, the planting pits of which had survived. The many carbonized grains of wheat and chaff found in and around a large building in the northeastern part of the courtyard enclosure suggest that wheat grown in the fields of the farm was processed here. The main crop at Voerendaal was spelt; very little emmer or bread wheat was present in the organic remains.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the rural villa with a possible walled garden (G) and its pool (P) south of the house (A). Hedges (rows of dots) enclosed the farmyard. Adapted from Willems 1992, Fig. 307. (Rights statement).   Images Dates Early second century CE to ca. 300 CE
Bibliography  W.J.H. Willems, &amp;ldquo;Die kaiserzeitliche Villa von Voerendaal&amp;rdquo;, in Spurensicherung. Archäologische Denkmalpflege in der Euregio Maas-Rhein, Mainz, 1992, pp. 526-534, figs. 307-308. worldcat P. Van Ossel, Établissements ruraux de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquité tardive dans le nord de la Gaule, Paris, 1992, pp. 363-365, fig. 155. worldcat  Pleiades ID 109442
TGN ID 7272601
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Houses of Insula 7 in Colonia Ulpia Traiana</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/colonia_ulpia_xanten/colonia_xanten_insula7/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/colonia_ulpia_xanten/colonia_xanten_insula7/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Xanten
Xanten (Pleiades)
Sublocation Industrial quarter
Sublocation Description This insula southeast of the forum is commonly referred to as an industrial quarter (Plan 1). It was divided into several long, narrow plots on which were houses, shops and workshops.
Garden The houses of Insula 7 in Colonia Ulpia Traiana (Xanten)
Keywords  insulae kitchen gardens courtyards  Garden Description Between the buildings were open areas, some paved and equipped with ovens and pottery kilns, wells and latrines, others unpaved. Some of the small courtyards have been reconstructed by the excavators as kitchen gardens and shrine gardens (Image 1). Organic material from a well in this insula included the remains of peas, beans, lentils, apples, pears and herbs. These fruits and vegetables may have grown in kitchen gardens in the insula, but they may, on the other hand, have been brought into the city from nearby farms.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the houses in *Insula* 7 with paved (stippled) and unpaved courtyards. The black dots are wells. Adapted from Precht and Rüger 1991. Rights statement.   Images   Image 1. Model of the houses in *Insula* 7 with courtyard garden. Photo courtesy of M. Carroll.   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  H.G. Horn, ed., Die Römer in Nordrhein-Westfalen, Stuttgart, 1987, pp. 634-636, fig. 542 (incorrectly labeled as Insula 26). worldcat G. Precht and C.B. Rüger, Archaologischer Stadtplan. Colonia Ulpia Traiana, Cologne, 1991. worldcat  Pleiades ID 108896
TGN ID 7208125
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>