<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/judaea/ein_gedi/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/judaea/ein_gedi/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Balsam Groves</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/judaea/ein_gedi/balsam_groves/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/judaea/ein_gedi/balsam_groves/</guid>
      <description>Province Judaea
Iudaea (province) (Pleiades)
Province Description Judaea, the Roman province, included parts of the areas of the Hasmonean and Herodium kingdoms, notably Biblical Judah, Samaria, and Edom. Its capital was Caesarea Maritima. Roman influence in the region began in 63 CE, when the Roman general Pompey the Great took over Syria from Mithridates and, coming into Jerusalem, occupied the Second Temple. Pompey appointed Antipater, the father of Herod, as the first Roman Procurator. Later these ties allowed Herod to seek backing from Rome against the Hasmoneans in 40 BCE, when the senate recognized him as “king of the Jews.” His territories came to include the regions of Galilee, Gaulanitis (the Golan),Peraea and the Decapolis. Herod balanced his allegiance to Rome with the independence of his kingdom, often employing architectural projects to express his ambitions and control of nature to express his capacity to rule . His many palaces, placed strategically around the kingdom, feature dramatically designed landscapes and gardens. Upon his death, his heirs were unable to maintain order and Judea was annexed to Syria in 6 CE, although it was assigned its own procurator. By the time of Trajan, Judea was reduced in size and the Herodian palaces abandoned, preserving them over the millennia for archaeologists. Hadrian renamed the province Syria Palaestina after the Bar Kochba revolts (132-135) provoked him to erase the name of Judea.
The period for which we have the richest evidence of a garden culture in this region is during the reign of Herod the Great. A client king of Rome, Herod’s relationships with Mark Antony, Cleopatra, Augustus and Marcus Agrippa and other officials have been preserved in the texts of Flavius Josephus. These constitute a rare record of interactions between Rome and its territories, and provide a valuable context for understanding the trends of design in the early imperial period. The proximity of Judea to Alexandria, whose palaces and gardens lie beneath the modern city and its harbors, may also provide a suggestion of the late Hellenistic garden culture that Romans emulated. Evidence of gardens in the Hasmonean winter palaces at Jericho and the palaces of Hyracanus the Tobiad on the other side of the Jordan Valley provide rare cases where texts can illuminate archaeological evidence. These gardens require further investigation and both are threatened by local development. This geography of Judaea comprises a wide variety of biomes, from richly watered plains of the Galilee and the Jordan, to the semi arid Judean Hills, the humid, fertile coastal plain of the Mediterranean, and the deserts of the Dead Sea valley and the Negev.
Location Ein Gedi
Ein Gedi (Pleiades)
Location Description The balsam groves of the Dead Sea region have been famous since the queen of Sheba (Egypt and Ethiopia) reputedly brought balsam as a gift to King Solomon (1 Kings 10:10; Josephus Ant.8. 6, 5-6.). From the time of Theophrastus, Jericho and Ein Gedi near the Dead Sea were renowned for their watered palm and balsam plantations (paradeisoi), described by Diodorus Siculus, Varro, Strabo, Virgil, Horace, Pausanias, Pliny the Elder, Solinus and Galen. They are described in some detail by Josephus (Antiquitates Judaeorum 14.54), who notes their water supply was destroyed during the Jewish Revolt. The balsam, however, is regarded as extinct and has not been identified archaeobotanically.
Itzar Hirshfeld identified a possible balsam terrace near the oasis of Ein Gedi, along the ancient road that links the palaces at Jericho with the fortress palace at Masada. Further studies were carried out by Guy Stibbel.
The only possible archaeobotanical evidence found to date for the plant itself comes from a cave at Qumran. Porath and Arubas report that a small Herodian-period juglet wrapped in palm fibers and carefully hidden in the rocks contains oil that does not correspond with any known modern oil and is consistent with ancient descriptions of balsam but analysis on the contents was less than conclusive. Date palm remains, by contrast, are commonly seen in the carbonized plant remains found in Jericho, Wadi Qelt, Masada,Kumran, and other excavations in the valley. In an astonishing recent development, botanist Elaine Solowey was able to use growth hormones to activate three dessicated date pits from excavated contexts at Masada. These were C14 dated to the Roman period. One seed successfully grew into a male palm. Subsequent work with desiccated pits from the Kumran area have produced female plants. (Sallon et al. 2020)
Garden Agriculture
Keywords  orchards  Dates 6-135 CE
Bibliography  Patrich, J.,“A Juglet Containing Balsam Oil (?) from a Cave near Qumran,” Israel Exploration Journal 39 (1989):43-49 (worldcat) Sallon, S., Cherif, E., Chabrillange, N., Solowey, E., Gros-Balthazard, M., Ivorra, S., &amp;amp; Aberlenc, F. (2020). Origins and insights into the historic Judean date palm based on genetic analysis of germinated ancient seeds and morphometric studies. Science advances, 6(6), eaax0384. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 196074068
TGN ID 7001389
Contributor Kathryn L. Gleason ORCID: 0000-0001-6260-8378 \
Publication date 09 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>