<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>nymphaea on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/nymphaea/</link>
    <description>Recent content in nymphaea on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 17:46:47 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/nymphaea/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Oberentfelden</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/oberentfelden/oberentfelden_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 17:46:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/oberentfelden/oberentfelden_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Province Description Location Oberentfelden
Oberentfelden (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Oberentfelden
Keywords archaeological garden
bathhouses (water recreation structures)
kitchen gardens
nymphaea (garden structures)
peristyles (columnades)
rural villas
villae rusticae
Garden Description The enclosed area of this villa rustica was 160 meters wide and at least 460 meters long; the eastern limits of the complex have not yet been found. The main residence and bath complex (A and B in Fig. 1), dating to the beginning of the 2nd century, stood on sloping land eight meters higher than the rest of the farmyard. At the eastern end of the service area (pars rustica) was a large peristyle building with a nymphaeum at the western end (D in Fig. 1). The open courtyard within this peristyle may have been a garden. Small kitchen gardens have been reconstructed between the various outbuildings and smaller houses (C in Fig. 1) in the pars rustica. Gardens here are possible, but it remains a matter of speculation whether these areas were actually planted.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the rural villa (A) with a bath (B), a nymphaeum (D) and various outbuildings and houses (C). Plan adapted from Drack and Fellmann 1988, fig. 418.   Images Dates 2nd century
Bibliography  W. Drack and R. Fellmann, Die Römer in der Schweiz, Stuttgart, 1988, pp. 457-459, fig. 418. (worldcat) R. Fellmann, La Suisse gallo-romaine. Cinq siècles d’histoire, Lausanne, 1992, pp. 152, 154, fig. 105. (worldcat) M. Carroll, Romans, Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 75, fig. 34. (worldcat)  Periodo ID Pleiades ID 177596
TGN ID 8703779
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 17 July 2020
Related articles </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>