<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/hispania_baetica/alameda/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2020 21:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/hispania_baetica/alameda/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Funerary Grove of T. Aemilius Vetus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/hispania_baetica/alameda/funerary_grove_of_t.aemilius_vetus-/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2020 21:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/hispania_baetica/alameda/funerary_grove_of_t.aemilius_vetus-/</guid>
      <description>Province Hispania Baetica
Location Alameda
Alameda (Pleiades)
Location Description Ruins of large Roman baths, now surrounded by an interpretive center, and numerous finds of Roman coins and pottery fragments make clear that there was a considerable Roman town here with its center in the heart of the modern town. Its name, however, has not been determined for certain. The villa described below is near the modern town cemetery. It seems, however, that the villa was reburied for its protection.
Garden Funerary Grove of T. Aemilius Vetus
Keywords Garden Description A grey limestone block found in 1975 at La Alameda, between Toledo and Cordova, and now preserved in the Museo Provinciale di Ciuidad Real, records the dedication of a funerary grove (lucus) by Minicia Saturnina for her son T. Aemilius Vetus, who died at age thirty-five sometime in the late first or early second century AD.
Maps Images Datess unspecified
Bibliography  L. Chioffi,&amp;ldquo;Sui luci sepolcrali,&amp;rdquo; Libitina e dintorni (Atti del XI Rencontre franco-italienne sur l’épigraphie) (Libitina 3), S. Panciera, ed. (Rome 2004) 22 and 27 n.9. (worldcat) Géza Alföldy, “Epigraphica Hispanica IX,” Zeitschrift für Papyrologie und Epigraphik 67, 1987, 235-36, Tav. VI, 5.(jstore) &amp;ldquo;Espagne Citérieure,&amp;rdquo; L&amp;rsquo;Année épigraphique Année 1987 (1990), 685. (jstore)  Pleiades ID 270382
270382
TGN ID 1061700
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 24 Sept 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa del Cortijo de los Vila</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/hispania_baetica/alameda/vila_del_cortijo_de_los_vila/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2020 13:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/hispania_baetica/alameda/vila_del_cortijo_de_los_vila/</guid>
      <description>Province Hispania Baetica
Location Alameda
Alameda (Pleiades)
Location Description Ruins of large Roman baths, now surrounded by an interpretive center, and numerous finds of Roman coins and pottery fragments make clear that there was a considerable Roman town here with its center in the heart of the modern town. Its name, however, has not been determined for certain. The villa described below is near the modern town cemetery. It seems, however, that the villa was reburied for its protection.
Garden Villa del Cortijo de los Vila
Keywords  fountains mosaics (visual works) peristyles (columnades) statuettes (free-standing sculpture)  Garden Description Excavations in 1985 and 1986 brought to light a villa dating to the end of the third or beginning of the fourth century AD. The villa is also known as the “Finca del Moral.” Measures were taken to preserve the fine mosaics. In the peristyle of the villa there was a rectangular garden area [A] with rounded corners and semicircles on the four sides. At its center is a square brick structure faced with marble, which was probably a fountain. Also found in the villa was a statuette of Priapus, who was often associated with gardens, and whose cult images often appeared in them. The figure, placed in the center of the garden and dating from the end of the second century, is adorned with bunches of grapes, surrounded by flowers, birds and a pair of sandals.
Maps Images Dates unspecified
Bibliography  F. Almohalla, M. J. Botos,Villa romana del cortijo de los Vila (Alameda), (Malaga 1989), (unpublished memorandum deposited with the Diputacion de Malaga, Area de Urbanismo) J. M. Blázquez,&amp;lsquo;Los jardines en la Hispania Romana,&amp;rsquo; Historia de los Parques y Jardines en España, C. Añón Feliu, ed. (Madrid 2001) 29. (worldcat) Mª L. Loza Azuaga,&amp;lsquo;La escultura de fuentes en Hispania: ejemplos de la Bética,&#39;Actas de la I Reunión sobre escultura romana en Hispania, T. Nogales Basarrate, ed. (Mérida 1993) 103. (worldcat) E. Arcos von Haartman, A. Alvarez Rubiera, ‘Análisis de la naturaleza, estructura y tecnología del conjunto de mosaicos de la villa romana del Cortijo Auta (Riogordo), villa romana del Cortijo Vila (Alameda) y del ninfeo romano de Carnicería de los Moros (Antequera),’ Mainake No. 10, (Malaga 1988), 159-80. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 521700444
521700444
TGN ID 1061700
Contributor (AUTHOR_ID) Publication date 24 Sept 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
