<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/saint-emilion_gironde/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:07:01 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/saint-emilion_gironde/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa du Palat, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/saint-emilion_gironde/gallia-aquitania_villa-du-palat_j.zhou/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:07:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/saint-emilion_gironde/gallia-aquitania_villa-du-palat_j.zhou/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_Aquitania Gallia_Aquitania (Pleiades)
Province Description A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location Saint-Emilion
Saint-Emilion, Gironde (Pleiades)
House Villa du Palat
House Description About half a kilometer southeast of the village of Saint-Emilion, on the west bank of the wet-weather branch La Fongaban, and about half way down the slope below plateau of the village, this aristocratic residence descended over several levels. It was reported in 1935, excavated by M. Gauthier in 1969-71 and then by C. Balmelle between 1981 and 1988.
The villa probably had a U shape, with the base of the U running southwest-to-northeast and the wings at either end extending to the southeast, probably crossing the branch. The interior of U was undoubtedly a garden. Only the southeast façade of the base of U has been uncovered; the rest of the construction continues under the road and on beyond in the vineyard on the other side. In the 17 known rooms, this sumptuous villa of late antiquity has no less than nine mosaic pavements of high quality. On the basis of stylistic criteria and ancient furnishings, its homogeneous construction is dated to the beginning of the fifth century – too late to have been built by Ausonius.
Garden Keywords  mosaics (visual works) colonnades porticoes fountains gutters (building drainage components) impluvia  Garden Description Across the 90-meter façade on the inside of the U ran a colonnade of marble Corinthian columns; between the colonnade and the rooms of the base wing was a portico 3.9 meters wide. In the center of this wing, a grand reception room opened for its full length (9.46 m) onto the portico and the garden on beyond. Its entrance from the portico was enlivened by a fountain with an octagonal pool lined with blue marble and decorated with a bottom mosaic with fish. A 13-centimeter wide gutter with a marble bottom ran around the outside of the pool, doubtless to catch the overflow. In the center, there was a marble footing with an octagonal base that no doubt supported a basin for the fountain that is now lost. On the threshold between the fountain and the portico ran a long, narrow mosaic showing a garland of laurel against a black background and sown with stylized leaves, rosettes, and lilies. In the middle, a crown of laurel surrounds a lily, and the lilies to either side open towards this central lily. A geometric carpet mosaic of the same width as the room seems to extend the room into the portico, for the floor of the portico on either side of this central room was a simple opus signinum.
In the presumed garden framed by the U-shaped gallery was an rectangular pool (60.3 x 6.93 m) with apses at either end. This pool is virtually the only thing visible at the site today. Its long axis ran parallel to the façade, and it was centered on reception room, so that it underscored nicely the lines of the façade. The sides were covered by a layer of rose-colored hydraulic mortar and topped by a parapet of limestone rounded above. The bottom was covered with reddish to yellowish brick tiles, giving a pleasant unity to the structure. The apses at either end were slightly narrower than the pool. The one on the south end was also paved with tile.
The pool was filled in at the end of the occupation of the house. Numerous fragments of polychrome mosaic, sometimes figured, were discovered in the fill. Also, some reworking of the apses has been observed, in both cases around the opening of the apse, but the purpose of the changes was unclear.
Plans   Fig. 1: Figure. 1. Plan of the Villa du Palat.     Fig. 2: Topographic plan of the situation of Saint-Emilion, drawing by M. -P. R., based on the the 1/25000e map of the IGN, 1636 Est.     Fig. 3: Plan of the archaeological remains before 1969, according to Oüy-Vernazobres, 1937.     Fig. 4: Plan of the villa after the excavations of 1981-87, by M.-P. R. after R. Monturet. According to Balmelle, Archéologie en Aquitaine, 1987, 44, fig.29.   Dates Unspecified
Excavation Dates 1969CE-1971CE，1981CE-1988CE
Bibliography  H. Sion, CAG 33/1, La Gironde, n° 286, pp. 197-207, plan fig. 120 p. 228. (worldcat) Catherine Balmelle, Les demeures aristocratiques d&amp;rsquo;Aquitaine, societe et culture de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquite tardive dans le sou-ouest de la Gaule, Ausonius, supple. d&amp;rsquo;Aquitania 10, Bordeaux 2001, p. 141-142 ; 403-405, 452 (with a bibliography of previous works). (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 140559
TGN ID Contributor Clopper Almon
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>