<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/xue_xia/pupput/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 10:39:31 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/xue_xia/pupput/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>House of the Black and White Triclinium (Maison du triclinium en noir et blanc)</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/xue_xia/pupput/house_of_the_black_and_white_triclinium/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/xue_xia/pupput/house_of_the_black_and_white_triclinium/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa Proconsularis Africa proconsularis (Pleiades)
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location Pupput
Pupput (Pleiades)
Location Description Pupput is located about three km to the northwest of Hammamed. Two inscriptions inform the designated title of the city, which became a colony (Colonia Aurelia Commoda Pia Felix Augusta Pupput) under the reign of Commodus. The city benefited from a strategic location at the crossroads linking Clupea to Thhuburbo and Carthage to Hadrumetum. Large residential quarters with houses and baths were excavated as well as a large necropolis.
Garden House of the Black and White Triclinium (Maison du triclinium en noir et blanc)
Keywords  peristyles (columnades) peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes basins (vessels) triclinia  Garden Description The house is laid out around a square shaped peristyle garden. Between the columns runs a low wall (0.30m) that separates the porticoes from the garden. There was a semicircular basin in the N facing the triclinium (Plan view, Fig.1). The house is dated from the II-III c.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the House of the Black and White Triclinium. (Rights statement)   Images Dates The house is dated from the II-III c.
Bibliography  A. Ben Abed, “Présentation de la maison du triclinium en noir et blanc à Pupput”, BullINAA 3, 1989 (1990), pp. 32-33. (worldcat) Bullo, S. and F. Ghedini, Amplissimae atque ornatissimae domus: l&amp;rsquo;edilizia residenziale nelle citta della Tunisia roman, Rome: Edizioni Quasar, 2003, p.188-189. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 315121
TGN ID 8697602
Contributor Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Viridarium (Maison du viridarium à niches)</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/xue_xia/pupput/house_of_the_viridarium/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/xue_xia/pupput/house_of_the_viridarium/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa Proconsularis Africa proconsularis (Pleiades)
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location Pupput
Pupput (Pleiades)
Location Description Pupput is located about three km to the northwest of Hammamed. Two inscriptions inform the designated title of the city, which became a colony (Colonia Aurelia Commoda Pia Felix Augusta Pupput) under the reign of Commodus. The city benefited from a strategic location at the crossroads linking Clupea to Thhuburbo and Carthage to Hadrumetum. Large residential quarters with houses and baths were excavated as well as a large necropolis.
Garden House of the Viridarium (Maison du viridarium à niches)
Keywords  peristyles (columnades) peristyles (Roman courtyards) mosaics (visual works)  Garden Description The house was located in the W neighborhood of the ancient city of Pupput and in present day lies in the precinct of a hotel, the construction of which badly damaged the house (Plan view, Fig.1).
The house has had three phases. During the second phase the garden peristyle (V) was bounded by a low wall that curved to make eight to nine semi circular niches (A, C, D, E, F, G, H, I) facing the galleries of the peristyle. The niches were paved with mosaics some of which figure birds among cut branches (D) and marine scenes (A, I). The second phase of the house is dated from the second half of the IV century.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the House of the Viridarium. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  A. Ben Abed “Mosaïques de la maison du viridarium à niches à Pupput (Tunisie)”, CMGR IV, p.265-271, Pl. CLXXI, Amplissimae, p.197-198. (worldcat) Bullo, S. and F. Ghedini, Amplissimae atque ornatissimae domus: l&amp;rsquo;edilizia residenziale nelle citta della Tunisia roman, Rome: Edizioni Quasar, 2003, p. 197-198. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 315121
TGN ID 8697602
Contributor Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
