<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>palaces on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/palaces/</link>
    <description>Recent content in palaces on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 14:48:37 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/palaces/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Palatial House in Insula 7 in Aventicum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_palatial_house_in_insula_7/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 14:48:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_palatial_house_in_insula_7/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Province Description Location Aventicum
Aventicum (Pleiades)
Location Description The town was established in the Augustan period as the civitas capital of the Helvetii. At this time the orthogonal street grid was laid out. Most probably in AD 71, it became Colonia Pia Flavia Constans Emerita Helvetiorum Foederata. The town was destroyed or badly damaged around AD 260, and it was progressively abandoned thereafter.
Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Palatial House in Insula 7 in Aventicum
Keywords archaeological garden
axial plan
bathhouses (water recreation structures)
drains
exedrae (site elements)
mosaics (visual works)
palaces
peristyles (Roman courtyards)
piscinae
presence chambers
Garden Description The remains of a palatial house (Palais de Derrière la Tour) were recently uncovered in excavations on the western edge of the city in an area characterized by luxurious domestic dwellings (Fig. 1). The house in its final state, from the Severan period to the middle of the 3rd century, had a peristyle courtyard measuring 42 x 69 meters. North of the courtyard was a reception room 12 x 18 meters in plan with a mosaic floor.
The courtyard was on two levels, divided on the north by a terrace wall with two small exedrae, possibly pools. An axially arranged central pathway between the reception room on the north and an apsed triclinium on the south further divided the courtyard into an eastern and a western half. Steps led up to the triclinium and to the northern wing of the house. A ground level gutter ran around the courtyard, and a covered drain crossed it beneath the central path. It can reasonably be assumed that the courtyard was designed as a garden (G in Fig. 1) with garden elements such as the path and the exedral pools. With the addition on the northeast of another wing terminating in a bath complex, the building ultimately had a length of around 200 meters. The excavators believe that the building in its latest phase had official character.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the courtyard house or palace on the western fringe of Insula 7, with a garden courtyard (G) with two small apsidal pools on one side. Plan adapted from Morel 1995, fig. 4. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Severnan Period - Middle of 3rd century
Bibliography  J. Morel, “Avenches VD, Derrière la Tour et insula 7 : Fouilles 1989/1990,” Annuaire de la Société Suisse de Préhistoire et d’Archéologie 74, 1991: 214-220, fig. 2. (worldcat) J. Morel, “Avenches, Palais de Derrière la Tour,” Bull. de l’Association Pro Aventico 37, 1995: 206-209, fig. 4.(worldcat) J. Morel, “L’habitat,” in : A. Hochuli-Gysel, ed., Avenches, capitale des Helvètes, Archéologie Suisse 24.1 2001: 47-49, fig. 62.(worldcat)  Periodo ID Pleiades ID 177495
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 14 July 2020
Related articles </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roman Palace in Fishbourne</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/fishbourne/fishbourne_roman_palace/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 18:05:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/fishbourne/fishbourne_roman_palace/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Fishbourne
Fishbourne (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Roman Palace in Fishbourne
Keywords archaeological garden
basins (vessels)
colonnades
loam
palaces
piscinae
presence chambers
terrace gardens
vegetable gardens
Garden Description Fishbourne Roman Palace was accidentally discovered during the digging of a water main trench in 1960. The discovery led to nine seasons of excavations (1961-69) that showed the site had developed from a military base at the time of the Roman invasion in AD 43 to a sumptuous palace by the end of the first century CE. Carefully excavated by Barry Cunliffe, using techniques of environmental archaeology, the garden excavations at the palace have long served as a model in the development of Roman garden archaeology, although the findings did not initially prompt the investigation of other gardens in Britain. Today the site has been developed for display and education.
The palace contains gardens within its internal courtyards, as well in a larger area to the south, where terraces and other landscape architectural features lay between the residence and the deep water channel (Fig 1.). The main garden of the palace is located in the large central courtyard, and dates to the late 1st century CE. Only the northern half has been excavated, while the remainder lies beneath the gardens of adjacent houses. The garden is bisected by a wide path leading between the entrance to the villa and a large audience hall. Lining the path, bedding trenches in alternating rectangular and semi-circular patterns survived as patterns of dark gray loam against an ochre-colored clay and gravel subsoil. Similar cuttings were found along the colonnades.
Pollen samples were taken in the garden areas in the hope that traces of pollen had survived from flowers and shrubs that had grown in the garden. Unfortunately, only a small quantity of pollen from weeds of cultivation, such as plantain and daisy, remained. As no positive archaeobotanical evidence for specific plants survived on site, literary sources were used to select plants that would have survived in the conditions of this northern province. Pliny the Younger refers to clipped box lining the edges of the pathways in the gardens of his Tuscan estate. This lime-loving shrub would have been very appropriate in the deliberately marled loam of these trenches, so, in 1968, it was planted and has thrived. Figure 2 shows the excavated trenches, and figure 3 shows the replanted box.
On the eastern side of the formal garden, alternating tree-pits and post holes were found. The pattern suggested an original arrangement of trees or shrubs planted against a trellis. Again, Pliny the Younger mentions espaliered apples in his gardens, and these have been successfully established at Fishbourne. Less successful was the effort to establish Italian cypress in the location of a large tree-pit found towards the western side of the garden.
Beneath the surface of the garden, the excavators discovered lines of ceramic pipes. They ran from the remains of the base of what is assumed to have been a water storage tank in the northwest corner of the formal garden. One line of pipes probably fed a pool in the entrance hall while others supplied small semi-circular basins set in recesses in the box hedging. Half a marble basin was found in the 1960&amp;rsquo;s.
There is circumstantial evidence for there having been a vegetable garden in the angle between the ends of the north and west wings of the palace where there is a dark, humus-rich soil containing heavily abraded pottery, suggesting that the soil had been intensively cultivated. It also had its own water supply, provided through wooden pipes with iron collars.
Limited excavations to the south of the palace revealed an artificial terrace which bore evidence of landscaping, including a pool, a gravel path, possible bedding trenches and what may have been the base for a column or statue. Excavations to the east of the palace in the mid 1980&amp;rsquo;s uncovered evidence for semi-formal gardens.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the Roman Palace showing the position of the gardens. Courtesy of David Rudkin for Fishbourne Roman Palace.   Images   Fig. 2: View of formal garden excavation. Photo courtesy of David Rudkin for Fishbourne Roman Palace.     Fig. 3: View of replanted formal garden. Photo courtesy of David Rudkin for Fishbourne Roman Palace.   Dates Late 1st century CE - unspecified
Excavation Dates 1961-69, mid 1980s
Bibliography  Barry Cunliffe, Excavations at Fishbourne, 1961-1969, Vols I &amp;amp; II, The Society of Antiquaries, London, 1971.(worldcat) B. W. Cunliffe, A.G. Down, and D. Rudkin, Excavations at Fishbourne 1969-1988, Chichester, 1996.(worldcat) B. Cunliffe, Fishbourne Roman Palace, Tempus, 1998. (worldcat) Amina-Aïcha Malek, A Sourcebook of Garden Archaeology, Bern: Peter Lang, 2012.(worldcat)  Periodo ID Pleiades ID 79466
TGN ID 7032567
Contributor Kathryn Gleason (ORCID:0000-0001-6260-8378)
Publication date 09 July 2020
Related articles </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>