<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>thermopolium on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/tags/thermopolium/</link>
    <description>Recent content in thermopolium on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 00:10:10 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/tags/thermopolium/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>II.viii.2-3</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_viii/iii.viii.2-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_viii/iii.viii.2-3/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region II
Insula Insula VIII
Keywords  thermopolium triclinia lecti lararium  Garden Description Customers at this thermopolium were served at a counter at the street and at the masonry triclinium (l. medius, 3.60 m.; l. imus 2.85; l. summus 2.30 m.) in the rear garden. This was located against the north wall to the front of this long, narrow garden and had a round table (0.50 m. in dia.) between the couches and a rectangular table (0.65 x 0.89 m.) at the end of the lectus summus. A niche lararium was next to it with a tufa altar below decorated with a large carved club. A bench for cooking was built against the south wall at the west end with two arched openings for fuel storage underneath.
Plans   Fig. 62, Plan of Region II, insula viii   Pleiades ID 456321707
TGN ID 7004658
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p.92 (worldcat) Orr, Roman Domestic Religion: A Study of the Roman Household Deities and their Shrines at Pompeii and Herculaneum, no.65 (worldcat)  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 10 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
