<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>pool on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/pool/</link>
    <description>Recent content in pool on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 11:20:32 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/pool/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Combination of the House of the Opus Sectile with the House of the Opus Quadratum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_combination-of-the-house-of-the-opus-sectile-with-the-house-of-the-opus-quadratum_y.sun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_combination-of-the-house-of-the-opus-sectile-with-the-house-of-the-opus-quadratum_y.sun/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania (Pleiades)
Location AUGUSTORITUM - Limoges
Augustoritum (Pleiades)
Location Description The earliest traces of settlement in this area are at the oppidum of Villejoubert 25 kilometers east of the city. The Roman settlement of Limoges proper dates from about 15-10 B.C. and was named Augustoritum (Augustus’s ford) in honor of the emperor. It covered some 65 to 100 hectares and was laid out in a regular rectangular grid. The ancient wall dates from the end of the third century. The town took water from several sources, including the aqueduct of Aigoulène; there were drains for waste water disposal. There were several public fountains and baths, a theater, an arena, and temples. The city declined in the fourth century. Its Roman name was replaced by the Celtic name of the local people; and its regular street pattern, almost totally lost.
Garden Combination of the House of the Opus Sectile with the House of the Opus Quadratum
Keywords  pool mosaic  Garden Description In the first half of the second century, the combination of these two beautiful houses made for truly sumptuous quarters. The residence, opening off of a vast vestibule with a central pool, covered an area of 5500 square meters, the whole of the insula. In the first phase of the work, heating was installed in the two reception rooms. Enjoyment of the east garden [1] of around 500 square meters was enhanced by a double-asped, 1.2-meter-deep pool in its center. It disappeared in a fire between the third and fourth century. In a second phase of embellishment, not prior to the years 226-235, the luxury of the décor was heightened. The reception room [2] was paved with a rich carpet of geometric opus sectile framed by a border of white marble, while new marble plates suppressed the old. To room [3] was added a large apse to the north, also furnished with a luxurious pavement of opus sectile and ornamented with a mosaic on either a wall or perhaps a semidome. The semicircle of this apse was constructed at the expense of a service courtyard. This courtyard [4] was bordered on the east by a portico which sheltered under its roof a well with a monolithic puteal. All of this magnificence was destroyed by fire in the late third or early fourth century.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the Combination of House of the Opus Sectile with House of the Opus Quadratum.    Dates First Phase：first half of the second century
Second Phase：226-235 CE
Bibliography  J.P. Loustaud. Limoges antique, Travaux d’Archéologie Limousine, supplément 5, 2000, p. 198-202, plan p. 198. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 138203
TGN ID 7030318 7008410
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House in the Rue des Clairettes</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-in-the-rue-des-clairettes_y.sun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-in-the-rue-des-clairettes_y.sun/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania (Pleiades)
Location AUGUSTORITUM - Limoges
Augustoritum (Pleiades)
Location Description The earliest traces of settlement in this area are at the oppidum of Villejoubert 25 kilometers east of the city. The Roman settlement of Limoges proper dates from about 15-10 B.C. and was named Augustoritum (Augustus’s ford) in honor of the emperor. It covered some 65 to 100 hectares and was laid out in a regular rectangular grid. The ancient wall dates from the end of the third century. The town took water from several sources, including the aqueduct of Aigoulène; there were drains for waste water disposal. There were several public fountains and baths, a theater, an arena, and temples. The city declined in the fourth century. Its Roman name was replaced by the Celtic name of the local people; and its regular street pattern, almost totally lost.
Garden House in the Rue des Clairettes
Keywords  pool portico  Garden Description This house was discovered in the excavation of 1998 in the rue des Clairettes. Constructed in the first half of the second century, it dominated the street. Only the wing running east-west is known. A portico must have opened onto a large garden to the north [1]. In the axis of this garden was the central room [2] of the wing with 125 square meters. In the center of this room was a large square pool, several times remodeled. Originally it was paved with marble or limestone and fed by an underground vaulted tunnel that crossed the whole room. To the south opened another portico overlooking a terrace two meters below; the street which defined the southern border was on beyond.
Dates Constructed in the first half of the second century。
Excavation Dates 1998
Bibliography  J.P. Loustaud. Limoges antique, Travaux d’Archéologie Limousine, supplément 5, 2000, p. 208-209, plan p. 208. (with a bibliography of earlier works) (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 138203
TGN ID 7030318 7008410
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Seventh of March (Nones de Mars)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-of-the-seventh-of-march-nones-de-mars_y.sun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-of-the-seventh-of-march-nones-de-mars_y.sun/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania (Pleiades)
Location AUGUSTORITUM - Limoges
Augustoritum (Pleiades)
Location Description The earliest traces of settlement in this area are at the oppidum of Villejoubert 25 kilometers east of the city. The Roman settlement of Limoges proper dates from about 15-10 B.C. and was named Augustoritum (Augustus’s ford) in honor of the emperor. It covered some 65 to 100 hectares and was laid out in a regular rectangular grid. The ancient wall dates from the end of the third century. The town took water from several sources, including the aqueduct of Aigoulène; there were drains for waste water disposal. There were several public fountains and baths, a theater, an arena, and temples. The city declined in the fourth century. Its Roman name was replaced by the Celtic name of the local people; and its regular street pattern, almost totally lost.
Garden House of the Seventh of March (Nones de Mars)
Keywords  pool  Garden Description Uncovered between 1982 and 1991, this vast residence south of the forum opens to the east onto the Cardo maximus. Constructed between A.D. 30 and 40 on a high artificial terrace, it occupies 3734 square meters, half of insula IV-6. Remodeled in the second or third century, it is sometimes considered a schola, but without certainty. Beyond a large atrium and a tablinum comes a first central peristyle [1] (25.1 x 20.8 m = 522 sq m) with Corinthian and Tuscan columns. In the middle is a rectangular pool 9.87 meters long fed from the town’s public aqueduct through a vaulted tunnel 52 meters long. A vast, T-shaped room for entertaining, the principal triclinium of the house, is centered on this peristyle, opening onto it through a large bay. On the further side, this room extends, along its whole length into the vast garden [4] (26 x 29 m). Embellished with triple Tuscan porticos in a U, it forms the second part of the house. The west portico provides access to a series of rooms which complete this vast residence.
Dates 20-30 CE
Excavation Dates 1982-1991
Bibliography  J.P. Loustaud. Limoges antique, Travaux d’Archéologie Limousine, supplément 5, 2000, p.179-91, plan p.181 (with bibliography of earlier works). (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 138203
TGN ID 7030318 7008410
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>