<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gallia_narbonensis on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/categories/gallia_narbonensis/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Gallia_narbonensis on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2020 00:08:52 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/categories/gallia_narbonensis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Suburban Villa</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/geneva/suburban_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2020 00:08:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/geneva/suburban_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Location Genava, ((Geneva, France)
Genava
Location Description Sublocation The Roman town, located at the western end of Lake Geneva at the confluence of the Rhone and Arve rivers, grew from a late first century B.C. settlement of the Gallic tribe of the Allobroges. The town flourished until the third century A.D., and the territory around Geneva attracted many villa owners. There are few remains of Late Roman Geneva, but it appears to have been fortified around A.D. 300 by a circuit wall.
Garden Suburban Villa
Keywords  villae suburbanae peristyle courtyard courtyard  Garden Description This villa suburbana in the modern Parc de la Grange lay outside the town on the southern shore of Lake Geneva. The villa, built originally in the mid 1st c. A.D., was extended in the 2nd and 3rd c., and was inhabited until the 4th c. (Fig. 8.2). It measured 40 x 30.50 m., and it had a separate bath complex on the northwest. The entire estate was 450 m. long and approximately 180 m. in width.
A peristyle courtyard surrounded by covered walkways on four sides took up an area of 22 x 11.80 m., about half of the building. In the center of the courtyard was a pool, very fragmentarily preserved, around which, in all probability, were plantings (G on plan).
To the northwest of the house were enclosed areas which have been interpreted as gardens (G on plan). In the corner of the most easterly of these was an L-shaped pergola. The property between the house and the shore of the lake at the north was terraced and possibly designed as a landscaped park or left as a &amp;ldquo;natural&amp;rdquo; park.
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Bibliography   L. Blondel and G. Darier, &amp;ldquo;La villa romaine de la Grange, Genève,&amp;rdquo; Anzeiger für schweizerische Geschichte 24, 1922:70-88, pls. 1-2. (worldcat)
  W. Drack, &amp;ldquo;Die Gutshöfe,&amp;rdquo; in Ur- und frühgeschichtliche Archäologie der Schweiz 5, Basel, 1975, p. 58, fig. 21. (worldcat)
  M.-A. Haldimann, P. André, E. Broillet-Ramjoué, Matthieu Poux, “Entre résidence indigène et domus gallo-romaine: le domaine antique du Parc de La Grange (GE),” Archéologie Suisse 24.2, 2001: 2-15, figs. 4, 13-14, 17. (worldcat)
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 177528
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Publication date 14 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb garden of an anonymous</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/briord/tomb_garden_of_an_anonymous/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2020 00:08:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/briord/tomb_garden_of_an_anonymous/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Location BRIORD
BRIORD
Location Description Sublocation Garden Tomb garden of an anonymous
Keywords  funerary buildings tomb  Garden Description Three fragments of a large funerary inscription found in the seventeenth century near a church at Briord (in the territory of the Ambarri) record part of the text establishing a foundation for the observance of annual rites at a tomb site ([ad Pa]rentalia celebranda…haec omnia annua fierent) from the revenue of an arepennis (a Gallic measure of land, equivalent to half a iugerum, about one quarter of an acre) of vineyard, or some portion of it.
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Bibliography  CIL 13.2465.   Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7662219
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Publication date 14 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb garden of Publicius Calistus</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/die/tomb_garden_of_publicius_calistus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2020 00:08:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/die/tomb_garden_of_publicius_calistus/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Location DIE, France
DIE, France
Location Description Sublocation Garden Tomb garden of Publicius Calistus
Garden Description A funerary monument found near Die and now on the terrace of the courthouse there records an epitaph of (probably) the second or third century consecrated (consecratum) by Publicius Calistus for himself, his wives, and his children and attaching to the tomb two thirds of an arepennis (a Gallic measure of land, equivalent to half a iugerum, about one quarter of an acre) of vineyard (i.e. about 830 m2), from the revenue of which, according to Hirschfeld’s plausible interpretation in CIL, he wanted no fewer than fifteen sextarii of wine to be poured in libation to him annually (on what occasions he does not say) (cum bese vineae arep(ennis), ex cuius reditu omnib(us) annis prolibari volo ne minus XV v(ini ?) s(extaris ?)).
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Bibliography   CIL 12.1657   J.-J. Hatt, La tombe gallo-romaine (Paris 1951) 71. (worldcat)
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7662219
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Publication date 14 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban House</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/geneva/geneva_urban_house/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2020 00:08:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/geneva/geneva_urban_house/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Location Genava, ((Geneva, France)
Genava
Location Description Sublocation The Roman town, located at the western end of Lake Geneva at the confluence of the Rhone and Arve rivers, grew from a late first century B.C. settlement of the Gallic tribe of the Allobroges. The town flourished until the third century A.D., and the territory around Geneva attracted many villa owners. There are few remains of Late Roman Geneva, but it appears to have been fortified around A.D. 300 by a circuit wall.
Garden Urban House
Keywords  peristyle terrace  Garden Description This badly preserved building situated on the Plateau des Tranchées was on a terraced slope overlooking Lake Geneva (Lacus Lemanus). Originally built between 20 and 40 A.D., and occupied until 180, the house had a central peristyle courtyard measuring 7.80 x 22 m. in size. Below the peristyle was a terrace where excavations uncovered a deposit 15 cm. thick of organically enriched soil. This evidence suggested to the excavators that the terrace was planted as a garden. Due to subsidence and shifting of masonry walls, the house was rebuilt between 50 and 70 without a peristyle courtyard or a garden terrace.
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Bibliography  M.-A. Haldimann, E. Ramjoué, and C. Simon, “Les fouilles de la cour de l’ancienne prison de Saint-Antoine,” Archäologie der Schweiz 14, 1991:194-204. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 177528
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Publication date 14 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House Cours Pouroules</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/arausio/house_cours_pourtoules/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2020 00:08:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/arausio/house_cours_pourtoules/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location arausio
arausio (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House Cours Pouroules
House House Cours Pourtoules
House Description In 1984 – 86, prior to construction of a parking garage, a large area of some 4,700 square meters was excavated south of the Cours Pourtoules. About a third of the ancient structures were reinforced and reburied; the rest was destroyed. The area encompassed several ancient houses; the one of interest to us is in the west insula.
Keywords  mosaics (visual works) doliums opus signinum reception rooms fountains opus sectile (visual works)  Garden Description The garden to the south is not completely known. The north gallery (BG), 5.5 meters wide at its widest point, was paved with black-and-white mosaics for at least 35 meters. At the west was a gallery (17 x 3.5 m) with a floor of pounded earth. One side was perhaps with a full wall pierced by windows. In the southwest corner of the garden was a well (FS) for which a half *dolium, found destroyed in the well, served as a puteal. The soil of the garden is brown clay with strata of sand. Analysis of this soil has not been able to identify traces of what was planted in it. The garden was probably put in during Augustan times, but the paucity of ceramic material that could support this date must be underlined.
In phase IIIA, the large room H was divided by columns into a central nave and aisles along the sides, where pilasters along the walls matched the columns. The central nave was paved with a new mosaic while the aisles kept a floor of opus signinum. The gallery [BG] kept the same floor as before. A long rectangular pool [BF] was installed along this gallery without touching it. Somewhat surprisingly, it was not centered either between the galleries of on the reception room [H].
In phase IIIB, in the second quarter of the second century, the east and west galleries of the garden were paralleled on the outside by two new open walks elevated some 40 centimeters above the level of the garden. To the south was added a structure to close in the garden. The well disappeared in this phase. In the area [CB] was installed a shallow pool suggestive of a foot bath. It was fed by a fountain roughly in the area [CI], but too badly damaged for precise description. Two little channels in the rim separating the two pools let the water flow between them. Fragments of a luxurious opus sectile which ornamented this arrangement were collected. Stairs at the northwest corner of the pool [BF] allowed one to get in and out of the pool. The smooth-shaft Corinthian columns of gallery [BG] were moved to be perpendicular to those of [FK]. Their regular spacing was interrupted in front of the large room [H] to leave open the view of the garden.
Among the objects found at Cours Pourtoules was a terracotta oscillum representing a theatrical mask. The site was abandoned at the end of the second or beginning of the third century.
Plans   General map of Cours Pourtoules     Phase 1 of Course Pourtoules     Phase 2 of Course Pourtoules     Phase 3 of Course Pourtoules     Cours Pourtoules, axonometric reconstruction by P. Vallauri. From Gallia 87-88, fig. 133 p. 322.   Images   House Cours Pouroules   Dates Bibliography   “Orange, Cours Pourtoules”, Informations archéologiques in Gallia 87-88, P. 321-26
  Bellet, Michel-Edouard. Orange Antique: Monuments Et Musée. Paris: Imprimerie nationale, 1991, P. 70-71 (worldcat)
  J.-D. Bouche, Orange, Cours Pourtoule, ilôt Ouest. Présentation des données de fouilles de l’état I et II 15-10 av. J.-C. à 40 ap. J.-C. mémoire de DEA Université d’Aix-en-Provence, dir. X. Lafon, 2003 (à verifier EM)
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7599818
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Puissalicon, villa de la Condoumine&#34;</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/andance/puissalicon_villa_de_la_condoumine/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2020 00:08:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/andance/puissalicon_villa_de_la_condoumine/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location andance
andance (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Puissalicon, villa de la Condoumine
Villa Puissalicon, villa de la Condoumine
Keywords  bathhouses (water recreation structures) [opus spicatum] columns (architectural elements) opus signinum statues fountains reception rooms  Villa Description This villa in the plain of the Libron at the place called la Condoumine in the commune of Puissalicon, was first noted between 1926 and 1942 and excavated beginning in 1965. The total site extends over six hectares; the constructions of the villa must have covered some 2500 square meters but only about a quarter of the structures are known for certain. Especially well known are the baths on the south of the villa, which were complemented by a large ornamental pool.
The chronology of the villa is incompletely known. Built in the last quarter of the first century B.C., it was remodeled several times. The baths were particularly affected at the end of the first century A.D. One senses a new series of transformations in the second century and an apparent impoverishment in the third century followed by a revival in the fourth with a remodeling of the baths at the end of the fourth or beginning of the fifth century. It was abandoned in the course of the fifth and sixth centuries. A walkway [2] separated the buildings to the south from those on the north. Paved in opus spicatum, it has yielded many fragments of its pictorial décor. The precise structure of this walkway, however, is puzzling. It would make good sense for the well-constructed wall A on the south to have supported the columns of a gallery, while the frescoes were on the south side of wall B. But wall B was of very rough construction with only mud mortar between the stones, hardly the proper support for such elegant decoration. Exactly what the structure was and where the frescoes were remains uncertain. In any event, south of wall A was a vast courtyard ornamented by a large pool parallel to the walkway (44 x 3 m, 1.2 m deep) with a horseshoe-shaped apse nine meters in diameter. It may have served also as a reserve of water. The bottom was lined with pavers of opus signinum with masonry quarterround to make edges between the bottom and the sides watertight. A lead pipe mounted in a marble plaque provided drainage. The water came from the baths in a canal lined with marble and poured into the pool though a series of mouths of which one in Carrara marble was found, broken, in the pool. The north wall of the pool extended another forty-five or so meters farther to the west to a little square building three meters on a side. In the opinion of the excavator, a garden extended to the south of the pool, where several fragments of high quality statuary were unearthed. A rare find was discovered in digging out a sewer: a marble fountain head, similar to the base of a column but having inside a circular disc, also of marble, with two holes and a bottom shaped so that the water pressure would cause it to turn in its housing, letting water spurt though when one of the holes was over the inflow pipe and otherwise cutting off the flow, thus giving the water jet an intermittent, bouncing effect. The gallery led to baths [19-26]. In a second phase, they were dismantled and the heating system filled in. Two little rectangular pools belonging to fountains were created, one on either side of the door of the former caldarium [23], and another ornamental fountain was placed against the south exterior wall of the baths, blocking a former door and passage way. The apse of the room was enlarged and assumed a horseshoe shape. One may well ask, with Alain Bouet, whether in this late phase the space did not take on the function of a reception room.
Plans   Plan of Puissalicon, villa de la Condoumine   Dates A.D. 75-100 built
Bibliography   J. P. Bacou, La villa gallo-romaine de Condoumine à Puissalicon, civitas de Béziers, Revue Archéologique de Narbonnaise, 1971, 4, P. 93 – 149.
  Bacou, J.-P. &amp;ldquo;La Villa Gallo-Romaine De Condoumine À Puissalicon (civitas De Béziers).&amp;rdquo; Revue Archéologique De Narbonnaise. 4.1 (1971): 93-149. (worldcat)
  Alain Bouet, Les thermes publics et privés en Gaule Narbonnaise, vol. II, catalogue, coll. École Française de Rome 320, Rome, 2003, P. 208-11. (worldcat)
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 1031774
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Saint-Florent, House B, House with the Polychrome Mosaic</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/arausio/saint_florent_house_b_house_with_the_polychrome_mosaic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2020 00:08:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/arausio/saint_florent_house_b_house_with_the_polychrome_mosaic/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location arausio
arausio (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Saint-Florent, House B, House with the Polychrome Mosaic
House Saint-Florent, House B, House with the Polychrome Mosaic
Keywords  mosaics (visual works) columns (architectural elements) peristyles (columnades) porticoes fountains opus signinum gutters (building drainage components)  House Description It was of high quality construction with eight black and white floor mosaics with occasional touches of color, columns and capitals in dressed stone, painted plaster, and a heated room. It was arranged in a U around a garden surrounded by a square peristyle 13.5 meters on a side. The principal room was in the center on the north side, looking south across a portico to the garden. The peristyle had eight columns on each side except the north, where the central two were missing to open the view of the garden from the main room. To judge by the foundations, the columns on either side of this opening were larger than the others. A rectangular pool (4.9 x 2.1 m.) on the garden side of this opening had a semicircular apse on its south side. It was probably about seventy or eighty centimeters deep; but the depth is uncertain, for the top has not been preserved. It was lined with opus signinum and had masonry quarterround to make the edges watertight. Around the garden, except at the pool, ran a gutter in dressed stone.
Plans   Plan of Saint-Florent, House B, House with the Polychrome Mosaic   Dates Bibliography   Bellet, Michel-Edouard. Orange Antique: Monuments Et Musée. Paris: Imprimerie nationale, 1991, P. 70-71 (worldcat)
  Maison 1996, t. II, P. 229-237 and P. 248-250.
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7599818
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Suburban Villa de la  Brunette</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/arausio/suburban_villa_de_la_brunette/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2020 00:08:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/arausio/suburban_villa_de_la_brunette/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location arausio
arausio (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Suburban Villa de la Brunette
House Suburban Villa de la Brunette
Keywords  atriums atrium houses porticoes gutters (building drainage components) reception rooms colonnades columns (architectural elements) statues  House Description To the west of Orange, this residence is just south of the amphitheater – which was destroyed in the eighteenth century. More than 2000 square meters have been unearthed. It is bounded on the south by a fencing wall 150 meters long and on the north by road that separates the house from the amphitheater. The east and west boundaries are not known. Constructed in the first century A.D. (condition 1), the habitation was greatly remodeled and embellished towards the end of the second century (condition 2) only to be abandoned in the first half of the third century.
Garden Description Condition 1: The central building is organized around an atrium which opens to the east on the garden through a 2.9-meter wide portico [3]. This portico extends all along the east side of the building and forms a transition between the rooms of the house and the garden. On the north, it opens onto the rooms [4] to [7]. Room [7] is the most spacious of the residential part. The garden [30] unfolds to the east of the villa. Its full surface is unknown, since its limits to the north and to the east are unknown. The form of the plantings has not been ascertained. In the garden, 15 meters from the portico [3], was a rectangular pool [31] 13.35 meters long, more than 3.5 meters wide (to the limit of the excavation) and more than a meter deep. It is covered with a layer of tile with waterproofing strips in the corners. Around the pool, the ground was covered with pebbles.
Condition 2: Towards the end of the second century, new constructions radically transformed the suburban villa. It was enlarged to the south, and was henceforth organized around an east-west axis of symmetry, that is to say, determined by the two courtyards with portico’s [23] and [27]. The first room, [23], is square (7 by 7 meters). Situated at the west of the building, it leads into several large rooms; the central part {of what?} doubtless had a stone floor. The large room [27] is between one courtyard [23] and the second courtyard [7], (7.20 by 11.50 meters), separated from the garden [46] by the portico [3]. This courtyard {first or second?} was certainly planted, for the soil is arable earth. It is surrounded by a U-shaped gallery with columns 2.50 meters apart and crowned with Corinthian capitals. A gutter at the foot of the portico collected rainwater. There was no passage towards the center. {What center???} Outside the axial room [25], two other reception rooms opened directly onto the courtyard: the rectangular room [29] and the room with the trilobe plan [31]. A fourth reception room [30], further back, opened into the southwest corner of the gallery.
In comparison to the previous phase, the garden [46] has been considerably enlarged; its southern limit has been pushed back about 40 meters. The portico which ran along the west side [3] has been lengthened up to the wall delimiting the villa on the south. It returns towards the east by a wider gallery [44]. The two galleries meet in a circular room 8 meters in diameter [45] of which only the foundations remain. The elevation could have been a curved wall pierced with bays or a colonnade.
At the heart of the garden, the rectangular pool [47] of the first condition was kept. Along the gallery [3], a semi-circular pool [48] with an internal diameter of six meters was added. It is separated from the gallery by an elongated.
Plans   Fig. 1 Plan of Suburban Villa de la Brunette     Fig. 2 Plan of Suburban Villa de la Brunette   Dates A.D. 1-100 constructed
Bibliography  J.-M. Mignon, I. Doray, V. Faure, A. Bouet, La Brunette à Orange premier établissement antique périurbain (Vaucluse), in R.A.N., 30, 1997, P.173-202.  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7599818
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The villa of Saint Martin</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/taradeau/the_villa_of_saint_martin/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2020 00:08:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/taradeau/the_villa_of_saint_martin/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location taradeau
taradeau (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation The villa of Saint Martin
Villa The villa of Saint Martin
Keywords  porticoes columns (architectural elements) opus signinum triclinia mosaics (visual works) reception rooms peristyles (columnades)  Villa Description Taradeau lies about thirty kilometers west of Fréjus in the valley of the Argens between Les Arcs and Lorgues. The Gallo-Roman villa sits at the foot of the hill of Saint Martin, at an altitude of 70 meters, some 750 meters north of the Argens. It was excavated from 1994 to 1999. This villa with a Roman wine press was occupied from the first century B.C. to seventh century A.D.. In stages 1 and 2, it was a farm, which was then remodeled into a villa (stage 3) in the last years of the first century or first half of the second. The former farm became the agricultural part, while a new pars urbana was created. It was organized around a garden [1], 34 meters on a side, surrounded on three sides by a U-shaped, 2.3 meter-wide portico with columns. In the center of the garden was an ornamental pool (7.2 by 2.8 meters and 1 meter deep) lined with opus signinum with an overflow drain to the exterior of the south enclosing wall. It is presumed that the villa was supplied water by an aquaduct. Around the pool, cuts into the substrate have attested the planting of trees or large bushes which would have embellished the interior of the garden. The northern portico, of the Rhodian type – that is, with higher columns than the other three – opened onto a main room [2] (7.6 by 3.6 meters) which is centered in the axis of the pool. To the west, a triclinium[3] (5 by 3.5 meters) had a floor paved in opus signnum decorated with marble plaques indicating the placement of the three couches.
In a fourth stage, the villa lost its residential character: the pars urbana was converted into a winery. The ornamental pool was modified to feed a hydraulic device [4]. It was extended to 18.4 meters in length and joined to a second rectangular basin (5.2 by 1 meters) which led the water into a final basin which served to turn a horizontal waterwheel.
Garden Description Plans   Plan of The Villa of Saint Martin   Dates Bibliography  Brun, Jean-Pierre. Carte Archéologique De La Gaule: 83, Le Var 1. Paris, 1999, vol.2, P. 765-771, plan P. 765. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7602340
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa de Château-Pipet</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/andance/villa_de_chateau_pipet/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2020 00:08:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/andance/villa_de_chateau_pipet/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location andance
andance (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Villa de Château-Pipet
Villa Villa de Château-Pipet
Keywords  basins (vessels) columns (architectural elements) opus signinum  Villa Description 1.2 kilometers south of the village of Andance, at the place called Château-Pipet, in the little valley of the Cueil, structures belonging without doubt to a Roman villa were discovered. As early as 1867, the abbot Chaillet noted the presence of ruins in this area. A salvage excavation in 1964 partially exposed a long ornamental pool associated with these structures. A rectangular garden [1] of 152 square meters formed a part of the villa. On the east side, the garden was bounded by a an unusual wall formed by eight half silos, or, seen form outside the garden, semicircular niches. Perhaps these niches were hidden by a wall along their back side, outside the garden, for a little of such a wall remains at either end. On the inside of the garden, in the middle of this wall were the beginnings of a larger apse (shown in dotted lines on the plan). One can see in this structure a supporting wall with internal buttresses. To the west and to the south, the space was bordered by a gallery [2] ; the shafts of its columns were discovered in the excavations.
Between the garden and the gallery on the west was a rectangular pool with a semicircular apse extending into the garden in the middle. This pool, about 24 meters long and 2.3 wide, was covered in opus signinum. It was perhaps completed by two arms along the other galleries, thus forming a U. On the south side were found the beginnings of five rooms, but it was not possible to excavate them. In the northwest corner of the garden, a repair was found in the form of a wall running parallel to the pool but 50 centimeters east of the garden-side pool wall. It has been interpreted as a waterproofing device: a fill of a layer of green clay was place there without doubt to stop infiltration of water [4].
No date was proposed for the structure in the excavation reports.
Plans   Plan of Villa de Château-Pipet   Dates Bibliography   M. LE GLAY, Informations archéologiques, dans Gallia, 1966, P. 519-520.
  Chr. FRAISSE, J. DUPRAZ, sous la resp. de M. Provost, L’Ardèche 07, Carte archéologique de la Gaule, 2001, P. 195-196, plan P. 196 (worldcat)
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 1031774
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa de Muscapeu</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/tourves/villa_de_muscapeu/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2020 00:08:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/tourves/villa_de_muscapeu/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location tourves
tourves (Pleiades)
Location Description Tourves is a village about 30 kilometers almost due north of Toulon on the via Aureliana in the valley of the Camary, a tributary of the Argens.Sublocation Villa de Muscapeu
Villa Villa de Muscapeu
Keywords  peristyles (columnades) opus signinum reception rooms porticoes mosaics (visual works) bathhouses (water recreation structures)  Villa Description In the locality of Muscapeu, at the foot of a slope, was found this villa. Partial excavations in 1950 to 1960 exposed 4200 square meters. Constructed in the first half of the first century B.C. , it was occupied until sometime in the third century. An aqueduct from a spring supplied water. The pars urbana is to the east; the pars rustica to the west.
In state 1, from a sort of podium, the pars urbana, 34.5 meters on a side, overlooked the surrounding fields. At the center was a peristyle [1] (16.6 by 3.2 meters); and in the center, a rectangular pool (16.6 by 3.2 meters) with a bottom of opus signinum. The drain came out of the southeast corner of the pool and flowed along the south façade.
The living quarters were between the colonnade of the peristyle [2] and that of the façade of the villa [3], which opened out onto the surrounding countryside. In this northern wing, in the axis of the pool, was a reception room [4] completely open to the portico of the peristyle. The other rooms of this wing are poorly known but they had floors with white mosaics with black borders and stone thresholds with sockets at the ends for the pins on which the doors pivoted. In the southwest corner, a room with an apse, a floor of opus signinum, one part elevated and a square masonry base in the center has posed problems of interpretation: is a lararium, a place for religious services, or part of the baths to the west?
In a second stage, in the first century, a bath complex [5] with an open-air esplanade was built to the southwest of the peristyle. In a third stage, these baths were redecorated with marble. In a final stage, in the second century, new baths [6] were constructed to the west of the original complex, but the original was not abandoned.
Plans   Plan of The Villa de Muscapeu   Dates Bibliography   Brun, Jean-Pierre. Carte Archéologique De La Gaule: 83, Le Var 1. Paris, 1999, vol.2, P. 835-840, plan P. 836. (worldcat)
  Bouet, Alain, and Philippe Leveau. Les Thermes Prives Et Publics En Gaule Narbonnaise. S.l.: s.n., 1996, P. 401, Fig. 279-283. (worldcat)
  R. AMBARD, La villa gallo-romaine de Muscapeu, in Provence historique, V, 1955, P. 104.
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 1035905
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa de Pardigon 3</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/cavalaire_sur_mer/villa_de_pardigon_3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2020 00:08:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/cavalaire_sur_mer/villa_de_pardigon_3/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location cavalaire_sur_mer
cavalaire_sur_mer (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Villa de Pardigon 3
Villa Villa de Pardigon 3
Keywords  peristyles (columnades) porticoes columns (architectural elements) reception rooms  Villa Description This wine-producing villa, constructed under the Flavians, lies in the plain, in immediate proximity to the sea. Excavated in 1985 and 1986 and covering an area of some 2000 square meters, it went through three stages between the last quarter of the first century and the beginning of the third century. The site was then re-occupied in the fourth century.
The principal buildings were constructed in the first century; in the second century, the peristyle [1] was added. The garden in it (8.3 by 6.6 meters) is surrounded on four sides by a 2.3 meter wide portico, with five columns on a side. In the garden were found trenches for planting trees and vegetables. To the south, a gallery serving as a façade runs along this peristyle. To the north, there was a square reception room [2] (4.5 meters on a side) later embellished by the construction of a large bay on its garden side. The bay was framed by two columns more massive than the others of the portico that supported a pediment and lifted the roof of this portico above those of the rest of the peristyle. To the west, a structure in the corner formed no doubt a tower and belvedere overlooking the sea. To the east of the peristyle, a second courtyard, [5] had a well whose rim was the top of a dolium. Further to the east was a bath wing (50 by 30 meters). North of the reception room was an open-air courtyard [4] 8.3 meters wide, and beyond it, the storage area for wine in casks occupied a large area 52 meters long and 12 wide.
In a final stage, at the beginning of the third century, the garden was transformed into a court and then into a dump, and the south branch of the peristyle was divided by a partition.
Plans   Plan of Villa de Pardigon 3   Dates A.D. 1-100 principal building constructed A.D. 100-200 peristyle added A,D. 200-300 garden transformed into a court then a dump
Bibliography  Brun, Jean-Pierre. Carte Archéologique De La Gaule: 83, Le Var 1. Paris, 1999, vol.2, P. 324-330, plan P. 326. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa de Saint-Symphorien</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/caumont_sur_durance/villa_de_saint_symphorien/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2020 00:08:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/caumont_sur_durance/villa_de_saint_symphorien/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location caumont_sur_durance
caumont_sur_durance (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Villa de Muscapeu
Sublocation Description Halfway between Avignon and Cavaillon, this villa is west of the present village of Caumont-sur-Durance where the road forks with one branch going to Bonpas and the other to Avignon. It sat upon a little mound overlooking the Durance. Known since its fortuitous discovery in the middle of the nineteenth century, the site is the source of the famous, acephalous Venus of Caumont, a beautiful marble statue now in the Calvet museum.Villa Villa de Muscapeu
Keywords  peristyles (columnades) mosaics (visual works) porticoes hypocausts orchards  Villa Description The site of the villa is practically completely covered by modern houses. The villa, of vast proportions, was built on successive terraces whose form survives in the present layout of lots. The part already excavated have revealed a sigma-shaped portico and at least two groups of rooms connected with baths. The construction was luxurious as attested by fragments of opus sectile, mosaics and wall paintings of quality, and especially by beautifully made architectural tiles called Campana plaques, with low-relief volutes and images of porticos, winged victories sacrificing bulls .
In the course of test probes for the construction of a subdivision, a large ornamental pool was found on the terrace below the villa. In 2001, a program of archeological research was begun on this vast terrain which was once a huge garden, 140.6 by 83.5 meters for a total surface of 1.2 hectares. To create a level surface, the lower parts to the south and east had been filled with earth moved from the upper parts. A wall around the outside 60 centimeters thick completely enclosed the terrace; sections fallen in place show that it was 2.9 meters high. It is still standing on south and east sides, where it continues to function as a retaining wall. On the west side, below the villa, it both served as a buttress and gave an esthetically pleasing, monumental façade to the terrace. In this part of the wall, semicircular niches, 3.32 meters in diameter extended out, away from the garden at regular, 18.75 meter intervals; open on the garden side, they may have served to accent sculptures. These niches alternated with semicircular buttresses, also protruding outside the garden but walled up on the line of the wall. The were constructed on top of the embankment and were thus anchored at a higher level..
The inside of the wall was covered by carefully executed opus reticulatum, a technique common in Italy but rare in Gaul. This fact has given rise to the hypothesis that the proprietor brought workmen from Italy. On the basis of the construction and the general context, a dating in Augustan times, in the last third of the first century B.C. has been proposed. Despite the internal buttresses, the wall was not sufficiently well founded against the embankment on the west side, and soon fell over.
Doubtless also from the Augustan period is the monumental, elongated rectangular pool (66.05 by 4.58 meters), 1.2 meters deep, which cuts across almost the entire width of the garden approximately in its center. It seems impossible to date its creation later than the year 1. The inside was covered with a thick layer of smooth opus signinum painted red. A rim of limestone flagstones terminated its border. The ground was covered with a careful opus spicatum extending over some 202 square meters with a blend of bricks of colors differing according to differences in firing. A flight of five limestone steps in one corner allowed easy descent into the pool.
The water supply system for the pool is not known. A nearby spring may have contributed to filling this 280 cubic meter pool, without, however having a sufficient output to fill the pool completely. One can also imagine pumping from an inlet cut in the bank of the nearby river, and the contribution of captured rain water is not to be forgotten. At the eastern end, a horizontal plughole permitted emptying the pool into a sewer. Outside the pool, running underground along its north side was a drain designed to lower the ground water level, keep the subsoil healthy, and avoid uplift under the pool when it was emptied. It is possible that, besides its ornamental function, the pool served for raising fish, though no chambers for egg laying were built into its walls and no submerged container for hatching was found, and carpological samples have given no positive results.
The first stage, described so far, was followed by a second in which an important restauration took place. The west wall, which had shown signs of weakness, was rebuilt along nearly 40 meters, this time with regular blocks of limestone bound together with lime. Rectangular pillars, encroaching on the garden, marked off rhythmical intervals of the wall. At the same time, fill added to the north west corner raised its level nearly a meter. Excavation of this fill yielded numerous fragments of furniture and of construction material, including nearly 50 fragments of Campana plaques. These fragments permit the dating of this whole operation to the beginning of the second century.
A third stage corresponds to the late use of the garden. In the southwest was installed the shop of a tile maker. North of the west end of the pool, near one of the niches, stuck against two buttresses of the wall were built small baths. They had a warm room with the pool in a little apse and a tepid room on little piles. Heating was provided by an exterior fireplace in a court. Since the pool was still filled with water, to connect to two halves of the area without a long detour around an end, a bridge was built over the pool. It rested on monolithic piles made from re-used columns. Some fifty coins and a purse lost at the bottom of the pool date this transformation to the second quarter of the fourth century.
The abandonment of the garden marked its fourth and final stage. Gradually, the pool filled in and the baths crumbled. At the end of the fourth or beginning of the fifth century, several burials were made in the area, notably in hypocaust under the collapsed baths, in tombs covered with tiles placed to form a little gabled roof or in African amphora.
In an effort to determine whether the garden was ornamental or productive, Philippe Boissinot, undertook a study of traces of planting in a area that was sealed in antiquity by the collapse of the enclosing wall. A series of pits could be clearly excavated (Fig. 1&amp;amp;2) Rectangular holes in lines corresponding to grape cultivation were associated with bigger pits, without doubt those of the trees that supported the vines. This method of viticulture, widespread in antiquity but rarely identified in the south of France, may well be suggested. The second zone investigated, against the southeast wall, was without doubt an orchard.
Images   Fig. 1 The Villa de Muscapeu     Fig. 2 The Villa de Muscapeu   Dates Bibliography   D. CARRU, D. LAVERGNE, J. MOURARET, Caumont-sur-Durance, Saint-Symphorien, in Bilan scientifique de la région Provence Alpes-Côte d’Azur, S.R.A, D.R.A.C, Marseille, 2002, P. 181-183.
  D.CARRU, Caumont sur Durance – Saint Symphorien, in Archéologie en Vaucluse, Journal d’information du service archéologique départemental de Vaucluse, 37, déc. 2002, P. 5.
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa des Baumelles</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_syr_sur_mer_var_83/villa_des_baumelles/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2020 00:08:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_syr_sur_mer_var_83/villa_des_baumelles/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location saint_cyr_sur_mer
saint_cyr_sur_mer (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Suburban Villa de la Brunette
Villa Villa des Baumelles
Keywords  aqueducts opus signinum colonnades stairs porticoes mosaics (visual works) reception rooms peristyles (columnades) triclinia  Villa Description On a cliff overlooking the sea stood a elegant maritime villa in what is now the quarter of the Baumelles. Excavations go back to the eighteenth century, but new researches were carried out between 1969 and 1973. The first building, dating from the times of Augustus or Tiberius was replaced during the last quarter of the first century by a grand residential villa which existed until the end of the fourth century, though there are traces, such as coins, of very late occupancy even into the fifth century. The luxurious pars urbana covered 1.4 hectares, while the pars agrarian spread out to the south. The villa was supplied with drinkable water by an aqueduct.
The villa descends, level by level, over several terraces that go down to the southwest towards the sea. The top terrace, in the northeast, opens to the southwest onto an interior garden [1] 32 meters wide with a rectangular pool (2.4 by 14.5 meters) coated with opus signinum. To the northeast, a colonnade (4.8 meters deep and 43 meters long) formed the façade in front of a residential wing, probably accessed by stairs. From the portico behind the colonnade, paved with a white mosaic and with walls covered in marble, opened three reception rooms [ 3, 4 and 5]. The garden was bordered by a buttressed wall which marks its limit. Along the southwest side ran a gallery in which a collector caught the rain water and drained it towards the pool [7] which could overflow into a channel leading to the sea. This sector was not all built at the same time.
To the southwest, a second residential complex, closer to the sea, was developed around a vast garden [8] surrounded by a peristyle with brick columns. The mosaics of the rooms of the northeast wing have been destroyed while the rooms of the southeast wing still have their marble plates and their mosaics in place. This wing is enriched by a series of beautiful reception rooms [9 to 12], of which [12], opening onto the portico, is considered a triclinium. The western and southern limits of the peristyle are poorly known.
An 80-meter gallery running the full length of the villa served as the southwest façade beside the sea. Its stone columns rested on cubical bases. To the south rose a tower, doubtless a belvedere [16], which was perhaps balanced by a symmetric one at the other end of the gallery.
To the south, a charming apartment overlooked the cove of the Madrague and may have been winter living quarters. Below, on the lowest level, another court [14] reached by stairs [13], was embellished by a large rectangular pool (9.92 by 6.15 meters) with an apse at either end. The pool was lined with opus signinum with quarter-round molding for waterproofing in the corners. Steps descended into this pool, and at the foot of the steps a lead pipe was found. The villa also had two facilities for heated baths, one at each end of the façade towards the sea.
Garden Description Plans   Plan of Villa des Baumelles   Dates Bibliography   Brun, Jean-Pierre. Carte Archéologique De La Gaule: 83, Le Var 1. Paris, 1999, vol.2, P. 639-649, plan P. 641. (worldcat)
  Bouet, Alain, and Philippe Leveau. Les Thermes Prives Et Publics En Gaule Narbonnaise. S.l.: s.n., 1996, P. 293-294. (worldcat)
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>21, rue Séguier, An Agricultural Establishment</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/nemausus/21_rue_seguier_an_agricultural_establishment/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 00:12:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/nemausus/21_rue_seguier_an_agricultural_establishment/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location nemausus
nemausus (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation 21, rue Séguier, An Agricultural Establishment
House 21, rue Séguier, An Agricultural Establishment
Keywords  amphorae (storage vessels) flowerpots porticoes  House Description This site is east of the ancient town, 300 meters from the wall of High Empire times. It was found during an emergency salvage excavation of rue Séguier in 1992-93. An agricultural use of the soil during the second and first centuries B.C. is indicated by ceramics for carrying waste water to the fields and by planting holes. Then a building was constructed around A.D. 30 only to be rapidly abandoned between A.D. 70 and 80. The stones of the building were carried off at the end of the first century, and two burials made around 80-100. The house is organized around a rectangular courtyard (14.3 by 9 meters) surrounded by galleries known on three sides and presumed on the fourth. The floor of these passage ways was of pounded earth covered, in places, by a bed of fragments of amphora and dolia.
In the central part of the courtyard were found a series of horticultural pots, some in place in their trench, others uncovered during the excavation. A total of nine pots were found during the excavation of the whole sector. Three were discovered in situ in the courtyard against the north-west wall. Two more were found at the ends of the gallery in trenches dug after the house was abandoned to get out the stones of the adjacent walls. These pots the excavator placed in the corners. Two more have been restored in the alignment at equal distance from the others, modern operations having disrupted this part of the line. The excavator thus reconstructed a line of seven pots presumably for ornamental plantings along the outside of the portico.
Plans   Fig. 1 Plan of 21, rue Séguier, An Agricultural Establishment     Fig. 2 Detail plan of 21, rue Séguier, An Agricultural Establishment   Dates B.C. 1-100 Agricultural use of the soil A.D. 30 A building constructed A.D 70-80 The building abandoned A.D 80-100 Two burials made
Bibliography   J.L. Fiches, A. Veyrac, Nîmes, CAG, 30/1, 1996, P. 127.
  Y. Manniez, A. Recolin, fiche Nîmes, 21, rue Séguier (Gard) in Forme de l’habitat rural en Gaule Narbonnaise, n° 2, ed. APDCA, Juan-les-Pins, 1994, 6 p.
  S. Barberan, Un aménagement horticole dans la cour d’un établissement pré-urbain à Nîmes (Gard) in Bulletin de l’Ecole antique de Nîmes, P. 67-22.(worldcat)
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7008371
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Baths of La Planchette</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/alba_helviorum/baths_of_la_planchette/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 00:12:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/alba_helviorum/baths_of_la_planchette/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location alba_helviorum
alba_helviorum (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Baths of La Planchette
Garden Baths of La Planchette
Keywords  bathhouses (water recreation structures) gutters (building drainage components) apsed pools  Garden Description To the northeast there are the baths of la Planchette, today backfilled. This bath complex of modest dimensions may have been attached to the northeast angle of the court of the house. It is surrounded on the exterior by a large gutter for rainwater. To the northeast of the bath building a rectangular pool has been found of about 3.5 x 2 m and having a semicircular apse with a diameter of 2 m. It is without doubt an ornamental pool belonging to the exterior garden associated with the baths. The nature of the ground surface around it is unknown. At the time of its discovery, the pool still had a water supply pipe of lead.
Plans   Fig.1 Plan of Baths of La Planchette_1     Fig.2 Plan of Baths of La Planchette_2   Dates Bibliography   La Maison Urbaine D&amp;rsquo;époque Romaine: Atlas Des Maisons De Gaule Narbonnaise. Vaucluse: Service d&amp;rsquo;archéologie du Conseil général de Vaucluse, 1996, P. 82-83. (worldcat)
  Chr. Fraisse, J. Dupraz, L’Ardèche, CAG 07, Gap, 2001, P. 155-156.
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 8712431
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Domus de La Marseillaise</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/nemausus/domus_de_la_marseillaise/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 00:12:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/nemausus/domus_de_la_marseillaise/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location nemausus
nemausus (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Domus de La Marseillaise
House Domus de La Marseillaise
Keywords  porticoes mosaics (visual works) exedrae (site elements) pilasters  House Description 390 meters north of the Maison Carrée, salvage excavations in 1966 found this dwelling dating from the high Empire and in use for some two centuries. The main entrance was probably on the south. The building was organized around a courtyard with porticos, paved with white mosaics, on three sides. From them, open the living spaces of the house. Onto the northern wing opens the principal room (19.6 square meters) in the form of an exedra flanked by two pilasters. It opens entirely onto the northern gallery. {What does “entirely” mean? }
At the time of the excavation, the central part of the courtyard (32.5 square meters) contained only earth. A trench cut at that time by V. Lassalle revealed a depression filled with stones which may indicate a pool that was suppressed at a later stage. The presence, in a first phase, of a garden with a pool of unknown size is possible. At a certain time, the courtyard was modified, destroying the pool and putting a wall on the line of the stylobate of the northern portico, thus reducing the view and the lighting of the principal room.
Plans   Plan of Domus de La Marseillaise   Dates A.D. 40-60 Built
Bibliography   Archéologie À Nîmes: Bilan De 40 Années De Recherches Et Découvertes : 1950-1990 : Ville De Nîmes, Musée Archéologique, Juin 1990. Nîmes: Musée archéologique, 1990, P. 141-144. (worldcat)
   J.L. Fiches, A. Veyrac, Nîmes, CAG, 30/1, 1996, P. 127.    P.Gros, J. Guyon, Ph. Leveau, dir.,La maison urbaine d&amp;rsquo;époque romaine, Atlas des maisons de la Gaule narbonnaise, t. II, Doc. d&amp;rsquo;Archéol. Vaucl, 6, 1996, Nîmes, fiche n°3 P. 194-195.(worldcat)
  M. Monteil, Nîmes antique et sa proche campagne, Monographie d&amp;rsquo;Archéologie Méditerranéenne, 3, 1999, P. 139-144.(worldcat)
  Garmy, Pierre, and Martial Monteil. Le Quartier Antique Des Bénédictins À Nîmes (gard): Découvertes Anciennes Et Fouilles, 1966-1992. Paris: Editions de la Maison des sciences de l&amp;rsquo;homme, 2000, P. 64-73.(worldcat)
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7008371
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Edifice of the Platform</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/forum_julii/edifice_of_the_platform/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 00:12:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/forum_julii/edifice_of_the_platform/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location forum_julii
forum_julii (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Edifice of the Platform
Garden Edifice of the Platform
Keywords  vestibules courtyards peristyles (Roman courtyards) cisterns (plumbing components) opus sectile (visual works) porticoes  House Description This construction is situated in the southeast corner of Network B of the town plan, near the port. The parcel has a surface 8,422 square meters with 6,860 for the habitation properly speaking and a covered useful surface of 3390 square meters. The present construction goes back to the end of the first century B.C., between 30 and 10 B.C., but there was an anterior condition. The edifice was lavishly decorated and underwent multiple rearrangements in second century and then again in late antiquity.
At the north, a large vestibule gives access to a vast courtyard with a peristyle [2] of 41.5 meters by 45 meters around which the residence is organized. This court was not a garden but rather was paved with flagstones and sloped, according to Charles Texier, to collect the rain water into a mighty central subterranean cistern that was covered by a rectangular ornamental pool of 9.5 by 12.5 meters. This cistern would have made the residence self-sufficient in water. The peristyles and courts that led to the apartments with many rooms seem also to have had no gardens, for the surface was hard, either of concrete or opus sectile. It is on the outside that a garden would have been developed, on the south façade of the construction along a portico or gallery; the garden [26] of 900 square meters of arable land was limited by the rampart to the south. It would have offered a panorama on the port and plain.
Plans   Edifice of the platform   Dates Bibliography   Bouet, Alain. La Maison Urbaine D&amp;rsquo;époque Romaine: Atlas Des Maisons De Gaule Narbonnaise. Vaucluse: Service d&amp;rsquo;Archéologie du Conseil Général de Vaucluse, 1996, P. 94-96, fiche n°2, P. 104-105 (worldcat)
  RIVET, D. BRENTCHALOFF, S. ROUCOLE, S. SAULNIER, Fréjus, Atlas topographique des villes de gaule méridionale, R.A.N., supplément 32, Montpellier, 2000, P. 251-257. (worldcat)
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7008791
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Horticultural pots</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/nemausus/horticultural_pots/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 00:12:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/nemausus/horticultural_pots/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location nemausus
nemausus (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House B, Les Villégiales, quarter of the Benedictines
21, rue Séguier, An Agricultural Establishment
House House B, Les Villégiales, quarter of the Benedictines
21, rue Séguier, An Agricultural Establishment
Keywords  oscilla  Element Description The archeologists of Nîmes have been particularly sensitive to the presence of horticultural pots. Besides those noted above (House B des Villégiales and 21, rue Séguier), Sébastien Barberan has noted their discovery, out of context, in several excavations: in 1982 at St. Joseph’s clinic; in 1993, seven pots at îlot Grill near the amphitheater; and in 1996, at the Ilôt Thérond and in the excavation for the “Quick”.
Plans Dates Bibliography  S. Barberan, Un aménagement horticole dans la cour d’un établissement pré-urbain à Nîmes (Gard) in Bulletin de l’Ecole antique de Nîmes, P. 71, n.8.(worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7008371
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House B, Les Villégiales, quarter of the Benedictines</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/nemausus/house_b_les_villegiales_quarter_of_the_benedictines/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 00:12:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/nemausus/house_b_les_villegiales_quarter_of_the_benedictines/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location nemausus
nemausus (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House B, Les Villégiales, quarter of the Benedictines
House House B, Les Villégiales, quarter of the Benedictines
Keywords  opus signinum reception rooms ditches water wells  House Description This site is 300 meters east of the big spring de la Fontaine at the foot of Mt. Cavalier. The house, discovered during an emergency dig in 1991-92, is not well preserved. Built in the middle of the first century, it seems to have existed until the middle of the second century. Though not very luxurious, it had however some opus signinum with geometric patterns of tessera. It is noteworthy, however, that in contrast to other houses in Nîmes of the same period, it seems to have had running water supplied by lead-lined canals in a utility tunnel in direct connection to the town water house. Covering a little more than 170 square meters, the dwelling is organized around a garden, which has been explored in an area of 8 by 6 meters, but which must have been somewhat longer and probably had an area of about 72 square meters. Along the east, west, and north sides ran galleries paved in opus signinum with inlays. On the north side, slightly off-center toward the west, there was a small reception room in the form of an exedra (4.8 by 3.8 m).
Planting in the garden is well attested by the discovery of nine horticultural pots of globular, ovoid, or truncated conical form made of a pale clay with three fairly large holes on the base of the pot. In all cases where the bottom was present, it had been scooped out before firing. {Does “scooped out” make sense?} They were found in place in circular ditches or at the extremities of long, parallel trenches which may have played a role in the irrigation of the plants. There seems to have been a certain symmetry in the placement of the pots relative to the two straight ditches.
The site had not been disturbed, whence the good state of preservation of the pots, but palynological analysis has not been able to establish the species of the plants on the basis of pollens. Post holes near the trenches, of which three have been identified thanks to wedging stones still in place, may indicate the presence of stakes to support climbing plants.
At the south of the garden there is a well which may have supplied the house before the connection to city water was installed; it could also have been used to water the garden. The absence of ceramic material in the ditches makes precise dating of them impossible, but the general context suggests a date in the first century A.D. for the establishment of the garden. A dump dug in the garden allows dating of one of the principal phases of occupation of the building to A.D. 60 to 90.
Plans   Fig. 1 Plan of House B, Les Villégiales, quarter of the Benedictines     Fig. 2 Plan of House B, Les Villégiales, quarter of the Benedictines   Dates A.D. 1-100 Built A.D. 60-90 One of the principal phases of occupation
Bibliography   J.L. Fiches, A. Veyrac, Nîmes, CAG, 30/1, 1996.
  P.Gros, J. Guyon, Ph. Leveau, dir.,La maison urbaine d&amp;rsquo;époque romaine, Atlas des maisons de la Gaule narbonnaise, t. II, Doc. d&amp;rsquo;Archéol. Vaucl, 6, 1996, Nîmes, fiche n°6 P. 200-201.(worldcat)
  M. Monteil, Nîmes antique et sa proche campagne, Monographie d&amp;rsquo;Archéologie Méditerranéenne, 3, 1999, P. 130-135.(worldcat)
  Garmy, Pierre, and Martial Monteil. Le Quartier Antique Des Bénédictins À Nîmes (gard): Découvertes Anciennes Et Fouilles, 1966-1992. Paris: Editions de la Maison des sciences de l&amp;rsquo;homme, 2000, P. 74-90, P 173-181.(worldcat)
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7008371
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House C, Les Villégiales, quarter of the Benedictines</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/nemausus/house_c_les_villegiales_quarter_of_the_benedictines/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 00:12:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/nemausus/house_c_les_villegiales_quarter_of_the_benedictines/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location nemausus
nemausus (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House C, Les Villégiales, quarter of the Benedictines
House House C, Les Villégiales, quarter of the Benedictines
Keywords  stairs  House Description House C is 300 meters east of the source of the big spring at the foot of Mt. Cavalier, at the northwest point of an block of houses and bordered by a north-south road paved with flagstones. Built during the years A.D. 40 – 60, it seems to have been occupied until the middle of the second century. {I do not understand “IIe dernier”: “the second last.” ???} The surface explored during the salvage excavations in 1991 covers about 810 square meters, with about 300 square meters of useful covered surface. The eastern part is unknowable because of destruction by modern operations. This part would have brought the total surface to more than 1000 square meters. How the whole of the place worked together remains, however, very hard to follow, for there has been an almost total loss of the floors and thresholds of the living areas. At a break in the slope of the land on the north side was placed a utility tunnel with lead pipes for bringing in running water. It defines the northern limit of the house. On the south, a courtyard [1], associated with a frequently rearranged zone [2] was bordered on the north by a series of three rooms with floor levels differing by 70 cm to 1 meter. Such a pronounced difference in levels would imply stairs in front of these spaces, but none has been found. This courtyard of at least 111 square meters yielded only a few traces of the paleosol on the bedrock. In a circular pit 3.90 meters in diameter and a little off-center to the south, was a pool. While the outside was circular, the inside – the space filled with water &amp;ndash; was a hexagonal with 1.2 meter sides. Its 40-cm deep inside was lined with hydraulic cement, and its bottom rested on a series of limestone flagstones which seem to plug a round cistern (1.18 meters in diameter) which belonged to an earlier condition of the house. Flanking the pool on either side, two dolia {(large, ceramic, roughly spherical tanks)} may have stored water or served as planters.
Plans   Fig. 1 Plan of House C, Les Villégiales, quarter of the Benedictines     Fig. 2 Plan of House C, Les Villégiales, quarter of the Benedictines     Fig. 3 Plan of House C, Les Villégiales, quarter of the Benedictines   Dates A.D. 40-60 Built
Bibliography   J.L. Fiches, A. Veyrac, Nîmes, CAG, 30/1, 1996.
  P.Gros, J. Guyon, Ph. Leveau, dir.,La maison urbaine d&amp;rsquo;époque romaine, Atlas des maisons de la Gaule narbonnaise, t. II, Doc. d&amp;rsquo;Archéol. Vaucl, 6, 1996, Nîmes, fiche n°6 P. 202-203.(worldcat)
  M. Monteil, Nîmes antique et sa proche campagne, Monographie d&amp;rsquo;Archéologie Méditerranéenne, 3, 1999, P. 130-139.(worldcat)
  Garmy, Pierre, and Martial Monteil. Le Quartier Antique Des Bénédictins À Nîmes (gard): Découvertes Anciennes Et Fouilles, 1966-1992. Paris: Editions de la Maison des sciences de l&amp;rsquo;homme, 2000, P. 74-76, P 83-88.(worldcat)
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7008371
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House Formigé Square - 2 phases</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/forum_julii/house_formige_square_2_phases/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 00:12:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/forum_julii/house_formige_square_2_phases/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location forum_julii
forum_julii (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House Formigé Square-2 phases
House House Formigé Square-2 phases
Keywords  vestibules atriums porticoes fountains  House Description The house found under Formigé square lies 200 m south of the intersection of the cardo maximus and the decumanus maximus at 150 meters from the quays of the port. It is in the southwest quarter of Insula A of the network of the city. A parcel of 462 square meters has been recovered with a useful covered surface of about 342 square meters. To the south it is paralleled by a decumanus and by other habitations to the north and east. The principal entrance was probably on the south. What may be called the first stage of construction, though it replaced a previous condition, seems to go back to around A.D. 1 – 5. In this condition, it was occupied until A.D. 60 – 70. Its pavements have been preserved, along with a large part of its painted decoration up to a considerable height.
One enters the house on the south from the edge of the street by a wide entrance with a floor of pounded earth, which accommodates a bench. At the end of the vestibule, there is an atrium [2] of 9.2 by 10.54 meters, around which the house is organized. The impluvium was surrounded by low walls on which an imaginary garden was painted. In a second phase, nine planters filled with earth were arranged on three sides of the impluvium.
Around A.D. 65 – 70, the house entered a second stage which lasted three and a half centuries. It was enlarged over a two-meter deep fill on which was planted a garden [1] of 12.5 by 10 meters, framed by a portico [2] and bordered on the south by four rooms. The portico was 2.8 meters wide, including the stylobate. The courtyard of the first condition was transformed into a rectangular pool (9 by 2.2 m) divided into two parts by a low wall with a fountain to the north and two rectangular planters (each 1.7 by 0.7 m ) on the south.
Plans   Fig. 1 Plan of the House Formigé Square-2 phases   images   Excavation of the House Formigé Square     Axon of the House Formigé Square   Dates A.D. 1-5 First Stage of Construction A.D. 65-70 Second Stage of Construction
Bibliography   Bouet, Alain. La Maison Urbaine D&amp;rsquo;époque Romaine: Atlas Des Maisons De Gaule Narbonnaise. Vaucluse: Service d&amp;rsquo;Archéologie du Conseil Général de Vaucluse, 1996, fiche n°3, P. 110-111, fiche n°4, P. 112-113. (worldcat)
  RIVET, D. BRENTCHALOFF, S. ROUCOLE, S. SAULNIER, Fréjus, Atlas topographique des villes de gaule méridionale, R.A.N., supplément 32, Montpellier, 2000, P. 195-198. (worldcat)
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7008791
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Silver Bust, La Vilasse Quarter</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/forum_julii/house_of_the_silver_bust_la_vilasse_quarter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 00:12:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/forum_julii/house_of_the_silver_bust_la_vilasse_quarter/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location forum_julii
forum_julii (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House of the Silver Bust, La Vilasse Quarter
House House of the Silver Bust, La Vilasse Quarter
Keywords  bathhouses (water recreation structures) vestibules columns (architectural elements) peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes reception rooms pergolas ditches  House Description This house was in a central residential quarter across the street (rue des Boutiques) from the public baths of the town center. Unearthed between 1924 and 1946, it occupied a parcel of 4354 square meters with a useful covered surface of 1957.3 square meters. The condition now shown goes back to the second half of the first century; though previous states are possible, nothing is known of them. It was subsequently occupied during at least two centuries. There was a fire and doubtless at least partial abandonment in the course of the third century. Its complex plan made it one of the largest grand homes of Vaison during the Flavian epoch. It groups together several elements of distinct origin: one or two houses to the east, one in the center, and a bath structure that was originally public. This development explains the different orientations of these buildings.
To the east, on the “rue des Boutiques,” was the principal entrance: a monumental vestibule paved with flagstones opened directly through a triple bay with two columns onto a peristyle [17] (13 by 8,50 m - 4 by 4 columns) of Tuscan order. The court was probably planted as a garden, but it had no pool. The western portico, somewhat wider than the others, underlined the importance of the reception room [16] which connected with the central part of the house.
A second garden [12] (15 by 13 m) was found in the southern part of the house, lying a meter below the main part and formed by rooms for lodging and reception, though their function is not altogether clear. This garden is dominated on the north by a portico with 7 columns; at each end a flight of steps descended to connect the house to covered walkways (with 5 columns) that extended south to form a U around the garden and delimit the house on this side, for there were no rooms attached. {I need the plan to be sure that I have understood “en U (7 x 5 colonnes)” correctly.} Along the portico on the north was a rectangular pool (10 by 1.5 meters) without water jets; it was originally covered with red tiles which are today much restored. A lead pipe, possibly for drainage, was noted during the excavation.
The spaces [13-14-15], on which little has been published, are badly preserved. Without any real certainty, [13] is considered a reception room at once having a dominating view onto the garden and opening directly past two columns onto a courtyard [14] (13 by 9.50 m) that was perhaps planted. Room [15] constitutes another room separated by a gallery and a portico from the other columns of the space [14]. The excavator, the abbot Sautel, proposed, without evident proof, to cover the space [13] with a pergola. The space [13-14-15], in the axis of the garden [12], formed an alternation of covered and open spaces giving air and light to the center of the house.
The western part of the house has been interpreted as a former public bath complex, with double baths (total surface of 2235 square meters), all subsequently incorporated into the house. The palestra of the bath was converted by the proprietor of the house into a large pleasure garden of 1590 square meters. Of trapezoidal form (36 x 30 m), it is bordered on four sides by a Tuscan portico 3.4 meters wide. Along all sides runs a trench lined with limestone for catching rainwater. The former natatio (14,50 x 4,40 m) in the southwest corner of the palestra became an ornamental pond with an east-west drainage ditch connecting to the sewer that crosses the peristyle.
Midway along the northern portico is placed just at the edge a well with a limestone top that is circular in the part that has been exposed.
In the northeast corner of the peristyle was discovered the famous silver bust which gives its name to the house. This 29.5 cm hight bust, now in the museum of Vaison-la-Romaine, was found in the context of the collapse of the roof of a burned portico. Along with it were found an Antonianus of Tetricus I {????} and two large lead plates of the roof. All of this would seem to give a general date for the abandonment of the garden.
To the north spread out the bath establishment, which continued to serve but as private baths. The space left free to the south of the baths has often been considered to have been a garden, but probably it was only a simple courtyard.
Finally, between the baths to the west and the “rue des boutiques,” the house is dominated on the north by a vast platform lying 3 to 4 meters higher. A rectangular pool (10 x 3,50 m) still preserved there ornamented, according to Sautel, another garden also related to the house, but this remains to be demonstrated. The lack of real excavation makes it impossible to say whether this space contained any construction.
A number of sculptural discoveries are noteworthy. In the vestibule [18] was found half of an oscillum 19 cm in diameter; on one face, a hare nibbles fruits coming out of a wicker basket while on the other are two dolphins in the water. In the east portico of the peristyle [17] was a fragmentary oscillum (26 cm long) in the form of a pelta; one horn terminates in the head of an eagle-griffon. On one of the faces is a mask of a bearded person in profile with frilly hair held by a band; on the reverse is a mask with wavy hair.
Plans   Plan of House of the Silver Bust   Dates Bibliography   P.Gros, J. Cuyon, Ph, Leveau, La maison urbaine d&amp;rsquo;epoque romaine, Atlas des mainsons urbaines en Gaule Narbonnaise, t. II, Doc.d&amp;rsquo;Arch. Vaucl., 6, 1996, fiche n°2, p. 342-345 (worldcat)
  Gros, Pierre. L’architecture romaine: du début du IIIe siècle av. J.-C. à la fin du Haut-Empire. 1, 1,. Paris: A. et J. Picard, 2011, P. 159-161.(worldcat)
  Chr. Goudineau, Y. de Kisch, Vaison-la-Romaine, Guide archéologique de France, 1999, 1ère éd. 1984, P. 28-33; (worldcat)
  Provost, Michel, Joe͏̈l-Claude Meffre, and Dominique Carru. Vaison-la-romaine Et Ses Campagnes. Paris: Académie des Inscriptions et Belles-Lettres, 2003, P.168-80. (worldcat)
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7008791
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House with the Arbor, Puymin Quarter, Formerly called the Praetorium</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/forum_julii/house_with_the_arbor_puymin_quarter_formerly_called_the_praetorium/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 00:12:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/forum_julii/house_with_the_arbor_puymin_quarter_formerly_called_the_praetorium/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location forum_julii
forum_julii (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House with the Arbor, Puymin Quarter, Formerly called the Praetorium
House House with the Arbor, Puymin Quarter, Formerly called the Praetorium
Keywords  praetoriums stairs porticoes water wells triclinia pergolas bathhouses (water recreation structures) colonnades  House Description This house stood southwest of the theater, on the Puymin hill, in the residential northeast quarter of the city. Unearthed between 1927 and 1929, it covered a surface of about 3000 square meters. A first stage was built around 40 – 30 B.C., followed by a considerable extension to the northeast in the first century A.D.. First interpreted as an official residence, a praetorium, by J. Sautel, it takes its present name from an arbor found in the garden. The house, organized on at least three levels, was considerably worn down so that interpreting the different phases is not easy.
Garden Description The residential part best known was organized around a garden 17 by 20 meters, framed by three wings in a U. At the center of the east wing, the bottom of the U, a grand stairway with two {curving?) symmetric ramps framing a niche (possibly for a statue) rose to the second storey where a portico overlooked the garden from three sides. To the west, the fourth side of the garden was closed against the outside by a straight wall. On it was supported a wall accented by a central apse (with a opening of 5.8 meters) centered on the axis of the garden. Along this wall, but separated from it by a space, lie three related pools which are below the garden. Built of masonry, one is semi-circular (3.85 meters in diameter) with a lateral set of stone steps for access, while the other two are symmetrically placed rectangles (2.4 by .85 meters). No water jet was noted. There was also a well with masonry rim in the southeastern part of the garden.
In the axis of the garden but a little off to the west is a structure with masonry walls in the form of a T, 7.15 m long. On top of this wall has been reconstructed without proof a T-shaped arbor shading the site of a summer triclinium. {Is this arbor “reconstitué” mentally or in wood ?} We believe that if there were here a pergola it would have covered a banquet space organized in a T + U shape and built of wood resting on the masonry of which only the T by itself is drawn. {Drawn in what sense?}
To the northeast of the house are remains in which it has been proposed to see a bath with a pool surrounded by a 3-by-5 colonnade. This pool could have also have served as a water reservoir for irrigation of the tree-covered slopes and gardens below the hill of Puymin.
Plans Dates B.C. 40-30 First Stage A.D. 1-100 Considerable extension to the northeast
Bibliography   La Maison Urbaine D&amp;rsquo;époque Romaine. Avignon: Service d&amp;rsquo;archéologie du Conseil général de Vaucluse, 1996, P. 80-81. (worldcat)
  Chr. Goudineau, Y. de Kisch, Vaison-la-Romaine, Guide archéologique de France, 1999, 1ère éd. 1984, P. 74-77; (worldcat)
  Provost, Michel, Joe͏̈l-Claude Meffre, and Dominique Carru. Vaison-la-romaine Et Ses Campagnes. Paris: Académie des Inscriptions et Belles-Lettres, 2003, P.267-274. (worldcat)
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7008791
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House, rue Nationale</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/nemausus/house_rue_nationale/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 00:12:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/nemausus/house_rue_nationale/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location nemausus
nemausus (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House, rue Nationale
House Baths of La Planchette
Keywords  decumanus vestibules peristyles (Roman courtyards) opus signinum gutters (building drainage components)  House Description This house is 240 meters northeast of the Maison Carrée at the angle of rue Nationale and rue la Ferrage on a 250-square-meter parcel. Salvage excavations were conducted in 1978 – 79. The known surface exceeds 140 square meters and one can estimate its total surface to have been between 400 and 600 square meters. It was probably turned towards the decumanus on the south, under the present rue Nationale. The location of the entrance from the outside is not known, but one entered the courtyard by a vestibule on its south side. Construction goes back to the Augustan period, near the year A.D. 1. The house, remodeled in the second half of the first century, was occupied two or three centuries; strata dated from the fourth century indicate abandonment by that time. The best known part is the courtyard with peristyle of 62 square meters and ornamented in its center by a rectangular pool. The galleries were paved in opus signinum sown with little crosses of black tessera.
Only about half of the rather deep pool has survived. The base of a fountain is found to the east of the pool. A gutter leads from this base towards the southeast corner of the peristyle.
Plans   Plan of House, rue Nationale   Dates A.D. 1
Bibliography   J.L. Fiches, A. Veyrac, Nîmes, CAG, 30/1, 1996, P. 375-379
  P.Gros, J. Guyon, Ph. Leveau, dir.,La maison urbaine d&amp;rsquo;époque romaine, Atlas des maisons de la Gaule narbonnaise, t. II, Doc. d&amp;rsquo;Archéol. Vaucl, 6, 1996, Nîmes, fiche n°2 P. 192-193.(worldcat)
  M. Monteil, Nîmes antique et sa proche campagne, Monographie d&amp;rsquo;Archéologie Méditerranéenne, 3, 1999, P. 157-172.(worldcat)
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7008371
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Le Pinard, House A</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/alba_helviorum/le_pinard_house_a/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 00:12:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/alba_helviorum/le_pinard_house_a/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location alba_helviorum
alba_helviorum (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Le Pinard, House A
Garden Le Pinard, House A
Keywords  porticoes triclinia water wells  Garden Description This vast house lies 120 m southwest of the theater in the southern quarter of the ancient town at a place called le pinard, “the wine” from the pinot grape. Partially excavated in 1967-1968, it is still not entirely unearthed. The known portions extend over 1250 m2 of which 715 m2 are useful covered area. The last state is dated to the second century, but one may well suppose that there were earlier states not yet studied or exposed.
The natural slope of the terrain towards the east led to building the house in levels around a central garden [9]. On three sides – north, south, and west – the garden is bordered by a gallery perhaps with a second floor above. The fourth, lower side was closed by a wall. The almost square courtyard, about 17.5 m on each side, was certainly treated as a garden. An ornamental pool is centered on the reception wing on the west side, which is dominated by a large triclinium [6] which opens onto the garden by a large bay. This rectangular pool is about 11 m in length and has the peculiarity that its bottom has two levels differing by about 20 cm although the water surface of the pool is all on the same level. It is terminated on the western, uphill side by a little semicircular apse surmounted by a niche in a mass of masonry. This little structure does not seem to have been intended to be viewed from the triclinium but from the other end of the garden. Into this masonry is integrated a well about 10 m deep, cut into the marl, which functions at the same time as the pool.
Plans   Plan of Le Pinard, House A   Dates Bibliography   Bouet, Alain. La Maison Urbaine D&amp;rsquo;époque Romaine: Atlas Des Maisons De Gaule Narbonnaise. Vaucluse: Service d&amp;rsquo;Archéologie du Conseil Général de Vaucluse, 1996, P. 76-77. (worldcat)
  Chr. Fraisse, J. Dupraz, L’Ardèche, CAG 07, Gap, 2001, P. 153-154
  Gros, Pierre. L’architecture romaine: du début du IIIe siècle av. J.-C. à la fin du Haut-Empire. 1, 1,. Paris: A. et J. Picard, 2011, P. 190-191.(worldcat)
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 8712431
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Le Pinard, House B</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/alba_helviorum/le_pinard_house_b/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 00:12:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/alba_helviorum/le_pinard_house_b/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location alba_helviorum
alba_helviorum (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Le Pinard, House B
House Le Pinard, House B
Keywords  ditches atriums vestibules  House Description This house is also 120 southwest of the theater, in front of house A. Excavated in 1967-1968, the parcel covers 450 sq m, with a useful covered surface of 401.5 sq m. It was constructed in the second century. Only the southwest corner is known; the rest is lost or not excavated.
On entering from the east-west street, after passing through two incidental rooms, one comes into a vast space [1] occupied by a pool of about 2.5 x 3.5 m connected by a ditch to the sewer in the street. This room, in which some see an atrium (?), may be a vestibule with pool connecting with the entrance of which the tower may have been treated as a garden (?). [This makes no sense to me; how can a tower be treated as a garden? Maybe “tour” (tower) was supposed to be “cour” (courtyard).]
Plans   Plan of Le Pinard, House B   Dates A.D 101-200
Bibliography   La Maison Urbaine D&amp;rsquo;époque Romaine: Atlas Des Maisons De Gaule Narbonnaise. Vaucluse: Service d&amp;rsquo;archéologie du Conseil général de Vaucluse, 1996, P. 80-81. (worldcat)
  Chr. Fraisse, J. Dupraz, L’Ardèche, CAG 07, Gap, 2001, P. 154
  Gros, Pierre. L’architecture romaine: du début du IIIe siècle av. J.-C. à la fin du Haut-Empire. 1, 1,. Paris: A. et J. Picard, 2011, P. 190-191.(worldcat)
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 8712431
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Les Basaltes, House A</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/alba_helviorum/les_basaltes_house_a/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 00:12:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/alba_helviorum/les_basaltes_house_a/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location alba_helviorum
alba_helviorum (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Les Basaltes, House A
House Les Basaltes, House A
Keywords  bathhouses (water recreation structures) peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes domus  House Description This house is in the eastern quarter of the town, near the temple of the Basaltes, 200 m to the west of the forum. It lies 35 m to the south of the apparently private baths of la Planchette, near the temple of the Basaltes. Excavated in 1983-1984, the walls are for the most part destroyed down to the level of the foundations. The house covers an area of 632.5 sq m, with a usable covered surface of 356.9 sq m. After a previous state not well known, it was rebuilt between 10 and 20 A.D.. It saw several phases before being abandoned at the end of the third century. The eastern part of the house is unknown.
At the end of the Augustan epoch, a courtyard occupied the southern part of the area, without doubt an area free of construction with an entrance porch on the south [7]. Later, it was rearranged with a space [4] on the west which was long considered agricultural.
A peristyle [15] seems to be starting off towards the north, but its limits are unknown. The stylobate delimiting the west branch of the portico [14] was constructed only in the Flavian period. We know only the southwest corner of the peristyle, however the nature of the surface of the open space has not been ascertained.
At first, this relatively modest dwelling was thought to have perhaps belonged to an artisan or peasant. But the presence of the private baths to the northeast opens the possibility of seeing in it a part of a great domus with porticos and a grand central garden and associated baths. There is, however, a discrepancy between the luxury of the baths and the simplicity of the excavated area of the house, which seems to have been a service or common area.
Plans   Plan of Les Basaltes, House A   Dates Bibliography Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 8712431
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Puymin Quarter,Sanctuary with Portico’s,Formerly called Pompey&#39;s Portico</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/vasio_voncontiorum/puymin_quarter_sanctuary_with_portico_s/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 00:12:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/vasio_voncontiorum/puymin_quarter_sanctuary_with_portico_s/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location forum_juji
forum_juji (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Puymin Quarter, Sanctuary with Portico’s
Garden Puymin Quarter, Sanctuary with Portico’s
Keywords  domus porticoes statues gutters (building drainage components) columns (architectural elements)  Garden Description Located to the east of the house of the Laurel-crowned Apollo, 110 meters south of the theater, the Sanctuary with Porticos is not entirely unearthed and continues under the modern city. Constructed in the course of the first century A.D., the monument was formerly interpreted as a public promenade or a the garden of a vast urban domus. Today it is considered a public edifice, a sanctuary connected perhaps to the cult of the waters. Covering 2,000 to 3,000 square meters, it was organized in at least two terraces overlooking an esplanade with porticos having a large, central, ornamental pool which was probably surrounded by plantings. A street-level, covered walkway of Tuscan order ran 52 meters along the north side, elevated 20 centimeters relative to the garden. In the center of this walkway was a room with an apse holding a central pedestal and two symmetric niches for statues.
A stone gutter to catch rainwater separated the walkway from the garden. One entered the garden through a porch having two columns more massive than the others which supported, no doubt, a higher pediment.
In the center of the court was a monumental pool 9.5 meters wide and 1.6 meters deep, as yet exposed for only 3.1 meters of its length. A large apse ornamented its northern end, and its bottom was paved with flagstones. Necks and bellies of terracotta amphora were inserted horizontally into the masonry to shelter fish. In the center of the pool, a masonry construction with walls 60 centimeters thick seems to have supported a small structure with two square rooms 5.25 meters on a side, perhaps a chapel. Stairs go down into the pool on the west side.
Plans   Plan of Sanctuary with Portico&amp;#39;s   Dates A.D. 1-100 constructed
Bibliography   Chr. Goudineau, Y. de Kisch, Vaison-la-Romaine, Guide archéologique de France, 1999, 1ère éd. 1984, P. 74-77; (worldcat)
  Provost, Michel, Joe͏̈l-Claude Meffre, and Dominique Carru. Vaison-la-romaine Et Ses Campagnes. Paris: Académie des Inscriptions et Belles-Lettres, 2003, P.251-254. (worldcat)
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7008791
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quarter of Saint-Florent – House A1, House of Clodius</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/arausio/quarter_of_saint_florent_house_a1_house_of_clodius/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 00:12:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/arausio/quarter_of_saint_florent_house_a1_house_of_clodius/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location arausio
arausio (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Quarter of Saint-Florent – House A1, House of Clodius
House Quarter of Saint-Florent – House A1, House of Clodius
Keywords  decumanus mosaics (visual works) cubicula (domestic spaces) columns (architectural elements) pilasters porticoes colonnades  House Description House A1, called the House of Clodius, is bordered on the north by a secondary decumanus and has a common wall with other houses on three sides. It seems to have occupied an area of a little more than 450 square meters, but exploration is incomplete on the northeast because of the limits imposed on the excavation. The edifice reached us in very bad condition with many of the stones of its walls carried off. It was built in the Augustan period, somewhere between 10 B.C. and 10 A.D. and was destroyed in 20-30 A.D., perhaps in a flood that struck the town in about 30, as in the quarter of the Cours Pourtoules. In one of the rooms, an inscription in tesserae reads CLODIVS, perhaps gives the name of the proprietor.
The house has an L shape. The rooms were along the north and east side of a rectangular courtyard of nearly 120 square meters; its purpose may have been utility or pleasure. The northern wing was divided relatively symmetrically with a series of residential rooms of large dimensions. This wing was dominated by a large reception room in plan like an up-side-down T (when viewed from the courtyard), which probably served as the triclinium. The rectangle which bounded the T was flanked by two smaller rectangular rooms which, to judge by the two-part mosaic on the floor, would seem to have been cubicula &amp;ndash; bedrooms. (The bed went over the rather plain mosaic, while the elaborate one was free to be enjoyed.)
The presumed triclinium opened through a wide entrance, flanked on either side by a column or pilaster (of which only the bases were found), onto a portico with a colonnade. The space between the columns widened at this point to give an uninterrupted view of the courtyard from the triclinium, a detail which would seem to support the interpretation of the courtyard as a garden.
Plans   Plan of Quarter of Saint-Florent – House A1, House of Clodius   Dates B.C 10-A.D 10 Built A.D 20-30 Destroyed
Bibliography  Bellet, Michel-Edouard. Orange Antique: Monuments Et Musée. Paris: Imprimerie nationale, 1991, P. 229-239 (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7599818
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quarter of Saint-Florent, House A – House of the Mosaic with Meanders</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/arausio/quarter_of_saint_florent_house_a_house_of_the_mosaic_with_meanders/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 00:12:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/arausio/quarter_of_saint_florent_house_a_house_of_the_mosaic_with_meanders/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location arausio
arausio (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Quarter of Saint-Florent, House A – House of the Mosaic with Meanders
House Quarter of Saint-Florent, House A – House of the Mosaic with Meanders
Keywords  peristyles (columnades) columns (architectural elements) reception rooms mosaics (visual works) gutters (building drainage components) porticoes opus signinum  House Description Some years after the destruction by flood of the house of Clodius (NAR15.10), and its neighbor (House A2), their ruins were leveled and this house built upon them. Some authorities place the construction in the last third of the first century, around the year 70; others, sometime in the second century. The dwelling seems to have lasted until about 260-280.
Garden Description The garden was in the square peristyle (9.7 m on a side) with six Corinthian columns on a side. (The east corner has not be found, but can be confidently conjectured, along with the fourth gallery.) The reception room [a] (of nearly 50 sq. m.) was ornamented with a black and white mosaics with meanders of alternating swastikas and squares, filled in with floral motifs, chalices and hederae (ivy). Slightly off-center relative to the garden, it opens through a large bay onto the north gallery of the peristyle, which also has a mosaic. This northern gallery was of the Rhodian type to open a larger view from the main room onto the garden. Just inside the peristyle, a gutter of cut stone caught rainwater from the roofs of the porticoes. A rectangular pool (7.4 x 2.5 m. and less than 70 or 80 cm. deep) running the full length of the north side of the garden occupied more than a third of its space. It was lined in opus signinum and had masonry quarterround in the edges to make them watertight. It was incompletely excavated on the south side and could well have had there a semicircular apse as in the neighboring House with the Polychrome Mosaic. Probably it had a well, as in other parts of Orange, but none has been located. Lying in the pool was found a collection of fragments of lead piping. Presumably, they had been pulled together after the house was abandoned with the intent to reuse them. These pieces permit the conjectural partial reconstruction of the water supply to the pool. The water came, it seems, in a pipe of average diameter, to the northeast corner of the pool, then passed through a truncated cone and came out through a curved section of smaller diameter. The purpose would seem to be to create the pressure necessary for a water jet in a fountain. A rather large sewer collector (30 x 40 cm in section) took the rainwater of the roofs and the overflow of the pool from the northeast corner of the garden and led them away to the north, picking up along the way the waste water of the baths. The overflow from the pool may perhaps have assured the necessary flux in latrines near the baths.
Plans   Plan of Quarter of Saint-Florent, House A – House of the Mosaic with Meanders   Dates B.C 10-A.D 10 Built A.D 20-30 Destroyed
Bibliography   Bellet, Michel-Edouard. Orange Antique: Monuments Et Musée. Paris: Imprimerie nationale, 1991, P. 69 (worldcat)
  Maison 1996, t. II, P. 229-237 and P. 240-242.
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7599818
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Saint-Pierre, House or Public Building</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/alba_helviorum/saint_pierre_house_or_public_building/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 00:12:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/alba_helviorum/saint_pierre_house_or_public_building/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location alba_helviorum
alba_helviorum (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Saint-Pierre, House or Public Building
House Saint-Pierre, House or Public Building
Keywords  porticoes mosaics (visual works) porticoes  House Description Excavations in 1964-1969 on the site of the former [or ancient] church of St. Peter brought partially to light a building with an area of about 1200 sq m. It was constructed towards the end of the first or beginning of the second century, but it is unclear whether it was public or private.
The western wing, of which 30 m is known, has rooms richly decorated with marble plaques, painted surfaces, and white mosaics. It borders a courtyard organized around a rectangular pool. The large room [1] (10.2 x 8 m) is centered on this pool and opens onto a portico with mosaics [5] 3.30 m wide. Against the portico, in the axis of the room [1] was placed a small, almost square pool, 2.40 x 2.6 m. A second pool, dug into the ground of courtyard, measures 8.30 x 12 m. Its walls and surroundings are made of large, rectangular limestone blocks. The limits of the space decorated by this pool are not known.
Plans   Fig.1 Plan of Saint-Pierre, House or Public Building   Dates Bibliography   R. Lauxerois, P. Andre, G. Jourdan, et alii, Alba, de la cité gallo-romaine au village (département de l’Ardèche), Guides archéologiques de la France, 1985, p. 61-62 (worldcat)
  Chr. Fraisse, J. Dupraz, L’Ardèche, CAG 07, Gap, 2001, P. 157-158.
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 8712431
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thès estate, villa of the Peacock</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/vasio_voncontiorum/thes_estate_villa_of_the_peacock/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 00:12:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/vasio_voncontiorum/thes_estate_villa_of_the_peacock/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location forum_julii
forum_julii (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Thès estate, villa of the Peacock
Villa Thès estate, villa of the Peacock
Keywords  mosaics (visual works) reception rooms porticoes fountains pilasters gutters (building drainage components)  Villa Description TThis building, thought to be a suburban villa, is in fact only very partially known. It is situated just at the edge of the town, below the “shopping quarter”. Discovered on property of the Thès family in 1964, it was excavated and studied from 1966 to 1989. The dwelling was built, according to Yves de Kisch, between approximately A.D. 70 and 100. In the Severin period, according to H. Lavagne, it received a rich decoration of homogeneous mosaics. Abandoned at the end of the third century, it shows traces of reoccupation in late antiquity. Only the northern part of the house is known; the wings to the east and west and the southern part were destroyed in the course of earth moving for a modern subdivision. The northern wing is constructed symmetrically relative to the axis of the principal reception room [4], where the peacock mosaic was found which gives the house its name. On the south, this room opened directly, without a portico, onto the courtyard, (25.5 m in the east-west direction) which was undoubtedly treated as a garden. The southern limit is unknown, but a hypothetical reconstruction has made it a rectangle with an area of some 1000 square meters, which seems on the high side. An ornamental fountain, now in ruins, stood in a pool in front of the reception room [4]. Of the fountain there remains only a block of concrete surrounded on three sides by a trench 18 centimeters deep. The pool had a marble revetment, and around it were three flagstones of white molasse (a soft sandstone.) The whole structure occupied a space 4 meters by 1.5 meters. The fountain was fed by a lead pipe, of which a fragment was found.
The façade of the back of the building opened to north by a portico [4], 3.45 meters wide. Beyond it lay an elongated courtyard (38.15 by 5.50 m) paved with concrete. An ornamental fountain with a water ladder was installed in a niche in the middle of the retaining wall in line with the center of the reception room. The top of the semi-dome of the niche has been found. Water supplied through a lead pipe gurgled over white marble steps framed between pilasters, spilled into a polygonal pool about 2.5 meters long, then rushed along a steeply sloped gutter under the reception room and into the courtyard on the south.
Plans   Plan of Villa of The Peacock   Images   Axon of Villa of The Peacock   Dates A.D. 70-100
Bibliography   KISCH, Yves . La Villa Du Paon: Le Quartier Des Boutiques : Vaison-La-Romaine. Vaison-la-Romaine: Mairie, 1990 (worldcat)
  H. Lavagne, Recueil génral des mosaïques de la Gaule romaine, III, province de Narbonnaise 3, partie sud-est, Xe suppl. à Gallia, Paris CNRS, 2000, n° 647-53, p. 157 ss.
  Provost, Michel, Joe͏̈l-Claude Meffre, and Dominique Carru. Vaison-la-romaine Et Ses Campagnes. Paris: Académie des Inscriptions et Belles-Lettres, 2003, P.277-287. (worldcat)
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7008791
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tower Enclosure, Insula III, House IIIA – 3 phases</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/forum_julii/tower_enclosure_insula_iii_house_iiia_3_phases/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 00:12:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/forum_julii/tower_enclosure_insula_iii_house_iiia_3_phases/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location forum_julii
forum_julii (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Tower Enclosure, Insula III, House IIIA – 3 phases
House Tower Enclosure, Insula III, House IIIA – 3 phases
Keywords  porticoes reception rooms domus water wells courtyards fountains water wells vestibules  House Description This house is 65 meters south of the rampart and 120 meters to the west of the theater. It occupies the northeast corner of an insula in network B, in the northeast quarter of the city. The house occupies a parcel of 192 square meters, with a useful covered area of 85.5 square meters. It was bordered on the north by a decumanus and on the east by a cardo with porticos. To the west and south, it had common walls with other habitations. Constructed around A.D. 20-25, the house continued in use for 40 – 45 years.
In the first phase, the house was composed of large rooms around an open space (10 by 5.5 m) that was perhaps a garden [4]. In the northeast corner there was a square masonry mass, 1.6 meters on a side, of unknown function. The court is bordered on the north by a portico [5] 10 meters long and 2.6 meters wide, which connected the rooms on that side of the house. {Literally, “which played the role of space for circulation in leading to the rooms of habitation to the north.”} In the axis of the entrance was the principal reception room.
In a second phase, around A.D. 70, houses IIIa and IIIa’’ were combined. The structure is called “House with the Greek style mosaic.” This new domus occupied a parcel of 375 square meters with a useful covered surface of 199.5 square meters. It adopted an L-shaped plan completed by a rectangular (15.3 by 6 m) garden [1] of 104.5 square meters. The north side of the garden is paralleled by a portico [2] 1.7 meters wide, which provides access to four rooms. In the southwest of the garden there was a well and in line with it one of the principal rooms of the house was arranged. {This makes little sense to me; how can a room be in line with a well? But a literal translation is worse: “… there was a well, in the axis of which one of the principal rooms of the house was arranged.” If the well is round, it has only one axis, and that is vertical! The plan might help.}
In a third and final phase, dated from around the end of the second century, the surface of the parcel grew to 401 square meters, with a useful covered surface 265 square meters. The oecus, or formal dining room, opened through a large bay to the south onto the garden. This courtyard of about 10 by 5.7 meters was certainly treated as a garden. {I do not understand the parenthesis. It seems to be a question by the author to himself.} A small pool of white marble, which runs along the west wing is fed from the north by a water jet that made a fountain. Drainage was through a lead pipe. Behind it was a second pool; at the back, against the wall, it had a narrow space filled with dirt, perhaps a planter for plants to mask the wall which was certainly without openings. This pool, of about 5.7 by 2.1 meters overall, was divided into two by a low wall and included a well at this level. The wall of the south façade is bordered by a drainage gutter. The courtyard was framed on two sides, north and west, by a portico with a space of 2.2 meters between columns, with the third {what?} to the east {from the east?} serving as a vestibule [1]. {I need the plan to know what is being said.} By the large door, one enters the eastern end of a portico 2 meters wide which opens onto the courtyard through a row of brick columns covered with stucco. The west wing has four rooms; the largest, ceremonial room [4] looked out onto the garden with the pool straight ahead.
Plans   Plan of Tower Enclosure, Insula III, House IIIA   Dates A.D. 20-15 First Phase A.D 70 Second Phase A.D. 200 Final Phase
Bibliography   La Maison Urbaine D&amp;rsquo;époque Romaine: Atlas Des Maisons De Gaule Narbonnaise. Vaucluse: Service d&amp;rsquo;archéologie du Conseil général de Vaucluse, 1996, P. 114-115. (worldcat)
  RIVET, D. BRENTCHALOFF, S. ROUCOLE, S. SAULNIER, Fréjus, Atlas topographique des villes de gaule méridionale, R.A.N., supplément 32, Montpellier, 2000, P. 127-128. (worldcat)
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7008791
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Various oscilla</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/nemausus/various_oscilla/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 00:12:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/nemausus/various_oscilla/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location nemausus
nemausus (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation 
House Keywords  oscilla  Element Description These were discovered out of context or the location of the find is not known:
●	A circular oscillum of white marble, 22 cm in diameter, with a theatrical mask, flute, and, to the right, a tambourine under a tree. Discovered around 1770.
●	Fragment of a rectangular oscillum showing, on one side, the leg of an animal supported on a wheel and, on the other, a theatrical mask. (The maximum height of the fragment is 14.5 cm.)
●	A rectangular oscillum with masks (15 by 22 cm). On one side, Ganymede gives drink to the eagle Jupiter; on the other, two theatrical masks.
Plans Dates Bibliography  J.L. Fiches, A. Veyrac, Nîmes, CAG, 30/1, 1996, P. 350, P. 512.  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7008371
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Edifice on St. Antoine’s Mound</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/forum_julii/edifice_on_st.antoines_mound/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Nov 2020 00:20:41 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/forum_julii/edifice_on_st.antoines_mound/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location forum_julii
forum_julii (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Edifice on St. Antoine’s Mound
House Edifice on St. Antoine’s Mound
Keywords  praetoriums courtyards porticoes peristyles (columnades) peristyles (Roman courtyards)  House Description This grand residential edifice may be either a public building or a great mansion. Built on St. Antoine’s mound, it is situated in the southwest corner of network A of the town plan. In immediate proximity of the port, it was first interpreded as the praetorium of the naval arsenal (A. Donnadieu 1932). Then it was assigned the role of residence of the perfect of the fleet or the occasional palace for the governor of the province (P.-A. Février, 1977). Less luxurious than the edifice of the platform (see below), it has been classified in the recent l’Atlas topographique de Fréjus among the public buildings of the city.
Less than half of the plan is known. The residence occupied more than 15,000 square meters, of which at least 6,000 were living space. The construction appears to go back to the first century B.C. with a poorly known prior condition.
The house was organized around a principal courtyard with porticos [1] with concrete floors. Composed of very many rooms, the mansion had a very large axial ceremonial room and four dwelling units, two of which were organized around peristyles leading to the apartments. Only peristyle [11] (5 x 10 m) can have had a garden; it is ornamented by a square pool with a frame about 1.30 meters long on each side.
The residence perhaps enjoyed an exterior garden in the vast open space of arable land along the eastern side of the construction. As in the intervallum of the military camps, some see in the open space a extensive garden estimated at 2,600 square meters. Irregular in shape and enclosed within the rampart, it overlooks the port.
Plans   Edifice on St. Antoine’s Mound   Dates Bibliography   Atlas Des Maisons De Gaule Narbonnaise. Avignon: Service d&amp;rsquo;archéologie du Conseil général de Vaucluse, 1996, P. 94-96 et fiche n°1, P. 100-101. (worldcat)
  RIVET, D. BRENTCHALOFF, S. ROUCOLE, S. SAULNIER, Fréjus, Atlas topographique des villes de gaule méridionale, R.A.N., supplément 32, Montpellier, 2000, P. 278-281. (worldcat)
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7008791
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enclos Milhaud, House of the Sea god</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/aix_en_provence/enclos_milhaud_house_of_the_sea_god/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Nov 2020 00:20:41 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/aix_en_provence/enclos_milhaud_house_of_the_sea_god/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location aix-en-provence
aix-en-provence (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Enclos Milhaud, House of the Sea god
House Enclos Milhaud, House of the Sea god
Keywords House Description fiche not translated
Plans   Enclos Milhaud, House of the Sea god   Dates Bibliography Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7010786
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enclos Milhaud, House with the large peristyle</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/aix_en_provence/enclos_milhaud_house_with_the_large_peristyle/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Nov 2020 00:20:41 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/aix_en_provence/enclos_milhaud_house_with_the_large_peristyle/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location aix-en-provence
aix-en-provence (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Enclos Milhaud, House with the large peristyle
House Enclos Milhaud, House with the large peristyle
Keywords House Description fiche not translatedPlans   Fig.1 Enclos Milhaud, House with the large peristyle   Dates Bibliography   Maison 1996, t. II,, P. 32-33
  “Aix-en-Provence,”Atlas, P. 62-4, 71.
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7010786
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enclos Reynaud, House of the pool with apses</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/aix_en_provence/enclos_reynaud_house_of_the_pool_with_apses/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Nov 2020 00:20:41 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/aix_en_provence/enclos_reynaud_house_of_the_pool_with_apses/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location aix-en-provence
aix-en-provence (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Enclos Reynaud, House of the pool with apses
House Enclos Reynaud, House of the pool with apses
Keywords  peristyles (Roman courtyards) courtyards  House Description According to a partial plan, the residence was organized around a large courtyard with peristyle [1] (14.5 x 8.0 m). Although covered with paving stones in the final phase, the courtyard may have been a garden in an earlier phase, for it had a pool in the center. This pool of an unusal, quadrilobe shape, was 9 meters long and covered in gray marble. This marble was reduced practically to chalk when the house burned. The pool was then used as a dump and was found filled with materials from the time of the invasions.
Plans   Enclos Reynaud,House of the pool with apses   Dates Bibliography   Maison 1996, t. II,, P. 32-33
  “Aix-en-Provence,”Atlas, P. 62-4, 71.
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7010786
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House under the Pasteur parking lot</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/aix_en_provence/house_under_the_pasteur_parking_lot/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Nov 2020 00:20:41 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/aix_en_provence/house_under_the_pasteur_parking_lot/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location aix-en-provence
aix-en-provence (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House under the Pasteur parking lot
House House under the Pasteur parking lot
Keywords  courtyards porticoes mosaics (visual works) statuettes (free-standing sculpture) domus terrace gardens reception rooms mural paintings (visual works) candelabras (candleholders)  House Description In its first phase, the house formed an L around a trapezoidal courtyard [1] (about 23 x 22 m) that was certainly developed as a garden. On the north and east it was bordered by a portico [2] with pilasters of which the foundation blocks remain. The portico (3.5 m wide) was bordered by two rectangular pools (each about 6.7 x 2.5 m) made of concrete with walls coated with cement. They drained to a collector. To the west of the courtyard is a circular well 4 meters deep lined with dressed hard limestone and without a puteal. It is not certain that it comes from Roman times.
The north wing of the house had six domestic rooms with concrete floors. The east side had the grand rooms decorated with mosaics and yielding fragments of wall painting, of marble, and of sculptural debris including a statuette and two marble hands belonging to feminine statues of life size. Further east opened a second garden [16], 10 meters wide and abutting the rampart.
Around the year 70, the house was extended to the south. In this Phase 2 form, it was the largest house as yet uncovered in the city. The excavated useful covered surface is 850 square meters, but it is estimated that the entire parcel was about 2847 square meters. It was on two levels; the new level to the south was about a meter below the original level. On its south side, the house was bordered by a domus not yet excavated, and perhaps the rampart was its northeast limit. It was accessed by a dead-end street running east-west and opening, it would seem, onto the cardo maximus. In this second phase, the house was occupied for two centuries.
Four groups of structures lay in a somewhat staggered pattern. All opened onto gardens through porticoes. The original structure on the upper terrace retained its L form with the north-south arm of the L between two gardens, [1 and 16]. The new, lower terrace was roughly square with portico-bordered gardens in the northeast [27] and southwest [17] quadrants and structures in the other two quadrants. The south garden [17], known only in part, included a rectangular pool and 3-meter wide porticoes on at least the north and east sides. The columns had finely sculptured Corinthian capitals [18]. Among the residential rooms should be noted the vast salon [23] for reception of guests. To the east, two other large rooms, [29] and [30] (12 x 7 m) on the axis of the pool were certainly also used for reception. They had a white mosaic with black framing lines and also beautiful mural paintings of high quality. Panels of cinnabar red were set off by inter-panel areas in Egyptian blue with pictures of theatrical masks hung from candelabra.Plans   House under the Pasteur parking lot_phase1     House under the Pasteur parking lot_phase2   Dates Bibliography   R. Boiron, C. Landure, N. Nin, Les fouilles de l’Aire du Chapitre, actuel parking Pasteur, Documents d’Archéologie aixoise, 2, 1986, P. 13-36(worldcat)
  Maison 1996, t. II,, P. 12-15 and fiche n°4, P. 22-23 ; fiche n°5, P. 24-25
  J. Guyon, N. Nin, L. Rivet, S. Saulnier, Aix-en-Provence,Atlas, P. 65-68 et P.261-277.
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7010786
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aix, Jardins de Grassi, House with the large peristyle</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/aix_en_provence/aix_jardins_de_grassi_house_with_the_large_peristyle/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 00:08:08 -1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/aix_en_provence/aix_jardins_de_grassi_house_with_the_large_peristyle/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location aix-en-provence
aix-en-provence (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Aix, Jardins de Grassi, House with the large peristyle
House Aix, Jardins de Grassi, House with the large peristyle
Keywords  peristyles (Roman courtyards) reception rooms opus sectile (visual works) exedrae (site elements) pilasters columns (architectural elements)  House Description This luxurious residence wrapped around a large (15 x 18 m) peristyle [1] with galleries 3 to 4 meters wide. The center was no doubt a garden. A vast reception room [15], paved with an opus sectile, looked out onto the central axis of the garden. It was flanked by two other handsome rooms; the one to the west [18] also had a marble floor. An exedra [5] with an opus sectile floor opened in the center of the east wing over a wide threshold, embellished on each side by a pilaster and column. Room 14, also with a marble floor, is more withdrawn. The principal reception room opened onto another open space [1], thought to have been 22 meters long by 7 meters wide, delimited at ground level by a stone border. Perhaps treated as a garden, it was made pleasant by two stone basins with water jets placed on the axis of the rooms [18] and [16]. The view was rounded off by the large flattened semicircle of the back (north) wall of the garden.
Plans   Fig 1. House with the large peristyle     Fig 2. House with the large peristyle   Dates Bibliography   Maison 1996, t. II,, p. 30-31
  Atlas De Provence-Côte D&amp;rsquo;azur: 1. Bruxelles: ACTES, 1974, P 62-64 and P261-277.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7010786
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enclos Reynaud, Combination of House with the large opus sectile with House of the semicircular bay</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/aix_en_provence/enclos_reynaud_combination_of_house_with_the_large_opus_sectile_with_house_of_the_semicircular_bay/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 00:08:08 -1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/aix_en_provence/enclos_reynaud_combination_of_house_with_the_large_opus_sectile_with_house_of_the_semicircular_bay/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location aix-en-provence
aix-en-provence (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Enclos Reynaud, House with the semicircular bay, phase I
house Enclos Reynaud, House with the semicircular bay, phase I
Keywords  mosaics (visual works) statues  House Description In the second century, to judge by the style of the mosaics, the two preceding houses, NAR6.3 and NAR6.4, were joined without, however, any major change in plan. Fragments of statues have been found. With an area greater than 1500 square meters, pavements of high quality, and statuary, it must have been an imposing home. It was occupied for some two centuries.
Plans   Combination of House with the large opus sectile with House of the semicircular bay   Dates Bibliography   Maison 1996, t. II,, p. 42-43
  J, Guyon, Nin N, Rivet L, and Saulnier S. Aix-En-Provence (Bouches-Du-Rhône), 1996, P. 50.
  P. Gros, L&amp;rsquo;architecture Romaine: Du Début Du Iiie Siècle Av. J.-C. À La Fin Du Haut-Empire. Paris: A. et J. Picard, 2011, P. 187-188 (worldcat)
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7010786
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NAR 6.3 Enclos Reynaud, House with the large opus sectile, phase I</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/aix_en_provence/enclos_reynaud_house_with_the_large_opus_sectile_phase_i/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 00:08:08 -1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/aix_en_provence/enclos_reynaud_house_with_the_large_opus_sectile_phase_i/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location aix-en-provence
aix-en-provence (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Enclos Reynaud, House with the large opus sectile, phase I
House Enclos Reynaud, House with the large opus sectile, phase I
Keywords  vestibules fountains opus sectile (visual works) courtyards porticoes  Garden Description This site, the northern part of 5 on the plan of Aix, lay 100 meters from the northern limit of the town. It was uncovered in 1842 by earth movers. It has been only incompletely explored, but 980 square meters of surface are known. Originally, it was thought to have been a public building; but it was, in fact, a house. It shares a common wall with the House with the Semicircular Bay (NAR6.4). A decumanus runs along the north side, where the entry is presumed to have been. To judge from the style of the paved floors, the construction goes back to the first century, and it was occupied for at least a century. An earlier structure has been detected by probes. The known part is organized in three distinct, successive spaces on the same axis running to the south. The first space, [9], is probably a vestibule and was ornamented in its first third by a quadrangular fountain of which a square block topped by a water jet was found. Then comes the principal room [2] (11 x 7 m), embellished by a very luxurious, geometric polychrome opus sectile with cross-ruling bands forming squares with rotated squares inside them, all in violet, green, gray, and red marble. In the central square is inscribed a disk. This room opens onto a portico [1] (13.5 x 12 m) around a courtyard or garden with a rectangular pool (11.2 x 6.8 m). East of the principal room [2] is a space thought to have been a rectangular pool [6] (6.0 x 4.2 m) surrounded on two sides by a portico.
Plans   House with the large opus sectile, phase I   Dates Bibliography   Maison 1996, t. II,, p. 30-31, 38-39.
  J, Guyon, Nin N, Rivet L, and Saulnier S. Aix-En-Provence (Bouches-Du-Rhône), 1996, P. 50.
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7010786
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NAR 6.4 Enclos Reynaud, House with the semicircular bay, phase I</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/aix_en_provence/enclos_reynaud_house_with_the_semicircular_bay_phase_i/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 00:08:08 -1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/aix_en_provence/enclos_reynaud_house_with_the_semicircular_bay_phase_i/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location aix-en-provence
aix-en-provence (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Enclos Reynaud, House with the semicircular bay, phase I
House Enclos Reynaud, House with the semicircular bay, phase I
Keywords  vestibules fountains opus sectile (visual works) courtyards  Garden Description On the north side, two rooms [1] and [2] are symmetrically placed on either side of a large axial room [3] (about 6 x 5.3 m) which opened onto the street. Its floor was covered by a white mosaic with black border. On its south side, a semicircular protrusion extended the room across the portico and out into the garden. “At about two thirds of the way from the northern to the southern wall, near the mosaic, the room is crossed by a chain of very hard calcareous stone which seems to have formed a sort of sanctuary or chancel in the part terminated by the rounded bay.” (Rouard, 1842). Beyond, to the south, a large square courtyard [4] (about 8.2 meters on a side) was presumably a garden. It must have been surrounded by a portico 1.7 meters wide; but only the floor, with a white mosaic bordered by the same very hard stone, was discovered.
Plans   House with the semicircular bay, phase I   Dates Bibliography   Maison 1996, t. II,, p. 30-31, 38-39.
  J, Guyon, Nin N, Rivet L, and Saulnier S. Aix-En-Provence (Bouches-Du-Rhône), 1996, P. 50.
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 7010786
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Gilded Stones</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_gilded_stones/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2020 21:26:02 -2400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_gilded_stones/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location saint-roman-en-gal
saint-roman-en-gal (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House of the Ocean Gods
Sublocation Description The northern end of this vast house is just west of the House of Five Mosaics and in the same insula. From the Passage des Grands Entrepôts along this northern limit, it runs over 100 meters southward to the “Voie I” along the south side of the archaeological site. The eastern edge is about 230 meters west of the Rhone. No less than five names have been given to the houses occupying part or all of the site. The following table of these names with approximate dates may help the reader keep them straight. The final house runs just over 100 meters from south to north. The first two houses covered only about the first 66 meters from the south, up to the noticeable kink in the north-south lines. The third house in the above list, the House of the Large Peristyle, was limited to the area north of this kink. The fourth house combined these two, while the last rebuilt the whole area keeping only the outline and a few walls. We describe the houses in chronological order. All plans for these houses are from La maison des dieux ocean, Equipe archèologique departmentale de Saint-Romain-en-Gal, published by Aglas, 1996.
House House of Gilded Stones
Keywords  peristyles (Roman courtyards) courtyards columns (architectural elements) fountains mosaics (visual works) porticoes  House Description  The living space was organized in U on three side of a garden with peristyle. An entrance on the south formed part of a porch [1] which led to the large vestibule [8] (8.5 x 6.4 m) which opened directly onto the peristyle [23]. From the stratigraphy of the soil it is not possible to know whether this peristyle court was planted or whether it was tamped earth. This courtyard (15.7 x 11.4 m) with an open area of 230 square meters is surrounded on all four sides by porticoes 2.5 meters wide. The columns have disappeared. A column with a phallus-formed top formed a fountain that was perhaps part of the décor of the peristyle; the column rested on a socle pierced by a channel for a conduit of lead which continued through the center of the column. A rectangular pool (7 x 3 m) with a semicircular apse of 2.5 meter diameter, perhaps ornamented by a fountain, occupied the northern half of the central area of the peristyle court. A lead pipe coming from the baths supplied water. The drain cut diagonally across the southern half of the courtyard and continued to the wall along the east side of the house, where it turned and ran parallel to this wall down to the channeled stream on the other side of the street to the south of the house.. On the west were rooms with concrete floors, perhaps bedrooms, except for the central room of the wing [16] (5 x 4.2 m) with a somewhat elevated floor in opus signinum. On the axis of the pool, to the north, was the most spacious room [20] (60 square m) which served as a triclinium; its presumed mosaic is totally lost. Room [18], with a mosaic floor, could have been a summer dinning room in connection with this garden, especially because of its position to the north. Further to the north, at the back of the lot, the house had a large garden [25] of 276 square meters with a portico [24] along the south side, 18.6 meters in length and 3 meters wide, with a floor of pounded earth. Below this portico lay a garden of 276 square meters, which one entered no doubt by steps. Study of the soil has not been able to determine how the place was planted. Was it a pleasure garden or a kitchen garden?
Plans   Plan of House of the Gilded Stones   Dates A.D. 20 – A.D. 60
Bibliography   Laroche, H. Savay-Guerraz, E. Chantriaux et al. Guides Archéologiques De La France. Saint-Romain-en-Gal: Conseil général du Rhône, Equipe archéologique de Saint-Romain-en-Gal, 1984, P. 46-57worldcat
  Maison 1996, t.II, p. 364-383
  Delaval, Eric, and Hugues Savay-Guerraz. La Maison Des Dieux Océan: (ier Siècle Avant J.-C. _ Iie Siècle Après J.-C.). Saint-Romain-en-Gal: AGLAS, 1996.worldcat
  Desbat, Armand. La Maison Des Dieux Océan À Saint-Romain-En-Gal (rhône). Paris: CNRS éditions, 1994, P. 86-132worldcat
  Prisset, Jean-Luc, Laurence Brissaud, and Odile Leblanc. Evolution Urbaine À Saint-Romain En-Gal: La Rue Du Commerce Et La Maison Aux Cinq Mosaïques. Paris: CNRS éd, 1994, P. 1-133. worldcat
  Gros, Pierre. L&amp;rsquo;architecture Romaine Du Début Du Iiie Siècle Av. J.-C. À La Fin Du Haut-Empire: 2 Maisons, Palais, Villas Et Tombeaux Paris: Picard, 2001, p. 160-162.worldcat
  Bouet, Alain, and Isabel Figueiral. Les Thermes Privés Et Publics En Gaule Narbonnaise. Rome: École française de Rome, 2003, P. 269-271, fig 189.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 5004109
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Cistern</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_the_cistern/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2020 21:26:02 -2400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_the_cistern/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location saint-roman-en-gal
saint-roman-en-gal (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House of the Ocean Gods
Sublocation Description The northern end of this vast house is just west of the House of Five Mosaics and in the same insula. From the Passage des Grands Entrepôts along this northern limit, it runs over 100 meters southward to the “Voie I” along the south side of the archaeological site. The eastern edge is about 230 meters west of the Rhone. No less than five names have been given to the houses occupying part or all of the site. The following table of these names with approximate dates may help the reader keep them straight. The final house runs just over 100 meters from south to north. The first two houses covered only about the first 66 meters from the south, up to the noticeable kink in the north-south lines. The third house in the above list, the House of the Large Peristyle, was limited to the area north of this kink. The fourth house combined these two, while the last rebuilt the whole area keeping only the outline and a few walls. We describe the houses in chronological order. All plans for these houses are from La maison des dieux ocean, Equipe archèologique departmentale de Saint-Romain-en-Gal, published by Aglas, 1996.
House House with the Cistern
Keywords  porticoes courtyards  House Description This house was exposed during a programmed excavation from 1981 to 1985. It occupies a plot of 1338 square meters facing Voie I, on which it opens through an entrance in the center of its façade. This phase, called the House with the Cistern, was constructed in the last years of the Augustan period on the site of an earlier building, itself Augustan and probably also a dwelling. It was occupied 20 to 25 years before being remodeled. In its unusual quadrilateral shape, no two sides were parallel, but the west and south sides were perpendicular, and the interior walls ran parallel to one or the other of them. The average width (in the east-west direction) was 24 meters and average length 66 meters. The construction was organized around three sides of the courtyard [12] (10 x 8 m); it may have been planted or may have had a simple earthen floor. To the north, a second open space, a court or a garden [17] (roughly 27 x 15 m) took up a third of the lot. A cylindrical structure [16] three meters in diameter, interpreted as a cistern, occupies an extension off the southeast corner. Nearly all of the floors are of pounded earth. Numerous areas of painted plaster have been discovered in the thirteen rooms that ring three sides of the courtyard [12]. However, the quality of the construction remained ordinary. Plans Dates B.C. 20 - A.D. 20
Bibliography   Laroche, H. Savay-Guerraz, E. Chantriaux et al. Guides Archéologiques De La France. Saint-Romain-en-Gal: Conseil général du Rhône, Equipe archéologique de Saint-Romain-en-Gal, 1984, P. 46-57worldcat
  Maison 1996, t.II, p. 364-383
  Delaval, Eric, and Hugues Savay-Guerraz. La Maison Des Dieux Océan: (ier Siècle Avant J.-C. _ Iie Siècle Après J.-C.). Saint-Romain-en-Gal: AGLAS, 1996.worldcat
  Desbat, Armand. La Maison Des Dieux Océan À Saint-Romain-En-Gal (rhône). Paris: CNRS éditions, 1994, P. 86-132worldcat
  Prisset, Jean-Luc, Laurence Brissaud, and Odile Leblanc. Evolution Urbaine À Saint-Romain En-Gal: La Rue Du Commerce Et La Maison Aux Cinq Mosaïques. Paris: CNRS éd, 1994, P. 1-133. worldcat
  Gros, Pierre. L&amp;rsquo;architecture Romaine Du Début Du Iiie Siècle Av. J.-C. À La Fin Du Haut-Empire: 2 Maisons, Palais, Villas Et Tombeaux Paris: Picard, 2001, p. 160-162.worldcat
  Bouet, Alain, and Isabel Figueiral. Les Thermes Privés Et Publics En Gaule Narbonnaise. Rome: École française de Rome, 2003, P. 269-271, fig 189.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 5004109
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Large Peristyle</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_the_large_peristyle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2020 21:26:02 -2400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_the_large_peristyle/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location saint-roman-en-gal
saint-roman-en-gal (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House of the Ocean Gods
Sublocation Description The northern end of this vast house is just west of the House of Five Mosaics and in the same insula. From the Passage des Grands Entrepôts along this northern limit, it runs over 100 meters southward to the “Voie I” along the south side of the archaeological site. The eastern edge is about 230 meters west of the Rhone. No less than five names have been given to the houses occupying part or all of the site. The following table of these names with approximate dates may help the reader keep them straight. The final house runs just over 100 meters from south to north. The first two houses covered only about the first 66 meters from the south, up to the noticeable kink in the north-south lines. The third house in the above list, the House of the Large Peristyle, was limited to the area north of this kink. The fourth house combined these two, while the last rebuilt the whole area keeping only the outline and a few walls. We describe the houses in chronological order. All plans for these houses are from La maison des dieux ocean, Equipe archèologique departmentale de Saint-Romain-en-Gal, published by Aglas, 1996.
Garden House of the Large Peristyle
Keywords  peristyles (columnades) colonnades peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes  Garden Description  Only its eastern end has been uncovered, and of the rooms for living &amp;ndash; presumably to the west – very little is known. What is known is a large peristyle of unusual form with a center certainly planted as a garden. The long axis of the peristyle ran almost due north to make an angle of about 80 degrees with the street along the north and with the axis of the living areas of the house to the west. The form of the peristyle (32.5 x 18 m with porticoes 3.7 meters wide) would have been a fairly normal, slightly trapezoidal “rectangle” with the south side missing were it not that more than half of the west side was also missing. The colonnade on that side ran straight into a wall, presumably of the neighbor’s house, which jutted out into the southwest corner of our owner’s elegant peristyle courtyard and garden. In the northern part of the courtyard, the presence of a U-shaped channel pool seems well attested but is not shown on the plan.
Plans   house of the large peristyle   Dates A.D. 20-A.D 60
Bibliography   Laroche, H. Savay-Guerraz, E. Chantriaux et al. Guides Archéologiques De La France. Saint-Romain-en-Gal: Conseil général du Rhône, Equipe archéologique de Saint-Romain-en-Gal, 1984, P. 46-57worldcat
  Maison 1996, t.II, p. 364-383
  Delaval, Eric, and Hugues Savay-Guerraz. La Maison Des Dieux Océan: (ier Siècle Avant J.-C. _ Iie Siècle Après J.-C.). Saint-Romain-en-Gal: AGLAS, 1996.worldcat
  Desbat, Armand. La Maison Des Dieux Océan À Saint-Romain-En-Gal (rhône). Paris: CNRS éditions, 1994, P. 86-132worldcat
  Prisset, Jean-Luc, Laurence Brissaud, and Odile Leblanc. Evolution Urbaine À Saint-Romain En-Gal: La Rue Du Commerce Et La Maison Aux Cinq Mosaïques. Paris: CNRS éd, 1994, P. 1-133. worldcat
  Gros, Pierre. L&amp;rsquo;architecture Romaine Du Début Du Iiie Siècle Av. J.-C. À La Fin Du Haut-Empire: 2 Maisons, Palais, Villas Et Tombeaux Paris: Picard, 2001, p. 160-162.worldcat
  Bouet, Alain, and Isabel Figueiral. Les Thermes Privés Et Publics En Gaule Narbonnaise. Rome: École française de Rome, 2003, P. 269-271, fig 189.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 5004109
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Ocean Gods</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_the_ocean_gods/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2020 21:26:02 -2400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_the_ocean_gods/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location saint-roman-en-gal
saint-roman-en-gal (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House of the Ocean Gods
Sublocation Description The northern end of this vast house is just west of the House of Five Mosaics and in the same insula. From the Passage des Grands Entrepôts along this northern limit, it runs over 100 meters southward to the “Voie I” along the south side of the archaeological site. The eastern edge is about 230 meters west of the Rhone. No less than five names have been given to the houses occupying part or all of the site. The following table of these names with approximate dates may help the reader keep them straight. The final house runs just over 100 meters from south to north. The first two houses covered only about the first 66 meters from the south, up to the noticeable kink in the north-south lines. The third house in the above list, the House of the Large Peristyle, was limited to the area north of this kink. The fourth house combined these two, while the last rebuilt the whole area keeping only the outline and a few walls. We describe the houses in chronological order. All plans for these houses are from La maison des dieux ocean, Equipe archèologique departmentale de Saint-Romain-en-Gal, published by Aglas, 1996.
Garden House of the Ocean Gods
Keywords  porticoes  Garden Description A century passed before further major modifications. Then the eight columns of the vestibule on the south were removed, and the mosaic floor with the heads of the ocean gods in the four corners (which gives its name to the house) was installed there. In the middle was of the vestibule was a circular pool (diameter 2.5 m) with water jets. North of the first peristyle garden, a huge room [14] was created connecting the first peristyle to the second. In the following peristyle [19], the U-shaped pool with the water jets was eliminated, though the rectangular pool (6.30 x 2.50 m), lined with white marble at the south end of the peristyle was kept. Its bottom was 40 centimeters below the level of the floor of the south portico. Several ovoid horticultural pots (oleae perforatae) in common pale earth ceramic were found against the north wall of this pool. The rest of the north end of the house remained unchanged. It should be added that the area [29] west of large room [30] may have been a third garden.
Plans Dates A.D. 185-A.D 247
Bibliography   Laroche, H. Savay-Guerraz, E. Chantriaux et al. Guides Archéologiques De La France. Saint-Romain-en-Gal: Conseil général du Rhône, Equipe archéologique de Saint-Romain-en-Gal, 1984, P. 46-57worldcat
  Maison 1996, t.II, p. 364-383
  Delaval, Eric, and Hugues Savay-Guerraz. La Maison Des Dieux Océan: (ier Siècle Avant J.-C. _ Iie Siècle Après J.-C.). Saint-Romain-en-Gal: AGLAS, 1996.worldcat
  Desbat, Armand. La Maison Des Dieux Océan À Saint-Romain-En-Gal (rhône). Paris: CNRS éditions, 1994, P. 86-132worldcat
  Prisset, Jean-Luc, Laurence Brissaud, and Odile Leblanc. Evolution Urbaine À Saint-Romain En-Gal: La Rue Du Commerce Et La Maison Aux Cinq Mosaïques. Paris: CNRS éd, 1994, P. 1-133. worldcat
  Gros, Pierre. L&amp;rsquo;architecture Romaine Du Début Du Iiie Siècle Av. J.-C. À La Fin Du Haut-Empire: 2 Maisons, Palais, Villas Et Tombeaux Paris: Picard, 2001, p. 160-162.worldcat
  Bouet, Alain, and Isabel Figueiral. Les Thermes Privés Et Publics En Gaule Narbonnaise. Rome: École française de Rome, 2003, P. 269-271, fig 189.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 5004109
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Vestibule with Columns</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_vestibule_with_columns/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2020 21:26:02 -2400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_vestibule_with_columns/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location saint-roman-en-gal
saint-roman-en-gal (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House of the Ocean Gods
Sublocation Description The northern end of this vast house is just west of the House of Five Mosaics and in the same insula. From the Passage des Grands Entrepôts along this northern limit, it runs over 100 meters southward to the “Voie I” along the south side of the archaeological site. The eastern edge is about 230 meters west of the Rhone. No less than five names have been given to the houses occupying part or all of the site. The following table of these names with approximate dates may help the reader keep them straight. The final house runs just over 100 meters from south to north. The first two houses covered only about the first 66 meters from the south, up to the noticeable kink in the north-south lines. The third house in the above list, the House of the Large Peristyle, was limited to the area north of this kink. The fourth house combined these two, while the last rebuilt the whole area keeping only the outline and a few walls. We describe the houses in chronological order. All plans for these houses are from La maison des dieux ocean, Equipe archèologique departmentale de Saint-Romain-en-Gal, published by Aglas, 1996.
House House of Vestibule with Columns
Keywords  porticoes vestibules colonnades columns (architectural elements) fountains triclinia mosaics (visual works) reception rooms  House Description  In phase I, the house had the L-shape due to the combination of the two previous houses. The main entrance was from the south, past a portico façade, and into a vestibule (12.9 x 11.9 m) that had a double colonnade. A square pool (4 x 4 m) with a water jet occupied its center. To the east and west, the vestibule was framed by rooms and shops. Beyond the vestibule, one came to the first garden [13]. It had a peristyle on four sides (13.5 x 12 m) with an open area of 167 square meters, porticoes 3 meters wide, and columns 3.3 meters high. A rectangular pool (3.5 x18 m) on the axis covered the central third of the garden. A masonry base of a fountain, statue or other ornament was found in the west part of the garden. North of the peristyle, in the center of the main building, was one of the main reception rooms of the house, on the axis of the pool. This triclinium (7.7 x 6.3 m) apparently had a mosaic that has been lost. The surrounding rooms are of small dimensions except for [15], a second reception area. Farther north, a portico [20] opens onto an esplanade [19] which makes the transition from one of the former houses to the other. The level of this free space was 1.4 meters above that of the garden ahead; stairs to the left and right led down. This second large garden (35 x 30 m), open towards the south, is surrounded on the other three sides by a peristyle with porticoes 3.7 meters wide. A channel pool 1.5 meters wide runs around the three sides of the peristyle. It has been proposed to see in room [25] (54 m2) a cold-weather dining room. The west gallery of the portico opened through three doors to the rooms of the building to the northwest. The space [28], with a pounded earth floor may have been intended as another reception room that was not finished. Beyond the corridor [31] there may have been more open space.
Phase III, from around the end of the first century, carried the ideas of Phase II into the first or southern peristyle garden. The pool in the center was converted into space for planting while a U-shaped channel pull was run around the east, south and west sides, while a wider, separate, rectangular pool ran along the north side. The south side had an apse projecting into the garden.
Plans NEW WAY ↓↓  plan of House of Vestibule with Columns   Dates A.D. 60 -A.D. 185
Bibliography   Laroche, H. Savay-Guerraz, E. Chantriaux et al. Guides Archéologiques De La France. Saint-Romain-en-Gal: Conseil général du Rhône, Equipe archéologique de Saint-Romain-en-Gal, 1984, P. 46-57worldcat
  Maison 1996, t.II, p. 364-383
  Delaval, Eric, and Hugues Savay-Guerraz. La Maison Des Dieux Océan: (ier Siècle Avant J.-C. _ Iie Siècle Après J.-C.). Saint-Romain-en-Gal: AGLAS, 1996.worldcat
  Desbat, Armand. La Maison Des Dieux Océan À Saint-Romain-En-Gal (rhône). Paris: CNRS éditions, 1994, P. 86-132worldcat
  Prisset, Jean-Luc, Laurence Brissaud, and Odile Leblanc. Evolution Urbaine À Saint-Romain En-Gal: La Rue Du Commerce Et La Maison Aux Cinq Mosaïques. Paris: CNRS éd, 1994, P. 1-133. worldcat
  Gros, Pierre. L&amp;rsquo;architecture Romaine Du Début Du Iiie Siècle Av. J.-C. À La Fin Du Haut-Empire: 2 Maisons, Palais, Villas Et Tombeaux Paris: Picard, 2001, p. 160-162.worldcat
  Bouet, Alain, and Isabel Figueiral. Les Thermes Privés Et Publics En Gaule Narbonnaise. Rome: École française de Rome, 2003, P. 269-271, fig 189.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 5004109
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>La Plaine, House A under the High School</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_b_under_the_high_school/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2020 21:26:02 -2400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_b_under_the_high_school/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location saint-roman-en-gal
saint-roman-en-gal (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House B under the High School
Sublocation Description Garden La Plaine, House B under the High School
Keywords Garden Description Plans   Plan of La Plaine, House B under the High School   Dates Bibliography   Maison 1996, t. II,, p. 362-363
  Lancha, Janine. Recueil General Des Mosaïques De La Gaule: Iii. Paris: CNRS, 1981, P. 302-307.worldcat
  M. Leglay, Informations archéologiques, in Gallia, 29, 2, 1971, P. 424-425.worldcat
  M. Leglay, “Les jardins à Vienne,” in Seventh Dumbarton Oaks Colloquium on the History of Landscape Architecture, Ancient Roman Gardens, Washington, 1981, P. 57-58.worldcat
  Bouet, Alain, and Isabel Figueiral. Les Thermes Privés Et Publics En Gaule Narbonnaise. Rome: École française de Rome, 2003, P. 275-277, Fig. 195.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 5004109
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>La Plaine, House A under the High School</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/la_plaine_house_a_under_the_high_school/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2020 21:26:02 -2400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/la_plaine_house_a_under_the_high_school/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location saint-roman-en-gal
saint-roman-en-gal (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation La Plaine, House A under the High School
Sublocation Description House La Plaine, House A under the High School
Keywords  domus peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes courtyards reception rooms  House Description This vast domus (120 x 60 m) presumably had its principal, monumental entry on the south side, along the Street of the Port. The south peristyle [6] (approximately 13.7 x 9.3 m) was surrounded by four porticoes with floors of terrazzo signinum. Three of them were 2 meters wide; the fourth, on the north, was 3 meters wide and gave access to the principal room [17].
The courtyard of this peristyle was certainly used as a garden. It had a rectangular pool (8.2 x 6.5 m) and within this pool, at the northern end, a semicircular pool. On the axis of the pool, the reception room [17] (11 x 10 m) served also as a transition to the second peristyle [33] with an open area (about 29.3 x 41.3 m) no doubt planted as a garden. The three-meter wide galleries of the porticoes gave access to a whole series of large rooms, one of which [39] had an apse on the outside, west wall. In the center of the garden was placed a first pool of 3 by 5 meters. To the south, a long, narrow second pool in front of room [17] has been only partially excavated. Along the north side of the courtyard was a rectangle (28.2 x 3.4 m) of water with an unusual apse in the center of its south side in the shape of a brace or accolade. In this apse was found a lead pipe. Against this apse was another pool, a square 5.8 meters on a side. The revetment of all of the pools in this northern peristyle was of marble.
In the northern wing of the house, a square reception room [53], 5.8 meters on a side, was centered on the axis of the garden. No mosaic was found in it, but the few remaining fragments of the pavement indicate that it was mainly of marble plaques.
Plans   Plan of La Plaine, House A under the High School   Dates Bibliography   Maison 1996, t. II,, p. 358-361
  Lancha, Janine. Recueil General Des Mosaïques De La Gaule: Iii. Paris: CNRS, 1981, P. 302-307.worldcat
  M. Leglay, Informations archéologiques, in Gallia, 29, 2, 1971, P. 57-58.worldcat
  M. Leglay, “Les jardins à Vienne,” in Seventh Dumbarton Oaks Colloquium on the History of Landscape Architecture, Ancient Roman Gardens, Washington, 1981, P. 57-58.worldcat
  Bouet, Alain, and Isabel Figueiral. Les Thermes Privés Et Publics En Gaule Narbonnaise. Rome: École française de Rome, 2003, P. 275-277, Fig. 195.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 5004109
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Columns</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_the_columns/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2020 23:06:02 -2400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_the_columns/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location saint-roman-en-gal
saint-roman-en-gal (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House of the Columns
House House of the Columns
Keywords  peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes reception rooms apsed pools fountains triclinia nymphaea (garden structures)  House Description The house had a linear plan starting from a garden on the south, then on the north side of the garden, a façade gallery, then several rooms, and finally a peristyle on the north. It went through three phases with the changes concentrated on the south garden. In the first phase, this garden [13] (23.5 x 11.5 m) was bordered on the north by a portico [12] 2.5 meters wide. In the garden, adjacent to this portico and directly in front of the principal reception room [8] was a rectangular pool (7.5 x 4 m) with an apse in the center of the south side. It probably had a fountain.
In the second phase, this south garden was reduced by the addition of two lateral porticoes (2.5 m wide) on its east and west sides. In keeping with the local fashion of the time, it was given a U-shaped rill or channel pool running around the outer rim of the garden. A 1.5 meter apse on the north side is slightly off the axis of the reception room [9]. In the center of the garden was a little square pool (1.5 m on a side) with an apse on the north. It was surrounded by benches in a U to form a masonry summer triclinium facing north. On the south side of the benches was a nymphaeum of three niches, a central semicircular one and a rectangular one to either side. At present, a water jet has been put in the middle of each of them. The final phase lasted about fifty years, beginning in the first half of the third century. The south garden was enlarged by the suppression of the east portico. The U-shaped channel pool lost its lateral arms, so that it became a simple rectangle (18 x 1.5 m) and it was made shallower. The apse, in practically the same place, was off-center to the west. The garden kept its summer triclinium and nympheum.
Plans   Fig. 1 Plan of House of the columns_phase1     Fig. 2 Plan of House of the columns_phase2     Fig. 3 Plan of House of the columns_phase2   Dates Bibliography   Maison 1996, t. II,, p. 309-401
  Guide Du Site Saint-Romain-En-Ga. Paris: Réunion des musées nationaux, 1999, P. 36-39.worldcat
  Gros, Pierre. L&amp;rsquo;architecture Romaine Du Début Du Iiie Siècle Av. J.-C. À La Fin Du Haut-Empire: 2 Maisons, Palais, Villas Et Tombeaux Paris: Picard, 2001, p. 189.worldcat
  Recherches Archéologiques a Saint-Romain-En-Gal (1988 - 1990). Vienne, 1992, P. 45-83.worldcat
  Bouet, Alain, and Isabel Figueiral. Les Thermes Privés Et Publics En Gaule Narbonnaise. Rome: École française de Rome, 2003, P. 271-275, fig. 194.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 5004109
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House with the Five Mosaics</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_with_the_five_mosaics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2020 23:06:02 -2400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_with_the_five_mosaics/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location saint-roman-en-gal
saint-roman-en-gal (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House with the Five Mosaics
House House with the Five Mosaics
Keywords  porticoes courtyards peristyles (Roman courtyards) opus signinum opus sectile (visual works) mosaics (visual works) triclinia  House Description Phase I: This phase is sometimes called the “House with the Off-Center Pool.” It occupied an area of 481 square meters with a usable covered surface of 213 square meters. Constructed after 138, it was built in part on the site and foundations of a commercial building going back to the middle of the first century. It was used only twenty to thirty years. It had an elongated, somewhat trapezoidal plan with two groups of rooms, one to the north and one to the south of a peristyle [5]. Most of the walls in short, east-west direction, were not perpendicular to the walls in the long, north-south direction. One entered the house by a modest doorway 1.8 meters wide into a little vestibule [1] which then led directly to the east portico of the courtyard, where presumably a garden grew. The principal room [7] (6.1 x 11.5 m) was on the south of the peristyle (8.5 x 11.5 m), where the gallery was wider and the roof presumably higher than on the other sides. This reception room had a good view of the rectangular pool along the south side of the garden. This 70-centimenter-deep pool (8.35 x 1.8 m) was lined in opus signinum.
Phase II: This phase (called the House of the Five Mosaics by those who call the first phase the House of the Off-center Pool), dates from the end of the second century, probably from 160 - 180. Although more luxurious than the first phase, it nevertheless kept the plan of the original. The covered area was enlarged to 293 square meters; but the garden, though reduced, remained central. The entrance [1] was shifted towards the south and got a more monumental gate 4.25 meter wide. In the southern wing, the main interior walls were rotated from their eastern end to be perpendicular to the north-south walls, with the result that the covered area was enlarged at the expense of the garden, which was reduced to 10-by-8 meters. It was bordered on the north and east by 1.5-meter-wide galleries, while the gallery to the south, though only 1.3 meters wide, had a floor of opus sectile. The east portico [2] became the only way to get from one of groups of rooms to the other. The garden received a U-shaped rill pool lined with white marble; the branches were of different length and less than a meter wide. The space left free at the end of the northern branch of the pool was the only access to the central part of the garden. In the two corners of the pool were found socles for some decorative elements, perhaps statues or fountains. Some parts of valves were found in the overflow from the pool. In the south wing, a large room [8] (7.5 x 7.0 m) opened onto the axis of the garden. With a mosaic of the xenia type, it apparently served as the triclinium. To the east, at the south end of the eastern gallery, was a smaller reception room for visitors [7] (4.0 x 4.5 m). The almost square (5 x 5 m) room [12] at the west end of the northern wing may have been, in the opinion of the excavators, a more familial, every-day triclinium. The house was occupied into the third century, but must have been abandoned, like the rest of the quarter, in the middle of that century.
Plans   Plan of house with five mosaics   Dates Bibliography   Lancha, Janine. Recueil General Des Mosaïques De La Gaule: Iii. Paris: CNRS, 1981, P. 259-286.worldcat
  Guides Archéologiques De La France. Saint-Romain-en-Gal: Conseil général du Rhône, Equipe archéologique de Saint-Romain-en-Gal, 1984, P. 57-58worldcat
  Lancha, Janine. Les Mosaïques De Vienne. Lyon: Presses universitaires de Lyon, 1990, P. 61-75.worldcat
  Recherches Archéologiques a Saint-Romain-En-Gal (1988 - 1990). Vienne, 1992, P. 86-132.worldcat
  Prisset, Jean-Luc, Laurence Brissaud, and Odile Leblanc. Evolution Urbaine À Saint-Romain En-Gal: La Rue Du Commerce Et La Maison Aux Cinq Mosaïques. Paris: CNRS éd, 1994, P. 1-133. worldcat
  Maison 1996, t. II,, p. 384-387
  Guide Du Site Saint-Romain-En-Ga. Paris: Réunion des musées nationaux, 1999, P. 64-69.worldcat
  Gros, Pierre. L&amp;rsquo;architecture Romaine Du Début Du Iiie Siècle Av. J.-C. À La Fin Du Haut-Empire: 2 Maisons, Palais, Villas Et Tombeaux Paris: Picard, 2001, p. 161-162.worldcat
  Bouet, Alain, and Isabel Figueiral. Les Thermes Privés Et Publics En Gaule Narbonnaise. Rome: École française de Rome, 2003, P. 269-271.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 5004109
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House with the Painted Portico</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_with_the_painted_portico/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2020 23:06:02 -2400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_with_the_painted_portico/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location saint-roman-en-gal
saint-roman-en-gal (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House with the Painted Portico
House House with the Painted Portico
Keywords  porticoes courtyards columns (architectural elements) apsed pools  House Description This house was destroyed to build the market and lies under it, but it is partly visible through glass plates in the floor. It was occupied approximately from 60 to 140. The lot covered 947 square meters and has two façade porticoes, one on the rue du Commerce and one on Voie III. The house was arranged around a central trapezoidal courtyard [1] (roughly 7,50 x 6,50 m) which may have been a garden. There were porticoes on only the north and east sides [2 and 3]. They had pounded earth floors; their black and green painted columns give the house its name. A one-meter wide channel pool ran around the north, east and south sides. Later, this pool was made shallower and its bottom covered with a concrete containing calcite crystals. A rectangular pool (5 x 2 m) with an axial apse of 1 meter closed the U-shaped channel pool on the west. A single cutting pot was found during the excavation.
Plans   Plan of house with the painted portico   Dates Bibliography   Maison 1996, t. II,, p. 392-393
  Guide Du Site Saint-Romain-En-Ga. Paris: Réunion des musées nationaux, 1999, P. 52-53.worldcat
  Recherches Archéologiques a Saint-Romain-En-Gal (1988 - 1990). Vienne, 1992, P. 45-83.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 5004109
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House I,  Quartier de la Verrerie at Trinquetaille</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/arelate/house1_quartier_de_la_verrer_at_trinquetaille/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Oct 2020 22:55:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/arelate/house1_quartier_de_la_verrer_at_trinquetaille/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location Arelate
Arelate (Pleiades)
Location Description Arles was one of the pilgrimage sites on route to the Cathedral of Santiago de Compostela. French pilgrimage routes to Compostela tend to follow old Roman roads, many of which continued to be utilized as primary roads of communication during the Middle Ages. Arles was a leading city of the west Roman Empire. It fell under Visigoth control during the 6th century and then under Muslims rule in 730. It has a Roman arena dating to the 1st century BCE, which is presently used for bullfights and plays. It also has many Roman ruins. Arles was home to Vincent van Gogh during a productive period of his career.
Sublocation House I, Quartier de la Verrerie at Trinquetaille
House House I, Quartier de la Verrerie at Trinquetaille
Keywords  mosaics (visual works) opus sectile (visual works) porticoes  House Description This house on the right bank of the Rhone is at [20] on the map. Excavations in 1982-1984, partially uncovered the remains of the building of about 240 square meters. Almost all of the fourteen known rooms of this rich house have mosaic or opus sectile floors. The house revealed by the excavations was built about 180 CE, but three prior phases, from the first and second century, were noted. It was occupied until about 260 and underwent repairs visible in restorations of the mosaics. The free space north of rooms [1], [2] and [9] was probably a garden without porticoes. How far it extended to the north and east is not known.
Plans   Plan of House I, Quartier de la Verrerie at Trinquetaille   Dates Excavations in 1982-1984
Bibliography   Cl. Sintès, Les fouilles de la verrerie de Trinquetaille, in Cl. SINTES, dir., Du nouveau sur Arles antique, Arles, 1987, p. 81-4.   Rouquette, Jean-Maurice, and Claude Sintès. Arles Antique: Monuments Et Sites Paris: Impr. nationale, p. 90-1.(worldcat)
  Pleiades ID 981537 148217
TGN ID 7030317 7008775
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Sucellus</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_sucellus/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 00:31:02 -0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_sucellus/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location saint-roman-en-gal
saint-roman-en-gal (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House of Sucellus
House House of Sucellus
Keywords  domus  House Description On leaving the House of the Lion from its northwest corner, following the rue du Rhône west for 35 meters and turning north on the rue des Thermes for 100 meters, one comes to the area now occupied by two structures, the House of Sucellus to the west and the Edifice with Pillars (Edifice aux piliers) to the east. Originally, the whole area was one house, called the House of the Fishpond (Maison au Vivier), which went through two phases. The space was then completely rearranged in a phase known as the House of the Large Gallery (Maison de la Grande Gallery), which was then transformed to its final state: the House of Sucellus to the west and the Edifice with Pillars to the east. The area was unearthed during a programmed excavation in 1990 and was found well preserved. The total surface area is about 2400 square meters.
Plans   Plan of House of Sucellus   Dates It was completely uncovered in 1987 so that its lines might be respected in the building above it, and then covered over to protect it during construction.
Bibliography   Maison 1996, t. II,, p. 406-411
  Gros, Pierre. L&amp;rsquo;architecture Romaine Du Début Du Iiie Siècle Av. J.-C. À La Fin Du Haut-Empire: 2 Maisons, Palais, Villas Et Tombeaux Paris: Picard, 2001, p. 189-190.worldcat
  Guide Du Site Saint-Romain-En-Ga. Paris: Réunion des musées nationaux, 1999, P. 30,33.worldcat
  Recherches Archéologiques a Saint-Romain-En-Gal (1988 - 1990). Vienne, 1992, P. 45-83.worldcat
  Bouet, Alain, and Isabel Figueiral. Les Thermes Privés Et Publics En Gaule Narbonnaise. Rome: École française de Rome, 2003, P. 271-275, fig.194.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 5004109
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Fishpond</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_the_fishpond/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 00:31:02 -0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/house_of_the_fishpond/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location saint-roman-en-gal
saint-roman-en-gal (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation House of the Fishpond
Garden House of the Fishpond
Keywords  domus  Garden Description In the course of the second century, some two meters of fill was added to the garden to bring it up to the same level as the rest of the house. The use of the space was completely inverted. Rooms were built on the filled-in garden, and the former house was torn down to become a garden. This new house continued to occupy the whole insula. No plan is available for this house, but the new eastern part would be practically completely preserved in the next house. To the east now extended the new garden, which may possibly have preserved three branches of the channel-pool of the earlier house.
Plans   house of the fishpond   Dates Bibliography   Maison 1996, t. II,, p. 406-411
  Gros, Pierre. L&amp;rsquo;architecture Romaine Du Début Du Iiie Siècle Av. J.-C. À La Fin Du Haut-Empire: 2 Maisons, Palais, Villas Et Tombeaux Paris: Picard, 2001, p. 189-190.worldcat
  Guide Du Site Saint-Romain-En-Ga. Paris: Réunion des musées nationaux, 1999, P. 30,33.worldcat
  Recherches Archéologiques a Saint-Romain-En-Gal (1988 - 1990). Vienne, 1992, P. 45-83.worldcat
  Bouet, Alain, and Isabel Figueiral. Les Thermes Privés Et Publics En Gaule Narbonnaise. Rome: École française de Rome, 2003, P. 271-275, fig.194.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 5004109
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The House of the Lion</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/the_house_of_the_lion/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 00:06:02 -0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/saint_roman_en-gal/the_house_of_the_lion/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location saint-roman-en-gal
saint-roman-en-gal (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation The House of the Lion
House The House of the Lion
Keywords  domus mosaics (visual works) courtyards peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes  House Description This house is today, as when it was built, only a few meters back from the right bank of the Rhone. It is now under the museum. It was completely uncovered in 1987 so that its lines might be respected in the building above it, and then covered over to protect it during construction. The museum sits above it on pilings so that at some future time the house can again be unearthed. It was built in the second century, covered a surface of more than 2500 square meters, and was occupied 100 to 150 years before being destroyed by the river. The name comes from a mosaic of a lion found in room [10] and now in the museum. The insula is separated into two parts by an east-west wall. It is difficult to determine whether the structures on either side are two halves of the same house or two different houses. However, the northern part was composed mainly of reception areas and lacked service rooms, so the assumption that it was somehow one house seems plausible.
Plans   Plan of the house of the lion   Dates It was completely uncovered in 1987 so that its lines might be respected in the building above it, and then covered over to protect it during construction.
Bibliography   Gros, Pierre. L&amp;rsquo;architecture Romaine Du Début Du Iiie Siècle Av. J.-C. À La Fin Du Haut-Empire: 2 Maisons, Palais, Villas Et Tombeaux Paris: Picard, 2001, p. 189-190.worldcat
  Recherches Archéologiques À Saint-Romain-En-Gal, 1988-1990. Vienne: Société des amis de Vienne, 1992, P.78,81.worldcat
  Bouet, Alain, and Isabel Figueiral. Les Thermes Privés Et Publics En Gaule Narbonnaise. Rome: École française de Rome, 2003, p.259-263, fig. 182-183.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 981537
TGN ID 7030317 5004109
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Domus under the Hôtel d’Assézat</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/tolouse/domus_under_the_hotel_d_assezat/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/tolouse/domus_under_the_hotel_d_assezat/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location Toulouse
Toulouse (Pleiades)
Location Description Toulouse was one of the pilgrimage sites on route to the Cathedral of Santiago de Compostela; French pilgrimage routes to Compostela tend to follow old Roman roads, many of which continued to be utilized as primary roads of communication during the Middle Ages. It is a prehistoric route, taken over by Romans in 106 BCE and then captured by Clovis in 508. Toulouse resisted the crusade against the &amp;ldquo;Albigensian heresy&amp;rdquo; in the early 13th century. It received parlement 1443 and was a witness to the Protestant massacre of 1562 and the scene of the British victory over the French in 1814. Between 1942 and 1944 it was occupied by Nazi rule. There are a number of noteworthy art museum here.Sublocation Domus under the Hôtel d’Assézat
House Domus under the Hôtel d’Assézat
Keywords  domus mosaics (visual works) courtyards peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes  House Description The Hôtel d’Assézat is a Renaissance palace which now houses the art collection of Georges Bemberg. In the heart of Toulouse, it is about 150 meters east of the Pont Neuf, in rue de Metz. After original finds in 1979, further vestiges of a domus came to light during salvage excavations in 1993-1994 in connection with expansion of facilities. After a first phase dating from A.D. 1 – 15, of which remain some painted plaster found in the trenches, there developed in the reign of Tiberius, between 15 and 30, a residence with rooms ornamented with carefully executed mosaics. They were organized around a courtyard for household work, as indicated by a fireplace and a sinkhole for waste water. The surface was tamped earth repaired three times – to judge from the surviving strips – with a new layer of clay. In a new phase, the house was completely remodeled with larger rooms sometime between 40 and 80. It took on a more coherent plan: the open space was transformed into a peristyle with a central garden. It was bordered on the three known sides with porticoes; strangely, no trace of the colonnade of the portico has been found. A shallow, U-shaped pool, of which the long arm on the south was at least 17 meters, runs along three of the sides. The garden side of the frame of the pool, the inside of the U, was marked off rhythmically by a little apse on the west side (the bottom of the U) and a rectangular notch on the northern arm, presumably matched by one on the south, though the poor condition of the remains makes any interpretation risky. The central part of the U remained free of any construction and is considered the garden. The bottom of the 90- centimeter-wide channels that formed the pool was hydraulic cement. Since they were 50 centimeters below the floor of the porticoes, these channels must have served to catch rain water as well as to embellish the garden. In a later phase, the bottom of the channels was covered with marble flagstones, which left their imprint in the mortar. The domus must have continued to exist beyond the first century, but no precise evidence of change has been detected before the great modifications of the holding which came in the fifth century.
Plans   Plan of Domus under the Hôtel d’Assézat   Dates After original finds in 1979, further vestiges of a domus came to light during salvage excavations in 1993-1994 in connection with expansion of facilities.
Bibliography   Jean. Catalo, Urbanisme antique et médiéval au 4, rue Clémence Isaure In Mémoire de la Société Archéologique du Midi de la France, 56, 1996, p. 51-74.(worldcat)
  Jean. Catalo, Toulouse, 4, av. clémence Isaure/extension de l’hôtel d’Assézat (1993-1994), Archéologie toulousaine, catalogue d’exposition, Musée Saint-Raymond, Toulouse, 1995, p. 184-6.(worldcat)
  Jean-Marie Pailler, l’habitat privé Mémoire de la Société Archéologique du Midi de la France,coll. Ecole Française de Rome 281, 2003, p. 252-54.(worldcat)
  Pleiades ID 981537 2466694
TGN ID 7030317 7008441
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House under the Crédit Agricole</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/arelate/house_under_the_credit_agricole/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_narbonensis/arelate/house_under_the_credit_agricole/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_narbonensis
Gallia_narbonensis (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location Arelate
Arelate (Pleiades)
Location Description Arles was one of the pilgrimage sites on route to the Cathedral of Santiago de Compostela. French pilgrimage routes to Compostela tend to follow old Roman roads, many of which continued to be utilized as primary roads of communication during the Middle Ages. Arles was a leading city of the west Roman Empire. It fell under Visigoth control during the 6th century and then under Muslims rule in 730. It has a Roman arena dating to the 1st century BCE, which is presently used for bullfights and plays. It also has many Roman ruins. Arles was home to Vincent van Gogh during a productive period of his career.Sublocation House under the Crédit Agricole
House House under the Crédit Agricole
Keywords  domus mosaics (visual works) courtyards peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes  House Description This house at [14] on the map, was discovered in 1977 in an emergency salvage excavation. It was constructed about 180 and destroyed in the third quarter of the third century. The portion revealed was composed of four rooms, aligned in an east-west direction, with polychrome mosaic floors and a southern wall that was seemingly without openings. Along the north side, however, was a wide portico giving light and air to the rooms. Beyond it, there extended an area that was perhaps a garden.
Plans   Plan of House under the Crédit Agricole   Dates After original finds in 1979, further vestiges of a domus came to light during salvage excavations in 1993-1994 in connection with expansion of facilities.
Bibliography  J.M. Rouquette, “Les découvertes du Crédit Agricole” in Claude Sintès, dir., Du nouveau sur Arles antique, Arles, 1987, p. 71-7; Maison 1996 t. II, p. 88-89.  Pleiades ID 981537 2466694
TGN ID 7030317 7008441
Contributor Eric Morvillez (ORCID: 0000-0002-7384-1762)
Emilie Chassillan
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
