<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>palaestra on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/palaestra/</link>
    <description>Recent content in palaestra on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 00:10:10 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/palaestra/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Park Area Adjacent to the Great Palaestra and the Amphitheater</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/other_reg_ii/park_area_adjacent_to_the_great_palaestra_and_the_amphitheater/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/other_reg_ii/park_area_adjacent_to_the_great_palaestra_and_the_amphitheater/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region II
Keywords  peristyles palaestra  Garden Description Park-like areas were located between the Great Palaestra and the Amphitheater and to the north. Here booths were set up under trees or awnings and a carnival atmosphere existed as depicted in a painting (Mus. Naz. inv. no. 112 222) found in the peristyle of house I.iii. 23. Two huge root cavities were found in front of the palaestra by Maiuri, although only one was recorded in his plan, and six trees grew in a row on the north side of the palaestra.
Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.I, pp. 13-14, 161-162 (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, pp. 91-92 (worldcat) Maiuri, Notizie degli scavi di antichità, p.194 (worldcat)  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 10 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Great Palaestra; Campus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_vii/the_great_palaestra_campus/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_vii/the_great_palaestra_campus/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region II
Insula Insula VII
Keywords  porticoe palaestra  Garden Description Colonnaded porticoes encircled the palaestra on the south, west and north and a large swimming pool (34.55 x 22.25 m.) was located in the center. Casts made of tree cavities planted eight meters apart in two rows around the north, west and south sides of the enclosed area indicated that these were plane trees, just under one hundred years old.
Plans   Fig. 61, Plan of Region II, insula vii, plan in Maiuri, NSc(1939), pl.9   Pleiades ID 456321707
TGN ID 7004658
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.I, pp. 160-161 and fig. 246 on p. 161 (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p.92 (worldcat) Maiuri, Notizie degli scavi di antichità, p. 193-195 and pl. 9 (plan shows only a part of the root cavities found).(worldcat)  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 10 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forum Baths</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tiffany_fong2/forum_baths/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tiffany_fong2/forum_baths/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Insula VI
House 1/7/8/10
Garden Forum Baths
Keywords  [palaestra] [portico]   Garden Description 555.VI.1/7/8/10. During 1873-1875 the courtyard (a) of the palaestra was excavated. A section of the northeast portico was not excavated until 1930. The courtyard measured 15.75 x 25.25 m. and was bounded by the portico on the west, north and east sides. Engaged columns stood along the south. This area was likely planted after the palestra was built. Although the original excavators labeled this as a garden, no detailed observations were recorded to confirm this supposition.
Plans   Plan of Casa A Graticcio   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1873-1875, 1930
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, 1:165 Maiuri,Herculaneum, p. 40 Maiuri, Ercolano, pp. 91, 100-102 and fig. 68 (plan) on p. 92 Ruggiero, Ercolano, p. 654 and pl. 12, where the garden is no. 55 on the plan.  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
