<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/mauretania/portus_magnus/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2020 10:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/mauretania/portus_magnus/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Large House with peristyle and basins</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/mauretania/portus_magnus/large_house_with_peristyle_and_basins/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2020 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/mauretania/portus_magnus/large_house_with_peristyle_and_basins/</guid>
      <description>Province Mauretania
Mauretania Caesariensis (province)(Pleiades)
Province Description An ancient district of Africa in Roman times, Mauretania lay west of Numidia and covered most of present-day Morocco and western Algeria. By the second century BCE, when Jugurtha of Numidia was rebelling against Rome, Jugurtha’s father-in-law Bocchus had most of Mauretania under his control. In 25 BCE Augustus appointed Juba II as ruler of Mauretania. Claudius divided it into two provinces: Mauretania Caesariensis, with Caesarea (modern Cherchel) as capital, and Mauretania Tingitana, with Tingis (modern Tangier) as capital. By the end of the 5th century CE, the province had disappeared.
Location Portus Magnus \
Portus Magnus (Pleiades)
Location Description The ancient city is located about 5 km from the modern city of Arzew and 35 km northeast of Oran. An important settlement on the west coast of Algeria, it served as a Roman trading post and naval base during the early Roman Empire period.
Garden Large House with peristyle and basins
Keywords  basins (vessels) columns (architectural elements) corridors courtyards peristyles (columnades) peristyle house  Garden Description The house with a symmetrical floor plan and an axial entry was laid out around a peristyle made up of 20 columns. Many rooms opened onto this space, which have contained a garden. Three semicircular basins extended into the courtyard of the peristyle. A circular pool was centered in the courtyard.
A corridor (see Fig. 1, label M) was bordered by two small gardens (labels N and O) enclosed on two sides by a portico. A semi circular basin extend into each garden. A large reception room had a view of the garden and basins.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Large House with peristyle and basins in Portus Magnus (Rights Statement)   Images Dates Excavation Dates Bibliography  S. Gsell, Monuments Antiques de l’Algérie, Paris, 1901, p. 19-21, fig. 87. worldcat  Pleiades ID 553386076
TGN ID Contributor Amina-Aïcha Malek
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Small House with peristyle and basins</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/mauretania/portus_magnus/small_house_with_peristyle_and_basins/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/mauretania/portus_magnus/small_house_with_peristyle_and_basins/</guid>
      <description>Province Mauretania
Mauretania Caesariensis (province)(Pleiades)
Province Description An ancient district of Africa in Roman times, Mauretania lay west of Numidia and covered most of present-day Morocco and western Algeria. By the second century BCE, when Jugurtha of Numidia was rebelling against Rome, Jugurtha’s father-in-law Bocchus had most of Mauretania under his control. In 25 BCE Augustus appointed Juba II as ruler of Mauretania. Claudius divided it into two provinces: Mauretania Caesariensis, with Caesarea (modern Cherchel) as capital, and Mauretania Tingitana, with Tingis (modern Tangier) as capital. By the end of the 5th century CE, the province had disappeared.
Location Portus Magnus \
Portus Magnus (Pleiades)
Location Description The ancient city is located about 5 km from the modern city of Arzew and 35 km northeast of Oran. An important settlement on the west coast of Algeria, it served as a Roman trading post and naval base during the early Roman Empire period.
Garden Small House with peristyle and basins
Keywords  basins (vessels) columns (architectural elements) courtyards peristyles (columnades) peristyle house  Garden Description The house was laid out around a peristyle that may have had a garden. 12 columns surrounded the courtyard, with three semicircular pools extending into it.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Small House with peristyle and basins in Portus Magnus (Rights Statement)   Images Dates Excavation Dates Bibliography  S. Gsell, Monuments Antiques de l’Algérie, Paris, 1901, p. 19-21, fig. 87. worldcat  Pleiades ID 79312
TGN ID Contributor Amina-Aïcha Malek
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
