<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>axial plan on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/axial-plan/</link>
    <description>Recent content in axial plan on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 13:09:50 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/axial-plan/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Dietikon</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/dietikon/dietikon_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 13:09:50 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/dietikon/dietikon_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Province Description Location Dietikon
Dietikon (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Dietikon
Keywords archaeological garden
axial plan
corridors
pergolas
piscinae
porticoes
rural villas
villae rusticae
Garden Description This villa rustica complex was built on a site at the bottom of a valley near and parallel to the river Limmat. Dietikon was situated on an important land and water traffic route from the Bündner Alps to Vindonissa and further north to the Rhine. Recent excavations supply valuable evidence for a garden in front of the entrance to a rural residence, giving insight into the appearance of other similar villas at which, for one reason or another, no physical remains of gardens have been retrieved. The excavations revealed a first villa with timber buildings dating to the Tiberian period, or early 1st century AD. Around the middle of the 1st century AD these first buildings were replaced by an axially-constructed stone-built villa complex with an enclosure, covering a total surface of 13 hectares (Fig.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Palatial House in Insula 7 in Aventicum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_palatial_house_in_insula_7/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 14:48:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_palatial_house_in_insula_7/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Province Description Location Aventicum
Aventicum (Pleiades)
Location Description The town was established in the Augustan period as the civitas capital of the Helvetii. At this time the orthogonal street grid was laid out. Most probably in AD 71, it became Colonia Pia Flavia Constans Emerita Helvetiorum Foederata. The town was destroyed or badly damaged around AD 260, and it was progressively abandoned thereafter.
Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Palatial House in Insula 7 in Aventicum
Keywords archaeological garden
axial plan
bathhouses (water recreation structures)
drains
exedrae (site elements)
mosaics (visual works)
palaces
peristyles (Roman courtyards)
piscinae
presence chambers
Garden Description The remains of a palatial house (Palais de Derrière la Tour) were recently uncovered in excavations on the western edge of the city in an area characterized by luxurious domestic dwellings (Fig. 1). The house in its final state, from the Severan period to the middle of the 3rd century, had a peristyle courtyard measuring 42 x 69 meters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Sudeley/Spoonley Wood</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/sudeley/sudeley_spoonley_wood_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 18:57:34 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/sudeley/sudeley_spoonley_wood_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Sudeley/Spoonley Wood
Sudeley/Spoonley Wood (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Sudeley/Spoonley Wood
Keywords archaeological garden
axial plan
barrier walls
terrace gardens
rural villas
villae rusticae
Garden Description The main residence of this rural estate in Gloucestershire, excavated in 1882, is of the winged corridor type (Fig. 1). From the north and south corners of the house, walls ran in a westerly direction to enclose an open courtyard (G in Fig. 1) approximately 65 meters wide and 45 meters deep from the outer boundary to the main entrance of the house. A paved path was axially arranged in the courtyard to connect the entrance to the courtyard with that of the residential building. The western third of the courtyard is marked off by low scarps which may be remains of garden terraces (T in Fig. 1). Finds from the site indicate a 3rd/4th century date for the complex.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Gorhambury</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/gorhambury/gorhambury_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 10:45:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/gorhambury/gorhambury_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Gorhambury
Gorhambury (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Gorhambury
Keywords arbors
archaeological garden
axial plan
loam
villae rusticae
Garden Description At this site in Hertfordshire near the town of Verulamium (St. Albans) excavations have revealed a multi-phased Roman farm, characterized in late Iron Age and Roman times by an outer courtyard with various service buildings and an inner courtyard in which the farm house stood (Fig. 1).
An avenue 20 meters wide led axially from the gate at the eastern end of the inner courtyard a cross to the front of the house (H in Fig. 1). On either side of the avenue was a line of circular pits spaced 4-6 meters apart (A in Fig. 1). These were filled with fine, homogeneous loam and have been interpreted as planting holes for trees or shrubs. Alternatively, the rows of holes have been interpreted as the postholes of a covered walkway or arbour leading to the house, supporting climbing plants.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Dionyius</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_dionysius/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 20:22:59 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_dionysius/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden House of Dionysius (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords urban villas
villae urbanae
triclinia
insulae
peristyles (Roman courtyards)
apsed pools
axial plan
piscinae
Garden Description The largest urban villa excavated thus far in Cologne is the House of Dionysos (3400 sq. m.), named after the early 3rd century mosaic floor decorated with Dionysiac motifs in the triclinium (Image 1??). The house occupies part of an insula in the northeastern corner of the city, bordered on the south by a street leading to the harbor.
The original house, erected after A.D. 50, was rebuilt under Vespasian and included a peristyle garden courtyard measuring 23 x 27 m.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>