<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>axial plan on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/axial-plan/</link>
    <description>Recent content in axial plan on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 13:09:50 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/axial-plan/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Dietikon</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/dietikon/dietikon_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 13:09:50 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/dietikon/dietikon_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Dietikon
Dietikon (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Dietikon
Keywords  archaeological garden axial plan corridors pergolas piscinae porticoes villae rusticae  Garden Description This villa rustica complex was built on a site at the bottom of a valley near and parallel to the river Limmat. Dietikon was situated on an important land and water traffic route from the Bündner Alps to Vindonissa and further north to the Rhine. Recent excavations supply valuable evidence for a garden in front of the entrance to a rural residence, giving insight into the appearance of other similar villas at which, for one reason or another, no physical remains of gardens have been retrieved. The excavations revealed a first villa with timber buildings dating to the Tiberian period, or early 1st century AD. Around the middle of the 1st century AD these first buildings were replaced by an axially-constructed stone-built villa complex with an enclosure, covering a total surface of 13 hectares (Fig. 1 and 4).
In the residential part of the farm (pars urbana) was a large corridor villa with two protruding wings enclosing a courtyard area on three sides. This area was planted as an ornamental garden in the mid-1st century (Fig 2, G in Fig. 2). On either side of the central path, garden zones were bordered by bedding trenches, 20-25 centimeters deep and 20-40 centimeters wide. The line of plantings flanking the path are curved to form two niches (Fig. 3). In Dietikon, digging of planting trenches would have been necessary because the massive layers of construction debris deposited to level this area for the building would have hampered a successful growing of garden plants. The archaeobotanical analysis of several soil samples revealed little of relevance, but box hedges have been suggested as the vegetation in the bedding trenches, forming a low living edge to these formal garden beds, and possibly climbing plants such as ivy along the porticoed façade. Shallow pits in the plots surrounded by the hedges may be the remains of bedding pits for trees or shrubs. A timber pergola in the courtyard ran parallel to the northeast wing of the house. To the west of the courtyard garden was a timber-lined pool fed by a stream, interpreted as a fishpond. Bedding trenches for hedges surrounded it.
In the late 1st century, around AD 70, the timber-lined pool in the west was replaced by a masonry pool lined with water-proof plaster on the same spot (Fig. 5). This was possibly fed by water from a small stream. At the same time, the timber pergola was dismantled, its place taken by a large masonry pool, 3 x 22 meters in plan. The planting pattern of the courtyard garden was retained (Fig. 5) until after the middle of the 2nd century when the pools were destroyed and the garden leveled.
Plans   Fig. 1: Overall plan of the site during the 2nd half of the 1st century and 1st half 2nd century AD. Plan courtesy of Christa Ebnöther.     Fig. 2: Plan of the main building with its garden, phase 1, ca. 50-70 AD. Plan courtesy of Christa Ebnöther.     Fig. 3: Plan of the main building showing the curved plantings flanking the path. (Rights Statement)   Images   Fig. 4: Reconstructed perspective drawing. (Rights Statement)     Fig. 5: Photo of the masonry pool with planting pattern of the courtyard garden retained. (Rights Statement)   Dates Garden: Late 1st century (~70 CE) - Middle of the 2nd century
First buildings: Early 1st century CE - Middle of 1st century CE
Stone-built villa: Middle of the 1st century CE
Bibliography  C. Ebnöther, &amp;ldquo;Die Gartenanlage in der pars urbana des Gutshofes von Dietikon ZH,&amp;rdquo; Archäologie der Schweiz 14, 1991:250-256. (worldcat) C. Ebnöther, Der römische Gutshof in Dietikon. Monographien der Kantonsarchäologie Zürich 25, Zürich, 1995, pp. 36-45, 49-50, figs. 21, 36-37,41-42. (worldcat) L. Flutsch, U. Niffeler, F. Rossi, eds., La Suisse du Paléolithique à l’aube du Moyen-Age (SPM) V. Epoque romaine/Età Romana, Basel, 2002, p. 143, fig. 140. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981525
TGN ID 7007345
Contributor Christa Ebnöther
Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 15 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Palatial House in Insula 7 in Aventicum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_palatial_house_in_insula_7/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 14:48:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_palatial_house_in_insula_7/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Aventicum
Aventicum (Pleiades)
Location Description The town was established in the Augustan period as the civitas capital of the Helvetii. At this time the orthogonal street grid was laid out. Most probably in AD 71, it became Colonia Pia Flavia Constans Emerita Helvetiorum Foederata. The town was destroyed or badly damaged around AD 260, and it was progressively abandoned thereafter.
Garden Palatial House in Insula 7 in Aventicum
Keywords  archaeological garden axial plan bathhouses (water recreation structures) drains exedrae (site elements) mosaics (visual works) palaces peristyles (Roman courtyards) piscinae presence chambers  Garden Description The remains of a palatial house (Palais de Derrière la Tour) were recently uncovered in excavations on the western edge of the city in an area characterized by luxurious domestic dwellings (Fig. 1). The house in its final state, from the Severan period to the middle of the 3rd century, had a peristyle courtyard measuring 42 x 69 meters. North of the courtyard was a reception room 12 x 18 meters in plan with a mosaic floor.
The courtyard was on two levels, divided on the north by a terrace wall with two small exedrae, possibly pools. An axially arranged central pathway between the reception room on the north and an apsed triclinium on the south further divided the courtyard into an eastern and a western half. Steps led up to the triclinium and to the northern wing of the house. A ground level gutter ran around the courtyard, and a covered drain crossed it beneath the central path. It can reasonably be assumed that the courtyard was designed as a garden (G in Fig. 1) with garden elements such as the path and the exedral pools. With the addition on the northeast of another wing terminating in a bath complex, the building ultimately had a length of around 200 meters. The excavators believe that the building in its latest phase had official character.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the courtyard house or palace on the western fringe of Insula 7, with a garden courtyard (G) with two small apsidal pools on one side. Plan adapted from Morel 1995, fig. 4. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Severnan Period - Middle of 3rd century
Bibliography  J. Morel, “Avenches VD, Derrière la Tour et insula 7 : Fouilles 1989/1990,” Annuaire de la Société Suisse de Préhistoire et d’Archéologie 74, 1991: 214-220, fig. 2. (worldcat) J. Morel, “Avenches, Palais de Derrière la Tour,” Bull. de l’Association Pro Aventico 37, 1995: 206-209, fig. 4.(worldcat) J. Morel, “L’habitat,” in : A. Hochuli-Gysel, ed., Avenches, capitale des Helvètes, Archéologie Suisse 24.1 2001: 47-49, fig. 62.(worldcat)  Pleiades ID 177495
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 14 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Sudeley/Spoonley Wood</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/sudeley/sudeley_spoonley_wood_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 18:57:34 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/sudeley/sudeley_spoonley_wood_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Sudeley/Spoonley Wood
Sudeley/Spoonley Wood (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Sudeley/Spoonley Wood
Keywords  archaeological garden axial plan terrace gardens rural villas villae rusticae  Garden Description The main residence of this rural estate in Gloucestershire, excavated in 1882, is of the winged corridor type (Fig. 1). From the north and south corners of the house, walls ran in a westerly direction to enclose an open courtyard (G in Fig. 1) approximately 65 meters wide and 45 meters deep from the outer boundary to the main entrance of the house. A paved path was axially arranged in the courtyard to connect the entrance to the courtyard with that of the residential building. The western third of the courtyard is marked off by low scarps which may be remains of garden terraces (T in Fig. 1). Finds from the site indicate a 3rd/4th century date for the complex.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the villa with a path (stippled) leading through a courtyard garden (G) and garden. (Rights statement)   Images Dates 3rd/4th century for the complex.
Excavation Dates 1882
Bibliography  Ancient and Historical Monuments in the County of Gloucester Vol. 1. Royal Commission on Historical Monuments of England, London, 1976, pp. 113-114, fig. on p. 114. (worldcat) C. Taylor, The Archaeology of Gardens. Shire Archaeology Series 30, Aylesbury, 1983, pp. 30-31, fig. 1. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 79693
TGN ID 7030316
Contributor Maureen Carroll
ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Gorhambury</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/gorhambury/gorhambury_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 10:45:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/gorhambury/gorhambury_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Gorhambury
Gorhambury (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Gorhambury
Keywords  arbors archaeological garden axial plan loam villae rusticae  Garden Description At this site in Hertfordshire near the town of Verulamium (St. Albans) excavations have revealed a multi-phased Roman farm, characterized in late Iron Age and Roman times by an outer courtyard with various service buildings and an inner courtyard in which the farm house stood (Fig. 1).
An avenue 20 meters wide led axially from the gate at the eastern end of the inner courtyard a cross to the front of the house (H in Fig. 1). On either side of the avenue was a line of circular pits spaced 4-6 meters apart (A in Fig. 1). These were filled with fine, homogeneous loam and have been interpreted as planting holes for trees or shrubs. Alternatively, the rows of holes have been interpreted as the postholes of a covered walkway or arbour leading to the house, supporting climbing plants. This feature of the courtyard is contemporary with the first masonry house built around A.D. 100, and represents an attempt to design the compound fronting the house in a more formal way. After 175 the avenue leading to the rebuilt house seems not to have been flanked by trees or an arbour, and numerous trackways leading into both courtyards from the north and south suggest that the entrance to the main residence was no longer strictly axial.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the farm with two ditched enclosures surrounding the house (H) and an avenue of trees or an arbor (A) leading to it. Adapted from Neal, Wardle, and Hunn. (Rights statement)   Images Dates around A.D. 100 - 175
Bibliography  A. Selkirk, “Gorhambury,” Current Archaeology 87, 1983: 120-121, fig. on p. 116. D.S. Neal, A. Wardle and J. Hunn, Excavation of the Iron Age, Roman and Medieval Settlement at Gorhambury, St. Albans. English Heritage Report 14, London, 1990, p. 44, fig. 56. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 79485
TGN ID 7030316
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Dionyius</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_dionysius/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 20:22:59 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_dionysius/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Garden House of Dionysius (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords  urban villas villae urbanae triclinia insulae peristyles (Roman courtyards) apsed pools axial plan piscinae  Garden Description The largest urban villa excavated thus far in Cologne is the House of Dionysos (3400 sq. m.), named after the early 3rd century mosaic floor decorated with Dionysiac motifs in the triclinium (Image 1??). The house occupies part of an insula in the northeastern corner of the city, bordered on the south by a street leading to the harbor.
The original house, erected after A.D. 50, was rebuilt under Vespasian and included a peristyle garden courtyard measuring 23 x 27 m. (G on Plan 1). The garden was surrounded on three sides by a peristyle, 3.35 m. in width. A ground level gutter ran around the edge of the garden. At this time, a masonry pool with a paved floor occupied a position in the eastern part of the garden. A piece of lead pipe and a bronze opening were found associated with the pool. This was later replaced in the second half of the 2nd century by an apsed pool (4.20 x 5.40 m.) in the western half of the garden which drained into the gutter at the west. The pool was axially arranged between the entrance to the house on the east and the dining room on the west, from which a view through a wide doorway onto the garden was afforded. The triclinium was unheated, leading the excavator to interpret it as a summer triclinium. The connection with the garden would, in this case, be quite understandable. An axial planting pattern in the garden with a path leading from the entrance of the house to the pool is possible. There is, however, no evidence for the planting pattern or the type of vegetation in this garden. The house was inhabited until the 4th century.
Maps   CAPTION   Plans   Plan 1: Plan of the House of Dionysos, built around a central courtyard garden (G) with a pool (grey). Plan adapted from Fremersdorf 1956, fig. 27. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Reign of Vespasian until the end of the fourth century CE
Bibliography  F. Fremersdorf, Das römische Haus mit dem Dionysosmosaik vor dem Südportal des Kölner Doms, Berlin, 1956. (worldcat) M. Carroll, Romans, Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 55, fig. 20. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108751
TGN ID 7004446
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
