<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>gutters on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/gutters/</link>
    <description>Recent content in gutters on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 12:55:08 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/gutters/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Actius Anicetus (I.iii.23)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_23/house_of_actius_anicetus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 12:55:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_23/house_of_actius_anicetus/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 23
Garden I.iii.20/22
Keywords  archaeological garden cisterns (plumbing components) gutters (building drainage components) mural paintings (visual works) peristyles (columnades) porticoes puteal  Garden Description This site was excavated in 1868 revealing a peristyle garden (a) at the rear of the house. A portico on the east and north side was supported by five columns connected by a low wall. There was an opening to the garden on the north. The middle of the garden had two cistern puteals. The west wall of the garden held the famous painting depicting the battle between the Nucerians and the Pompeians in the ampitheator (1.60 m. high by a little less than 2.00 m. wide; Mus. Naz. Inv. No. 112 222; Ruesch no. 1344). This event was recorded by Tacitus (Annals 14.17). A gutter went along the east, south, and north edges of the garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1868
Bibliography  DePetra, GiornSc, n.s., 1 (1865-1869), cols. 185-187 (where the address is given as I.ii). Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 74 and pp. 145-146, no. 401. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., pp. 52-53.(worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 27. (worldcat) Matz, BdI (1869), pp. 240-241. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 78. Niccolini, Case, vol. 4, “Supplemento,” p1. 32. Maiuri, NSc (1939), pp. 168-169. Schefold, WändP, p.12. Sogliano, “Pitture,” p. 204, no.604. Warscher, “Codex.” photos nos. 44-50.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 29 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.iii.20/22</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/houses_20&#43;22/i.iii.20&#43;22/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 13:25:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/houses_20&#43;22/i.iii.20&#43;22/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 20/22
Garden I.iii.20/22
Keywords  altars (religious fixtures) archaeological garden doliums gutters (building drainage components) peristyles (columnades) puteal triclinia  Garden Description At the rear of this house there was a garden (a) with a passageway on the north and the west. The garden had a gutter along the east, north, and west edges. Embedded in the garden were four large dolia. A large triclinium (b) on the east side had a window that looked out into the garden. Fiorelli surmised that the remains of one couch of a masonry triclinium in the west passageway indicated the possible presence of a room that had been destroyed by the earthquake. There was also a small altar on the right side of the peristyle and a terra-cotta puteal in the passageway.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 24, no. 25. Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 73. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., p. 54.(worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 27. (worldcat) Matz, BdI (1869), p. 242. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 78. Soprano, p. 308, no. 36. Warscher, “Codex.”  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 28 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.iii.3</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_3/i.iii.3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 13:03:42 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_3/i.iii.3/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 3
Garden I.iii.3
Keywords  alleys (streets) archaeological garden exedrae (site elements) gutters (building drainage components) hearths lararia peristyles (columnades) pilasters porticoes puteal tufa  Garden Description The front of this house excavated in 1869 had an unusual design in that it was set back some distance from the street. The peristyle garden was entered at the end of the entranceway at the rear of a long angiprotus (alleyway). Rooms of the house were located at the right and rear of the garden. The peristyle had undergone various changes and was supported on the east and north by tall tufa columns. The portico roof on the west was supported by two low brick columns and two pilasters surmounted by arches. A low wall enclosed the garden, joining the columns either side of the entrance between the two columns to the west. A terra-cotta puteal was adjacent to the west wall along with a hearth covered with a small vault decorated with a rough, bearded head supposed to be Vulcan. A large window on the south wall gave a view from the exedra (b) into the garden. The east peristyle wall contained a lararium niche and a gutter ran along the north, east, and west edges of the garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1869
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 24, no. 22. Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 72. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., pp. 52-53.(worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 1 (1868-69), cols. 300-301. Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 26. (worldcat) Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 78. Pernice, p. 34. Warscher, “Codex.” photos nos. 16-21.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 28 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Epidius Fortunatus (I.iii.3)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_3/house_of_epidius_fortunatus_i.iii.3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 19:24:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_3/house_of_epidius_fortunatus_i.iii.3/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 3
Garden House of Epidius Fortunatus (I.iii.3)
Keywords  archaeological garden aqueducts basins (vessels) gutters (building drainage components) peristyles (columnades) podiums (building divisions) porticoes puteal tablina tufa  Garden Description On the right of the tablinum were ten steps that led to the peristyle garden (a). A portico enclosed the garden on the west, north and east sides. This was supported by ten columns and two engaged columns which were stuccoed brick painted red. The north, east, and west edges of the garden had a gutter. There were two cistern openings, according to Mau, one located in the northeast corner of the garden with a tufa puteal and the other in the corresponding corner of the portico. Water emptied at the northeast corner from the gutter into the cistern and into the street at the southeast and southwest corners. An aqueduct pipe came out of the first column, (counting from the south, on the west portico), and ran between the gutter and the portico. The pipe rose, supported from the second column on the west side, to spurt a jet of water in the gutter. Flanking the west and the north porticos, it disappeared going to the northwest. On the west side it was possible in two places to let water flow into the gutter by a widening of the pipe. The gutter had openings to the gardens at these two points to serve as watering outlets. There were keys before and after the widen pipe sections to control the flow of water. Two branches of this pipe entered a room (b) off the northwest corner of the peristyle where there was a basin.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2 : Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Scavi, pp. 70-71. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., pp.50-51.(worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 26. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 181-182. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 77. Pernice, p. 14. Warscher, “Codex.” photos nos. 4, 6-10a.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 27 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>