<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title># on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/#/</link>
    <description>Recent content in # on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/#/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Acropolis Palace at Jebel Khalid</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/syria/jebel_khalid/jebel_khalid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/syria/jebel_khalid/jebel_khalid/</guid>
      <description>Province Syria
Province Description In 64 BCE, after his successes in Armenia, Pompey the Great added Syria to the list of annexed eastern provinces of the growing Roman Empire. The conquest of Syria had not been difficult, because the remnants of the once dominant Seleucid Empire had weakened following the defeats of king Antiochus III at Thermopylae in 191 and Magnesia in Asia shortly after. Ultimately, the Seleucids could not withstand the powers of the Nabatean kingdom to the south, the Hasmonean kingdom to the west, and the new threats of Roman hegemony. With the fall of the Seleucids, Rome inherited the majority of Alexander the Great’s former conquests, and the Syrian desert would become a stage for Roman emperors to settle civil conflicts and win triumphs. Smaller Arab settlements sprang up across the region, re-inhabiting Seleucid sites and establishing new ones, and cities such as Palmyra grew in power by taking over the wealthy trade routes of the Nabateans in the second century CE. The Syrian city of Antioch, formerly Seleucia, would become one of the greatest cities of the Roman empire. Although Macedonian presence in the region introduced western styles in art and architecture before the arrival of the Romans, the cities remained Syrian in culture, population and character.
Covering the substantial central part of the Fertile Crescent, the province of Syria sat in an advantageous position between the mountain ranges of eastern Anatolia, the Mediterranean Sea, and the Arabian deserts, and it served as an area of expansion for the larger kingdoms around it. Important trans-Asian trade routes made Syria a key component in the Roman imperial economy, and large navigable rivers, such as the Euphrates and the Orontes, were exploited to connect the Persian Gulf with northern cities. The climate, although arid in the inland mountainous areas, was quite conducive to cultivation. River valleys in the mountain chains skirting the coast provided fertile terrain for agriculture, and the Orontes and Euphrates created well-watered plateaus in the steppe and desert regions of the southeast.
An irrigation system based around the qanat, an underground water channel, was used in Syria during the Roman period to water fields and gardens. Although qanats were likely introduced to the region via the earlier Achaemenid Persian dynasty, it was during the Roman and Byzantine periods that irrigation technology improved, and the majority of known qanats date to this time. The water could flow from these channels into canals, small reservoirs known today as birkas, or large wells. The ancient field systems of Syria have been well studied in areas such as the Hauran, a basalt region in the south. Cereals, olives and grapes were important crops, and were cultivated in either the broad fields on the lowland plains, or long, segmented plots on terraces in the rocky highlands. These terraced plots would have held fruit trees or vineyards.
Location Jebel Khalid
Jebel Khalid (Pleiades)
Location Description A colonial military settlement of Macedonian Greeks on the west bank of the Euphrates in North Syria, established in the wake of Alexander the Great&amp;rsquo;s conquests at a control point on the great river highway of the Euphrates (fig.1: location map of Jebel Khalid; fig. 2: aerial view of Jebel Khalid.) By the time the Jebel Khalid palace was constructed in the course of the third century BCE, these resettled Macedonians had been occupying for half a century not only the royal palaces of the Achaemenids, the powerful fifth and fourth century Persian dynasty, but also the palaces of their satraps, the local governors, and we know from literary testimony that both the royal and local palaces boasted paradeisoi, gardens for pleasure and relaxation. It is therefore reasonable that their Greek successors and replacements adopted in the third century what they found to be one of the agreeable and relaxing amenities enjoyed by their fourth-century Persian predecessors. And from here the concept passed to the Greek builders of elaborate villas as exemplified in Greek South Italy of the second century BCE.
While the general settlement of Jebel Khalid appears to have been systematically abandoned at the end of the Seleucid period (late 70s/early 60s BCE), some seasonal occupation continued into the early Roman period in some of the rooms of the Acropolis Palace. The multiplicity of weak floors in some areas suggests occupation by seasonal pastoralists, and Roman–period coins dating from the third century CE onwards occur in areas of stone-robbing. When major elements of the building eventually collapsed they fell on up to a metre of wind-blown soil – up on the Acropolis high-ground there is not the possibility of alluvial wash-down – implying that the building had stood substantially intact but unroofed for several centuries after its abandonment. The ruins attracted Roman-period scavengers, sightseers and stone robbers, who even scratched graffiti in the plaster of fallen masonry (Clarke: 1992/3).
Garden Acropolis Palace at Jebel Khalid
Keywords  cisterns (plumbing components) colonnades courtyards palaces terrace gardens trenches  Garden Description It is apparent that there was once a large limestone outcrop within the Acropolis at the highest point of the Jebel range, providing panoramic views of the Euphrates valley (figs. 3 and 4: overall plan of the site and ground plan of Acropolis palace). This outcrop was quarried to a rough level terrace, leaving a rocky bluff (and evident quarry face) on the western side, against which a stout retaining wall was built, also serving as the exterior western wall of the building. Nowhere, even in foundation trenches, is there any trace of previous occupation. This building was laid out on a virgin site, or the initial quarrying operations totally cleared away any vestige of any earlier habitation. The coin and stamped amphora handle evidence confirms a third-century BCE construction date.
The building was planned around a square central courtyard, &amp;lsquo;room 26&amp;rsquo; (measurements from central point of column bases are N.17100mm, S.17100mm, E.17800mm, W.17840mm; measurements from the corners of &amp;lsquo;room 26&amp;rsquo; are N.25.3m, S.25.1m, E.26.2m, W.26.0m). The bedrock floor of this courtyard was evidently quarried to drain towards a large cistern in the southeast corner, conveniently located close to a major entertainment room (room 20) with two store-rooms and kitchens (rooms 19 and 21) to either side of it. This cistern is bell-shaped and subsequent excavation has revealed that it was lined with an impermeable plaster; it has a roughly circular mouth, 1.5 meter wide, a depth of 6.6 m, and maximum width of 6.7 m. No well-head was found. While it can be assumed that water from the roofs of the surrounding courtyard rooms was collected, no evidence was found for a drainage system into this cistern, although a settling pond and sluice arrangement has been uncovered by excavation. Indeed, there could have been large pithoi or barrels to collect water from lion-headed waterspouts overhead (fig. 5: example of lion-headed water-spout).
A circular stand was found carved into the bedrock (c. 5 cm deep, 37~38 cm in diameter) by the northern stylobate in the courtyard: it may have served to house a garden pot. (Fig. 6: possible stand for flower pot.) A drain, 4.9 m in length and 14 cm in depth, cut into the bedrock across the colonnade floor on the southwestern side of the courtyard have released any water seeping down from the western rocky outcrop and accumulating beneath room 24. There is another drain with a similar function towards the north end of the western stylobate, which released water into the courtyard across a shallow channel, but it did not continue across the courtyard floor. The courtyard floor itself consisted of a few centimeters of a very hard packed mixture of clay and gritty limestone over bedrock, creating a particularly hard surface. The floor of the colonnade was similarly constituted. As flagstones have manifestly been robbed elsewhere in the building, it is possible that the whole area was once paved over this prepared surface.
A stylobate was laid on the four sides of this courtyard on leveled bedrock using ashlar blocks with neatly drafted edges (av. dimensions: 0.860 m x 0.680 m and 0.210~0.260 m deep, but there is considerable variation) with some rustication visible on the courtyard side below the courtyard floor level (fig. 7 details of stylobate). The colonnade is decastyle, with ten columns to a side, 36 in total. A deep and unusually wide foundation trench was cut in front of the stylobate on the courtyard side—going down in places 0.97 m from paving level and being up to 0.82 m wide (fig. 8: excavated garden bed.) Normally one would expect such a trench to be filled with builders&amp;rsquo; rubble and chippings, but in this case, it was filled with rich brown, nitrogenous soil (not the light grey wind-blown dust that has accumulated over time elsewhere at the site). It seems clear that a formal garden was installed around the inside perimeter of much of the courtyard, easily watered from the roof-water collection. Soil samples were taken but have yet to be analysed: there is no other sign of courtyard planting. As such, it constitutes the earliest recorded courtyard garden in a Greek building and it helps to explain the sudden appearance of such plantings in the courtyards of southern Italian houses such as at Pompeii in the second century BCE.
Maps   Fig. 1: Location map of Jebel Khalid   Plans   Fig. 2: Overall plan of the site     Fig. 3: Ground plan of the Acropolis palace   Images   Fig. 4: Aerial view of Jebel Khalid     Fig. 5: Example of lion-headed water-spout     Fig. 6: Possible stand for a garden pot     Fig. 7: Detail of stylobate     Fig. 8: Excavated garden bed   Dates 3rd century BCE
Bibliography  G. Clarke. &amp;ldquo;Greek Graffiti from North Syria.&amp;rdquo; Mediterranean Archaeology 5/6 (1992/3): 117-120, plates 39-40. ibid. &amp;ldquo;Jebel Khalid on the Euphrates: The Acropolis Building.&amp;rdquo; Proceedings of the Second Macedonian Conference, Melbourne, in Mediterranean Archaeology 7 (1994): 69-75, plates 1-3. ibid., ed., &amp;ldquo;Jebel Khalid on the Euphrates: Report on Excavations 1986-1996.&amp;rdquo; Meditarch Suppl. 5 (2002): 25-48, plates IV-VIII and 10-25. Inge Nielsen (ed.) The Royal Palace Institution in the First Millennium BC. Regional Development and Cultural Change between East and West, Monographs of the Danish Institute at Athens, vol. 4, pp. 215-247.  Pleiades ID 167649937 (Acropolis palace at Jebel Khalid)
TGN ID #
Contributor Graeme Clark
Publication date 3 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Agora of the Italians</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/delos/delos_agora_of_the_italians/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/delos/delos_agora_of_the_italians/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Location Delos
Delos (Pleiades)
Location Description Delos is a small island in the center of the Cyclades measuring about five kilometers north-south and 1.3 kilometers east-west at the widest. In antiquity, it was famous as the birthplace of Apollo. Apollo’s sanctuary, founded in the seventh century B.C., is situated on a small plain next to the main port. It became a principal Panhellenic cult center and always formed the heart of the later settlement and city. The city was under Athenian supremacy in the fifth and fourth centuries B.C. and became independent only in 314 B.C. Although extensive public building occurred during the period of its status as an independent city-state and the island began to develop as a commercial center, the city remained relatively small and was still mainly engaged in local and regional trade with the surrounding Cycladic islands. This changed significantly when the Romans handed control of Delos to Athens in 167 B.C. and declared it a free port. It soon developed into a booming cosmopolitan trade center with merchants coming from all over the Mediterranean world. As a consequence the city grew considerably, mostly to meet the needs of its new purpose. Squares, quays, warehouses, shops, new residential quarters, and clubhouses of foreign associations were constructed, and public buildings and sanctuaries were either renovated and extended or newly built. Although Delos was sacked twice, in 88 B.C. by the troops of Mithridates and 69 B.C. by the pirates under Athenodoros, its desertion during the first century B.C. is predominantly due to the rivalry of increasingly successful Roman ports like Puteoli and Ostia. Life in Delos did not come to an abrupt halt as evidenced by remains of Roman thermae and several Christian basilicas, but it continued on a much smaller scale.
Garden Agora of the Italians
Keywords  colonnades courtyards exedrae (site elements) niches peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes water wells  Garden Description The Agora of the Italians, with a size of some 6,000 square meters, is situated prominently in the center of Delos, between the famous sanctuary of Apollo to the south and the Sacred Lake to the north. The design of the Agora centers on a vast courtyard with four double-storied porticoes enclosing 3,450 square meters of an open unpaved terrain (Figs. 1-4). The colonnades are surrounded by the following rooms: (a) a series of three large exedrae (15, 30, 42) and four small exedrae (10, 23, 46, 98), which were all accessible by large thresholds on the ground floor level, with the exception of the raised exedra 98; (b) 27 rectangular (7, 9, 13, 18, 24, 32, 37, 39, 41, 44, 47, 54, 59, 97, 102, 105) and semicircular (16, 25, 30b, 34, 35, 68, 73, 90, 93, 95, 100) statue niches on all sides, which were not accessible, as their openings were closed by doors or grills and the thresholds of many were raised far above the ground floor level; (c) a bath suite with two round sweat baths in the north-west (27-31); (d) a group of three rooms in the west (20-22); and (e) two latrines to the west (5) and east (64). Access to the building is provided by a Doric propylon to the west (3) and two narrow side entrances to the west (2) and the east (70). Two rows of shops bordering the east and south porticoes as well as a row of shops on the northwestern corner of the building do not open to the interior of the Agora, but face the surrounding streets.
The building was erected on the former site of the so-called Sacred Lake, a huge swamp varying over time in size and water level. On the arid island of Delos, this was one of the most humid and fertile places. While the building site for the Agora was drained and stabilized with huge deposits of debris, the Sacred Lake was canalized with an exterior wall, thereby attaining its present form. The Agora itself was neither planned nor constructed in its present form, but is the result of a long building process with about five phases. The original building (Fig. 4) comprised only the large courtyard with double-storied porticoes, the three large lavish Ionic exedrae (15, 30, 42) in the west and north, the propylon (3) and the secondary entrance (2) in the west, and – as a result of the use of earlier walls – some rooms in the west (1, 18/20, 21, 28). The rows of the southern and eastern shops formed part of the original plan, but were only added subsequently in a second phase. In contrast to these, the small exedrae (10, 23, 46, 98), the statue niches, and the bath suite did not belong to the first plan, but were added in a third and fourth phase as a kind of makeshift arrangement and as a reaction to changing needs. In a fifth phase the northwestern shops were gained at the expense of public land.
The Agora of the Italians was most probably constructed between 130-120 B.C., partly destroyed during the raids of 88 B.C., then repaired, and finally abandoned after 69 B.C. Its function is contested, with identifications ranging from a multifunctional commercial meeting place for the Romans and Italians, a slave market, a commercial agora or macellum, a combined palaestra-gladiatorial arena-bath complex to, most recently, a garden-porticus, i.e., a luxurious park-like meeting place with a garden, porticoes, and exedrae.
The exploration of the vast courtyard during the early excavations between 1877 and 1905 was considered disappointing because very few objects were found. Large parts of the courtyard seem to have been dug up, but remains of plants, shrubs or trees were not recorded because they were probably not recognized or of sufficient interest. To this day, the courtyard is often overgrown with plants, flowers, and small trees. Future specialized investigation of the courtyard might definitely prove the existence of plants, but for the moment the following evidence for a garden can be cited.
The courtyard contained perhaps as many as eight wells, three of which are still visible today and five of which were tentatively identified in recent geophysical examinations. The area of the former swamp was still sufficiently humid and could have supplied the necessary water for plants. Although many Hellenistic squares and agorai were not paved, the lack of a pavement is remarkable within the context of Delos. In the last third of the second century B.C. all heavily frequented squares, streets, and quays, which were especially used for commerce and trade, were fully paved with large gneiss slabs. Since the Italians spared no expenses in constructing their first agora or in embellishing it later on, the unpaved floor of the courtyard cannot be due to financial shortcomings, but must have been chosen deliberately to meet a specific purpose. The courtyard lacks a sewer to dispose of waste and especially rain water. The wastewater of the later bath suite (room 27) was not emptied into the sewer of the nearby street, as usual, but was instead drained into the courtyard. Therefore, all available water seems to have been deliberately used to irrigate a garden. Comparisons with other buildings show that the original building of the Agora of the Italians has nothing in common with civic-political agorai, or specific commercial markets, or palaestrae, but resembles much larger ambulatory garden-peristyles of Hellenistic palaces (e.g. Aigai, Pella, Jericho) and Late Republican houses in the Vesuvian area or the lavish garden-porticus in Rome such as the Porticus Pompei and the Porticus Liviae. Like these, the Agora of the Italians was most probably conceived and used as a public park for all kinds of agreeable meetings and sojourns.
The porticoes, and maybe even the courtyard, were decorated with statues. Most of the nearly 240 sculptural fragments found within the confines and in the immediate neighborhood of the Agora seem to come from honorary statues, which were mostly presented in the rectangular and semicircular statue niches, but also outside of them, probably in the porticoes. However, some fragments belonged to historical-political monuments (e.g., at least two or even as many as six statues of Celts) and to decorative sculpture suited for a garden (e.g., Dionysos, Satyr/Apollo/Pothos, herms). These statues could have been placed either in the porticoes or in the courtyard.
Finally, numerous Greek, Latin, and bilingual inscriptions attest that the Agora of the Italians was never referred to as an agora, but probably as a pastas italike (as restored in Roussel and Launey, Inscriptions de Délos, no. 2612). The Latin translation of this could have been porticus Italica or porticus Italicorum which would have more appropriate for a luxurious garden-portico, rather than the agora or forum.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Agora of the Italians, reconstructed plan of the original building (first phase), 1:500. Drawing by M. Trümper.     Fig. 2: Agora of the Italians, reconstructed plan, 1:500. Drawing by M. Trümper after Ét. Lapalus 1939, Fig. 2. Permission courtesy of Michèle Brunet, École Française d’Athènes.   Images   Fig. 3 : Agora of the Italians, overview from southwest. Photo courtesy of M. Trümper.     Fig. 4: Agora of the Italians, overview from southeast. Photo courtesy of M. Trümper.   Dates 2nd-1st c. BCE
Bibliography  P. Roussel and M. Launey, Inscriptions de Délos. Paris, 1937. Ét. Lapalus, L’Agora des Italiens. Exploration archéologique de Délos XIX. Paris, 1939. J. Marcadé, Au Musée de Délos. Étude de la sculpture hellénistique en ronde bosse découverte dans l’île. BEFAR 215, 1969. I. Nielsen, Hellenistic Palaces. Tradition and Renewal. Studies in Hellenistic Civilization V. Aarhus, 1994. E. M. Steinby, ed., LTUR IV, Roma, 1999. A. Sarris, “L’Agora des Italiens,” BCH 125, 2001: 612-615 J. Marcadé and F. Queyrel, “Le Gaulois blessé de Délos reconsidéré,” MonPiot 82, 2003: 5-97. Ph. Bruneau and J. Ducat, Guide de Délos. École française d Athènes. 4th edition, Paris, 2005. M. Trümper, &amp;ldquo;Die Agora des Italiens,&amp;rdquo; in Delos. Baugeschichte, Architektur, Ausstattung und Funktion einer späthellenistischen Porticus-Anlage. Internationale Archäologie 104. Rahden/Westfalen, 2008.  Pleiades ID 394168051 (Agora of the Italians)
TGN ID 7011273 (Dhílos,island)
Contributor Monika Trümper
Publication date 3 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Imperial Residence at Batnae</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/syria/batnae/batnae/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/syria/batnae/batnae/</guid>
      <description>Province Syria
Province Description In 64 BCE, after his successes in Armenia, Pompey the Great added Syria to the list of annexed eastern provinces of the growing Roman Empire. The conquest of Syria had not been difficult, because the remnants of the once dominant Seleucid Empire had weakened following the defeats of king Antiochus III at Thermopylae in 191 and Magnesia in Asia shortly after. Ultimately, the Seleucids could not withstand the powers of the Nabatean kingdom to the south, the Hasmonean kingdom to the west, and the new threats of Roman hegemony. With the fall of the Seleucids, Rome inherited the majority of Alexander the Great’s former conquests, and the Syrian desert would become a stage for Roman emperors to settle civil conflicts and win triumphs. Smaller Arab settlements sprang up across the region, re-inhabiting Seleucid sites and establishing new ones, and cities such as Palmyra grew in power by taking over the wealthy trade routes of the Nabateans in the second century CE. The Syrian city of Antioch, formerly Seleucia, would become one of the greatest cities of the Roman empire. Although Macedonian presence in the region introduced western styles in art and architecture before the arrival of the Romans, the cities remained Syrian in culture, population and character.
Covering the substantial central part of the Fertile Crescent, the province of Syria sat in an advantageous position between the mountain ranges of eastern Anatolia, the Mediterranean Sea, and the Arabian deserts, and it served as an area of expansion for the larger kingdoms around it. Important trans-Asian trade routes made Syria a key component in the Roman imperial economy, and large navigable rivers, such as the Euphrates and the Orontes, were exploited to connect the Persian Gulf with northern cities. The climate, although arid in the inland mountainous areas, was quite conducive to cultivation. River valleys in the mountain chains skirting the coast provided fertile terrain for agriculture, and the Orontes and Euphrates created well-watered plateaus in the steppe and desert regions of the southeast.
An irrigation system based around the qanat, an underground water channel, was used in Syria during the Roman period to water fields and gardens. Although qanats were likely introduced to the region via the earlier Achaemenid Persian dynasty, it was during the Roman and Byzantine periods that irrigation technology improved, and the majority of known qanats date to this time. The water could flow from these channels into canals, small reservoirs known today as birkas, or large wells. The ancient field systems of Syria have been well studied in areas such as the Hauran, a basalt region in the south. Cereals, olives and grapes were important crops, and were cultivated in either the broad fields on the lowland plains, or long, segmented plots on terraces in the rocky highlands. These terraced plots would have held fruit trees or vineyards.
Location Batnae
Batnae/Markopolis (Pleiades)
Location Description The broad plain of Batanaea lay to the west of the uplands, known as Auranitis, in the Hauran, a basalt region that straddled the boundary between ancient Syria and Arabia. Batanaea was not a naturally well-watered area, but it did develop during the Roman period into a successful grain-producing settlement via a careful management of rainwater. The agriculture of the area, which included small enclosed gardens and plantations surrounding villages, depended on precipitation; a large cistern, or birket, commonly found throughout the Hauran and Batanaea, likely served the village and not irrigation purposes. Although the village was perhaps the most ubiquitous settlement type, there did exist some imperial and private estates, potentially with their own gardens.
Garden Imperial Residence at Batnae
Keywords Garden Description The Emperor Julian described the imperial residence in Batnae in Syria in one of his letters to Libanius in 363 CE (Epist. 58). According to him, Batnae was thickly wooded with groves of cypress trees. The palace located there hardly seemed grand, but its garden was worthy of praise; Julian (Epist. 58) compared it to the gardens of Alcinous and Laertes in Homer’s Odyssey. It contained a small grove of cypresses, as well as rows of such trees planted along the garden wall, and in the middle of the garden were vegetable beds and fruit trees of all sorts.
Maps Plans Images Dates fourth century CE
Bibliography  K. Butcher, Roman Syria and the Near East, Los Angeles: Getty Publications, 2003.  Pleiades ID 658405
TGN ID #
Contributor Catherine Kearns and Maureen Carroll
Publication date 3 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kitchen and Commercial Gardens</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/delos/delos_kitchen_commercial_gardens/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/delos/delos_kitchen_commercial_gardens/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Location Delos
Delos (Pleiades)
Location Description Delos is a small island in the center of the Cyclades measuring about five kilometers north-south and 1.3 kilometers east-west at the widest. In antiquity, it was famous as the birthplace of Apollo. Apollo’s sanctuary, founded in the seventh century B.C., is situated on a small plain next to the main port. It became a principal Panhellenic cult center and always formed the heart of the later settlement and city. The city was under Athenian supremacy in the fifth and fourth centuries B.C. and became independent only in 314 B.C. Although extensive public building occurred during the period of its status as an independent city-state and the island began to develop as a commercial center, the city remained relatively small and was still mainly engaged in local and regional trade with the surrounding Cycladic islands. This changed significantly when the Romans handed control of Delos to Athens in 167 B.C. and declared it a free port. It soon developed into a booming cosmopolitan trade center with merchants coming from all over the Mediterranean world. As a consequence the city grew considerably, mostly to meet the needs of its new purpose. Squares, quays, warehouses, shops, new residential quarters, and clubhouses of foreign associations were constructed, and public buildings and sanctuaries were either renovated and extended or newly built. Although Delos was sacked twice, in 88 B.C. by the troops of Mithridates and 69 B.C. by the pirates under Athenodoros, its desertion during the first century B.C. is predominantly due to the rivalry of increasingly successful Roman ports like Puteoli and Ostia. Life in Delos did not come to an abrupt halt as evidenced by remains of Roman thermae and several Christian basilicas, but it continued on a much smaller scale.
Garden Kitchen and Commercial Gardens
Keywords inscriptions market gardens
Garden Description The inscriptions of the sanctuary of Apollo mention nearly 30 kepoi within the period of 433 B.C. to 156/155 B.C., which were either private or belonged to Apollo and were rented or leased. Most of these cannot be localized because they were named after their former owners and with topographical references or surnames unknown today. However, in the years between 167 and 155 B.C., three kepoi were situated near identified buildings: the sanctuary of Leto, the Hippodrome, and the Neorion. A fourth was located near the palaestra, the identification of which among the several palaestra-buildings in Delos is contested. The first three kepoi were located east of the sanctuary of Apollo in a zone which was regarded as specifically humid and fertile because the Inopos, the main watercourse of Delos, was believed to have passed here before emptying into the Bay of Skardhana to the north. However, it has been shown that the Inopos ended south of the sanctuary of Apollo and could therefore never have irrigated the potential garden zone east of Apollo’s sacred precinct.
The kepoi were certainly always located outside the residential quarters and were used as kitchen or commercial gardens. They were identified as terrain for the cultivation of plants that needed irrigation, such as vines, olives, and figs. This terrain had to be enclosed by walls or fences to keep animals out. In contrast to the kepoi, the choria equally mentioned in the inscriptions of the sanctuary of Apollo served for the growing of cereals and stock farming. According to this definition, kepoi could have been laid out either next to farmhouses serving as kitchen gardens or on some of the many cultural terraces which extended far beyond the center of the city to the south, north, and east of the residential zones (Fig. 1). The necessary water supply was provided by wells, reservoirs, and large pools, some of which have been discovered on these terraces. The water was either distributed by hand or through a system of irrigation channels, starting from one of the reservoirs or large pools.
The variety of trees and plants cultivated in ancient Delos is known from the epigraphic evidence. Among the sporadically listed plants are pomegranates, apples, laurel, almonds, palms, vines, figs, and olives. Fig trees, which to this day form the majority of the Delian tree population, appear most often in the inscriptions.
Maps   Archaeological plan of the island, 1:2500. Drawing by Nicolas Bresch from Brunet 1999, fig. 1.   Dates fifth to second c. BCE
Bibliography  P. Bruneau, “Deliaca II: No. 31. Les jardins urbains de Délos,” BCH 103, 1979: 89-99. P. Bruneau and J. Ducat, Guide de Délos. École française d Athènes. Fourth edition, Paris, 2005, Nos. 75, 128. M. Brunet, “Contribution à l’histoire rurale de Délos aux époques classique et hellénistique,” BCH 114, 1990:669-682. M.-C. Hellmann, Recherches sur le vocabulaire de l’architecture grecque, d’après les inscriptions de Délos. BEFAR 278, 1992. M. Brunet, “La campagne délienne,” in V. Anagnostopoulos, ed., L’espace grec, cent cinquante ans de fouilles de l’École française d’Athènes. Paris 1996:59-66. J.-C. Moretti, “Le gymnase de Délos,&amp;rdquo; BCH 120, 1996:617-638. J.-P. Brun and M. Brunet, “Une huilerie du premier siècle avant J.-C. dans le Quartier du théâtre à Délos,” BCH 121, 1997:573-609. M. Brunet, “Le paysage agraire de Délos dans l’Antiquité,” Journal des Savants 1999:1-50. M. Brunet, et al., “L’eau à Délos: un milieu naturel et son aménagement durant l’Antiquité,” BCH 125, 2001:620-627. M. Brunet, “Le courtil et le paradis,” in: J.-P. Brun and P. Jockey, eds., Techniques et sociétés en Méditerranée. Hommage à Marie-Claire Amouretti. Collection L’atelier méditerranéen. Travaux du Centre Camille Jullian, Aix, 2001:157-168. C. Prêtre, ed., Nouveau choix d&amp;rsquo;inscriptions de Délos. Lois, comptes et inventaires. Études épigrapiques 4, 2002.  Pleiades ID 599588 (Delos, island)
TGN ID 7011273 (Dhílos,island)
Contributor Monika Trümper
Publication date 3 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Peristyle Gardens</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/delos/delos_peristyle_gardens/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/achaea/delos/delos_peristyle_gardens/</guid>
      <description>Province Achaea
Location Delos
Delos (Pleiades)
Location Description Delos is a small island in the center of the Cyclades measuring about five kilometers north-south and 1.3 kilometers east-west at the widest. In antiquity, it was famous as the birthplace of Apollo. Apollo’s sanctuary, founded in the seventh century B.C., is situated on a small plain next to the main port. It became a principal Panhellenic cult center and always formed the heart of the later settlement and city. The city was under Athenian supremacy in the fifth and fourth centuries B.C. and became independent only in 314 B.C. Although extensive public building occurred during the period of its status as an independent city-state and the island began to develop as a commercial center, the city remained relatively small and was still mainly engaged in local and regional trade with the surrounding Cycladic islands. This changed significantly when the Romans handed control of Delos to Athens in 167 B.C. and declared it a free port. It soon developed into a booming cosmopolitan trade center with merchants coming from all over the Mediterranean world. As a consequence the city grew considerably, mostly to meet the needs of its new purpose. Squares, quays, warehouses, shops, new residential quarters, and clubhouses of foreign associations were constructed, and public buildings and sanctuaries were either renovated and extended or newly built. Although Delos was sacked twice, in 88 B.C. by the troops of Mithridates and 69 B.C. by the pirates under Athenodoros, its desertion during the first century B.C. is predominantly due to the rivalry of increasingly successful Roman ports like Puteoli and Ostia. Life in Delos did not come to an abrupt halt as evidenced by remains of Roman thermae and several Christian basilicas, but it continued on a much smaller scale.
Garden Peristyle Gardens
Keywords  impluvia nymphaea (garden structures) oeci peristyles (Roman courtyards)  Garden Description In the Late Hellenistic houses of Delos the impluvia of peristyle courtyards were usually paved, and rainwater falling into these courtyards was emptied as wastewater by sewers into nearby streets. However, in two large houses (Quarter of the Theater, Insula II, Houses E and F) and two clubhouses of associations (House of Fourni; Quarter of the Stadium, Insula I, building B, the so-called perfumery) the impluvia of the peristyle courtyards were not paved, with the exception of some scattered stone settings. Whereas one of them might have been left unfinished in a phase of remodeling (Quarter of the Theater, insula II, House F), the others were certainly all used, comprising of different phases of enlargement and embellishment. Thus, the lack of pavement cannot be due to the unfinished state of the buildings, but must have been deliberate. The sizes of these impluvia range from 30.20 square meters to 75.80 square meters. In all cases no cistern was established under the impluvium, as is usual in Delian buildings with peristyles. Furthermore, all four peristyle courtyards are provided with a sewer for the drainage of rain and waste water; the earthen floor of the impluvium could probably not absorb the occasional large quantities of rain water pouring down in heavy storms, so that at least some of the rain water had to be drained away.
So far, planting was only proposed for the courtyard of the so-called perfumery, but no specialized examinations or excavations were performed in any of the four courtyards. In addition to the above-mentioned characteristics, some other features might speak in favor of luxurious garden-peristyles for these Delian buildings.
The core building of the House of Fourni is arranged along a main axis with rooms on at least three different levels (Fig. 1). The main rooms were not oriented towards the south, as is usual in Delos, but towards the west, thus providing a view of the nearby bay of Fourni and the sea. A kind of nymphaeum (k), carved out of the natural rock and placed exactly on the main axis of the building, was added subsequently to the eastern façade of the building. A broad staircase led from the impluvium of the courtyard (q) to a large raised room in the east (j), a remarkably open oecus maior with doors on three sides and an opening to the nymphaeum on the fourth side. Therefore, the impluvium of 75.80 square meters will have been frequently used and would certainly have been paved, had it not been conceived for a special purpose like planting. Today, the courtyard is (again?) covered with small shrubs. The overall design and some other features like opus signinum pavements (rooms i, h and o) and ‘liturgical’ paintings for the cult of the lares compitales, a cult usually performed by slaves and liberti of Italians or Romans, point to a Roman or Italian association, which might have introduced some new fashionable traits into Delian private architecture.
The so-called perfumery was equipped with a Rhodian peristyle (e), an open oecus maior with colonnades and doors on all four sides (m-n), and with a kind of nymphaeum-reservoir (p) (Figs. 2-3). The latter opened off the oecus maior and was placed on the visual axis of the main entrance. Perfume was produced in a large exedra (f), which was connected with the peristyle to its north by an Ionic colonnade. The overall design is as unique as in the House of Fourni and could well have comprised a peristyle with a stylish garden of 51.20 square meters. A Roman or Italian association might have owned this clubhouse because Romans and Italians showed particular interest in the perfume trade. Slaves and liberti of several gentes that are attested in Delos distinguished themselves as thurarii (dealers of incense) in the Mediterranean world.
The three-sided peristyle in the courtyard (b) of House E in the insula II of the Quarter of the theater comprised a large rectangular altar in its center (Figs. 4-5). An exedra with two columns (f) opened to the north and was only accessible via the impluvium. Again, this arrangement would have required frequent use of the impluvium and, therefore, even more so its systematic pavement. Instead, the impluvium of 48.80 square meters, which is only equipped with some scattered stone slabs, was probably transformed into a kind of sacred garden. Two altars at either side of the entrance, which were probably combined with ‘liturgical’ paintings, might indicate that a Roman or Italian owned this house at least for a certain period.
Whether the impluvium of 30.20 square meters (a) of House F in insula II of the Quarter of the Theater was left unfinished or planned or even realized as a garden, cannot be decided (Fig. 6). Following the latest fashion, the initiators of the last major transformation of this house might well have conceived of a planted impluvium. This house, however, was not (yet?) equipped with any water supply.
In Delian private buildings, peristyle gardens were probably introduced rather late, during the heyday of the free port in the three or four decades before 88 B.C. Within the local context, the Agora of the Italians could have served as the most immediate model for this new fashion. The design of these gardens would have been simple. They would have consisted mostly of small trees, shrubs, and plants, which did not need much water. All of them had to be irrigated by hand, like the garden of the Agora of the Italians and many of the kitchen and commercial gardens, as Late Hellenistic Delos was not provided with a water pipe system.
Maps Plans   Fig 5: Maison de Fourni, sketch, 1:250. Drawing by M. Trümper after Bruneau and Ducat 2005, Dépliant VIII; Bruneau 1972 : 305-316, nos. 325-339, figs. 271-294 ; Le Roy 1984 : 167-173, plate 1.     Fig. 6: Plan of the ‘Perfumery,’ Quarter of the Stadium, Insula I, building B, 1:250. Drawing by M. Trümper after Plassart 1916, pl. V-VII.     Fig. 7: Plan of Quarter of the Theater, Insula II, houses E and F, 1:250. Drawing by M. Trümper after J. Chamonard 1922/24, pl. III-IV.   Images   Fig. 8: ‘Perfumery,’ Quarter of the Stadium, Insula I, building B, overview from southeast. Photo courtesy of M. Trümper.     Fig. 9: Quarter of the Theater, insula II, house E, overview of the courtyard from southwest. Photo courtesy of M. Trümper.     Fig. 10: Quarter of the Theater, Insula II, house F, overview of the courtyard from southwest. Photo courtesy of M. Trümper.   Dates 1st c. BCE
Bibliography  A. Plassart, “Fouilles de Délos exécutées aux frais de M. Le Duc de Loubat (1912-1913). Quartier d’habitations privées à l’est du stade,” BCH 40, 1916:166-175. J. Chamonard, Le Quartier du théâtre. Étude sur l’habitation délienne à l’époque hellénistique. Exploration archéologique de Délos VIII. Paris 1922/24. P. Bruneau, Recherches sur les cultes de Délos à l’époque hellénistique et à l’époque impériale. BEFAR 217, 1970. P. Bruneau, Les mosaïques. Exploration archéologique de Délos 29. Paris 1972. C. Le Roy, “Le tracé et le plan d’une villa hellénistique. La maison de Fourni à Délos,” in Le dessin d’architecture dans les sociétés antiques. Actes du Colloque de Strasbourg, 26-28 janvier 1984. Travaux du Centre de Recherche sur le Proche Orient et la Grèce Antiques 8, 1985:167-173, pl. 1. P. Bruneau and J. Ducat, Guide de Délos. École française d Athènes. 4th edition, Paris 2005, Nos. 79, 117, 124. M. Trümper, Wohnen in Delos. Eine baugeschichtliche Untersuchung zum Wandel der Wohnkultur in hellenistischer Zeit. Internationale Archäologie 46, Rahden/Westfalen 1998: 262-265, 317-318, figs. 59. 62, plan I. J.-P. Brun, “La Maison IB du Quartier du stade et la production des parfums à Délos,” BCH 123, 1999:87-155. M. Trümper, “Negotiating Religious and Ethnic Identity: the Case of Clubhouses in Late Hellenistic Delos,” in ed. I. Nielsen, Zwischen Kult und Gesellschaft. Kosmopolitische Zentren des antiken Mittelmeerraums als Aktionsraum von Kultvereinen und Religionsgemeinschaften. Akten eines Symposiums des Archäologischen Instituts der Universität Hamburg (12.-14. Oktober 2005). Hephaistos 24, 2006, pp. 113-150. M. Trümper, Die &amp;lsquo;Agora des Italiens’ in Delos. Baugeschichte, Architektur, Ausstattung und Funktion einer späthellenistischen Porticus-Anlage. Internationale Archäologie 104. Rahden/Westfalen, 2008, pp. 91-92, figs. 105-107.  Pleiades ID 599588 (Delos, island)
TGN ID 7011273 (Dhílos,island)
Contributor Monika Trümper
Publication date 3 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Petra Garden and Pool Complex</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/arabia_petraea/petra/petra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/arabia_petraea/petra/petra/</guid>
      <description>Province Arabia Petraea
Location Petra
Petra (697725)
Garden Petra Garden and Pool Complex
Keywords  archaeobotany artificial islands colonnades garden pavilions horticultural containers pergolas temene terrace gardens water features (landscaping)  Garden Description The only example of a garden investigated using specialized garden archaeology techniques in the region of Arabia Petraea is found at Petra. A large open area was believed to be the site of a marketplace, the so-called “Lower Market,” until excavations revealed the remnants of a formal garden and pool complex. The garden is situated on an artificial terrace on the southern slope of the Wadi Musa, overlooking the main colonnaded street and flanked by the so-called “Middle Market” to the east, and the Great Temple complex to the west. To the south of the garden is a residential quarter on top of a high sandstone ridge (Ez-Zantur), where several private villas have been excavated. Primary access into the garden was apparently from the west, through a triple colonnade that marks the boundary between the Great Temple’s “lower temenos” and the garden terrace.
The garden is composed of two distinct parts: on the north is a large earthen terrace that is elevated approximately six meters above the main street and is level with the Great Temple’s “lower temenos”; to the south of the earthen terrace and elevated another two and a half meters above it is a monumental pool with a central island-pavilion (Fig. 1).
The garden’s earthen terrace measures sixty-five by fifty-three meters and is supported on the north by a double retaining wall. Prior to archaeological study of the site, the terrace appeared devoid of visible architectural features, with the exception of a short stretch of a low wall at its center. The terrace’s southwest quarter has a raised earthen area, bounded on the north and west by reused architectural fragments, attesting to the modern use of the site as an agricultural field by the local Bedouin inhabitants of Petra.
The application of ground-penetrating radar (GPR) provided valuable information about the buried garden. It revealed that the terrace is primarily earthen with a series of stone structures aligned along its central north-south axis. Follow-up excavations uncovered two stone platforms—one at the center of the terrace and one several meters to the south, between the central platform and the pool. Each platform is constructed of a core of unhewn fieldstones faced with sandstone ashlars, typical of Nabataean masonry. There is also evidence that the southern platform was enlarged and redesigned, probably during the Roman and Byzantine periods. At the northern end of the terrace, aligned with the platforms, two soundings exposed the foundations of a large structure that appeared as a pronounced rectangular stone outline (ca. 8.5 x 11 meters) in the GPR data. The gravel interior floor surface and lack of evidence for substantial walls or a roof suggest that it was an open structure, perhaps a pergola, designed to provide shade while viewing the surrounding garden. Remnants of a gravel pathway were uncovered along the central east-west axis (Fig. 2). The pathway’s border is defined by the foundations of a stylobate, suggesting a colonnaded or trellised walkway with bays for constructed views of the garden. Fragments of a flower pot (Fig. 3), perforated for drainage and aeration, were found near the pathway along with several root cavities, which provide evidence for plantings along the path’s edge. Similar flower pot fragments were uncovered during preliminary excavations in the so-called “Upper Market” in 2009 and may be indicative of a second garden site at Petra.
To the south of the garden terrace, the sandstone hillside was quarried out to create a space for a monumental pool. The area of the pool-complex measures sixty-five by thirty-two meters and is bounded on the south and east by vertical sandstone escarpments rising up to sixteen meters above pool-level; to the west is the Eastern Perimeter Wall of the Great Temple complex. A staircase provides access from the garden terrace up to the pool’s west promenade. The pool is a monumental construction with massive walls built to hold approximately 2069 cubic meters (547,000 gallons) of water. Stretching at least forty-six meters across the width of the site, the pool’s north wall measures three and a half meters wide and is preserved to a height of six courses (2.2 m). The wall’s exterior faces are constructed of close-fitting sandstone ashlars typical of Nabataean masonry; between them are alternating rows of roughly hewn sandstone blocks and rubble, bonded into a solid mass with an impervious white mortar. Large rectangular pavers preserved in situ indicate there was once a nicely paved promenade around the pool’s perimeter. Porticoed promenades were commonly associated with ornamental pools of the Hellenistic and Roman periods. To the rear of the pool, a screen wall masks the quarried face of the naturally veined bedrock and displays a central niche and flanking exedrae (only the western exedra has been excavated) that provide focal points at different locations around the pool.
The interior dimensions of the open-air pool measures forty-three by twenty-three meters, and it is two and a half meters deep. Its interior walls and floor are lined with a thick coat of concrete such as is typically used to line Nabataean reservoirs and cisterns. A stone staircase is built into the northeast corner to facilitate entrance into the pool. At the center of the pool is an island-pavilion perched on top of a massive stone plinth (8.5 x 11 x 2.5 m). The pavilion is rectangular in plan with broad, open doorways on at least three sides. Interior columns with marble-faced bases supported the pavilion’s roof. Numerous fragments of painted red stucco, as well as some blue and white, provide some indication of the pavilion’s decorative color scheme. An interior channel or drain cuts diagonally across the floor to connect with a channel that encircles the exterior perimeter of the pavilion, just above the maximum water level of the pool. It is likely that this exterior channel was originally capped and functioned as an overflow channel between pavilion and pool.
Excavations revealed an elaborate water distribution system incorporated into the design and construction of the pool. A holding tank perched on top of the eastern escarpment fed water to the pool and garden below. The pool’s north wall functioned as an aqueduct with channels and pipelines conducting water across the top of the wall to a castellum, or central holding tank and redistribution point built into the wall. Water then exited the castellum and was fed into stone channels that form part of an irrigation system for the garden that was laid out on the earthen terrace. In addition, two large capped channels cut into the bedrock along the eastern edge of the complex may be intended to direct excess or waste water into the wadi. What appears to be a large subterranean cistern fed and drained by pipelines has been identified through GPR in the southeastern quadrant of the terrace, but remains unexcavated.
The archaeological record indicates that the large terrace upon which the garden was found was constructed during the reign of the Nabataean king, Aretas IV (9 B.C. – A.D. 40) and thus it is believed that the garden and monumental pool were initially created at the end of the first century B.C. or early first century A.D. The role of the garden and pool complex within Petra in this earliest phase remains ambiguous. The site is closely associated with the neighboring Great Temple complex. However, the original function of the Great Temple monument remains unsettled, with theories ranging from religious/sacred (temple) to private/royal (possibly a palace or audience hall). Close parallels found in the gardens and pools of the contemporary palaces in neighboring Judaea during the reign of the Hasmonean Dynasty (168-40 B.C.) and Herod the Great (37-4 B. C.) support the interpretation of the Petra garden as part of a palace complex.
The Petra garden continued in use after the Roman annexation of Petra in A.D. 106, at which time the Great Temple was converted into an odeion or bouleutereion. It is likely that, within this context, the garden functioned as a public park much like the urban parks in contemporary Rome. Several examples of evidence for renovations have been identified with this phase of the site. For example, the addition of a bridge allowed easy access to the island-pavilion that was originally only accessible by swimming or possibly boating. In addition, a reorganization of the hydraulic system may represent a new approach to water consumption influenced by the Romans, whose rules about the use of natural resources differed from those of local inhabitants.
A deep deposit of sediment above the pool floor indicates that the pool went out of use or was not well-maintained for a period of time before the collapse of the pavilion walls into the pool as a result of the earthquake of A.D. 363 that caused much destruction in Petra. The remnants of later walls, evidence for the reuse of the hydraulic installations, and a raised field that occupies part of the earthen terrace, testify to the continued use of the site for agricultural purposes through the post-Roman occupation of Petra and into the modern era.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the garden and pool complex, 2007. Plan by F. Ishaqat, A. Leung, C. Kanellopoulous, and L.-A. Bedal.   Images   Fig. 2: Gravel pathway with stone border and excavated root cavities. Photograph by L.-A. Bedal.     Fig. 3: Part of the perforated flower pot discovered in the Nabataean garden. Photograph by L.-A. Bedal.     Fig. 3: Garden trellis painting at Little Petra. Photograph by L.-A. Bedal.   Dates ca. 90 BCE - 363 CE and later
Bibliography  Leigh-Ann Bedal, “A Paradeisos in Petra: New Light on the ‘Lower Market’.” Annual of the Department of Antiquities of Jordan 43(1999): 227-239 ibid; “Paradise Found: Petra’s Urban Oasis,” Expedition 42/2(2000): 23-36 ibid, &amp;ldquo;A Pool-Complex in Petra’s City Center.&amp;rdquo; Bulletin of the American Schools of Oriental Research 324(2001):23-41 ibid; “The Petra Garden Feasibility Study,” American Journal of Archaeology 106/3(2002): 448-450; ibid; “Desert Oasis: Water Consumption and Display in the Nabataean Capital,” Near Eastern Archaeology 65/4(2002): 225-34; Leigh-Ann Bedal, Kathryn L. Gleason, and James G. Schryver (with archaeobotanical report by J. H. Ramsay and coinage report by J.Bowsher), “The Petra Garden and Pool Complex, 2003-2005,” Annual of the Department of Antiquities of Jordan 51 (2007): 151-76. Chrysanthos Kanellopoulos,“The Layout of the Garden and Pool Complex in Petra: A Metrological Analysis,” in Annual of the Department of Antiquities of Jordan 47(2003):149-158. Elizabeth R. Macaulay Lewis, “Planting pots at Petra: a preliminary study of ollae perforatae at the Petra Garden Pool Complex and at the ‘Great Temple’,” Levant 38 (2006):159-170. Jennifer H. Ramsay and Leigh-Ann Bedal, “Garden Variety Seeds? Botanical Remains from the Petra Garden and Pool Complex,” Vegetation History and Archaeobotany 24 (2015): 621–34.  Pleiades ID 511547525 (Garden and Pool Complex at Petra)
TGN ID 7002383 (Petra)
Contributor Leigh-Ann Bedal
Publication date 3 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Private Houses at Antioch</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/syria/antioch/antioch-houses/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/syria/antioch/antioch-houses/</guid>
      <description>Province Syria
Location Antioch Antioch (Pleiades)
Location Description Antioch on the Orontes was founded by the Macedonian general Seleucus I as the capital of his Syrian empire, following the breakup of Alexander’s empire (ca. 300 BCE). He selected the site at the edge of the fertile Amuk Plain at the crossroads of important trade routes linking Syria with Palestine, the Mediterranean, and Asia Minor. Antioch was also the capital of the Roman province of Syria, annexed in 64 BCE. In the Augustan period Strabo (16.2.5) compares Antioch favorably to Alexandria in power and size. It was built along the banks of the River Orontes below the craggy heights of Mount Silpios. Because of its advantageous location, Antioch became a cultural, religious, and commercial center in the Roman period. The presence of an imperial residence, as well as buildings for the staging of athletic contests modeled after the Olympic Games, a sanctuary of Apollo, and thermal spa at Daphne, contributed to its renown in the ancient world.
Garden Private Houses at Antioch
Keywords  courtyards fountains mosaics (visual works) statues water features (landscaping)  Garden Description The most significant finds from the international excavations conducted from 1932 to 1939 were the many houses built in and around the city center, on the surrounding terraces of the mountain slopes, in the suburb of Daphne, and in the port of Seleucia Pieria. Scores of floor mosaics dating from the second to the sixth centuries CE paved these houses and brought the private lives of the elite into focus. Although no gardens have been excavated in Antioch, the examination of the figural mosaics, statuary, and the fragmentary remains of house plans suggest that there were private gardens.
During the hot summer months, the wealthy citizens of Antioch retired to Daphne, a settlement on a plateau overlooking the plain of Antioch about five miles south, for cooler breezes and its refreshing springs (Lib. Ep. 419). The suburb was admired for its “varied gardens and charming inns and an abundance of springs and houses hidden in trees and chambers which rise above the groves and luxurious baths…” (Lib. Or. 11.234). The excavations revealed the remains of houses that were richly decorated with mosaics, pools, and fountains. The fact that Daphne was the source for the water carried by two aqueducts to Antioch allowed for a generous use of water in private houses. As in Pompeii, pools and fountains seem to form the natural focal point of house designs. We turn to Libanius, a rhetorician from fourth century CE Antioch, for confirmation of the archaeological evidence: “One can judge the wealth of our waters by the number of the houses, since there are as many fountains as there are houses, or rather there are many fountains in each house” (Lib. Or. 11.246).
Unfortunately, the houses of Antioch were incompletely excavated and their state of preservation makes it difficult to distinguish the boundaries of individual houses or even the entrances into rooms. This leaves many questions, including the evidence for gardens, unanswered. The third century CE House of Menander at Daphne provides the most complete plan from Antioch, but it can only hint at the possibility of a garden (Fig. 1). The most typical feature of Antiochene houses is the sequential arrangement of the dining room, columned court, and fountain or pool (e.g., House of Menander, House of the Boat of the Psyches, House of the Drinking Contest). A similar alignment of spaces occurs in the House of Bacchus and Ariadne in Thuburbo Maius, modern Tunisia, where the diners could look out from two different dining rooms through a columned screen to a mosaic basin and beyond into a garden area (one is a peristyle garden; the other is a courtyard garden) where evidence of plantings was found. It would seem from such parallels, including the evidence of many excavated gardens in Pompeii, that plantings in the peristyles and courts were closely aligned with dining vistas and water features. One might reasonably conjecture that the courtyards and pseudo-peristyle areas with fountains and pools in the House of Menander at Daphne contained potted plants. As most of the areas of the excavated houses at Antioch were paved with mosaic, it seems less likely that there were open soil areas for plantings of evergreen trees as found in Pompeii, such as the House of Polybios. However, given the nearby topos of the cypress-filled grove of Daphne with its gurgling thermal springs and the original laurel bush (see Sacred Grove at Daphne), it is not difficult to imagine greenery inserted into the courtyards and areas accented by niched fountains and pools in the Antiochene houses.
Maps Plans Images Dates second to the sixth centuries CE
Bibliography  G. Downey, A History of Antioch in Syria from Seleucus to the Arab Conquest, Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1961 J. Lassus, “La Mosaique de Yakto, ” in eds. R. Stillwell, G.W. Elderkin, F.O. Waagé and D.B. Waagé, Antioch-on-the-Orontes I, Princeton: Department of Art and Archaeology, 1934, pp. 128-136 D. Levi, Antioch Mosaic Pavements, Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1947, pp. 326-337, pl. 79-80 E. Weber, Tabula Peutingeriana: Codex Vindobanensis 324, Graz: Akademische Druck- u. Verlagsanstalt, 1976, p. 18.  Pleiades ID 658381
TGN ID 7002354
Contributor Christine Kondoleon and Elizabeth Macaulay-Lewis
Publication date 15 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sacred Grove at Daphne</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/syria/antioch/daphne/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/syria/antioch/daphne/</guid>
      <description>Province Syria
Province Description In 64 BCE, after his successes in Armenia, Pompey the Great added Syria to the list of annexed eastern provinces of the growing Roman Empire. The conquest of Syria had not been difficult, because the remnants of the once dominant Seleucid Empire had weakened following the defeats of king Antiochus III at Thermopylae in 191 and Magnesia in Asia shortly after. Ultimately, the Seleucids could not withstand the powers of the Nabatean kingdom to the south, the Hasmonean kingdom to the west, and the new threats of Roman hegemony. With the fall of the Seleucids, Rome inherited the majority of Alexander the Great’s former conquests, and the Syrian desert would become a stage for Roman emperors to settle civil conflicts and win triumphs. Smaller Arab settlements sprang up across the region, re-inhabiting Seleucid sites and establishing new ones, and cities such as Palmyra grew in power by taking over the wealthy trade routes of the Nabateans in the second century CE. The Syrian city of Antioch, formerly Seleucia, would become one of the greatest cities of the Roman empire. Although Macedonian presence in the region introduced western styles in art and architecture before the arrival of the Romans, the cities remained Syrian in culture, population and character.
Covering the substantial central part of the Fertile Crescent, the province of Syria sat in an advantageous position between the mountain ranges of eastern Anatolia, the Mediterranean Sea, and the Arabian deserts, and it served as an area of expansion for the larger kingdoms around it. Important trans-Asian trade routes made Syria a key component in the Roman imperial economy, and large navigable rivers, such as the Euphrates and the Orontes, were exploited to connect the Persian Gulf with northern cities. The climate, although arid in the inland mountainous areas, was quite conducive to cultivation. River valleys in the mountain chains skirting the coast provided fertile terrain for agriculture, and the Orontes and Euphrates created well-watered plateaus in the steppe and desert regions of the southeast.
An irrigation system based around the qanat, an underground water channel, was used in Syria during the Roman period to water fields and gardens. Although qanats were likely introduced to the region via the earlier Achaemenid Persian dynasty, it was during the Roman and Byzantine periods that irrigation technology improved, and the majority of known qanats date to this time. The water could flow from these channels into canals, small reservoirs known today as birkas, or large wells. The ancient field systems of Syria have been well studied in areas such as the Hauran, a basalt region in the south. Cereals, olives and grapes were important crops, and were cultivated in either the broad fields on the lowland plains, or long, segmented plots on terraces in the rocky highlands. These terraced plots would have held fruit trees or vineyards.
Location Antioch
Antioch (Pleiades)
Location Description Antioch on the Orontes was founded by the Macedonian general Seleucus I as the capital of his Syrian empire, following the breakup of Alexander’s empire (ca. 300 BCE). He selected the site at the edge of the fertile Amuk Plain at the crossroads of important trade routes linking Syria with Palestine, the Mediterranean, and Asia Minor. Antioch was also the capital of the Roman province of Syria, annexed in 64 BCE. In the Augustan period Strabo (16.2.5) compares Antioch favorably to Alexandria in power and size. It was built along the banks of the River Orontes below the craggy heights of Mount Silpios. Because of its advantageous location, Antioch became a cultural, religious, and commercial center in the Roman period. The presence of an imperial residence, as well as buildings for the staging of athletic contests modeled after the Olympic Games, a sanctuary of Apollo, and thermal spa at Daphne, contributed to its renown in the ancient world.
Garden Sacred Grove at Daphne
Keywords  sacred groves  Garden Description Antioch was most famous for its public gardens, such as the sacred grove of Daphne in the precinct of Apollo. The sanctuary was described by Strabo as a “large, thickly shaded grove intersected by fountain streams in the midst of which there is an asylum precinct and a temple of Apollo and Artemis” (16.2.6). This impression is reinforced in the lecture given in 360 CE by Libanius who praises Daphne for “the number and thickness and height of the cypresses, the shady paths, the choruses of singing birds, the even breeze, the odors sweeter than spices, the stately aqueducts, the vines trained to form banqueting hall – these are the gardens of Alcinous…a veritable Sybaris” (Lib. Or. 11.236).
Of Hellenistic origin, the site was famous during the Roman period for its cypress (Cupressus sp.) grove (Libanius, Or. 11.234-243; Strabo, 16.2.6). There is art historical and textual evidence for the grove, but no archaeological excavations of the grove have been undertaken nor has the precinct been defined. According to Libanius, Seleucus dedicated Daphne to Apollo because he found one of the arrow heads that Apollo had shot off in anger after the transformation of Daphne into a laurel (Laurus nobilis) (Libanius, Or. 11.94-99). According to the myth, it was here that the eponymous nymph, daughter of Ge and river god Ladon, was pursued and overtaken by Apollo at which point she was transformed into the laurel (Greek daphne, Fig. 2). In his disappointment at losing the nymph, Apollo shot all of his arrows, among which was one with his name that fell into the earth. When Seleucus found this buried arrow, he honored the discovery by creating a sacred enclosure, planting a grove of cypress trees, and dedicating a temple of Apollo (Lib. Or. 11.94-99). The esteem in which the grove at Daphne was held is attested by Libanius who remarks that he will write the emperor himself when an official threatened to cut the cypresses (Lib. Or. I.262-3). Reportedly, Seleucus planted a cypress grove and constructed a temple at the site (Sozomen, Hist. eccl., 5.19). Malalas (204.9-16) writes that Herakles planted a cypress grove and that the Heraklia was located outside the grove near the temple of Athena. Philostratus, however, reports a different story about the grove: the Landon worshipped the laurel. A cypress grove surrounded the temple, and a single cypress sapling grew naturally in honor of Cyparissus, an Assyrian youth who also experienced a metamorphosis (Philostratus, V A, 1.16).
The purposeful evocation of a sacred landscape can be seen in the placement of the temple near the spring Castalia in which the oracle of Apollo was considered to reside. A representation of the journey from the springs of Daphne to Antioch along a tree-lined street is picturesquely depicted in the topographic border of the mosaic of Megalopsychia found in the mid-fifth century CE villa at Daphne (Yakto area) (Fig. 3). Water flows from a vase held by a nude female, identified by a Greek inscription as the personification “Kastalia,” into a semi-circular colonnaded nymphaeum. Another stream of water flows from her into a reservoir with another nymph identified as “Pallas,” but there is no sign of the sacred grove or the temple. In addition, the grove was the symbol for Daphne on a medieval copy of the Tabula Peutingeriana (4th century CE). Though archaeologists have not found any material traces of the revered grove at Daphne, there is archaeological evidence for the planting of groves at the Sanctuary of Apollo Hylates (“He of the woodlands”) in Kourion, Cyprus, and elsewhere (see: cross-references here).
Maps Plans Images Dates Hellenistic
Bibliography  G. Downey, A History of Antioch in Syria from Seleucus to the Arab Conquest, Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1961 J. Lassus, “La Mosaique de Yakto, ” in eds. R. Stillwell, G.W. Elderkin, F.O. Waagé and D.B. Waagé, Antioch-on-the-Orontes I, Princeton: Department of Art and Archaeology, 1934, pp. 128-136 D. Levi, Antioch Mosaic Pavements, Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1947, pp. 326-337, pl. 79-80 E. Weber, Tabula Peutingeriana: Codex Vindobanensis 324, Graz: Akademische Druck- u. Verlagsanstalt, 1976, p. 18.  Pleiades ID 658381
TGN ID 7002354
Contributor Christine Kondoleon and Elizabeth Macaulay-Lewis
Publication date 3 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shrine Complex in Insula E125</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/arabia_petraea/havarra/havarra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/arabia_petraea/havarra/havarra/</guid>
      <description>Province Arabia Petraea
Location Auara
Auara (Pleiades)
Garden Shrine Complex in Insula E125
Keywords  aqueducts basins (vessels) insulae naoi (chambers) planters (containers) shrines (structures) temene  Garden Description A few decades after a Nabataean shrine at Hawara (Roman Havarra) had been severely damaged during the Roman conquest of Arabia Petraea, the site’s inhabitants built another shrine at the same location. The Roman period shrine occupied the southeast corner of a multi-unit insula (E125), but could only be accessed from outside the complex. This shrine consisted of a square naos (containing the cult statue and votive offerings) enclosed in a rectangular open-air temenos (Figs. 1-2). Upon entering the temenos, worshippers walked to the naos along a 20 m long paved processional way that was flanked by two long raised planters. An aqueduct-fed basin next to the door of the naos appears to have supplied the shrine with so much fresh water that it must have been intended not just for ritual cleansing, but for supplying the planters as well. Given the relatively shallow depth of the planters, and that no root balls or pots were found within, they probably contained shrubs and/or flowers rather than trees. Although the architect clearly tried to make the planters symmetrical in size, shape, and location, their design (and that of the whole Roman shrine) was constrained by the reuse of some Nabataean walls as foundations.
Maps Plans   Plan of Shrine Complex in Insula E125.   Images   Perspective reconstruction of Shrine Complex in Insula E125 with the low naos and notched peak behind.   Dates first century CE, mid‐second to third century CE
Bibliography  Oleson, John Peter, M. Barbara Reeves, Gregory S. Baker, Erik de Bruijn, Yvonne Gerber, M. Nikolic, and Andrew N. Sherwood. 2008. “Preliminary Report on Excavations at Al-Humayma, Ancient Hawara, 2004 and 2005.” Annual of the Department of Antiquities of Jordan 52: 309–42. (Stable URL). Reeves, M. Barbara. 2019. “A Nabataean and Roman Shrine with Civic and Military Gods at Humayma, Jordan.” Arabian Archaeology &amp;amp; Epigraphy 30 (1): 134–55. (DOI).  Pleiades ID 746716 (Auara)
TGN ID 7007646 (Ḥawwārah)
Contributor M. Barbara Reeves
Publication date 3 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb garden at Tyre</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/syria/tyrus/tyrus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/syria/tyrus/tyrus/</guid>
      <description>Province Syria
Province Description In 64 BCE, after his successes in Armenia, Pompey the Great added Syria to the list of annexed eastern provinces of the growing Roman Empire. The conquest of Syria had not been difficult, because the remnants of the once dominant Seleucid Empire had weakened following the defeats of king Antiochus III at Thermopylae in 191 and Magnesia in Asia shortly after. Ultimately, the Seleucids could not withstand the powers of the Nabatean kingdom to the south, the Hasmonean kingdom to the west, and the new threats of Roman hegemony. With the fall of the Seleucids, Rome inherited the majority of Alexander the Great’s former conquests, and the Syrian desert would become a stage for Roman emperors to settle civil conflicts and win triumphs. Smaller Arab settlements sprang up across the region, re-inhabiting Seleucid sites and establishing new ones, and cities such as Palmyra grew in power by taking over the wealthy trade routes of the Nabateans in the second century CE. The Syrian city of Antioch, formerly Seleucia, would become one of the greatest cities of the Roman empire. Although Macedonian presence in the region introduced western styles in art and architecture before the arrival of the Romans, the cities remained Syrian in culture, population and character.
Covering the substantial central part of the Fertile Crescent, the province of Syria sat in an advantageous position between the mountain ranges of eastern Anatolia, the Mediterranean Sea, and the Arabian deserts, and it served as an area of expansion for the larger kingdoms around it. Important trans-Asian trade routes made Syria a key component in the Roman imperial economy, and large navigable rivers, such as the Euphrates and the Orontes, were exploited to connect the Persian Gulf with northern cities. The climate, although arid in the inland mountainous areas, was quite conducive to cultivation. River valleys in the mountain chains skirting the coast provided fertile terrain for agriculture, and the Orontes and Euphrates created well-watered plateaus in the steppe and desert regions of the southeast.
An irrigation system based around the qanat, an underground water channel, was used in Syria during the Roman period to water fields and gardens. Although qanats were likely introduced to the region via the earlier Achaemenid Persian dynasty, it was during the Roman and Byzantine periods that irrigation technology improved, and the majority of known qanats date to this time. The water could flow from these channels into canals, small reservoirs known today as birkas, or large wells. The ancient field systems of Syria have been well studied in areas such as the Hauran, a basalt region in the south. Cereals, olives and grapes were important crops, and were cultivated in either the broad fields on the lowland plains, or long, segmented plots on terraces in the rocky highlands. These terraced plots would have held fruit trees or vineyards.
Location Tyrus
Tyrus (Pleiades)
Location Description Tyre, an ancient Phoenician port city (est. 2750 BCE), became part of the Roman Empire in 64 BCE. It was legendary as the birthplace of the goddess Europa and queen Dido, founder of Carthage.
Garden Tomb garden at Tyre
Keywords  tombs basins (vessels) niches  Garden Description A tomb garden (Tomb Complex 15) has been found in a cemetery complex dating to the fourth century CE. (Fig. 1) Excavated by Maurice Chéhab, it features an enclosed garden (18x21 m) surrounded by a wall. The west wall supports a water channel which fed a rectangular basin in the apsidal hall and a large square basin in the northeast corner of the garden. (Fig. 2) A small square basin was installed by the great basin to catch the water and transmit it to channels in the garden itself. Along the central axis of the garden postholes were found, suggesting a free-standing trellis, or perhaps some form of fence. Other features of the walls include decorative niches, possibly for sculpture. No evidence for plants has been recovered, but from the structural arrangement, it is clearly a garden. Such tomb gardens provided a gracious place for visiting the dead and perhaps for growing produce for offerings and subsidizing the maintenance of the complex.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Tomb Complex 15 showing garden beds, basins, water channels and post holes (Chéhab, Fig. 42).   Images   Fig. 2: Photograph of Tomb Complex 15 showing the garden, basins and adjacent rooms (Chéhab, Pl. XLVIII).   Dates fourth century CE
Bibliography  M. H. Chéhab, Fouilles de Tyr: La Necropole. Paris: Bulletin du Musée de Beyrouth XXXIV (1984): 270-280. (worldcat) L. De Jong, “Performing Death in Tyre: The Life and Afterlife of a Roman Cemetery in the Province of Syria. AJA 114.4 (Oct. 2010) pp. 597-630. (jstor)  Pleiades ID 678437
TGN ID 7030348
Contributor Kathryn L. Gleason and Amina-Aïcha Malek
Publication date 3 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>