<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The House aux Fleurons (boulevard de la Paix) on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/the-house-aux-fleurons-boulevard-de-la-paix/</link>
    <description>Recent content in The House aux Fleurons (boulevard de la Paix) on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/the-house-aux-fleurons-boulevard-de-la-paix/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The House aux Fleurons (boulevard de la Paix)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/the_house_aux_fleurons_boulevard_de_la_paix/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/the_house_aux_fleurons_boulevard_de_la_paix/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location DUROCORTORUM (Reims, France)
DUROCORTORUM (Pleiades)
Garden The House aux Fleurons (boulevard de la Paix)
Keywords  porticos trench  Garden Description BEL 2.2.1: Reims, House aux Flerurons Along the north side runs a secondary street following the orientation of the town in Augustan times. Along this street, in the northern part of the house, a series of rooms with mosaics were found. On the south side, the space A (about 30 x 14 m) was probably a garden. The central part, surrounded on three sides by porticos, had two wide trenches (a) cut into the chalk and filled with clay, a strong indication of a garden. The trenches seem to be connected on the south side, and the south wall seems to be the limit of the parcel.
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Ch. Loriquet, La mosaïque des Promenades et autres trouvées à Reims, Reims, 1862 (worldcat) D.R.A.H..A., La Bourse du Travail à Reims, Bulletin de la société archéologique champenoise, n°4, 1977, p. 77-79  R. Neiss, La structure urbaine de Reims antique et son évolution du Ier au IIIe siècle après J.-C. Les villes de la Gaule Belgique au Haut-Empire, in: Actes du colloque tenu à Saint-Riquier (Somme). Revue archéologique de Picardie, n°3-4, 1984, p. 171-191, (worldcat) A. Balmelle, R. Neiss, Les maisons de l’élite à Durocortorum, in Archéologie urbaine à Reims, Bulletin de la société archéologique champenoise, t. 96, 2003, 4, p. 74. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108945
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>