<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>sacred Grove on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/sacred-grove/</link>
    <description>Recent content in sacred Grove on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2020 10:39:31 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/sacred-grove/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Temple Grove of Apollo</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/shamika_ghate/6._didyma_temple_grove_of_apollo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/shamika_ghate/6._didyma_temple_grove_of_apollo/</guid>
      <description>Province Asia Asia (Pleiades)
Province description The region of what is now modern Turkey became a part of the Roman Empire in 133 B.C. when king Attalos III of Pergamum bequeathed his kingdom to the Roman people. The province included the heartland of the Pergamene kingdom as well as the territories of Mysia, Lydia, Ionia, Caria, western Phrygia and the eastern Aegean islands. Under Augustus in 27 B.C. Asia was declared a senatorial province and the governance of a proconsul. The capital of the province was Ephesos, although Pergamon may have fulfilled this role initially. Under Diocletian (284-305 A.D.) the province was subdivided into smaller administrative units: Hellespontus, Asia, Lydia, Caria, Phrygia I and Phrygia II. Due to its excellent harbors on the west coast and its many navigable rivers, Asia’s water-borne trade with the rest of the Mediterranean flourished. In the second century A.D. Asia experienced great prosperity, to which the growth and architectural aggrandizement of many of its cities attest. In the area of Kibyra, bordering the regions of Lycia, Caria, Phrygia and Pisidia, numerous inscriptions refer to the large imperial estates of Roman families. Woolen textiles, marble, and timber constituted a significant part of the commodities exported from the province.
While the Romans might have looked to the Greeks for inspiration in philosophy, architecture, sculpture, and the fine arts, the non-Greek peoples of the eastern Mediterranean are their inspiration for luxury, fine-living, and the status conferred by displays of individual wealth (Athenaeus Deip. XV.690). Asia was a center for such splendor, first in the kingdoms of Lydia, Phrygia, and Lycia, and then continued by the Persian satraps, and later the Hellenistic kings. The Persian paradeisos is particularly well-attested in literature referencing Asia. That these gardens are known primarily from Roman-period literary sources indicates their continuing influence. For example, long after the gold of Lydia’s Pactolus River had disappeared, Lydia remained a literary topos, not only for copious wealth, but for a life of luxury set in a landscape of natural abundance. Athenaeus (Deipnosophistae 12.515d-f) wrote in the second century A.D. that
&amp;ldquo;The Lydians in their luxury planned parks and made them like gardens and so kept in the shade. For they thought it more dainty not to have the sun’s rays touch them at all…&amp;rdquo;
Other districts of Asia captured the Roman imagination: Pliny the Elder writes of an ancient plane tree (Sycamorus orientalis) in Lycia with a girth of sufficient circumference to house a grotto in its hollow trunk, ornamented with pumice and moss with provisions for 18 people to dine there (Pliny HN 12.9).
The paradeisoi of the Persian satraps are of particular influence on the introduction of horti and gardens of Rome. The paradeisos, from the Persian, paira daeza, or “enclosed place,” is a term that had evolved by the Hellenistic period to mean a large enclosed park with luxurious gardens as well as orchards, collections of trees, crops, and hunting areas (see Sardis below). It was at Sardis that the Greek Lysander visited Cyrus the Younger, a visit recorded by Clearchus and retold by Xenophon. It is an essential moment in garden history recounted for the Romans by Cicero, De Senectute. 17.59. These paradeisoi, in the sense of luxurious orchards, are said by the Romans to have been brought to Greece by Kimon (Aristot. apud Plut. Cim. 10; comp. Cic. de Off. 2.18Plutarch), and were adopted by Hellenistic kings throughout Greece and southern Italy during the late Hellenistic period. The hunting parks at Daskyleion and Celenae are also vividly described by Xenophon (See Anabasis 1.2.7, 2.4.14 and Oeconomicus 4.13). Xenophon also describes how paradeisoi were occupied or cut down by armies during the fourth and third centuries BC. Appreciation for these parks apparently continued, and Seleucus of Syria took over the royal paradeisos at Sardis (Plutarch, Demetrios 50.6). Years of instability followed, so it is difficult to know what the Romans themselves thought of paradeisoi in Asia in the second and first centuries B.C. Notable examples of paradeisoi, in some form, may have been visible to Romans visiting Asia, as well. For example, the Mausoleum at Halicarnassus is now thought by its excavators to have been set in a grove or park.
Thus, the paradeisos, the alsos, the gymnasium, and the quadriporticus are not forms the Romans suddenly “discovered.” They had had a long influence and were integrated into the Hellenistic architectural forms of the Italic landscape. In the second century B.C., however, when the Roman generals began to define themselves as rulers of an empire, they turned directly to the palaces and paradeisoi of the Hellenistic monarchs to establish their power, to display spoils of war, and to create the luxurious setting for life in Rome. They further adapted the evolving quadriporticus form for display to the public Despite the importance of Asia Minor in the history of the Roman landscape, archaeological evidence is scant. The excavators contacted for this essay indicated that parks, gardens, and other planted areas have yet to become a subject of research design for the region and finds appear to be few—primarily inscriptions and wall paintings. Most of the smaller domestic courtyards—often the most manageable to investigate - are paved. The larger palaestrae, gymnasia, and enclosed open spaces have not been investigated for landscape architectural and planting features, although recently an important campaign of work in the South Agora at Aphrodisias is setting an important precedent (see below). This catalog includes areas with dirt and incomplete paved surfaces, and notes sites where the excavators have some level of optimism about fruitful future study. The subject of designed landscapes, gardens, and planted areas in Asia Minor awaits archaeological investigation.
Location DIDYMA (Didim, Turkey) (Pleiades)
Garden Temple Grove of Apollo
Keywords  sacred grove sanctuary  Garden Description The sanctuary of Apollo at Didyma was a regional sanctuary that lay on the border of Caria and Ionia (Strabo 12.1.2). The Temple of Apollo, attested by Strabo (12.1.5), was built on the site of the spring and oracle of Apollo mentioned by Herodotus (1.92.159) and Pausanius (7.2.6). Inscriptions found in the area of the sanctuary attest to a “sacred grove” [(CIG 2885d)] and Strabo (14.1.5) specifies that in his day a grove (alsos) was planted inside and outside the temple precinct.
The precinct has been well-defined archaeologically, but the archaeologists identified no traces of the trees.
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  K. Tuchelt, “Didyma” in ed. E. Meyers, Oxford Encyclopedia of Archaeology in the Near East, Oxford: Oxford University Press, Oxford,1996 : p.160 (worldcat) Birge,D E. Sacred Groves in the Ancient Greek World. PhD. Dissertation. University of California at Berkeley, 1982, 394-395. (worldcat) B. Haussoullier, &amp;ldquo;le temple d&amp;rsquo;Apollon didymien&amp;rdquo; Revue de Philologie 22 (1898) 50-51.(worldcat)  Pleiades ID 599593
TGN ID 7002358
Contributor Kathryn Gleason (ORCID: 0000-0001-6260-8378)
Publication date 03 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Funerary Grove of Epikrates and Tomb Garden of Tertia and Secundus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/funerary_grove_of_epikrates_and_tomb_garden_of_tertia_and_secundus/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 19:30:32 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/funerary_grove_of_epikrates_and_tomb_garden_of_tertia_and_secundus/</guid>
      <description>Province Asia
Province Description The region of what is now modern Turkey became a part of the Roman Empire in 133 BCE, when king Attalos III of Pergamum bequeathed his kingdom to the Roman people. The province included the heartland of the Pergamene kingdom as well as the territories of Mysia, Lydia, Ionia, Caria, western Phrygia and the eastern Aegean islands. Under Augustus in 27 BCE Asia was declared a senatorial province and the governance of a proconsul. The capital of the province was Ephesos, although Pergamon may have fulfilled this role initially. Under Diocletian (284-305 CE) the province was subdivided into smaller administrative units: Hellespontus, Asia, Lydia, Caria, Phrygia I and Phrygia II. Due to its excellent harbors on the west coast and its many navigable rivers, Asia’s water-borne trade with the rest of the Mediterranean flourished. In the second century CE Asia experienced great prosperity, to which the growth and architectural aggrandizement of many of its cities attest. In the area of Kibyra, bordering the regions of Lycia, Caria, Phrygia and Pisidia, numerous inscriptions refer to the large imperial estates of Roman families. Woolen textiles, marble, and timber constituted a significant part of the commodities exported from the province.
While the Romans might have looked to the Greeks for inspiration in philosophy, architecture, sculpture, and the fine arts, the non-Greek peoples of the eastern Mediterranean are their inspiration for luxury, fine-living, and the status conferred by displays of individual wealth (Ath. Deip. 15.690). Asia was a center for such splendor, first in the kingdoms of Lydia, Phrygia, and Lycia, and then continued by the Persian satraps, and later the Hellenistic kings. The Persian paradeisos is particularly well attested in literature referencing Asia. That these gardens are known primarily from Roman-period literary sources indicates their continuing influence. For example, long after the gold of Lydia’s Pactolus River had disappeared, Lydia remained a literary topos, not only for copious wealth, but for a life of luxury set in a landscape of natural abundance. Athenaeus (Deip. 12.515d-f) wrote in the second century CE that
 &amp;quot;The Lydians in their luxury planned parks and made them like gardens and so kept in the shade. For they thought it more dainty not to have the sun’s rays touch them at all&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;
 Other districts of Asia captured the Roman imagination: Pliny the Elder writes of an ancient plane tree (Sycamorus orientalis) in Lycia with a girth of sufficient circumference to house a grotto in its hollow trunk, ornamented with pumice and moss with provisions for 18 people to dine there (Plin. HN 12.5).
The paradeisoi of the Persian satraps are of particular influence on the introduction of horti and gardens of Rome. The paradeisos, from the Persian, paira daeza, or “enclosed place,” is a term that had evolved by the Hellenistic period to mean a large enclosed park with luxurious gardens as well as orchards, collections of trees, crops, and hunting areas. It was at Sardis that the Greek Lysander visited Cyrus the Younger, a visit recorded by Klearchos and retold by Xenophon. It is an essential moment in garden history recounted for the Romans by Cicero (Sen. 59). These paradeisoi, in the sense of luxurious orchards, are said by the Romans to have been brought to Greece by Kimon (Aristotole apud Plut. Cim. 10; cf. Cic. de Off. 2.64), and were adopted by Hellenistic kings throughout Greece and southern Italy during the late Hellenistic period. The hunting parks at Daskyleion and Celenae are also vividly described by Xenophon (see An. 1.2.7, 2.4.14 and Oec. 4.13). Xenophon also describes how paradeisoi were occupied or cut down by armies during the fourth and third centuries BCE. Appreciation for these parks apparently continued, and Seleucus of Syria took over the royal paradeisos at Sardis (Plut. Dem. 50). Years of instability followed, so it is difficult to know what the Romans themselves thought of paradeisoi in Asia in the second and first centuries BCE. Notable examples of paradeisoi, in some form, may have been visible to Romans visiting Asia, as well. For example, the Mausoleum at Halicarnassus is now thought by its excavators to have been set in a grove or park.
Thus, the paradeisos, the alsos, the gymnasium, and the quadriporticus are not forms the Romans suddenly “discovered.” They had had a long influence and were integrated into the Hellenistic architectural forms of the Italic landscape. In the second century BCE, however, when the Roman generals began to define themselves as rulers of an empire, they turned directly to the palaces and paradeisoi of the Hellenistic monarchs to establish their power, to display spoils of war, and to create the luxurious setting for life in Rome. They further adapted the evolving quadriporticus form for display to the public
Despite the importance of Asia Minor in the history of the Roman landscape, archaeological evidence is scant. The excavators contacted for the gardens of this region indicated that parks, gardens, and other planted areas have yet to become a subject of research design for the region and finds appear to be few — primarily inscriptions and wall paintings. Most of the smaller domestic courtyards — often the most manageable to investigate — are paved. The larger palaestrae, gymnasia, and enclosed open spaces have not been investigated for landscape architectural and planting features, although recently an important campaign of work in the South Agora at Aphrodisias is setting an important precedent (CROSS-REF). The gardens included in this province include areas with dirt and incomplete paved surfaces, as well as sites where the excavators have some level of optimism that future study may yet reveal more about gardens. The subject of designed landscapes, gardens, and planted areas in Asia Minor remains in its archaeological infancy.
Location Nakrason
Nakrason (Pleiades)
Garden Funerary Grove of Epikrates and Tomb Garden of Tertia and Secundus
Keywords  stelae funerals watercourses vineyards groves (plant communities) Ulmus (genus) woodlands (plant communities) buildings (structures) wall tombs inscription Athenaeus Pliny the Elder Cicero Aristotle Plutarch quadriportici palaestrae gymnasiums  Garden Description A large stele of light grey marble inscribed on both sides and found in 1965 lying in a field between Akhisar (Thyateira) and Kirkağuç (Nakrason) in the border land between Lydia and Mysia records the final part (perhaps second half) of the will of a certain Epikrates, the son of Epikrates, from Thyateira, establishing a foundation to provide commemorative funerary rites for his son Diophantos, also from Thyateira. The detailed provisions of the will, which include specific topographical indications for the disposition of various productive properties to support the foundation, reveal a network of watercourses, vineyards, olive groves, cultivated fields, and open land in which a funerary grove (alsos) is set aside for Diophantos and another exception is made for “the garden in which my mother Tertia and my maternal uncle Secundus are buried” (κήπου, ἐν ᾦ τέθαπται Τερτία μου ἡ μήτηρ καὶ ὁ πρὸς μητρὸς θεῖος Σεκοῦνδος, lines 90-91). Two of the nearby properties are identified with toponyms, the “Elm Grove” (Πτελεών, lines 16, 18, 30) and the “Brickworks” (Πλινθούλκιον, line 28), which suggest productive areas comprising woodlands and claybeds as well as cultivated plots. The funerary complex described by Epikrates included buildings (οἰκοδομήματα, line 47), surrounding walls (περικείμενοι τοῖχοι, line 47), and the tomb of Diophantos, destined eventually to house the remains also of Epikrates and other members of his family (lines 76-79). The male line of the clan (Epikrates, Epikrates, and Diophantos) proclaimed its Greek ethnicity in its nomenclature, but the women of the family—his mother Tertia (sister of Secundus), his wife Laevilla, his daughter Tertia, and his granddaughter Cestia—all bore Roman names. Such mixed marriages of local male élites and women from the families of the Roman governing class (or, eventually, simply bearing Roman names) are characteristic of the provincial aristocracy of Asia Minor during the first century, the period to which, on the basis of its vocabulary and lettering, the inscribed testament of Epikrates belongs.
Maps Plans Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  P. Herrmann and K. Z. Polaktan, Das Testament des Epikrates und andere neue Inschriften aus dem Museum von Manisa (Sitz. Wien 265.1). Vienna, 1969, pp. 7-36. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 811119038
TGN ID Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 9 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>