<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>FLIESSEM-OTRANG on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/categories/fliessem-otrang/</link>
    <description>Recent content in FLIESSEM-OTRANG on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/categories/fliessem-otrang/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/fliessem-otrang-villa-rural/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/fliessem-otrang-villa-rural/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location FLIESSEM-OTRANG (Germany)
FLIESSEM-OTRANG (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa
Keywords  villae rusticae mosaic porticoes courtyard  Garden Description This villa rustica was built on the slope of a hill about 30 kilometers north of Colonia Augusta Treverorum, close to the Roman road from Trier to Cologne, now B 51/E29. It is a kilometer or two south of the village of Fliessem. The original core of the villa is of second century date, but the building was enlarged considerably in the third century to take up an area of 4225 square meters (Fig. 1). It was occupied until around AD 400. The house (A on plan) occupied a position at the eastern end of the property, and in its final state it measured 60 x 60 meters and had 66 rooms, many of them decorated with mosaic floors. On the northern and southern sides were porticoes, and from the southern portico with its pavilions a view of the valley below was afforded.
The entrance to the house on the west was flanked by two protruding pavilions framing an open courtyard. Immediately to the west of this was another open courtyard enclosed by a wall. It might be expected, even if the evidence is sparse, that a garden or park was laid out at least in front of the entrance at the west (G on plan).
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  H. Mylius, &amp;ldquo;Die Rekonstruktion der römischen Villen von Nennig und Fliessem,&amp;rdquo; Bonner Jahrbuch 129, 1924:120-128, fig. 3, pl. 7; E. M. Wightman, Roman Trier and the Treveri, London, 1970, pp. 143-145, fig. 15; H. Cüppers, ed., Die Römer in Rheinland-Pfalz, Stuttgart,1990, pp. 367-371, figs. 264-265. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/1075378207) E. M. Wightman, Roman Trier and the Treveri, London, 1970, pp. 143-145, fig. 15 [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/1001859813) H. Cüppers, ed., Die Römer in Rheinland-Pfalz, Stuttgart,1990, pp. 367-371, figs. 264-265. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/924024101)  Pleiades ID 108982
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 12 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
