<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>lararium on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/lararium/</link>
    <description>Recent content in lararium on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 00:10:10 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/lararium/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>II.viii.2-3</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_viii/iii.viii.2-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_viii/iii.viii.2-3/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region II
Insula Insula VIII
Keywords  thermopolium triclinia lecti lararium  Garden Description Customers at this thermopolium were served at a counter at the street and at the masonry triclinium (l. medius, 3.60 m.; l. imus 2.85; l. summus 2.30 m.) in the rear garden. This was located against the north wall to the front of this long, narrow garden and had a round table (0.50 m. in dia.) between the couches and a rectangular table (0.65 x 0.89 m.) at the end of the lectus summus. A niche lararium was next to it with a tufa altar below decorated with a large carved club. A bench for cooking was built against the south wall at the west end with two arched openings for fuel storage underneath.
Plans   Fig. 62, Plan of Region II, insula viii   Pleiades ID 456321707
TGN ID 7004658
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p.92 (worldcat) Orr, Roman Domestic Religion: A Study of the Roman Household Deities and their Shrines at Pompeii and Herculaneum, no.65 (worldcat)  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 10 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa del Mobilio Carbonizzato</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tiffany_fong2/casa_del_mobilio_carbonizzato/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tiffany_fong2/casa_del_mobilio_carbonizzato/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Insula V
House 5
Garden Casa del Mobilio Carbonizzato
Keywords  fauces aedicula opus signinum aedicula lararium [lararium]  Garden Description 549.V.5. Visible from the fauces, this little courtyard (a) had an elaborate aedicula shrine which was excavated in 1932-1933. A low double wall with a gutter bordered the courtyard on the west and north sides with a cistern opening located in the center of the west edge of garden. Four small flower beds on the sides and a circular bed in the center had raised borders to retain the water for the plants within, and the remainder of the courtyard was paved in opus signinum. Jashemski commented that the garden had been restored with eleven such small planting beds. The east wall had traces of an animal painting on a blue background by the aedicula lararium. A deer was painted on the right side and several more indistinct animal forms were noted over the lararium. At the south end of this wall there were traces of leaves and a lattice fence suggesting a garden painting may have been located here.
Plans   Plan of Casa dell’Ara Laterizia     Plan of Casa dell’Ara Laterizia   Images   Illustration of Casa dell’Ara Laterizia     Illustration of Casa dell’Ara Laterizia   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1932-1933
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 370-371 Maiuri, Herculaneum,p. 44 Maiuri, Ercolano, pp.260-261 and fig. 203 (plan) on p. 256.  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
