<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/labastide-darmagnac_landes/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 12:39:10 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/labastide-darmagnac_landes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa of Géou, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/labastide-darmagnac_landes/gallia_villa_of_ge%CC%81ou_yji/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 12:39:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/labastide-darmagnac_landes/gallia_villa_of_ge%CC%81ou_yji/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania
Province Description&amp;ndash;&amp;gt; A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location LABASTIDE-D’ARMAGNAC
(Pleiades)
House Villa of Géou
House Description Situated two kilometers southeast of the town, at a place called Géou, this villa sits on a little plateau overlooking the Douze. It has been known since the middle of the nineteenth century and was excavated between 1970 and 1978.
Garden Courtyard
Keywords  archaeological garden mosaic peristyles (Roman courtyards) pool [masonry](not sure which one)  Garden Description From the first phase of occupation in the early empire there remain only the foundations of a villa rustica. In late antiquity, the villa was totally remodeled. In the new phase, it had an ample, slightly trapezoidal peristyle (44 x 34 m) with a large (7.4 m diameter) pool. This courtyard was presumably planted as a garden. The floors of the porticoes of the peristyle bore polychrome mosaics. Along the southeast and southwest sides of the peristyle stretched the rooms for daily life. The reception room (7.5 x 8.75 m) opened off the middle of the southeast portico. Because the peristyle was trapezoidal – leaning to the right as seen from the reception room – the pool had to be off center to the left in the courtyard to be fully enjoyed from this room. Two symmetric, rectangular masonry masses extend outward from the wall of pool.
Plans   Labastide-d&amp;#39;Armagnac. Plan of Villa of Géou （cat. N.22)   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1970-1978
Bibliography  .-P. Bost et al., “La villa gallo-romaine de Géou à Labastide-d’Armagnac (Landes)” Bull.de la société de Borda (Dax), 1984, p. 651-703 (with an unfolding plan by R. Monturet) (worldcat) B. Boyrie-Fénié, Carte archéologique de la Gaule, Les Landes(40), 1994, p. 96-99, n°131 worldcat Catherine Balmelle, Les demeures aristocratiques d&amp;rsquo;Aquitaine, societe et culture de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquite tardive dans le sou-ouest de la Gaule, Ausonius, supple. d&amp;rsquo;Aquitania 10, Bordeaux 2001, p.357-359, plan p. 449. For the pool see, Gallia J. Coupry, 19, 1961, p. 392, 21, 1963, p. 529-30 ; 29 ; 1971 p. 356 ; 33, 1975, p. 483, 35, 1977, p. 465 ; 37, 1979, p. 514. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 249913
TGN ID []()
Contributor Clopper Almon (https://www.econ.umd.edu/facultyprofile/almon/clopper)
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>