<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>sarcophagi on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/sarcophagi/</link>
    <description>Recent content in sarcophagi on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 09:07:30 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/sarcophagi/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Ti. Claudios Lykos</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/macedonia/thessaloniki/thessaloniki_tomb_garden_of_tib_claudios_lykos/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 09:07:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/macedonia/thessaloniki/thessaloniki_tomb_garden_of_tib_claudios_lykos/</guid>
      <description>Province Macedonia
Location Thessaloniki
Thessaloniki (Pleiades)
Garden Tomb Garden of Ti. Claudios Lykos
Keywords tombs
sarcophagi
epitaphs
Garden Description A limestone sarcophagus found at Thessaloniki and first reported in 1962 preserves an epitaph set up in 147 A.D. by Ti. Claudios Lykos, a local town counselor (bouleutÆw), for himself, his loving wife Meinoukia (Minucia) Theoprepes, and his two daughters Roda and Theoprepes. As Robert correctly observed (Bull. Épigr. 1963:134), the garbled inscription—a product, it seems, of two drafts of the text being confused by the carver—nonetheless makes clear that Lykos had built a tomb garden complex, which he calls a ≤r“on, comprising “a field, house, garden, and, burial place” (égrÒw, oﬁk€a, k∞pow, tÒpow), in which were situated various sarcophagi (lhnÒi) and statues (éndriãntew) and which he attempted to prevent from future alienation. Two other inscriptions found in the same complex identify Lykos as granting, in one case, a cinerary urn (kaÊstra), in the other, in 167 A.D., a burial place (tÒpow) to others for their monuments. A secondary inscription on the cover of Lykos’s sarcophagus attests its reuse later in the third century. Robert and Kubińska considered the “house” (oﬁk€a) to be that of a gardener appointed to oversee the garden complex, but the traditional formulaic pairing of field and house, garden and tomb attested elsewhere (at the tomb gardens of C. Hostius Pamphilus at Rome [cross-ref, XXX] and of C. [Ma?]rcius C. l. Cleon at Bari [cross-ref XXX]) suggests that it is Lykos’s own house that is meant and, perhaps, that the tomb garden is located on its property. For the conventional “tomb” (tãfow, sepulchrum, monumentum) Lykos substitutes “burial place” (tÒpow, Latin locus, as in l(ocus) d(atus) d(ecreto) d(ecurionum), a formula for awarding honorific burials with which Lykos the decurion was assuredly familiar), but his conformity to the traditional conceptual juxtapositions is apparent. To judge from the presence of statues and more than one sarcophagus, and from the granting of burial space to others, Lykos’s funerary garden was a substantial complex.
Maps Images Dates 147 CE, 167 CE
Bibliography : IG X 2,1.608; J. Kubińska, Les monuments funéraires dans les inscriptions grecques de l’Asie Mineure. Warsaw, 1968, p. 146; P. Petsas, “AgrÒw, oﬁk€a, k∞pow, tÒpow,” in J. H. Dell, ed. Macedonian Studies in Honor of Charles F. Edson. Thessaloniki, 1981, pp. 295-98; Bull. Épigr. 1963, 134; 1984, 252.
Pleiades ID 491741
TGN ID 7011182
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 16 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cemetery Garden of Metrodorus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/dalmatia/salona/salona_cemetery_garden_of_metrodorus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 10:10:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/dalmatia/salona/salona_cemetery_garden_of_metrodorus/</guid>
      <description>Province Dalmatia
Location Salona
Salona (Pleiades)
Sublocation Garden Cemetery Garden of Metrodorus
Keywords tombs
epitaphs
sarcophagi (coffins)
Garden Description A sarcophagus found at Salona in 1824, transported to the museum in Split, and subsequently lost bore an inscription recording the donation by Aur(elius) Aprilianus to Aur(elius) Amurus and Aur(elia) Quinta of a sarcophagus “which is in the garden of Metrodorus” and specifying that it was put into position while they were still alive (Aur(elius) Aprilianus se vivo donavet arcam Aur(elio) Amuro et Aur(eliae) Quinte que est in orto Metrodori. Vivi sibi posuerunt…). The find spot of the sarcophagus is not known, but Wilkes plausibly associates the garden of Metrodorus with a walled cemetery a hundred meters outside the city gate on the north side of the road leading west from town, which comprises a number of individual familial plots marked out by dividing walls within an area enclosed by a massive masonry perimeter built of blocks more than four meters long. The garden of Metrodorus was perhaps home also to the monument of Iulia Mutiana erected “among the sarcophagi in the middle in the garden, near the road, overlooking the old (?) courtyard (or seed bed)” (see the preceding entry): the two inscriptions belong broadly to the same period (the latter second or third century) and might well be contemporary with each other.
Maps Plans Images Dates Late second or third century (CE)
Bibliography  CIL 3.2207 M. Abramic´, VAHD 52, 1935-49:1-18 J. J. Wilkes, Dalmatia. London, 1969, pp. 360-61, fig. 16.  Pleiades ID 197488
TGN ID 7017320
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 15 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>