<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>waterspouts on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/waterspouts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in waterspouts on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 12:08:30 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/waterspouts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Darenth</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/darenth/darenth_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 12:08:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/darenth/darenth_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Darenth
Darenth (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Darenth
Keywords  archaeological garden kitchen gardens piscinae rural villas villae rusticae waterspouts  Garden Description Excavations at this site of a Roman villa in Kent uncovered a large rectangular masonry pool in the courtyard, which was enclosed by buildings on the north, west, and east (Fig. 1). The villa buildings took up an area of 150 x 225 meters in total, including the courtyard with a width of 26.5 meters. Occupation at the site began after A.D. 100 and continued until the closing decades of the 4th century.
This pool (P in Fig. 1), measuring 25.6 x 3.36 meters, lay at right angles to the center of the main residence and bisected an enclosed courtyard, possibly a garden (G in Fig. 1) in front of the house. The pool would have been a decorative element in the courtyard. Within the pool at the end nearest the house was found a small bronze water-spout in the form of the head of a lioness. At the other end was a semi-circular pool with provision for the inflow and outflow of water.
South of the western range of rooms was a large, open space measuring 14.6 x 58.4 meters, enclosed by walls. There was no paving in this area, nor was there any evidence for partitions. It has been suggested that this might have been a kitchen garden (G in Fig. 1).
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the villa with the main house (A), garden areas (G), and a large pool (P). Adapted from Detsicas 1983, fig. 20. (Rights statement)   Dates After 100 CE - Closing decades of the 4th century
Bibliography  A. Detsicas, The Cantiaci, Gloucester, 1983, pp. 103-107, fig. 20. (worldcat) B. Philp, Excavations in the Darent Valley, Kent, Gloucester, 1984, pp. 89-92, figs. 24, 33. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 79413
TGN ID 7027349
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>