<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Britannia on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/categories/britannia/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Britannia on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 18:57:34 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/categories/britannia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Sudeley/Spoonley Wood</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/sudeley/sudeley_spoonley_wood_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 18:57:34 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/sudeley/sudeley_spoonley_wood_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Sudeley/Spoonley Wood
Sudeley/Spoonley Wood (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Sudeley/Spoonley Wood
Keywords archaeological garden
axial plan \
terrace gardens
rural villas
villae rusticae
Garden Description The main residence of this rural estate in Gloucestershire, excavated in 1882, is of the winged corridor type (Fig. 1). From the north and south corners of the house, walls ran in a westerly direction to enclose an open courtyard (G in Fig. 1) approximately 65 meters wide and 45 meters deep from the outer boundary to the main entrance of the house. A paved path was axially arranged in the courtyard to connect the entrance to the courtyard with that of the residential building. The western third of the courtyard is marked off by low scarps which may be remains of garden terraces (T in Fig. 1). Finds from the site indicate a 3rd/4th century date for the complex.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the villa with a path (stippled) leading through a courtyard garden (G) and garden. (Rights statement)   Images Dates 3rd/4th century for the complex.
Excavation Dates 1882
Bibliography  Ancient and Historical Monuments in the County of Gloucester Vol. 1. Royal Commission on Historical Monuments of England, London, 1976, pp. 113-114, fig. on p. 114. (worldcat) C. Taylor, The Archaeology of Gardens. Shire Archaeology Series 30, Aylesbury, 1983, pp. 30-31, fig. 1. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 79693
TGN ID 7030316
Contributor Maureen Carroll
ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Latimer</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/latimer/latimer_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/latimer/latimer_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Latimer
Latimer (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Latimer
Keywords archaeological garden \
fences (site elements)
flower gardens
orchards
rural villas
vegetable gardens
villae rusticae
Garden Description Excavations at this country house in Buckinghamshire have produced evidence for gardens adjacent to the main residence in its latest phase dating to the beginning of the 4th century (Fig. 1). The house at the west is of the winged corridor type, fronted by a large courtyard bisected by a paved central drive with a banked edge. Between the outer courtyard wall and the house were areas used for gardening (G in Fig. 1). Just inside the outer yard wall on the south side of the drive traces of at least six bedding trenches cut into the natural subsoil and running parallel to each other were followed for at least 5 meters (b in Fig. 1). These have been interpreted by the excavator as the remains of vegetable gardens (Fig. 2). He also attributed a number of stake holes in this area to small fences bounding the vegetable gardens, and suggested the possibility of an orchard on the northern side of the drive as well as a formal flower garden nearer to the house between the projecting wings, for which there is no concrete archaeological evidence. Finally a small pit just inside the courtyard gateway may represent a pit dug to take one of a pair of trees flanking the entrance.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the residential building (A) with excavated bedding trenches (b) in its garden courtyard (G). Adapted from Branigan 1971, fig. 20.(Rights statement)   Images   Fig. 2: Reconstruction of the house and garden. Courtesy of K. Branigan.   Dates Evidence for gardens dating to the beginning of 4th century
Bibliography  K. Branigan, Latimer. Belgic, Roman, Dark Age and Early Modern Farm, Bristol, 1971, pp. 85-86, 184, figs. 14, 20 (worldcat) R.J. Zeepvat, “Roman Gardens in Britain,” in: A.E. Brown, ed., Garden Archaeology. Council for British Archaeology Research Report 78, London, 1991, p. 56, fig. 5.3. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 79555
TGN ID 1029792
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Gorhambury</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/gorhambury/gorhambury_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 10:45:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/gorhambury/gorhambury_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Gorhambury
Gorhambury (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Gorhambury
Keywords arbors
archaeological garden
axial plan
loam
villae rusticae
Garden Description At this site in Hertfordshire near the town of Verulamium (St. Albans) excavations have revealed a multi-phased Roman farm, characterized in late Iron Age and Roman times by an outer courtyard with various service buildings and an inner courtyard in which the farm house stood (Fig. 1).
An avenue 20 meters wide led axially from the gate at the eastern end of the inner courtyard a cross to the front of the house (H in Fig. 1). On either side of the avenue was a line of circular pits spaced 4-6 meters apart (A in Fig. 1). These were filled with fine, homogeneous loam and have been interpreted as planting holes for trees or shrubs. Alternatively, the rows of holes have been interpreted as the postholes of a covered walkway or arbour leading to the house, supporting climbing plants. This feature of the courtyard is contemporary with the first masonry house built around A.D. 100, and represents an attempt to design the compound fronting the house in a more formal way. After 175 the avenue leading to the rebuilt house seems not to have been flanked by trees or an arbour, and numerous trackways leading into both courtyards from the north and south suggest that the entrance to the main residence was no longer strictly axial.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the farm with two ditched enclosures surrounding the house (H) and an avenue of trees or an arbor (A) leading to it. Adapted from Neal, Wardle, and Hunn. (Rights statement)   Images Dates around A.D. 100 - 175
Bibliography  A. Selkirk, “Gorhambury,” Current Archaeology 87, 1983: 120-121, fig. on p. 116. D.S. Neal, A. Wardle and J. Hunn, Excavation of the Iron Age, Roman and Medieval Settlement at Gorhambury, St. Albans. English Heritage Report 14, London, 1990, p. 44, fig. 56. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 79485
TGN ID 7030316
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Estate in Gatcombe</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/gatcombe/gatcombe_rural_estate/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jul 2020 15:13:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/gatcombe/gatcombe_rural_estate/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Gatcombe
Gatcombe (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Estate in Gatcombe
Keywords archaeological garden \
Garden Description This site of a large rural estate about 9 hectares in size in Somerset is enclosed within a massive wall (Fig.1). Although the site was not completely excavated, there is evidence to suggest that the main residence (A in Fig. 1) was located at the southern end of the complex, separated from various workshops and subsidiary buildings in the northern half by an area of cultivated soil. This area has been interpreted as a garden, based on the absence of buildings and the presence of 10-15 centimeters thick layer of rich humus (G in Fig. 1). The complex was built between A.D. 280 and 300, with occupation ending around 380.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the farm with villa buildings (A).(Rights statement)   Images Dates The complex was built between A.D. 280 and 300, with occupation ending around 380.
Bibliography  K. Branigan, The Roman Villa in South-West England, Bradford-on-Avon, 1976, pp. 55, 77, fig. 34. (worldcat) K. Branigan, Gatcombe. The Excavation and Study of a Romano-British Villa Estate, 1967-1976. British Archeological Reports, Brit. Ser. 44, Oxford, 1977, pp. 50, 141, 181-182, figs. 2, 33. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 79477
TGN ID 7026972
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 10 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roman Palace in Fishbourne</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/fishbourne/fishbourne_roman_palace/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 18:05:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/fishbourne/fishbourne_roman_palace/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Location Fishbourne
Fishbourne (Pleiades)
Garden Roman Palace in Fishbourne
Keywords archaeological garden
basins (vessels)
colonnades
loam
palaces
piscinae
presence chambers
terrace gardens
vegetable gardens
Garden Description Fishbourne Roman Palace was accidentally discovered during the digging of a water main trench in 1960. The discovery led to nine seasons of excavations (1961-69) that showed the site had developed from a military base at the time of the Roman invasion in AD 43 to a sumptuous palace by the end of the first century CE. Carefully excavated by Barry Cunliffe, using techniques of environmental archaeology, the garden excavations at the palace have long served as a model in the development of Roman garden archaeology, although the findings did not initially prompt the investigation of other gardens in Britain. Today the site has been developed for display and education.
The palace contains gardens within its internal courtyards, as well in a larger area to the south, where terraces and other landscape architectural features lay between the residence and the deep water channel (Fig 1.). The main garden of the palace is located in the large central courtyard, and dates to the late 1st century CE. Only the northern half has been excavated, while the remainder lies beneath the gardens of adjacent houses. The garden is bisected by a wide path leading between the entrance to the villa and a large audience hall. Lining the path, bedding trenches in alternating rectangular and semi-circular patterns survived as patterns of dark gray loam against an ochre-colored clay and gravel subsoil. Similar cuttings were found along the colonnades.
Pollen samples were taken in the garden areas in the hope that traces of pollen had survived from flowers and shrubs that had grown in the garden. Unfortunately, only a small quantity of pollen from weeds of cultivation, such as plantain and daisy, remained. As no positive archaeobotanical evidence for specific plants survived on site, literary sources were used to select plants that would have survived in the conditions of this northern province. Pliny the Younger refers to clipped box lining the edges of the pathways in the gardens of his Tuscan estate. This lime-loving shrub would have been very appropriate in the deliberately marled loam of these trenches, so, in 1968, it was planted and has thrived. Figure 2 shows the excavated trenches, and figure 3 shows the replanted box.
On the eastern side of the formal garden, alternating tree-pits and post holes were found. The pattern suggested an original arrangement of trees or shrubs planted against a trellis. Again, Pliny the Younger mentions espaliered apples in his gardens, and these have been successfully established at Fishbourne. Less successful was the effort to establish Italian cypress in the location of a large tree-pit found towards the western side of the garden.
Beneath the surface of the garden, the excavators discovered lines of ceramic pipes. They ran from the remains of the base of what is assumed to have been a water storage tank in the northwest corner of the formal garden. One line of pipes probably fed a pool in the entrance hall while others supplied small semi-circular basins set in recesses in the box hedging. Half a marble basin was found in the 1960&amp;rsquo;s.
There is circumstantial evidence for there having been a vegetable garden in the angle between the ends of the north and west wings of the palace where there is a dark, humus-rich soil containing heavily abraded pottery, suggesting that the soil had been intensively cultivated. It also had its own water supply, provided through wooden pipes with iron collars.
Limited excavations to the south of the palace revealed an artificial terrace which bore evidence of landscaping, including a pool, a gravel path, possible bedding trenches and what may have been the base for a column or statue. Excavations to the east of the palace in the mid 1980&amp;rsquo;s uncovered evidence for semi-formal gardens.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the Roman Palace showing the position of the gardens. Courtesy of David Rudkin for Fishbourne Roman Palace.   Images   Fig. 2: View of formal garden excavation. Photo courtesy of David Rudkin for Fishbourne Roman Palace.     Fig. 3: View of replanted formal garden. Photo courtesy of David Rudkin for Fishbourne Roman Palace.   Dates Late 1st century CE - unspecified
Excavation Dates 1961-69, mid 1980s
Bibliography  Barry Cunliffe, Excavations at Fishbourne, 1961-1969, Vols I &amp;amp; II, The Society of Antiquaries, London, 1971.(worldcat) B. W. Cunliffe, A.G. Down, and D. Rudkin, Excavations at Fishbourne 1969-1988, Chichester, 1996.(worldcat) B. Cunliffe, Fishbourne Roman Palace, Tempus, 1998. (worldcat) Amina-Aïcha Malek, A Sourcebook of Garden Archaeology, Bern: Peter Lang, 2012.(worldcat)  Pleiades ID 79466
TGN ID 7032567
Contributor Kathryn Gleason (ORCID:0000-0001-6260-8378)
Publication date 09 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Eccles</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/eccles/eccles_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 17:53:24 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/eccles/eccles_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Eccles
Eccles (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Eccles
Keywords archaeological garden
ditches
drains
horticultural containers
piscinae
rural villas
villae rusticae
water baths
Garden Description This country estate in modern Kent possessed a large ornamental pool (P in Fig. 1) in the area in front of the main residence (A in Fig. 1) and to the east of the attached bath house (Fig. 1). The masonry pool measuring 25 x 3.50 meters lay parallel to the house frontage. From the pool ran a masonry drain. Although no traces of bedding trenches or plantings have been detected in the yard around the pool, it might be assumed that the pool was a centerpiece of a garden (G in Fig. 1). Interestingly, in the backfill of a ditch under the southeast wing of the villa at least thirty planting pots were retrieved in excavations. The vessels had three knife-cut triangular holes in the lower body and a round hole through the base (Fig. 2, nest page). The pots were misfired and almost certainly manufactured in kilns near the villa in the decade after A.D. 50. Although the planting pots were not found in context in pits within a garden, it is clear that they were being produced locally for use at Eccles or other gardens nearby. Excavations have established that the estate was continually occupied from the middle of the 1st century until the 4th century. In its final 4th century form, the villa complex measured 89 x 116 meters, including its wings and the courtyard.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the villa with the main house (A), a possible garden (G) and a large pool (P). Adapted from Detsicas 1983, fig. 25. (Rights statement)   Images   Fig. 2: Clay planting pot with cut-out holes. Adapted from Detsicas 1981, fig. 26.2. (Rights statement)   Dates Middle of 1st century - 4th century
Bibliography  A. Detsicas, The Cantiaci, Gloucester, 1983, pp. 103-107, fig. 20. (worldcat) R.J. Zeepvat, “Fishponds in Roman Britain,” in: M. Aston, ed., Medieval Fish, Fisheries and Fishponds in England. British Archaeological Reports, Brit. Ser. 182, Oxford, 1988, p. 18, fig. 2. (worldcat) A. Detsicas, “A group of pottery from Eccles, Kent,” in Roman Pottery Research in Britain and Northwest Europe, British Archaeological Reports, Int. Ser. 123, Oxford, 1981, pp. 441-445.  Pleiades ID 79448
TGN ID 1029144
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Darenth</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/darenth/darenth_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 12:08:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/darenth/darenth_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Darenth
Darenth (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Darenth
Keywords archaeological garden
kitchen gardens
piscinae
rural villas
villae rusticae
waterspouts
Garden Description Excavations at this site of a Roman villa in Kent uncovered a large rectangular masonry pool in the courtyard, which was enclosed by buildings on the north, west, and east (Fig. 1). The villa buildings took up an area of 150 x 225 meters in total, including the courtyard with a width of 26.5 meters. Occupation at the site began after A.D. 100 and continued until the closing decades of the 4th century.
This pool (P in Fig. 1), measuring 25.6 x 3.36 meters, lay at right angles to the center of the main residence and bisected an enclosed courtyard, possibly a garden (G in Fig. 1) in front of the house. The pool would have been a decorative element in the courtyard. Within the pool at the end nearest the house was found a small bronze water-spout in the form of the head of a lioness. At the other end was a semi-circular pool with provision for the inflow and outflow of water.
South of the western range of rooms was a large, open space measuring 14.6 x 58.4 meters, enclosed by walls. There was no paving in this area, nor was there any evidence for partitions. It has been suggested that this might have been a kitchen garden (G in Fig. 1).
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the villa with the main house (A), garden areas (G), and a large pool (P). Adapted from Detsicas 1983, fig. 20. (Rights statement)   Images Dates After 100 CE - Closing decades of the 4th century
Bibliography  A. Detsicas, The Cantiaci, Gloucester, 1983, pp. 103-107, fig. 20. (worldcat) B. Philp, Excavations in the Darent Valley, Kent, Gloucester, 1984, pp. 89-92, figs. 24, 33. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 79413
TGN ID 7027349
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Chedworth</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/chedworth/chedworth_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 08:19:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/chedworth/chedworth_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Chedworth
Chedworth (Pleiades)
Sublocation Garden Rural Villa in Chedworth
Keywords archaeological garden
animal bone
bathhouses (water recreation structures)
drains
mosaics (visual works)
rural villas
sherds
villae rusticae
Garden Description This Roman villa in Gloucestershire was partially excavated in the late 19th century, but only the built features and their mosaic floors appear to have been of interest to the Victorian diggers. Excavations in the courtyard conducted between 2000 and 2002 revealed that earlier excavators had not disturbed the courtyard.
Parts of the villa may date to the early 3rd century A.D. at the latest, but extensions to existing buildings and the arrangement of the residential wings around an open courtyard can be ascribed to the early 4th century (Fig. 1). The slightly trapezoidal courtyard had a maximum width of 25 meters and a maximum length of 40 meters. The recent excavations in the courtyard show that in the early 4th century soil was brought in and dumped over earlier built features such as drains, transforming the newly created courtyard into a garden (G in Fig. 1). In places, this garden soil was as much as 50 centimeters deep. The dark garden soil containing domestic refuse does not appear to have been reworked regularly for cultivation since the sherds and animal bones in it were not abraded. The courtyard surface may have been lawned rather than planted with flowers, hedges or other vegetation. Excavations have not revealed planting pits or planting beds, but the possibility of randomly spaced trees cannot be ruled out. The courtyard must have been a high-status element of this residential part of the estate, the rooms arranged around the garden having included private dining rooms and baths. In the second half of the 4th century the garden was abandoned and parts of the courtyard roughly paved with flagstones, indicating that the area in its later years possibly functioned as a yard for animals and wheeled traffic or for other utilitarian purposes.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the villa and its garden (G) in the courtyard. Plan by M. Carroll and C. Merrony.(Rights statement)   Images Dates Early 4th century - unspecified
Excavation Dates Late 19th century, 2000-2002
Bibliography  R. Goodburn, Chedworth Roman Villa, London, 1996. (worldcat) G. de la Bedoyere, Roman Villas and the Countryside, London, 1993, pp. 59-61, fig. 44. (worldcat)  Periodo ID Pleiades ID 79383
TGN ID 7032560
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 July 2020
Related articles </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Bancroft</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/bancroft/bancroft_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2020 18:04:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/bancroft/bancroft_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Bancroft
Garden Rural Villa in Bancroft
Keywords archaeological garden
bathhouses (water recreation structures)
drains
gazebos
horticultural containers
piscinae
rural villas
villae rusticae
Garden Description Excavations between 1983 and 1986 at this site in Buckinghamshire revealed a Roman villa of the winged corridor type, which was built in the late 3rd century and rebuilt and enlarged in the mid-4th century (Fig.1).
From the two projecting wings of the house at the northeast and southeast two walls ran eastward, forming an enclosed courtyard 35.5 meters in width and ca. 42 meters in length in front of the 4th century house. In the centre of the yard was a stone-built rectangular fishpond (P in Fig. 1), 2.6 x 13 meters in size and 50-80 centimeters deep which was continually fed by a drain running from an overflow in the cold plunge bath at the south end of the house. An overflow at the east end of the pool may have led to a nearby stream. Although traces of plantings or planting beds were not preserved in the gravelly subsoil, a shallow rectangular depression just west of the fishpool, filled with dark humic soil, may represent a flowerbed through which the water pipe feeding the pool ran. The courtyard therefore was at least partially planted as a garden (G in Fig. 1). Adjacent to the courtyard enclosure at the south was an octagonal structure with stone walls, interpreted as a possible gazebo (A in Fig. 1).
The villa complex that preceded the winged corridor house is also of interest in regard to gardens. The earlier aisled house of late 1st to late 2nd century date was part of a series of buildings and enclosures that included a walled area to the northeast measuring 27 x 18.3 meters in size. Inside this enclosure was a deposit of dark humic soil between 4 and 6 centimeters deep. Environmental analysis of soil samples from the enclosure suggests that the area was used as a kitchen garden with plants such as brassicas, celery, mustard, coriander, summer savory and caper spurge. Three ceramic vessels with at least one hole pierced through the side or the base, possibly planting pots, may have been associated with this phase of the villa garden.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the villa with its garden courtyard (G), a central pool (P), and a possible gazebo (A). Adapted from Zeepvat 1991, fig. 5.4.(Rights statement.)   Images Dates Roman villa&amp;hellip; built in the late 3rd century and rebuilt and enlarged in the mid-4th century.
Excavation Dates 1983-1986
Bibliography  R. J. Williams and R. J. Zeepvat, Bancroft. The late Bronze Age and Iron Age Settlement and Roman Villa and Temple-Mausoleum. Buckinghamshire Archaeological Society Monograph Series 7, Aylesbury, 1994, pp. 154, 163, 188-191, figs. 66, 80, 83, 85, 93, 101-103, pls. 57-59. (worldcat) R.J. Zeepvat, “Roman Gardens in Britain,” in: A. E. Brown, ed., Garden Archaeology. Council for British Archaeology Research Report 78, London, 1991, pp. 56-58, fig. 5.4. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 79312
TGN ID 7030316
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 07 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Suburban Gardens in Camulodunum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/camulodunum/camulodunum_suburban_gardens/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2020 16:47:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/camulodunum/camulodunum_suburban_gardens/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Camulodunum
Camulodunum (Pleiades)
Location Description Camulodunum began as an Iron Age settlement defended by dykes, a combination of V-shaped ditch and rampart created by the upcast earth. It extended from the Roman river on the south to the Colne on the north, a distance of some four kilometers. Within this larger area, a legionary fort was built after the Claudian conquest of Britain in AD 43. On the site of the fort, a veteran colony was planted in about AD 49 and given the name Colonia Victricensis, City of Victory. It became the first provincial capital, later superseded by Londinium (London). Outside its walls was a V-shaped defensive ditch.
Garden Suburban Gardens in Camulodunum
Keywords archaeological garden
ditches
villae suburbanae
Garden Description Outside the walls of the city, utilitarian gardens were planted, possibly in the 3rd century, in allotments along the road leading to the Balkerne Gate. Upon the widening of the defensive ditch at the foot of the walls around AD 275, a thick dump of soil was deposited on these garden allotments, preserving a short stretch of mounded cultivation beds laid out in rows. The excavators have suggested that the beds might have been formed for growing vines or plants such as asparagus. It is uncertain whether the gardens were attached to suburban dwellings at this time, but by about 300 practically all suburban houses in this area had been demolished without replacement.
Maps Images Images not available
Fig. 1: Area outside the Balkerne gate before widening of the town ditch. Details of the beds in the middle of the section of are gardens in the foreground are based on excavation. From Crummy, City of Victory, p. 42. (Rights statement)
Dates 3rd century - about 300
Bibliography  P. Crummy, Excavations at Lion Walk, Balkerne Lane and Middleborough, Colchester, Essex. Colchester Archaeological Report 3, Colchester, 1984, fig. 106. (worldcat) P. Crummy, City of Victory, Colchester, 1997, pp. 114-115, figs. on pp. 100, 116-117. (worldcat)  Periodo ID Pleiades ID 79393
TGN ID 7011866
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 06 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>