<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Britannia on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/categories/britannia/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Britannia on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 18:57:34 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/categories/britannia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Sudeley/Spoonley Wood</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/sudeley/sudeley_spoonley_wood_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 18:57:34 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/sudeley/sudeley_spoonley_wood_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Sudeley/Spoonley Wood
Sudeley/Spoonley Wood (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Sudeley/Spoonley Wood
Keywords axial plan
terrace gardens
villae rusticae
Garden Description The main residence of this rural estate in Gloucestershire, excavated in 1882, is of the winged corridor type (Fig. 1). From the north and south corners of the house, walls ran in a westerly direction to enclose an open courtyard (G in Fig.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Latimer</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/latimer/latimer_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/latimer/latimer_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Latimer
Latimer (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Latimer
Keywords fences (site elements)
orchards
villae rusticae
Garden Description Excavations at this country house in Buckinghamshire have produced evidence for gardens adjacent to the main residence in its latest phase dating to the beginning of the 4th century (Fig. 1). The house at the west is of the winged corridor type, fronted by a large courtyard bisected by a paved central drive with a banked edge.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Gorhambury</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/gorhambury/gorhambury_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 10:45:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/gorhambury/gorhambury_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Gorhambury
Gorhambury (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Gorhambury
Keywords arbors
axial plan
loam
villae rusticae
Garden Description At this site in Hertfordshire near the town of Verulamium (St. Albans) excavations have revealed a multi-phased Roman farm, characterized in late Iron Age and Roman times by an outer courtyard with various service buildings and an inner courtyard in which the farm house stood (Fig.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Estate in Gatcombe</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/gatcombe/gatcombe_rural_estate/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jul 2020 15:13:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/gatcombe/gatcombe_rural_estate/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Gatcombe
Gatcombe (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Estate in Gatcombe
Keywords barrier walls
Garden Description This site of a large rural estate about 9 hectares in size in Somerset is enclosed within a massive wall (Fig.1). Although the site was not completely excavated, there is evidence to suggest that the main residence (A in Fig. 1) was located at the southern end of the complex, separated from various workshops and subsidiary buildings in the northern half by an area of cultivated soil.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roman Palace in Fishbourne</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/fishbourne/fishbourne_roman_palace/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 18:05:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/fishbourne/fishbourne_roman_palace/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Fishbourne
Fishbourne (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Roman Palace in Fishbourne
Keywords colonnades
palaces
piscinae
Garden Description Fishbourne Roman Palace was accidentally discovered during the digging of a water main trench in 1960. The discovery led to nine seasons of excavations (1961-69) that showed the site had developed from a military base at the time of the Roman invasion in AD 43 to a sumptuous palace by the end of the first century CE.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Eccles</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/eccles/eccles_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 17:53:24 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/eccles/eccles_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Eccles
Eccles (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Eccles
Keywords piscinae
villae rusticae
water baths
Garden Description This country estate in modern Kent possessed a large ornamental pool (P in Fig. 1) in the area in front of the main residence (A in Fig. 1) and to the east of the attached bath house (Fig. 1). The masonry pool measuring 25 x 3.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Darenth</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/darenth/darenth_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 12:08:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/darenth/darenth_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Darenth
Darenth (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Darenth
Keywords piscinae
villae rusticae
waterspouts
Garden Description Excavations at this site of a Roman villa in Kent uncovered a large rectangular masonry pool in the courtyard, which was enclosed by buildings on the north, west, and east (Fig. 1). The villa buildings took up an area of 150 x 225 meters in total, including the courtyard with a width of 26.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Chedworth</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/chedworth/chedworth_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 08:19:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/chedworth/chedworth_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Chedworth
Chedworth (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Chedworth
Keywords bathhouses (water recreation structures)
mosaics (visual works)
sherds
villae rusticae
Garden Description This Roman villa in Gloucestershire was partially excavated in the late 19th century, but only the built features and their mosaic floors appear to have been of interest to the Victorian diggers. Excavations in the courtyard conducted between 2000 and 2002 revealed that earlier excavators had not disturbed the courtyard.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Bancroft</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/bancroft/bancroft_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2020 18:04:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/bancroft/bancroft_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Bancroft
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Bancroft
Keywords bathhouses (water recreation structures)
gazebos
piscinae
villae rusticae
Garden Description Excavations between 1983 and 1986 at this site in Buckinghamshire revealed a Roman villa of the winged corridor type, which was built in the late 3rd century and rebuilt and enlarged in the mid-4th century (Fig.1).
From the two projecting wings of the house at the northeast and southeast two walls ran eastward, forming an enclosed courtyard 35.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Suburban Gardens in Camulodunum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/camulodunum/camulodunum_suburban_gardens/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2020 16:47:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/camulodunum/camulodunum_suburban_gardens/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Camulodunum
Camulodunum (Pleiades)
Location Description Camulodunum began as an Iron Age settlement defended by dykes, a combination of V-shaped ditch and rampart created by the upcast earth. It extended from the Roman river on the south to the Colne on the north, a distance of some four kilometers. Within this larger area, a legionary fort was built after the Claudian conquest of Britain in AD 43.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>