<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>lararia on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/lararia/</link>
    <description>Recent content in lararia on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 15:31:46 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/lararia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Capella (I.iii.24)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_24/house_of_capella/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 15:31:46 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_24/house_of_capella/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 24
Garden House of Capella (I.iii.24)
Keywords  archaeological garden lararia mural paintings (visual works) peristyles (columnades) porticoes triclinia  Garden Description At the rear of the house, excavated in 1868, there was a peristyle garden (a) with a portico supported by three brick columns on the east and north sides. The south wall had a lararium painting and a crude animal painting on one corner of the south garden wall. This had been executed in the manner of a topiary painting according to the excavators, who reported a lion consuming a deer, below which there was a dog pouncing on a hare. A good view of the garden was obtained through the triclinium (b) on the north.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1868
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 24, no. 261. Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 74, p. 150, no. 456 . (worldcat) Idem, Desc., pp. 56-57.(worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 28. (worldcat) Idem, Gardens, vol.II, p. 313. (worldcat) Matz, BdI (1869), pp. 239-240. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 78. Schefold, WändP, p. 13 . Sogliano, “Pitture,” p. 225, no. 705.  Warscher, “Codex,” photo no. 54.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 29 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.iii.3</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_3/i.iii.3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 13:03:42 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_3/i.iii.3/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 3
Garden I.iii.3
Keywords  alleys (streets) archaeological garden exedrae (site elements) gutters (building drainage components) hearths lararia peristyles (columnades) pilasters porticoes puteal tufa  Garden Description The front of this house excavated in 1869 had an unusual design in that it was set back some distance from the street. The peristyle garden was entered at the end of the entranceway at the rear of a long angiprotus (alleyway). Rooms of the house were located at the right and rear of the garden. The peristyle had undergone various changes and was supported on the east and north by tall tufa columns. The portico roof on the west was supported by two low brick columns and two pilasters surmounted by arches. A low wall enclosed the garden, joining the columns either side of the entrance between the two columns to the west. A terra-cotta puteal was adjacent to the west wall along with a hearth covered with a small vault decorated with a rough, bearded head supposed to be Vulcan. A large window on the south wall gave a view from the exedra (b) into the garden. The east peristyle wall contained a lararium niche and a gutter ran along the north, east, and west edges of the garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1869
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 24, no. 22. Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 72. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., pp. 52-53.(worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 1 (1868-69), cols. 300-301. Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 26. (worldcat) Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 78. Pernice, p. 34. Warscher, “Codex.” photos nos. 16-21.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 28 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Caupona of Innulus (I.ii.20)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_20/caupona_of_innulus-i.ii.20/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 15:39:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_20/caupona_of_innulus-i.ii.20/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 20
Garden Caupona of Innulus (I.ii.20)
Keywords  archaeological garden cauponae biclinia lararia tables (support furniture)  Garden Description This small caupona had a garden (a) at the rear with a roofed passageway on the east and the south. It was excavated in 1873 and a masonry biclinium (l.medius, 2.65m.; l.imus 2.94 m.) with a round table (dia. 0.93 m.) was uncovered in the northwest corner and a niche lararium on the north garden wall.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation dates 1873
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 23, no. 13. Fiorelli, Descr., p. 45. (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), col. 47-48. Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 24. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), p. 264. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr.,&amp;rdquo; pg. 77. Soprano, p.305, no. 24. Viola, “Scavi” pp. 12-13. (worldcat) Warscher, “Codex.”  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of L. Vousius Faustus and M. Vousius Faustus (I.ii.10)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_10/house_of_l._vousius_faustus_and_m._volusius_faustus-i.ii.10/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2020 18:18:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_10/house_of_l._vousius_faustus_and_m._volusius_faustus-i.ii.10/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 10
Garden House of L. Vousius Faustus and M. Vousius Faustus (I.ii.10)
Keywords  aedicules archaeological garden biclinia drains lararia mural paintings (visual works) piscinae triclinia  Garden Description The garden at the rear of the house, excavated in 1873, is almost totally destroyed. According to Mau, most of the garden was occupied by a large pool (5.40 X 2.90 m.) which was sloped toward the west from where it drained into the street through a pipe. The pool was surrounded by a low wall about 0.55 m. high leaving only a narrow space between the pool and the walls. In the northwest corner were the two beds of a masonry biclinium which sloped toward the wall, as was customary. Rainwater falling on them was carried away by a terra-cotta drain which emptied into the pool. A square niche under the north couch provided a storage space. On the wall above this couch was a rectangular niche lararium with a roughly made aedicula facade (Fig. 3, 2.19.72). At the east end of this couch was a masonry table. Fiorelli reports a planting bed attached to the rear (east) wall. There was a view from the triclinium through the large window in the east wall, across the pool to the garden painting on the rear wall.
Garden Painting
When this garden was excavated in 1873, the excavators reported three panels on the east wall with garden paintings. The center panel had a body of water with swimming fish with assorted animals in the background that included a grazing deer and a springing leopard. The two panels on either side each had a large crater-shaped fountain surrounded by thick growth. Large red flowers and yellow apples could be identified to the left of each fountain and the right, pomegranates (Punica granatum L.). Jashemski examined this painting in 1964 to find it had been covered by a growth of ivy which had destroyed most of the painting. A section of a large pomegranate bush was all that was left intact at the time. She describes the leaves, painted in blue-green with darker shading and a few yellow leaves and the fruit, deep yellow with reddish-orange shading, as being rendered in an impressionistic manner. At the right of the entrance to the garden area was a cistern opening. Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I.ii.10; 2.19.72, S. A. Jashemski.   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1873
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 22, no. 6. Fiorelli, Descr., p. 42. (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), col. 57.  Jashemski, Gardens, 1:1 10-1 1 1. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 22. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 313. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 197-198. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. Gen.,” p. 76. Schefold, WandP, p. 9 (describes this painting as a paradeisos, with sea, deer, panther, and nymphaeum). (worldcat)  Sogliano, “Pitture,” p. 224, no. 694. (worldcat)  Soprano, p.305, no. 23. Viola, “Scavi” p. 11. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 24 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Bad Kreuznach</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/bad_kreuznach/bad_kreuznach_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 12:39:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/bad_kreuznach/bad_kreuznach_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Bad Kreuznach
Bad Kreuznach (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Bad Kreuznach
Keywords  apsed triclinium colonnades cryptoportici fountains gutters (building drainage components) lararia mosaics (visual works) peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes villae rusticae  Garden Description This villa, almost 6000 square meters in size, gives eloquent testimony to the wealth and status of the owner of the rural estate. The estate was built in the second half of the 2nd century and occupied until its destruction around 275.
The three-storied villa with more than 50 rooms on the ground floor alone, many decorated with mosaics and imported marble revetment, was centered on a colonnaded garden courtyard (G in Fig. 1). Many of the sandstone columns from the peristyle, as well as fragments of sculpture from the garden, were found in the courtyard. The house was built into a hill, and the courtyard was terraced on two levels. Around the edges of the garden was a ground level gutter. From the apsed triclinium on the south, with a mosaic floor and a marble fountain in the middle, there was an excellent view of the garden.
At the northeast of the villa was a garden (G in Fig. 1) with a lararium. On the southwest there was a garden (G in Fig. 1) with a fountain. The northern facade had a cryptoporticus below and a porticoed corridor on the story above. The service area of the villa rustica lay in front of the villa to the north.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the rural villa with gardens (G) in the central courtyard and in the corners of the house. Plan adapted from Cüppers 1990, fig. 204.(Rights statement)   Dates Second half of 2nd century - around 275
Bibliography  G. Rupprecht, &amp;ldquo;Die Kreuznacher Mosaikbodenvilla. Kurzbericht (Stand: April 1977),&amp;rdquo; Saalburg Jahrbuch 34, 1977:78-87. G. Rupprecht, &amp;ldquo;Leben auf dem Land,&amp;rdquo; Archäologie in Deutschland 4, 1986: 36-39. (worldcat) Heinz Cüppers, Die Römer in Rheinland-Pfalz, Stuttgart, 1990, pp.321-323, fig. 204. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981525
TGN ID 7012371
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 15 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>