<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/shamika_ghate/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 10:39:31 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/shamika_ghate/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Terrace House 2</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/shamika_ghate/7._ephesos_terrace_house/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/shamika_ghate/7._ephesos_terrace_house/</guid>
      <description>Province Asia Asia (Pleiades)
Province description The region of what is now modern Turkey became a part of the Roman Empire in 133 B.C. when king Attalos III of Pergamum bequeathed his kingdom to the Roman people. The province included the heartland of the Pergamene kingdom as well as the territories of Mysia, Lydia, Ionia, Caria, western Phrygia and the eastern Aegean islands. Under Augustus in 27 B.C. Asia was declared a senatorial province and the governance of a proconsul. The capital of the province was Ephesos, although Pergamon may have fulfilled this role initially. Under Diocletian (284-305 A.D.) the province was subdivided into smaller administrative units: Hellespontus, Asia, Lydia, Caria, Phrygia I and Phrygia II. Due to its excellent harbors on the west coast and its many navigable rivers, Asia’s water-borne trade with the rest of the Mediterranean flourished. In the second century A.D. Asia experienced great prosperity, to which the growth and architectural aggrandizement of many of its cities attest. In the area of Kibyra, bordering the regions of Lycia, Caria, Phrygia and Pisidia, numerous inscriptions refer to the large imperial estates of Roman families. Woolen textiles, marble, and timber constituted a significant part of the commodities exported from the province.
While the Romans might have looked to the Greeks for inspiration in philosophy, architecture, sculpture, and the fine arts, the non-Greek peoples of the eastern Mediterranean are their inspiration for luxury, fine-living, and the status conferred by displays of individual wealth (Athenaeus Deip. XV.690). Asia was a center for such splendor, first in the kingdoms of Lydia, Phrygia, and Lycia, and then continued by the Persian satraps, and later the Hellenistic kings. The Persian paradeisos is particularly well-attested in literature referencing Asia. That these gardens are known primarily from Roman-period literary sources indicates their continuing influence. For example, long after the gold of Lydia’s Pactolus River had disappeared, Lydia remained a literary topos, not only for copious wealth, but for a life of luxury set in a landscape of natural abundance. Athenaeus (Deipnosophistae 12.515d-f) wrote in the second century A.D. that
&amp;ldquo;The Lydians in their luxury planned parks and made them like gardens and so kept in the shade. For they thought it more dainty not to have the sun’s rays touch them at all…&amp;rdquo;
Other districts of Asia captured the Roman imagination: Pliny the Elder writes of an ancient plane tree (Sycamorus orientalis) in Lycia with a girth of sufficient circumference to house a grotto in its hollow trunk, ornamented with pumice and moss with provisions for 18 people to dine there (Pliny HN 12.9).
The paradeisoi of the Persian satraps are of particular influence on the introduction of horti and gardens of Rome. The paradeisos, from the Persian, paira daeza, or “enclosed place,” is a term that had evolved by the Hellenistic period to mean a large enclosed park with luxurious gardens as well as orchards, collections of trees, crops, and hunting areas (see Sardis below). It was at Sardis that the Greek Lysander visited Cyrus the Younger, a visit recorded by Clearchus and retold by Xenophon. It is an essential moment in garden history recounted for the Romans by Cicero, De Senectute. 17.59. These paradeisoi, in the sense of luxurious orchards, are said by the Romans to have been brought to Greece by Kimon (Aristot. apud Plut. Cim. 10; comp. Cic. de Off. 2.18Plutarch), and were adopted by Hellenistic kings throughout Greece and southern Italy during the late Hellenistic period. The hunting parks at Daskyleion and Celenae are also vividly described by Xenophon (See Anabasis 1.2.7, 2.4.14 and Oeconomicus 4.13). Xenophon also describes how paradeisoi were occupied or cut down by armies during the fourth and third centuries BC. Appreciation for these parks apparently continued, and Seleucus of Syria took over the royal paradeisos at Sardis (Plutarch, Demetrios 50.6). Years of instability followed, so it is difficult to know what the Romans themselves thought of paradeisoi in Asia in the second and first centuries B.C. Notable examples of paradeisoi, in some form, may have been visible to Romans visiting Asia, as well. For example, the Mausoleum at Halicarnassus is now thought by its excavators to have been set in a grove or park.
Thus, the paradeisos, the alsos, the gymnasium, and the quadriporticus are not forms the Romans suddenly “discovered.” They had had a long influence and were integrated into the Hellenistic architectural forms of the Italic landscape. In the second century B.C., however, when the Roman generals began to define themselves as rulers of an empire, they turned directly to the palaces and paradeisoi of the Hellenistic monarchs to establish their power, to display spoils of war, and to create the luxurious setting for life in Rome. They further adapted the evolving quadriporticus form for display to the public Despite the importance of Asia Minor in the history of the Roman landscape, archaeological evidence is scant. The excavators contacted for this essay indicated that parks, gardens, and other planted areas have yet to become a subject of research design for the region and finds appear to be few—primarily inscriptions and wall paintings. Most of the smaller domestic courtyards—often the most manageable to investigate - are paved. The larger palaestrae, gymnasia, and enclosed open spaces have not been investigated for landscape architectural and planting features, although recently an important campaign of work in the South Agora at Aphrodisias is setting an important precedent (see below). This catalog includes areas with dirt and incomplete paved surfaces, and notes sites where the excavators have some level of optimism about fruitful future study. The subject of designed landscapes, gardens, and planted areas in Asia Minor awaits archaeological investigation.
Location EPHESOS (Efes, Turkey) (Pleiades)
Location Description Remains of gardens have yet to be discovered in this city, but an appreciation for garden culture is seen in the Terrace Houses, dating to the second and third centuries A.D., where wall paintings not only depict gardens, but use garden images to create the illustionistic experience of being in the space of garden.
House Terrace House 2
Keywords  courtyard dado peristyle (Roman courtyards) medallion (ornament areas) putto  House Description The most striking remains are in Terrace House 2, in Room 20 (Residence 4), excavated by H. Vetters between 1967-1983. Here, in a space originally designed as a courtyard, the walls are decorated with an elaborate garden scene. Much of the painting is covered by a later painting of marble panels, but on the north and west walls the garden scene has been partially revealed (Figs. 1 and 2). The viewer within the room looks out past a real marble dado on top of which is an illusionistic marble fence with an unusual egg and dart design along the top. Beyond is a garden scene, similar to those seen in Pompeii or the famous garden scene of Livia at Prima Porta. The scene is filled with luxuriant foliage, out of which apple trees rise up against the blue sky bearing apples or quinces. A bird flies over a young juniper or cypress. The illusion of the garden continues without a break around the corners. It allows the viewers to feel present in a garden, while knowing they are in a room looking out at it. The later painting completely destroys both the illusion and any recollection that the space had formerly been an open courtyard.
In the central peristyle of Residence 2 of Terrace House 2, Vetters uncovered a late Imperial mosaic of Dionysius and Ariadne in a niche. The peristyle itself is a paved courtyard, but the mosaic offers the viewer a rich view of a paradisiacal vineyard. A lunette features a mosaic of two peacocks holding a garland over a basket or urn of grapes and fruits, with white geese to each side standing on a green lawn with roses and lilies (Fig. 3). The ceiling of the niche features Dionysias and Ariadne in a central medallion set into a panel of blue, against which is arrayed a vine laden with grapes and doves (Fig. 4). In the upper corner, the vine emerges from the ground, and along the base of the wall, a winged putto leads two harnessed leopards or panthers. The opposite side is not preserved.
Just off the peristyle in Room 17, the walls feature a variety of birds, individually portrayed on white backgrounds either sitting on branches or standing among small plants. In Room 24, the landscape themes continue with a painting of stags in woodland, apparently being chased by a putto. Only a small fragment remains. In Room 14, mythological scenes of Achilles and Skyros (west wall) and Achilles and Priam (south wall) are set in a landscape of rocks and trees (Fig. 6). Bird and plant themes are represented through this house.
Maps Plans Images Dates 1st-3rd c. CE
Bibliography  Forschungen in Ephesos Vol. VIII/1, Figs. 207-219 (worldcat) Forschungen in Ephesos Vol. VIII/2 Figs. 109-130 (worldcat) W. Jobst, Romische Mosaiken aus Ephesos I: Die Hanghauser des Embolos,Vienna, 1977 (worldcat) C. Kearns, “Visual representations of gardens: diachronic perspectives on the art of landscape,” In ed. K. Gleason, Cultural History of Gardens, London. 2013. pp. 164-165. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 599612
TGN ID 7002358
Contributor Kathryn Gleason (ORCID: 0000-0001-6260-8378)
Publication date 22 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden and Orchard of Aphrodisios and Flavia</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/shamika_ghate/8._ephesos_tomb_garden_and_orchard_of_aphrodisios_and_flavia/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/shamika_ghate/8._ephesos_tomb_garden_and_orchard_of_aphrodisios_and_flavia/</guid>
      <description>Province Asia Asia (Pleiades)
Province description The region of what is now modern Turkey became a part of the Roman Empire in 133 B.C. when king Attalos III of Pergamum bequeathed his kingdom to the Roman people. The province included the heartland of the Pergamene kingdom as well as the territories of Mysia, Lydia, Ionia, Caria, western Phrygia and the eastern Aegean islands. Under Augustus in 27 B.C. Asia was declared a senatorial province and the governance of a proconsul. The capital of the province was Ephesos, although Pergamon may have fulfilled this role initially. Under Diocletian (284-305 A.D.) the province was subdivided into smaller administrative units: Hellespontus, Asia, Lydia, Caria, Phrygia I and Phrygia II. Due to its excellent harbors on the west coast and its many navigable rivers, Asia’s water-borne trade with the rest of the Mediterranean flourished. In the second century A.D. Asia experienced great prosperity, to which the growth and architectural aggrandizement of many of its cities attest. In the area of Kibyra, bordering the regions of Lycia, Caria, Phrygia and Pisidia, numerous inscriptions refer to the large imperial estates of Roman families. Woolen textiles, marble, and timber constituted a significant part of the commodities exported from the province.
While the Romans might have looked to the Greeks for inspiration in philosophy, architecture, sculpture, and the fine arts, the non-Greek peoples of the eastern Mediterranean are their inspiration for luxury, fine-living, and the status conferred by displays of individual wealth (Athenaeus Deip. XV.690). Asia was a center for such splendor, first in the kingdoms of Lydia, Phrygia, and Lycia, and then continued by the Persian satraps, and later the Hellenistic kings. The Persian paradeisos is particularly well-attested in literature referencing Asia. That these gardens are known primarily from Roman-period literary sources indicates their continuing influence. For example, long after the gold of Lydia’s Pactolus River had disappeared, Lydia remained a literary topos, not only for copious wealth, but for a life of luxury set in a landscape of natural abundance. Athenaeus (Deipnosophistae 12.515d-f) wrote in the second century A.D. that
&amp;ldquo;The Lydians in their luxury planned parks and made them like gardens and so kept in the shade. For they thought it more dainty not to have the sun’s rays touch them at all…&amp;rdquo;
Other districts of Asia captured the Roman imagination: Pliny the Elder writes of an ancient plane tree (Sycamorus orientalis) in Lycia with a girth of sufficient circumference to house a grotto in its hollow trunk, ornamented with pumice and moss with provisions for 18 people to dine there (Pliny HN 12.9).
The paradeisoi of the Persian satraps are of particular influence on the introduction of horti and gardens of Rome. The paradeisos, from the Persian, paira daeza, or “enclosed place,” is a term that had evolved by the Hellenistic period to mean a large enclosed park with luxurious gardens as well as orchards, collections of trees, crops, and hunting areas (see Sardis below). It was at Sardis that the Greek Lysander visited Cyrus the Younger, a visit recorded by Clearchus and retold by Xenophon. It is an essential moment in garden history recounted for the Romans by Cicero, De Senectute. 17.59. These paradeisoi, in the sense of luxurious orchards, are said by the Romans to have been brought to Greece by Kimon (Aristot. apud Plut. Cim. 10; comp. Cic. de Off. 2.18Plutarch), and were adopted by Hellenistic kings throughout Greece and southern Italy during the late Hellenistic period. The hunting parks at Daskyleion and Celenae are also vividly described by Xenophon (See Anabasis 1.2.7, 2.4.14 and Oeconomicus 4.13). Xenophon also describes how paradeisoi were occupied or cut down by armies during the fourth and third centuries BC. Appreciation for these parks apparently continued, and Seleucus of Syria took over the royal paradeisos at Sardis (Plutarch, Demetrios 50.6). Years of instability followed, so it is difficult to know what the Romans themselves thought of paradeisoi in Asia in the second and first centuries B.C. Notable examples of paradeisoi, in some form, may have been visible to Romans visiting Asia, as well. For example, the Mausoleum at Halicarnassus is now thought by its excavators to have been set in a grove or park.
Thus, the paradeisos, the alsos, the gymnasium, and the quadriporticus are not forms the Romans suddenly “discovered.” They had had a long influence and were integrated into the Hellenistic architectural forms of the Italic landscape. In the second century B.C., however, when the Roman generals began to define themselves as rulers of an empire, they turned directly to the palaces and paradeisoi of the Hellenistic monarchs to establish their power, to display spoils of war, and to create the luxurious setting for life in Rome. They further adapted the evolving quadriporticus form for display to the public Despite the importance of Asia Minor in the history of the Roman landscape, archaeological evidence is scant. The excavators contacted for this essay indicated that parks, gardens, and other planted areas have yet to become a subject of research design for the region and finds appear to be few—primarily inscriptions and wall paintings. Most of the smaller domestic courtyards—often the most manageable to investigate - are paved. The larger palaestrae, gymnasia, and enclosed open spaces have not been investigated for landscape architectural and planting features, although recently an important campaign of work in the South Agora at Aphrodisias is setting an important precedent (see below). This catalog includes areas with dirt and incomplete paved surfaces, and notes sites where the excavators have some level of optimism about fruitful future study. The subject of designed landscapes, gardens, and planted areas in Asia Minor awaits archaeological investigation.
Location EPHESOS (Efes, Turkey) (Pleiades)
Location Description Remains of gardens have yet to be discovered in this city, but an appreciation for garden culture is seen in the Terrace Houses, dating to the second and third centuries A.D., where wall paintings not only depict gardens, but use garden images to create the illustionistic experience of being in the space of garden.
Garden Tomb Garden and Orchard of Aphrodisios and Flavia
Keywords  stele sarcophagi (coffins) pvmãrin pomarium tomb monuments  Garden Description According to a secondary inscription carved horizontally, perhaps in the third century A.D., across the back of a figured grave stele of perhaps the third or second century B.C., found on the road between the Magnesia gate and the Temple of Artemis at Ephesus, “this orchard with its sarcophagi and pavilion (?yÒlow) belongs to Aphrodisios and his wife and children” (toËto tÚ pvmãrin §st‹n sÁn tew svro›w k¢ t“ yÒlƒ ÉAfrodis¤ou k¢ g(u)n(aikÚw) Flab€aw k¢ t°knv[n]). The first editor, Hicks, interpreted the word pvmãrin to mean “cover” or “lid” (p«ma) and thought that the stele originally protected the entrance to the monument, but Keil (who corrected the misreading §vro›wto svro›w[for soro›w], “sarcophagi”), rightly saw that pvmãrin was nothing more than a transliterated form of the Latin pomarium, fruit orchard, an amenity often attached to tomb monuments in the Roman world. The character of the yÒlow is uncertain—the term is attested only once elsewhere in Asia Minor in a funerary context, in Pisidia, where a yÒlow is equipped with statues (Monumenta Asiae Minoris Antiquae. Manchester and London, 1928-1993, VIII, 375; cf. Kubin’ska)—but the transliterated pumarin gives reason to suspect that a Roman context is here relevant, in which case one naturally thinks of the sort of ornamental (often round) pavilion (diaeta) frequently found in Roman tomb gardens.
Maps Plans Images Dates 2nd or 3rd c. B.C.
Bibliography  E. L. Hicks, The Collection of Ancient Greek Inscriptions in the British Museum III.2 Ephesos. Oxford, 1890, no. 625b (worldcat) B. Keil, “Über kleinasiatische Grabinschriften,” Hermes 43, 1908:546, n. 1 (worldcat) J. Kubin’ska, Les monuments funéraires dans les inscriptions grecques de l’Asie Mineure. Warsaw, 1968, pp. 115, 144 (worldcat) C. Börker and R. Merkelbach, Die Inschriften von Ephesos, Teil V. Bonn, 1980 (I.Ephesos V), 1625b. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 599612
TGN ID 7002358
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 22 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Temple Grove of Apollo</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/shamika_ghate/6._didyma_temple_grove_of_apollo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/shamika_ghate/6._didyma_temple_grove_of_apollo/</guid>
      <description>Province Asia Asia (Pleiades)
Province description The region of what is now modern Turkey became a part of the Roman Empire in 133 B.C. when king Attalos III of Pergamum bequeathed his kingdom to the Roman people. The province included the heartland of the Pergamene kingdom as well as the territories of Mysia, Lydia, Ionia, Caria, western Phrygia and the eastern Aegean islands. Under Augustus in 27 B.C. Asia was declared a senatorial province and the governance of a proconsul. The capital of the province was Ephesos, although Pergamon may have fulfilled this role initially. Under Diocletian (284-305 A.D.) the province was subdivided into smaller administrative units: Hellespontus, Asia, Lydia, Caria, Phrygia I and Phrygia II. Due to its excellent harbors on the west coast and its many navigable rivers, Asia’s water-borne trade with the rest of the Mediterranean flourished. In the second century A.D. Asia experienced great prosperity, to which the growth and architectural aggrandizement of many of its cities attest. In the area of Kibyra, bordering the regions of Lycia, Caria, Phrygia and Pisidia, numerous inscriptions refer to the large imperial estates of Roman families. Woolen textiles, marble, and timber constituted a significant part of the commodities exported from the province.
While the Romans might have looked to the Greeks for inspiration in philosophy, architecture, sculpture, and the fine arts, the non-Greek peoples of the eastern Mediterranean are their inspiration for luxury, fine-living, and the status conferred by displays of individual wealth (Athenaeus Deip. XV.690). Asia was a center for such splendor, first in the kingdoms of Lydia, Phrygia, and Lycia, and then continued by the Persian satraps, and later the Hellenistic kings. The Persian paradeisos is particularly well-attested in literature referencing Asia. That these gardens are known primarily from Roman-period literary sources indicates their continuing influence. For example, long after the gold of Lydia’s Pactolus River had disappeared, Lydia remained a literary topos, not only for copious wealth, but for a life of luxury set in a landscape of natural abundance. Athenaeus (Deipnosophistae 12.515d-f) wrote in the second century A.D. that
&amp;ldquo;The Lydians in their luxury planned parks and made them like gardens and so kept in the shade. For they thought it more dainty not to have the sun’s rays touch them at all…&amp;rdquo;
Other districts of Asia captured the Roman imagination: Pliny the Elder writes of an ancient plane tree (Sycamorus orientalis) in Lycia with a girth of sufficient circumference to house a grotto in its hollow trunk, ornamented with pumice and moss with provisions for 18 people to dine there (Pliny HN 12.9).
The paradeisoi of the Persian satraps are of particular influence on the introduction of horti and gardens of Rome. The paradeisos, from the Persian, paira daeza, or “enclosed place,” is a term that had evolved by the Hellenistic period to mean a large enclosed park with luxurious gardens as well as orchards, collections of trees, crops, and hunting areas (see Sardis below). It was at Sardis that the Greek Lysander visited Cyrus the Younger, a visit recorded by Clearchus and retold by Xenophon. It is an essential moment in garden history recounted for the Romans by Cicero, De Senectute. 17.59. These paradeisoi, in the sense of luxurious orchards, are said by the Romans to have been brought to Greece by Kimon (Aristot. apud Plut. Cim. 10; comp. Cic. de Off. 2.18Plutarch), and were adopted by Hellenistic kings throughout Greece and southern Italy during the late Hellenistic period. The hunting parks at Daskyleion and Celenae are also vividly described by Xenophon (See Anabasis 1.2.7, 2.4.14 and Oeconomicus 4.13). Xenophon also describes how paradeisoi were occupied or cut down by armies during the fourth and third centuries BC. Appreciation for these parks apparently continued, and Seleucus of Syria took over the royal paradeisos at Sardis (Plutarch, Demetrios 50.6). Years of instability followed, so it is difficult to know what the Romans themselves thought of paradeisoi in Asia in the second and first centuries B.C. Notable examples of paradeisoi, in some form, may have been visible to Romans visiting Asia, as well. For example, the Mausoleum at Halicarnassus is now thought by its excavators to have been set in a grove or park.
Thus, the paradeisos, the alsos, the gymnasium, and the quadriporticus are not forms the Romans suddenly “discovered.” They had had a long influence and were integrated into the Hellenistic architectural forms of the Italic landscape. In the second century B.C., however, when the Roman generals began to define themselves as rulers of an empire, they turned directly to the palaces and paradeisoi of the Hellenistic monarchs to establish their power, to display spoils of war, and to create the luxurious setting for life in Rome. They further adapted the evolving quadriporticus form for display to the public Despite the importance of Asia Minor in the history of the Roman landscape, archaeological evidence is scant. The excavators contacted for this essay indicated that parks, gardens, and other planted areas have yet to become a subject of research design for the region and finds appear to be few—primarily inscriptions and wall paintings. Most of the smaller domestic courtyards—often the most manageable to investigate - are paved. The larger palaestrae, gymnasia, and enclosed open spaces have not been investigated for landscape architectural and planting features, although recently an important campaign of work in the South Agora at Aphrodisias is setting an important precedent (see below). This catalog includes areas with dirt and incomplete paved surfaces, and notes sites where the excavators have some level of optimism about fruitful future study. The subject of designed landscapes, gardens, and planted areas in Asia Minor awaits archaeological investigation.
Location DIDYMA (Didim, Turkey) (Pleiades)
Garden Temple Grove of Apollo
Keywords  sacred grove sanctuary  Garden Description The sanctuary of Apollo at Didyma was a regional sanctuary that lay on the border of Caria and Ionia (Strabo 12.1.2). The Temple of Apollo, attested by Strabo (12.1.5), was built on the site of the spring and oracle of Apollo mentioned by Herodotus (1.92.159) and Pausanius (7.2.6). Inscriptions found in the area of the sanctuary attest to a “sacred grove” [[need GI ref]] and Strabo (14.1.5) specifies that in his day a grove (alsos) was planted inside and outside the temple precinct.
The precinct has been well-defined archaeologically, but the archaeologists identified no traces of the trees.
Maps Plans Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  K. Tuchelt, “Didyma” in ed. E. Meyers, Oxford Encyclopedia of Archaeology in the Near East, Oxford: Oxford University Press, Oxford,1996 : p.160 (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 599593
TGN ID 7002358
Contributor Kathryn Gleason (ORCID: 0000-0001-6260-8378)
Publication date 03 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Anonymous</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/shamika_ghate/4._cayster_river_valley_1-tomb_garden_of_anonymous/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/shamika_ghate/4._cayster_river_valley_1-tomb_garden_of_anonymous/</guid>
      <description>Province Asia Asia (Pleiades)
Province description The region of what is now modern Turkey became a part of the Roman Empire in 133 B.C. when king Attalos III of Pergamum bequeathed his kingdom to the Roman people. The province included the heartland of the Pergamene kingdom as well as the territories of Mysia, Lydia, Ionia, Caria, western Phrygia and the eastern Aegean islands. Under Augustus in 27 B.C. Asia was declared a senatorial province and the governance of a proconsul. The capital of the province was Ephesos, although Pergamon may have fulfilled this role initially. Under Diocletian (284-305 A.D.) the province was subdivided into smaller administrative units: Hellespontus, Asia, Lydia, Caria, Phrygia I and Phrygia II. Due to its excellent harbors on the west coast and its many navigable rivers, Asia’s water-borne trade with the rest of the Mediterranean flourished. In the second century A.D. Asia experienced great prosperity, to which the growth and architectural aggrandizement of many of its cities attest. In the area of Kibyra, bordering the regions of Lycia, Caria, Phrygia and Pisidia, numerous inscriptions refer to the large imperial estates of Roman families. Woolen textiles, marble, and timber constituted a significant part of the commodities exported from the province.
While the Romans might have looked to the Greeks for inspiration in philosophy, architecture, sculpture, and the fine arts, the non-Greek peoples of the eastern Mediterranean are their inspiration for luxury, fine-living, and the status conferred by displays of individual wealth (Athenaeus Deip. XV.690). Asia was a center for such splendor, first in the kingdoms of Lydia, Phrygia, and Lycia, and then continued by the Persian satraps, and later the Hellenistic kings. The Persian paradeisos is particularly well-attested in literature referencing Asia. That these gardens are known primarily from Roman-period literary sources indicates their continuing influence. For example, long after the gold of Lydia’s Pactolus River had disappeared, Lydia remained a literary topos, not only for copious wealth, but for a life of luxury set in a landscape of natural abundance. Athenaeus (Deipnosophistae 12.515d-f) wrote in the second century A.D. that
&amp;ldquo;The Lydians in their luxury planned parks and made them like gardens and so kept in the shade. For they thought it more dainty not to have the sun’s rays touch them at all…&amp;rdquo;
Other districts of Asia captured the Roman imagination: Pliny the Elder writes of an ancient plane tree (Sycamorus orientalis) in Lycia with a girth of sufficient circumference to house a grotto in its hollow trunk, ornamented with pumice and moss with provisions for 18 people to dine there (Pliny HN 12.9).
The paradeisoi of the Persian satraps are of particular influence on the introduction of horti and gardens of Rome. The paradeisos, from the Persian, paira daeza, or “enclosed place,” is a term that had evolved by the Hellenistic period to mean a large enclosed park with luxurious gardens as well as orchards, collections of trees, crops, and hunting areas (see Sardis below). It was at Sardis that the Greek Lysander visited Cyrus the Younger, a visit recorded by Clearchus and retold by Xenophon. It is an essential moment in garden history recounted for the Romans by Cicero, De Senectute. 17.59. These paradeisoi, in the sense of luxurious orchards, are said by the Romans to have been brought to Greece by Kimon (Aristot. apud Plut. Cim. 10; comp. Cic. de Off. 2.18Plutarch), and were adopted by Hellenistic kings throughout Greece and southern Italy during the late Hellenistic period. The hunting parks at Daskyleion and Celenae are also vividly described by Xenophon (See Anabasis 1.2.7, 2.4.14 and Oeconomicus 4.13). Xenophon also describes how paradeisoi were occupied or cut down by armies during the fourth and third centuries BC. Appreciation for these parks apparently continued, and Seleucus of Syria took over the royal paradeisos at Sardis (Plutarch, Demetrios 50.6). Years of instability followed, so it is difficult to know what the Romans themselves thought of paradeisoi in Asia in the second and first centuries B.C. Notable examples of paradeisoi, in some form, may have been visible to Romans visiting Asia, as well. For example, the Mausoleum at Halicarnassus is now thought by its excavators to have been set in a grove or park.
Thus, the paradeisos, the alsos, the gymnasium, and the quadriporticus are not forms the Romans suddenly “discovered.” They had had a long influence and were integrated into the Hellenistic architectural forms of the Italic landscape. In the second century B.C., however, when the Roman generals began to define themselves as rulers of an empire, they turned directly to the palaces and paradeisoi of the Hellenistic monarchs to establish their power, to display spoils of war, and to create the luxurious setting for life in Rome. They further adapted the evolving quadriporticus form for display to the public Despite the importance of Asia Minor in the history of the Roman landscape, archaeological evidence is scant. The excavators contacted for this essay indicated that parks, gardens, and other planted areas have yet to become a subject of research design for the region and finds appear to be few—primarily inscriptions and wall paintings. Most of the smaller domestic courtyards—often the most manageable to investigate - are paved. The larger palaestrae, gymnasia, and enclosed open spaces have not been investigated for landscape architectural and planting features, although recently an important campaign of work in the South Agora at Aphrodisias is setting an important precedent (see below). This catalog includes areas with dirt and incomplete paved surfaces, and notes sites where the excavators have some level of optimism about fruitful future study. The subject of designed landscapes, gardens, and planted areas in Asia Minor awaits archaeological investigation.
Location Cayster River Valley (Pleiades)
Garden Tomb Garden(?) of an Anonymous
Keywords  inscription heroon tomb grave  Garden Description A highly fragmentary inscription found in the south part of the Cayster River valley records the dedication of a piece of landed property apparently attached to a heroon. The tomb is not explicitly mentioned with the property in the surviving text (kayi°[rvsen d¢ k¢ kt∞ma ?t]Ú prosÚn t“ [≤r–ƒ]) but is implied in the reference elsewhere in the inscription to a banquet served at the monument (eÈvx¤[an e‰nai &amp;mdash;]da §p‹ toË mnh[me¤ou]). The combination of the two suggests the standard configuration of tomb with productive property attached—whether a field or a garden is impossible to say— to provide revenue for commemorative funerary celebrations at the grave.
Maps Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  J. Keil and A. von Premerstein, Bericht über eine dritte Reise in Lydien. Vienna, 1914, no. 112 (worldcat) J. Kubin’ska, Les monuments funéraires dans les inscriptions grecques de l’Asie Mineure. Warsaw, 1968, p. 145. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 550492
TGN ID 7002358
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 25 September 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Anonymous</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/shamika_ghate/5._cayster_river_valley_2-tomb_garden_of_anonymous/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/shamika_ghate/5._cayster_river_valley_2-tomb_garden_of_anonymous/</guid>
      <description>Province Asia Asia (Pleiades)
Province description The region of what is now modern Turkey became a part of the Roman Empire in 133 B.C. when king Attalos III of Pergamum bequeathed his kingdom to the Roman people. The province included the heartland of the Pergamene kingdom as well as the territories of Mysia, Lydia, Ionia, Caria, western Phrygia and the eastern Aegean islands. Under Augustus in 27 B.C. Asia was declared a senatorial province and the governance of a proconsul. The capital of the province was Ephesos, although Pergamon may have fulfilled this role initially. Under Diocletian (284-305 A.D.) the province was subdivided into smaller administrative units: Hellespontus, Asia, Lydia, Caria, Phrygia I and Phrygia II. Due to its excellent harbors on the west coast and its many navigable rivers, Asia’s water-borne trade with the rest of the Mediterranean flourished. In the second century A.D. Asia experienced great prosperity, to which the growth and architectural aggrandizement of many of its cities attest. In the area of Kibyra, bordering the regions of Lycia, Caria, Phrygia and Pisidia, numerous inscriptions refer to the large imperial estates of Roman families. Woolen textiles, marble, and timber constituted a significant part of the commodities exported from the province.
While the Romans might have looked to the Greeks for inspiration in philosophy, architecture, sculpture, and the fine arts, the non-Greek peoples of the eastern Mediterranean are their inspiration for luxury, fine-living, and the status conferred by displays of individual wealth (Athenaeus Deip. XV.690). Asia was a center for such splendor, first in the kingdoms of Lydia, Phrygia, and Lycia, and then continued by the Persian satraps, and later the Hellenistic kings. The Persian paradeisos is particularly well-attested in literature referencing Asia. That these gardens are known primarily from Roman-period literary sources indicates their continuing influence. For example, long after the gold of Lydia’s Pactolus River had disappeared, Lydia remained a literary topos, not only for copious wealth, but for a life of luxury set in a landscape of natural abundance. Athenaeus (Deipnosophistae 12.515d-f) wrote in the second century A.D. that
&amp;ldquo;The Lydians in their luxury planned parks and made them like gardens and so kept in the shade. For they thought it more dainty not to have the sun’s rays touch them at all…&amp;rdquo;
Other districts of Asia captured the Roman imagination: Pliny the Elder writes of an ancient plane tree (Sycamorus orientalis) in Lycia with a girth of sufficient circumference to house a grotto in its hollow trunk, ornamented with pumice and moss with provisions for 18 people to dine there (Pliny HN 12.9).
The paradeisoi of the Persian satraps are of particular influence on the introduction of horti and gardens of Rome. The paradeisos, from the Persian, paira daeza, or “enclosed place,” is a term that had evolved by the Hellenistic period to mean a large enclosed park with luxurious gardens as well as orchards, collections of trees, crops, and hunting areas (see Sardis below). It was at Sardis that the Greek Lysander visited Cyrus the Younger, a visit recorded by Clearchus and retold by Xenophon. It is an essential moment in garden history recounted for the Romans by Cicero, De Senectute. 17.59. These paradeisoi, in the sense of luxurious orchards, are said by the Romans to have been brought to Greece by Kimon (Aristot. apud Plut. Cim. 10; comp. Cic. de Off. 2.18Plutarch), and were adopted by Hellenistic kings throughout Greece and southern Italy during the late Hellenistic period. The hunting parks at Daskyleion and Celenae are also vividly described by Xenophon (See Anabasis 1.2.7, 2.4.14 and Oeconomicus 4.13). Xenophon also describes how paradeisoi were occupied or cut down by armies during the fourth and third centuries BC. Appreciation for these parks apparently continued, and Seleucus of Syria took over the royal paradeisos at Sardis (Plutarch, Demetrios 50.6). Years of instability followed, so it is difficult to know what the Romans themselves thought of paradeisoi in Asia in the second and first centuries B.C. Notable examples of paradeisoi, in some form, may have been visible to Romans visiting Asia, as well. For example, the Mausoleum at Halicarnassus is now thought by its excavators to have been set in a grove or park.
Thus, the paradeisos, the alsos, the gymnasium, and the quadriporticus are not forms the Romans suddenly “discovered.” They had had a long influence and were integrated into the Hellenistic architectural forms of the Italic landscape. In the second century B.C., however, when the Roman generals began to define themselves as rulers of an empire, they turned directly to the palaces and paradeisoi of the Hellenistic monarchs to establish their power, to display spoils of war, and to create the luxurious setting for life in Rome. They further adapted the evolving quadriporticus form for display to the public Despite the importance of Asia Minor in the history of the Roman landscape, archaeological evidence is scant. The excavators contacted for this essay indicated that parks, gardens, and other planted areas have yet to become a subject of research design for the region and finds appear to be few—primarily inscriptions and wall paintings. Most of the smaller domestic courtyards—often the most manageable to investigate - are paved. The larger palaestrae, gymnasia, and enclosed open spaces have not been investigated for landscape architectural and planting features, although recently an important campaign of work in the South Agora at Aphrodisias is setting an important precedent (see below). This catalog includes areas with dirt and incomplete paved surfaces, and notes sites where the excavators have some level of optimism about fruitful future study. The subject of designed landscapes, gardens, and planted areas in Asia Minor awaits archaeological investigation.
Location  Cayster River Valley (Pleiades)  Sublocation  Thyaira (Pleiades)  Garden Tomb Garden (peribolion) of an Anonymous
Keywords  inscription crematory periboloi ustrina tomb monument  Garden Description A broken inscription found near Thyaira in 1901 records the second part of a funerary dedication in which the dedicant prescribes who can be buried in his monument and forbids anyone “to sell this tomb or the garden (peribÒlion) in front of it with the crematory in it oÈk §j°stai d¢ oÈden[‹] pvl∞sai toËto tÚ ≤r“on oÈd¢ tÚ prÚ aÈtoË peribÒlion §n ⁄ §stin ≤kaÊstra)”. The prohibition against alienation suggests that peribÒlion here, like peribÒlow at Attaleia and Hypaipa in Lydia and often elsewhere, refers metonymically to a garden enclosed within the wall rather than simply to the wall itself. The crematory (≤kaÊstra)—a feature seldom mentioned in funerary inscriptions in Asia Minor—suggests a Roman style tomb garden, with ustrina	and tomb monument enclosed within the same perimeter wall, as often around Rome and on the Bay of Naples.
Maps Images Dates 1901 CE
Bibliography  Frontrier, REA 4, 1902:263, no. 12 (Persée) R. Cagnat et al, Inscriptiones Graecae ad res Romanas pertinentes. Paris, 1906-1927, IV, 1605 (worldcat) J. Kubin’ska, Les monuments funéraires dans les inscriptions grecques de l’Asie Mineure. Warsaw, 1968, pp. 66, 144. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 599981
TGN ID 7002358
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 25 September 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Bassos son of Euarestos</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/shamika_ghate/2._attaleia_tomb_garden_of_bassos_son_of_euarestos/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/shamika_ghate/2._attaleia_tomb_garden_of_bassos_son_of_euarestos/</guid>
      <description>Province Asia Asia (Pleiades)
Province description The region of what is now modern Turkey became a part of the Roman Empire in 133 B.C. when king Attalos III of Pergamum bequeathed his kingdom to the Roman people. The province included the heartland of the Pergamene kingdom as well as the territories of Mysia, Lydia, Ionia, Caria, western Phrygia and the eastern Aegean islands. Under Augustus in 27 B.C. Asia was declared a senatorial province and the governance of a proconsul. The capital of the province was Ephesos, although Pergamon may have fulfilled this role initially. Under Diocletian (284-305 A.D.) the province was subdivided into smaller administrative units: Hellespontus, Asia, Lydia, Caria, Phrygia I and Phrygia II. Due to its excellent harbors on the west coast and its many navigable rivers, Asia’s water-borne trade with the rest of the Mediterranean flourished. In the second century A.D. Asia experienced great prosperity, to which the growth and architectural aggrandizement of many of its cities attest. In the area of Kibyra, bordering the regions of Lycia, Caria, Phrygia and Pisidia, numerous inscriptions refer to the large imperial estates of Roman families. Woolen textiles, marble, and timber constituted a significant part of the commodities exported from the province.
While the Romans might have looked to the Greeks for inspiration in philosophy, architecture, sculpture, and the fine arts, the non-Greek peoples of the eastern Mediterranean are their inspiration for luxury, fine-living, and the status conferred by displays of individual wealth (Athenaeus Deip. XV.690). Asia was a center for such splendor, first in the kingdoms of Lydia, Phrygia, and Lycia, and then continued by the Persian satraps, and later the Hellenistic kings. The Persian paradeisos is particularly well-attested in literature referencing Asia. That these gardens are known primarily from Roman-period literary sources indicates their continuing influence. For example, long after the gold of Lydia’s Pactolus River had disappeared, Lydia remained a literary topos, not only for copious wealth, but for a life of luxury set in a landscape of natural abundance. Athenaeus (Deipnosophistae 12.515d-f) wrote in the second century A.D. that
&amp;ldquo;The Lydians in their luxury planned parks and made them like gardens and so kept in the shade. For they thought it more dainty not to have the sun’s rays touch them at all…&amp;rdquo;
Other districts of Asia captured the Roman imagination: Pliny the Elder writes of an ancient plane tree (Sycamorus orientalis) in Lycia with a girth of sufficient circumference to house a grotto in its hollow trunk, ornamented with pumice and moss with provisions for 18 people to dine there (Pliny HN 12.9).
The paradeisoi of the Persian satraps are of particular influence on the introduction of horti and gardens of Rome. The paradeisos, from the Persian, paira daeza, or “enclosed place,” is a term that had evolved by the Hellenistic period to mean a large enclosed park with luxurious gardens as well as orchards, collections of trees, crops, and hunting areas (see Sardis below). It was at Sardis that the Greek Lysander visited Cyrus the Younger, a visit recorded by Clearchus and retold by Xenophon. It is an essential moment in garden history recounted for the Romans by Cicero, De Senectute. 17.59. These paradeisoi, in the sense of luxurious orchards, are said by the Romans to have been brought to Greece by Kimon (Aristot. apud Plut. Cim. 10; comp. Cic. de Off. 2.18Plutarch), and were adopted by Hellenistic kings throughout Greece and southern Italy during the late Hellenistic period. The hunting parks at Daskyleion and Celenae are also vividly described by Xenophon (See Anabasis 1.2.7, 2.4.14 and Oeconomicus 4.13). Xenophon also describes how paradeisoi were occupied or cut down by armies during the fourth and third centuries BC. Appreciation for these parks apparently continued, and Seleucus of Syria took over the royal paradeisos at Sardis (Plutarch, Demetrios 50.6). Years of instability followed, so it is difficult to know what the Romans themselves thought of paradeisoi in Asia in the second and first centuries B.C. Notable examples of paradeisoi, in some form, may have been visible to Romans visiting Asia, as well. For example, the Mausoleum at Halicarnassus is now thought by its excavators to have been set in a grove or park.
Thus, the paradeisos, the alsos, the gymnasium, and the quadriporticus are not forms the Romans suddenly “discovered.” They had had a long influence and were integrated into the Hellenistic architectural forms of the Italic landscape. In the second century B.C., however, when the Roman generals began to define themselves as rulers of an empire, they turned directly to the palaces and paradeisoi of the Hellenistic monarchs to establish their power, to display spoils of war, and to create the luxurious setting for life in Rome. They further adapted the evolving quadriporticus form for display to the public Despite the importance of Asia Minor in the history of the Roman landscape, archaeological evidence is scant. The excavators contacted for this essay indicated that parks, gardens, and other planted areas have yet to become a subject of research design for the region and finds appear to be few—primarily inscriptions and wall paintings. Most of the smaller domestic courtyards—often the most manageable to investigate - are paved. The larger palaestrae, gymnasia, and enclosed open spaces have not been investigated for landscape architectural and planting features, although recently an important campaign of work in the South Agora at Aphrodisias is setting an important precedent (see below). This catalog includes areas with dirt and incomplete paved surfaces, and notes sites where the excavators have some level of optimism about fruitful future study. The subject of designed landscapes, gardens, and planted areas in Asia Minor awaits archaeological investigation.
Location Attaleia (Pleiades)
Garden Tomb (peribolos) garden of Bassos son of Euarestos
Keywords  statue peribolo tomb  Garden Description A statue base found in 1886 in a modern cemetery midway along the path between Gueuktché-Ahmed and Seldjikli preserves, on its front, a decree of the local senate and people at Attaleia passed, probably, some time during the second century honoring Bassus and his father Euarestos for their demonstration of piety toward the guardian Zeus of the city; on its right side, an excerpt from Euarestos’s will instructing his heir to provide oil to the community on one day a year annually; and, on its left side, detailed instructions for the implementation of the foundation: “From the first to the fifth hour of the day the oil shall be provided from the revenues of the garden (per™€bolow) purchased from Eubolos, the son of Antiphanes, for Bassos, son of Euarestos, grandson of Phocas”. (épÚ Àraw a&amp;rsquo; ßvw e&amp;rsquo; t`eyÆsetai tÚ ¶leon §k prosÒdvn peribÒlou toË égorasy°ntow parå EÈboÊlou ÉAntifãnouw efiw Bãsson EÈar°[s]tou Fvkç tÚn ÍÒn). The location of the garden in relation to Bassos’s tomb is not specified, and the statue base recording its purchase and the honorific decree recognizing it were probably set up in a public place rather than at the tomb, but the commemorative purpose of the garden in supporting an annual distribution in his name is clear, and it is likely that the two properties were near each other, if not contiguous. In accordance with an idiomatic usage common in both Greek and Latin and favored in Lydia (as at Hypaipa and Thyaira), the garden is identified metonymically by reference to its enclosure wall (per™€bolow), the sine qua non of a tomb garden in the Greco-Roman world.
Maps Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  G. Radet and H. Lechat, “Notes de géographie ancienne,” BCH 11, 1887:399-401 (worldcat) R. Cagnat, et al., Inscriptiones Graecae ad res Romanas pertinentes. Paris, 1906-1927, IV, 1168 (worldcat) B. Laum, Stiftungen in der griechischen und römischen Antike. Leipzig, 1914, II, no. 72 (worldcat) J. Kubin’ska, Les monuments funéraires dans les inscriptions grecques de l’Asie Mineure. Warsaw, 1968, p. 144 (worldcat) P. Herrmann, Tituli Lydiae linguis Graeca et Latina conscripti (Tituli Asiae Minoris V, 2). Vienna, 1989, 828c4.(worldcat)  Pleiades ID 550472
TGN ID 7002358
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 25 September 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Papias son of Adrastos</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/shamika_ghate/3._attouda_tomb-garden_of_papias_son_of_adrastos/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/shamika_ghate/3._attouda_tomb-garden_of_papias_son_of_adrastos/</guid>
      <description>Province Asia Asia (Pleiades)
Province description The region of what is now modern Turkey became a part of the Roman Empire in 133 B.C. when king Attalos III of Pergamum bequeathed his kingdom to the Roman people. The province included the heartland of the Pergamene kingdom as well as the territories of Mysia, Lydia, Ionia, Caria, western Phrygia and the eastern Aegean islands. Under Augustus in 27 B.C. Asia was declared a senatorial province and the governance of a proconsul. The capital of the province was Ephesos, although Pergamon may have fulfilled this role initially. Under Diocletian (284-305 A.D.) the province was subdivided into smaller administrative units: Hellespontus, Asia, Lydia, Caria, Phrygia I and Phrygia II. Due to its excellent harbors on the west coast and its many navigable rivers, Asia’s water-borne trade with the rest of the Mediterranean flourished. In the second century A.D. Asia experienced great prosperity, to which the growth and architectural aggrandizement of many of its cities attest. In the area of Kibyra, bordering the regions of Lycia, Caria, Phrygia and Pisidia, numerous inscriptions refer to the large imperial estates of Roman families. Woolen textiles, marble, and timber constituted a significant part of the commodities exported from the province.
While the Romans might have looked to the Greeks for inspiration in philosophy, architecture, sculpture, and the fine arts, the non-Greek peoples of the eastern Mediterranean are their inspiration for luxury, fine-living, and the status conferred by displays of individual wealth (Athenaeus Deip. XV.690). Asia was a center for such splendor, first in the kingdoms of Lydia, Phrygia, and Lycia, and then continued by the Persian satraps, and later the Hellenistic kings. The Persian paradeisos is particularly well-attested in literature referencing Asia. That these gardens are known primarily from Roman-period literary sources indicates their continuing influence. For example, long after the gold of Lydia’s Pactolus River had disappeared, Lydia remained a literary topos, not only for copious wealth, but for a life of luxury set in a landscape of natural abundance. Athenaeus (Deipnosophistae 12.515d-f) wrote in the second century A.D. that
&amp;ldquo;The Lydians in their luxury planned parks and made them like gardens and so kept in the shade. For they thought it more dainty not to have the sun’s rays touch them at all…&amp;rdquo;
Other districts of Asia captured the Roman imagination: Pliny the Elder writes of an ancient plane tree (Sycamorus orientalis) in Lycia with a girth of sufficient circumference to house a grotto in its hollow trunk, ornamented with pumice and moss with provisions for 18 people to dine there (Pliny HN 12.9).
The paradeisoi of the Persian satraps are of particular influence on the introduction of horti and gardens of Rome. The paradeisos, from the Persian, paira daeza, or “enclosed place,” is a term that had evolved by the Hellenistic period to mean a large enclosed park with luxurious gardens as well as orchards, collections of trees, crops, and hunting areas (see Sardis below). It was at Sardis that the Greek Lysander visited Cyrus the Younger, a visit recorded by Clearchus and retold by Xenophon. It is an essential moment in garden history recounted for the Romans by Cicero, De Senectute. 17.59. These paradeisoi, in the sense of luxurious orchards, are said by the Romans to have been brought to Greece by Kimon (Aristot. apud Plut. Cim. 10; comp. Cic. de Off. 2.18Plutarch), and were adopted by Hellenistic kings throughout Greece and southern Italy during the late Hellenistic period. The hunting parks at Daskyleion and Celenae are also vividly described by Xenophon (See Anabasis 1.2.7, 2.4.14 and Oeconomicus 4.13). Xenophon also describes how paradeisoi were occupied or cut down by armies during the fourth and third centuries BC. Appreciation for these parks apparently continued, and Seleucus of Syria took over the royal paradeisos at Sardis (Plutarch, Demetrios 50.6). Years of instability followed, so it is difficult to know what the Romans themselves thought of paradeisoi in Asia in the second and first centuries B.C. Notable examples of paradeisoi, in some form, may have been visible to Romans visiting Asia, as well. For example, the Mausoleum at Halicarnassus is now thought by its excavators to have been set in a grove or park.
Thus, the paradeisos, the alsos, the gymnasium, and the quadriporticus are not forms the Romans suddenly “discovered.” They had had a long influence and were integrated into the Hellenistic architectural forms of the Italic landscape. In the second century B.C., however, when the Roman generals began to define themselves as rulers of an empire, they turned directly to the palaces and paradeisoi of the Hellenistic monarchs to establish their power, to display spoils of war, and to create the luxurious setting for life in Rome. They further adapted the evolving quadriporticus form for display to the public Despite the importance of Asia Minor in the history of the Roman landscape, archaeological evidence is scant. The excavators contacted for this essay indicated that parks, gardens, and other planted areas have yet to become a subject of research design for the region and finds appear to be few—primarily inscriptions and wall paintings. Most of the smaller domestic courtyards—often the most manageable to investigate - are paved. The larger palaestrae, gymnasia, and enclosed open spaces have not been investigated for landscape architectural and planting features, although recently an important campaign of work in the South Agora at Aphrodisias is setting an important precedent (see below). This catalog includes areas with dirt and incomplete paved surfaces, and notes sites where the excavators have some level of optimism about fruitful future study. The subject of designed landscapes, gardens, and planted areas in Asia Minor awaits archaeological investigation.
Location Attouda (Pleiades)
Garden Tomb Garden of Papias son of Adrastos
Keywords  marble slab epitaphs  Garden Description A marble slab found immured in a house wall at Hisarköy (Attouda) in Caria near the border with Phrygia records an epitaph set up by Papias, the son of Adrastos, grandson of Zeuxis, great grandson of Kounbarion, for himself and his heirs and sets aside a plot of unencumbered land six cubits square around it, from which it was permitted to derive revenue ([t“] mnhme€ƒ periÒria [di]°[ye]to pÆxiw ©é[ne]pikvlut€, nomØn ka‹ karpe€an énepikvlut€). The modest size of the allotment (less than ten m2) suggests that the productive plot was probably a garden.
Maps Images Dates 2nd century BC
Bibliography  Monumenta Asiae Minoris Antiquae. Manchester and London, 1928-1993, VI, 83. (worldcat) J. Kubin’ska, Les monuments funéraires dans les inscriptions grecques de l’Asie Mineure. Warsaw, 1968, p. 145. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 638779
TGN ID 7002358
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 24 September 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aphrodisias (Lelégōn Pólis,Megálē Pólis, Ninóē, Stauroúpolis)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/shamika_ghate/1._aphrodisias/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/shamika_ghate/1._aphrodisias/</guid>
      <description>Province Asia Asia (Pleiades)
Province description The region of what is now modern Turkey became a part of the Roman Empire in 133 B.C. when king Attalos III of Pergamum bequeathed his kingdom to the Roman people. The province included the heartland of the Pergamene kingdom as well as the territories of Mysia, Lydia, Ionia, Caria, western Phrygia and the eastern Aegean islands. Under Augustus in 27 B.C. Asia was declared a senatorial province and the governance of a proconsul. The capital of the province was Ephesos, although Pergamon may have fulfilled this role initially. Under Diocletian (284-305 A.D.) the province was subdivided into smaller administrative units: Hellespontus, Asia, Lydia, Caria, Phrygia I and Phrygia II. Due to its excellent harbors on the west coast and its many navigable rivers, Asia’s water-borne trade with the rest of the Mediterranean flourished. In the second century A.D. Asia experienced great prosperity, to which the growth and architectural aggrandizement of many of its cities attest. In the area of Kibyra, bordering the regions of Lycia, Caria, Phrygia and Pisidia, numerous inscriptions refer to the large imperial estates of Roman families. Woolen textiles, marble, and timber constituted a significant part of the commodities exported from the province.
While the Romans might have looked to the Greeks for inspiration in philosophy, architecture, sculpture, and the fine arts, the non-Greek peoples of the eastern Mediterranean are their inspiration for luxury, fine-living, and the status conferred by displays of individual wealth (Athenaeus Deip. XV.690). Asia was a center for such splendor, first in the kingdoms of Lydia, Phrygia, and Lycia, and then continued by the Persian satraps, and later the Hellenistic kings. The Persian paradeisos is particularly well-attested in literature referencing Asia. That these gardens are known primarily from Roman-period literary sources indicates their continuing influence. For example, long after the gold of Lydia’s Pactolus River had disappeared, Lydia remained a literary topos, not only for copious wealth, but for a life of luxury set in a landscape of natural abundance. Athenaeus (Deipnosophistae 12.515d-f) wrote in the second century A.D. that
&amp;ldquo;The Lydians in their luxury planned parks and made them like gardens and so kept in the shade. For they thought it more dainty not to have the sun’s rays touch them at all…&amp;rdquo;
Other districts of Asia captured the Roman imagination: Pliny the Elder writes of an ancient plane tree (Sycamorus orientalis) in Lycia with a girth of sufficient circumference to house a grotto in its hollow trunk, ornamented with pumice and moss with provisions for 18 people to dine there (Pliny HN 12.9).
The paradeisoi of the Persian satraps are of particular influence on the introduction of horti and gardens of Rome. The paradeisos, from the Persian, paira daeza, or “enclosed place,” is a term that had evolved by the Hellenistic period to mean a large enclosed park with luxurious gardens as well as orchards, collections of trees, crops, and hunting areas (see Sardis below). It was at Sardis that the Greek Lysander visited Cyrus the Younger, a visit recorded by Clearchus and retold by Xenophon. It is an essential moment in garden history recounted for the Romans by Cicero, De Senectute. 17.59. These paradeisoi, in the sense of luxurious orchards, are said by the Romans to have been brought to Greece by Kimon (Aristot. apud Plut. Cim. 10; comp. Cic. de Off. 2.18Plutarch), and were adopted by Hellenistic kings throughout Greece and southern Italy during the late Hellenistic period. The hunting parks at Daskyleion and Celenae are also vividly described by Xenophon (See Anabasis 1.2.7, 2.4.14 and Oeconomicus 4.13). Xenophon also describes how paradeisoi were occupied or cut down by armies during the fourth and third centuries BC. Appreciation for these parks apparently continued, and Seleucus of Syria took over the royal paradeisos at Sardis (Plutarch, Demetrios 50.6). Years of instability followed, so it is difficult to know what the Romans themselves thought of paradeisoi in Asia in the second and first centuries B.C. Notable examples of paradeisoi, in some form, may have been visible to Romans visiting Asia, as well. For example, the Mausoleum at Halicarnassus is now thought by its excavators to have been set in a grove or park.
Thus, the paradeisos, the alsos, the gymnasium, and the quadriporticus are not forms the Romans suddenly “discovered.” They had had a long influence and were integrated into the Hellenistic architectural forms of the Italic landscape. In the second century B.C., however, when the Roman generals began to define themselves as rulers of an empire, they turned directly to the palaces and paradeisoi of the Hellenistic monarchs to establish their power, to display spoils of war, and to create the luxurious setting for life in Rome. They further adapted the evolving quadriporticus form for display to the public Despite the importance of Asia Minor in the history of the Roman landscape, archaeological evidence is scant. The excavators contacted for this essay indicated that parks, gardens, and other planted areas have yet to become a subject of research design for the region and finds appear to be few—primarily inscriptions and wall paintings. Most of the smaller domestic courtyards—often the most manageable to investigate - are paved. The larger palaestrae, gymnasia, and enclosed open spaces have not been investigated for landscape architectural and planting features, although recently an important campaign of work in the South Agora at Aphrodisias is setting an important precedent (see below). This catalog includes areas with dirt and incomplete paved surfaces, and notes sites where the excavators have some level of optimism about fruitful future study. The subject of designed landscapes, gardens, and planted areas in Asia Minor awaits archaeological investigation.
Location Geyre, Caria region, Turkey
Aphrodisias (Pleiades)
Location Description Aphrodisias (Lelégōn Pólis, Megálē Pólis, Ninóē, Stauroúpolis), in Caria, was home to the cult image of Aphrodite of Aphrodisias. Located about 100 miles from the port at Smyrna, the area featured important marble quarries of the Hellenistic and Roman era. An abundance of sculpture has been found during excavations, and inscriptions indicate that the art landscape as well as architectural settings.
Sublocation Place of the Palms (Pleiades)
Garden Place of the Palms (South Agora)
Keywords  Nymphs temenos strategos palm-grove agora  Garden Description An inscription (MAMA VIII, 448) indicates that Artemidorus Pedias, during his term as strategos, promised to “adorn a palm grove with a statue of Hermes, and a gilded Aphrodite with Erotes holding lamps on either side and a marble Eros in Front” (Roueché, 70.) The location of this garden is not specified. Robert suggests, based on the location of the inscription, that it was in the temenos of Aphrodite (Robert, 257). Roueché conjectures that it perhaps lay on the east side of the agora, based upon the presence of Hermes Agoraios (MAMA VIII, 406, 445, 446, and CIG 2770). She proposes that the grove was later embellished by the fountain at the agora gate, where inscriptions (Hell. IV, 131-2) honor the conversion of the gate into a fountain, alluding to the Nymphs of the “place of the palms.” Roueché notes that this palm-grove, with its walks, statuary, and fountains was clearly an elaborately decorated park. The agora and temenos have been identified. The south agora (215 x 70m) features a long, monumental basin in its center.
Maps Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  T. Reinach, “Inscriptions d’Aphrodisias” REG 19 (1906), n. 15, p. 107 (worldcat) Charlotte Roueché, Joyce Maire Reynolds, Aphrodisias in late antiquity: the late Roman and Byzantine Inscriptions including texts from the excavations conducted at Aphrodisias by Kenan T. Erim. London: Society for the Promotion of Roman Studies, 1989, Pp. 70, 71, 78. (worldcat) Wilson, A. I. (2015). Water, nymphs and a palm grove: monumental water display at Aphrodisias (R. R. R. Smith, J. Lenaghan, A. Sokolicek, &amp;amp; K. Welch, Eds.), Aphrodisias Papers 5: Excavation and Research at Aphrodisias, 2006-2012, Portsmouth, Journal of Roman Archaeology. Supplement 103, 100-135. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 82786301
TGN ID 7002358
Contributor Kathryn Gleason(ORCID: 0000-0001-6260-8378)
Publication date 24 September 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>