<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>orchards on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/orchards/</link>
    <description>Recent content in orchards on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 10:33:04 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/orchards/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Anonymous Gaul in Andematunnum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/andematunnum/andematunnum_tomb_garden_of_anonymous_gaul/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 10:33:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/andematunnum/andematunnum_tomb_garden_of_anonymous_gaul/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Andematunnum
Andematunnum (Pleiades)
Garden Tomb Garden of Anonymous Gaul in Andematunnum
Keywords  former reservoirs inscription literary garden mausoleums orchards tombs  Garden Description A famous inscription from the territory of the Lingonian Gauls (Langres) known only from a manuscript of the tenth century records the will of a local hunting enthusiast who built for himself a lavish mausoleum (cella memoriae) and equipped it with orchards (pomaria) and a reservoir (lacus) put in the care of two freedmen who are instructed to devote the revenues from them to upkeep of the tomb complex, and three landscape gardeners (topiarii) and their apprentices, each to be supported annually by the testator’s grandson, Sex. Iulius Aquila, and his heirs. The will goes on to provide for annual banquets at the tomb site, to be funded by Aquila and his heirs (not explicitly from proceeds of the orchards), and to ensure that any deviations from the testator’s prescriptions be undertaken only in order that the complex be better adorned, better planted, and better perfected (nisi..ut melius colantur et conserantur perficianturque).
Maps Images Dates unspecified
Bibliography  CIL 13.5708. EDCS-19800561 ILS 8379. FIRA III 49. J.-J. Hatt, La tombe gallo-romaine (Paris 1951) 65-84. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 177441
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 13 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Niederzier Hambach 59</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/niederzier-hambach/niederzier-hambach59/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:55:45 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/niederzier-hambach/niederzier-hambach59/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Province Description Location Niederzier-Hambach
Niederzier-Hambach (Pleiades)
Location Description In the Hambacher Forst region, which lies approximately 30-35 km. west of the former capital city Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium (mod. Cologne), a number of modest villae rusticae have been excavated.
Garden Niederzier Hambach 59
Keywords  villae rusticae ditches fences (site elements) hedges water wells orchards cherry (plant)  Garden Description This farm, known as Hambach 59, was built in the late 1st century A.D. and inhabited until its destruction in the 4th century (Plan 1). The farmhouse, 19.50 x 26 m. in size (A on plan), occupied a position in the northern part of the complex, and looked out on the rest of the farm to the south where various outbuildings and stables stood. There was no division between the residential part and the service area of the farm.
The farmyard was enclosed by a hedge (dotted lines on plan) and took up an area of approximately 1.5 hectares. Outside of the enclosed farmyard to the north were four large plots, presumably for orchards and cultivated fields, which were marked off by ditches or fences (outlined in black on plan). Two of these plots were approximately one hectare in size. The reconstruction of the vegetation on the farm is based on the palaeobotanical analysis of deposits from the four wells in front of the house. The material includes charred fruits and seeds as well as unburnt plant remains and pollen. Cherry pits are evidence for sweet cherry trees. Oak pollen, as well as the water-logged remains of the buds and bud scales of the oak tree, suggest that a shady oak may have grown near one of the wells in the courtyard. Walnut pollen was found in such large quantities in the wells, that one can safely assume the presence of walnut trees near the house. The same applies for lime trees attested by their pollen in the sediments. The remains of coriander and linseed in the wells suggest that these plants may have grown in the vegetable garden in the immediate vicinity of the house. The hedge surrounding the farm compound may have consisted of a combination of hazelnut, elderberry, raspberry and brambleberry, which were all present as pollen, shells, and seeds in the sediments. Box is attested by the pollen in the wells, but it is uncertain where this plant grew on the site.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the farm with hedges (dotted lines) and fences (solid lines) enclosing orchards, fields and the farmyard with its house (A). Plan adapted from Gaitzsch 1990, fig. on p. 238. (Rights statement).   Images Dates Late first century CE until the fourth century CE.
Bibliography  W. Gaitzsch, &amp;ldquo;Der römische Gutshof im &amp;lsquo;Gewährhau’ bei Niederzier,&amp;rdquo; in H. Hellenkemper, H. Koschik and B. Trier, eds., Archäologie in Nordrhein-Westfalen, Cologne, 1990, pp. 235-41. worldcat K.-H. Knörzer and J. Meurers-Balke, &amp;ldquo;Die Wirtschafts- und Nutzflächen eines römischen Gutshofes,&amp;rdquo; in H. Hellenkemper, H. Koschick and B.Trier, eds., Archäologie in Nordrhein-Westfalen, pp. 242-46. worldcat W. Gaitzsch, &amp;ldquo;Antikes Landleben im Modell einer villa rustica,&amp;rdquo; Archäologie im Rheinland 1990, Cologne, 1991, pp. 46-49.  Pleiades ID 109210
TGN ID 7128518
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 24 July 2020
Related articles Niederzier-Hambach 69.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Niederzier Hambach 69</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/niederzier-hambach/niederzier-hambach69/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:55:45 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/niederzier-hambach/niederzier-hambach69/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Province Description Location Niederzier-Hambach
Niederzier-Hambach (Pleiades)
Location Description In the Hambacher Forst region, which lies approximately 30-35 km. west of the former capital city Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium (mod. Cologne), a number of modest villae rusticae have been excavated.
Garden Niederzier Hambach 69
Keywords  villae rusticae fences (site elements) ditches hedges kitchen gardens orchards water wells cherry (plant)  Garden Description This villa rustica was situated west of Cologne in the same region as Hambach 59. It was built in the late 1st century A.D. and inhabited until the 4th century (Plan 1). The farm had a calculated overall area, including the cultivated land, of 50 hectares. The farm compound itself was one hectare in size. The modest house (A on plan) stood just inside the western border of the complex. Elsewhere on the property were various stables, barns, a pond and several wells.
To the east of the house was an area marked off by a narrow ditch (B on plan). This was probably a bedding trench for a protective hedge around a vegetable garden (G on plan). Palaeobotanical material, all of it carbonized, from deposits in wells and pits provide information on the field crops. Considerable amounts of charred chaff in a well in the eastern part of the farmyard suggest that a threshing area for the grain grown on the farm may have been situated near the well. The botanical remains indicate that spelt wheat was the main crop, followed by barley. The farmyard has hedge borders, the planting trenches for which were excavated. Within this area, fruit trees, oaks and alders as well as elderberry bushes possibly were planted.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the farm house (A) and the farmyard enclosed by a hedge (grey line). A vegetable garden (G) may have lain within another hedge (B). Adapted from Gaitzsch 1986, fig. 5. (Rights statement).   Dates Late first century CE until the fourth century CE.
Bibliography  K.-H. Knörzer, &amp;ldquo;Veränderungen der Unkrautvegetation auf rheinischen Bauernhöfen seit der Römerzeit,&amp;rdquo; Bonner Jahrbuch 184, 1984: 491-503. worldcat W. Gaitzsch, &amp;ldquo;Grundformen römischer Landsiedlungen im Westen der CCAA,&amp;rdquo; Bonner Jahrbuch 186, 1986: 397-427, fig. 5. worldcat  Pleiades ID 109210
TGN ID 7128518
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 24 July 2020
Related articles Niederzier-Hambach 59.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Latimer</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/latimer/latimer_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/latimer/latimer_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Latimer
Latimer (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Latimer
Keywords archaeological garden \
 fences (site elements) flower gardens orchards rural villas vegetable gardens villae rusticae  Garden Description Excavations at this country house in Buckinghamshire have produced evidence for gardens adjacent to the main residence in its latest phase dating to the beginning of the 4th century (Fig. 1). The house at the west is of the winged corridor type, fronted by a large courtyard bisected by a paved central drive with a banked edge. Between the outer courtyard wall and the house were areas used for gardening (G in Fig. 1). Just inside the outer yard wall on the south side of the drive traces of at least six bedding trenches cut into the natural subsoil and running parallel to each other were followed for at least 5 meters (b in Fig. 1). These have been interpreted by the excavator as the remains of vegetable gardens (Fig. 2). He also attributed a number of stake holes in this area to small fences bounding the vegetable gardens, and suggested the possibility of an orchard on the northern side of the drive as well as a formal flower garden nearer to the house between the projecting wings, for which there is no concrete archaeological evidence. Finally a small pit just inside the courtyard gateway may represent a pit dug to take one of a pair of trees flanking the entrance.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the residential building (A) with excavated bedding trenches (b) in its garden courtyard (G). Adapted from Branigan 1971, fig. 20.(Rights statement)   Images   Fig. 2: Reconstruction of the house and garden. Courtesy of K. Branigan.   Dates Evidence for gardens dating to the beginning of 4th century
Bibliography  K. Branigan, Latimer. Belgic, Roman, Dark Age and Early Modern Farm, Bristol, 1971, pp. 85-86, 184, figs. 14, 20 (worldcat) R.J. Zeepvat, “Roman Gardens in Britain,” in: A.E. Brown, ed., Garden Archaeology. Council for British Archaeology Research Report 78, London, 1991, p. 56, fig. 5.3. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 79555
TGN ID 1029792
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>