<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>orchards on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/tags/orchards/</link>
    <description>Recent content in orchards on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 10:33:04 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/tags/orchards/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Anonymous Gaul in Andematunnum</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/andematunnum/andematunnum_tomb_garden_of_anonymous_gaul/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 10:33:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/andematunnum/andematunnum_tomb_garden_of_anonymous_gaul/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Andematunnum
Andematunnum (Pleiades)
Garden Tomb Garden of Anonymous Gaul in Andematunnum
Keywords  former reservoirs inscription literary garden mausoleums orchards tombs  Garden Description A famous inscription from the territory of the Lingonian Gauls (Langres) known only from a manuscript of the tenth century records the will of a local hunting enthusiast who built for himself a lavish mausoleum (cella memoriae) and equipped it with orchards (pomaria) and a reservoir (lacus) put in the care of two freedmen who are instructed to devote the revenues from them to upkeep of the tomb complex, and three landscape gardeners (topiarii) and their apprentices, each to be supported annually by the testator’s grandson, Sex. Iulius Aquila, and his heirs. The will goes on to provide for annual banquets at the tomb site, to be funded by Aquila and his heirs (not explicitly from proceeds of the orchards), and to ensure that any deviations from the testator’s prescriptions be undertaken only in order that the complex be better adorned, better planted, and better perfected (nisi..ut melius colantur et conserantur perficianturque).
Maps Images Dates unspecified
Bibliography  CIL 13.5708. EDCS-19800561 ILS 8379. FIRA III 49. J.-J. Hatt, La tombe gallo-romaine (Paris 1951) 65-84. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 177441
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 13 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Niederzier Hambach 59</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/niederzier-hambach/niederzier-hambach59/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:55:45 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/niederzier-hambach/niederzier-hambach59/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Province Description Location Niederzier-Hambach
Niederzier-Hambach (Pleiades)
Location Description In the Hambacher Forst region, which lies approximately 30-35 km. west of the former capital city Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium (mod. Cologne), a number of modest villae rusticae have been excavated.
Garden Niederzier Hambach 59
Keywords  villae rusticae ditches fences (site elements) hedges water wells orchards cherry (plant)  Garden Description This farm, known as Hambach 59, was built in the late 1st century A.D. and inhabited until its destruction in the 4th century (Plan 1). The farmhouse, 19.50 x 26 m. in size (A on plan), occupied a position in the northern part of the complex, and looked out on the rest of the farm to the south where various outbuildings and stables stood. There was no division between the residential part and the service area of the farm.
The farmyard was enclosed by a hedge (dotted lines on plan) and took up an area of approximately 1.5 hectares. Outside of the enclosed farmyard to the north were four large plots, presumably for orchards and cultivated fields, which were marked off by ditches or fences (outlined in black on plan). Two of these plots were approximately one hectare in size. The reconstruction of the vegetation on the farm is based on the palaeobotanical analysis of deposits from the four wells in front of the house. The material includes charred fruits and seeds as well as unburnt plant remains and pollen. Cherry pits are evidence for sweet cherry trees. Oak pollen, as well as the water-logged remains of the buds and bud scales of the oak tree, suggest that a shady oak may have grown near one of the wells in the courtyard. Walnut pollen was found in such large quantities in the wells, that one can safely assume the presence of walnut trees near the house. The same applies for lime trees attested by their pollen in the sediments. The remains of coriander and linseed in the wells suggest that these plants may have grown in the vegetable garden in the immediate vicinity of the house. The hedge surrounding the farm compound may have consisted of a combination of hazelnut, elderberry, raspberry and brambleberry, which were all present as pollen, shells, and seeds in the sediments. Box is attested by the pollen in the wells, but it is uncertain where this plant grew on the site.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the farm with hedges (dotted lines) and fences (solid lines) enclosing orchards, fields and the farmyard with its house (A). Plan adapted from Gaitzsch 1990, fig. on p. 238. (Rights statement).   Images Dates Late first century CE until the fourth century CE.
Bibliography  W. Gaitzsch, &amp;ldquo;Der römische Gutshof im &amp;lsquo;Gewährhau’ bei Niederzier,&amp;rdquo; in H. Hellenkemper, H. Koschik and B. Trier, eds., Archäologie in Nordrhein-Westfalen, Cologne, 1990, pp. 235-41. worldcat K.-H. Knörzer and J. Meurers-Balke, &amp;ldquo;Die Wirtschafts- und Nutzflächen eines römischen Gutshofes,&amp;rdquo; in H. Hellenkemper, H. Koschick and B.Trier, eds., Archäologie in Nordrhein-Westfalen, pp. 242-46. worldcat W. Gaitzsch, &amp;ldquo;Antikes Landleben im Modell einer villa rustica,&amp;rdquo; Archäologie im Rheinland 1990, Cologne, 1991, pp. 46-49.  Pleiades ID 109210
TGN ID 7128518
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 24 July 2020
Related articles Niederzier-Hambach 69.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Niederzier Hambach 69</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/niederzier-hambach/niederzier-hambach69/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:55:45 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/niederzier-hambach/niederzier-hambach69/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Province Description Location Niederzier-Hambach
Niederzier-Hambach (Pleiades)
Location Description In the Hambacher Forst region, which lies approximately 30-35 km. west of the former capital city Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium (mod. Cologne), a number of modest villae rusticae have been excavated.
Garden Niederzier Hambach 69
Keywords  villae rusticae fences (site elements) ditches hedges kitchen gardens orchards water wells cherry (plant)  Garden Description This villa rustica was situated west of Cologne in the same region as Hambach 59. It was built in the late 1st century A.D. and inhabited until the 4th century (Plan 1). The farm had a calculated overall area, including the cultivated land, of 50 hectares. The farm compound itself was one hectare in size. The modest house (A on plan) stood just inside the western border of the complex. Elsewhere on the property were various stables, barns, a pond and several wells.
To the east of the house was an area marked off by a narrow ditch (B on plan). This was probably a bedding trench for a protective hedge around a vegetable garden (G on plan). Palaeobotanical material, all of it carbonized, from deposits in wells and pits provide information on the field crops. Considerable amounts of charred chaff in a well in the eastern part of the farmyard suggest that a threshing area for the grain grown on the farm may have been situated near the well. The botanical remains indicate that spelt wheat was the main crop, followed by barley. The farmyard has hedge borders, the planting trenches for which were excavated. Within this area, fruit trees, oaks and alders as well as elderberry bushes possibly were planted.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the farm house (A) and the farmyard enclosed by a hedge (grey line). A vegetable garden (G) may have lain within another hedge (B). Adapted from Gaitzsch 1986, fig. 5. (Rights statement).   Dates Late first century CE until the fourth century CE.
Bibliography  K.-H. Knörzer, &amp;ldquo;Veränderungen der Unkrautvegetation auf rheinischen Bauernhöfen seit der Römerzeit,&amp;rdquo; Bonner Jahrbuch 184, 1984: 491-503. worldcat W. Gaitzsch, &amp;ldquo;Grundformen römischer Landsiedlungen im Westen der CCAA,&amp;rdquo; Bonner Jahrbuch 186, 1986: 397-427, fig. 5. worldcat  Pleiades ID 109210
TGN ID 7128518
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 24 July 2020
Related articles Niederzier-Hambach 59.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Balsam Groves</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/ein_gedi/balsam_groves/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/ein_gedi/balsam_groves/</guid>
      <description>Province Judaea
Iudaea (province) (Pleiades)
Province Description Judaea, the Roman province, included parts of the areas of the Hasmonean and Herodium kingdoms, notably Biblical Judah, Samaria, and Edom. Its capital was Caesarea Maritima. Roman influence in the region began in 63 CE, when the Roman general Pompey the Great took over Syria from Mithridates and, coming into Jerusalem, occupied the Second Temple. Pompey appointed Antipater, the father of Herod, as the first Roman Procurator. Later these ties allowed Herod to seek backing from Rome against the Hasmoneans in 40 BCE, when the senate recognized him as “king of the Jews.” His territories came to include the regions of Galilee, Gaulanitis (the Golan),Peraea and the Decapolis. Herod balanced his allegiance to Rome with the independence of his kingdom, often employing architectural projects to express his ambitions and control of nature to express his capacity to rule . His many palaces, placed strategically around the kingdom, feature dramatically designed landscapes and gardens. Upon his death, his heirs were unable to maintain order and Judea was annexed to Syria in 6 CE, although it was assigned its own procurator. By the time of Trajan, Judea was reduced in size and the Herodian palaces abandoned, preserving them over the millennia for archaeologists. Hadrian renamed the province Syria Palaestina after the Bar Kochba revolts (132-135) provoked him to erase the name of Judea.
The period for which we have the richest evidence of a garden culture in this region is during the reign of Herod the Great. A client king of Rome, Herod’s relationships with Mark Antony, Cleopatra, Augustus and Marcus Agrippa and other officials have been preserved in the texts of Flavius Josephus. These constitute a rare record of interactions between Rome and its territories, and provide a valuable context for understanding the trends of design in the early imperial period. The proximity of Judea to Alexandria, whose palaces and gardens lie beneath the modern city and its harbors, may also provide a suggestion of the late Hellenistic garden culture that Romans emulated. Evidence of gardens in the Hasmonean winter palaces at Jericho and the palaces of Hyracanus the Tobiad on the other side of the Jordan Valley provide rare cases where texts can illuminate archaeological evidence. These gardens require further investigation and both are threatened by local development. This geography of Judaea comprises a wide variety of biomes, from richly watered plains of the Galilee and the Jordan, to the semi arid Judean Hills, the humid, fertile coastal plain of the Mediterranean, and the deserts of the Dead Sea valley and the Negev.
Location Ein Gedi
Ein Gedi (Pleiades)
Location Description The balsam groves of the Dead Sea region have been famous since the queen of Sheba (Egypt and Ethiopia) reputedly brought balsam as a gift to King Solomon (1 Kings 10:10; Josephus Ant.8. 6, 5-6.). From the time of Theophrastus, Jericho and Ein Gedi near the Dead Sea were renowned for their watered palm and balsam plantations (paradeisoi), described by Diodorus Siculus, Varro, Strabo, Virgil, Horace, Pausanias, Pliny the Elder, Solinus and Galen. They are described in some detail by Josephus (Antiquitates Judaeorum 14.54), who notes their water supply was destroyed during the Jewish Revolt. The balsam, however, is regarded as extinct and has not been identified archaeobotanically.
Itzar Hirshfeld identified a possible balsam terrace near the oasis of Ein Gedi, along the ancient road that links the palaces at Jericho with the fortress palace at Masada. Further studies were carried out by Guy Stibbel.
The only possible archaeobotanical evidence found to date for the plant itself comes from a cave at Qumran. Porath and Arubas report that a small Herodian-period juglet wrapped in palm fibers and carefully hidden in the rocks contains oil that does not correspond with any known modern oil and is consistent with ancient descriptions of balsam but analysis on the contents was less than conclusive. Date palm remains, by contrast, are commonly seen in the carbonized plant remains found in Jericho, Wadi Qelt, Masada,Kumran, and other excavations in the valley. In an astonishing recent development, botanist Elaine Solowey was able to use growth hormones to activate three dessicated date pits from excavated contexts at Masada. These were C14 dated to the Roman period. One seed successfully grew into a male palm. Subsequent work with desiccated pits from the Kumran area have produced female plants. (Sallon et al. 2020)
Garden Agriculture
Keywords  orchards  Dates 6-135 CE
Bibliography  Patrich, J.,“A Juglet Containing Balsam Oil (?) from a Cave near Qumran,” Israel Exploration Journal 39 (1989):43-49 (worldcat) Sallon, S., Cherif, E., Chabrillange, N., Solowey, E., Gros-Balthazard, M., Ivorra, S., &amp;amp; Aberlenc, F. (2020). Origins and insights into the historic Judean date palm based on genetic analysis of germinated ancient seeds and morphometric studies. Science advances, 6(6), eaax0384. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 196074068
TGN ID 7001389
Contributor Kathryn L. Gleason ORCID: 0000-0001-6260-8378 \
Publication date 09 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Byzantine Law Court and Roof Garden</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/caesarea_maritima/byzantine_law_court_and_roof_garden/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/caesarea_maritima/byzantine_law_court_and_roof_garden/</guid>
      <description>Province Judaea
Iudaea (province) (Pleiades)
Province Description Judaea, the Roman province, included parts of the areas of the Hasmonean and Herodium kingdoms, notably Biblical Judah, Samaria, and Edom. Its capital was Caesarea Maritima. Roman influence in the region began in 63 CE, when the Roman general Pompey the Great took over Syria from Mithridates and, coming into Jerusalem, occupied the Second Temple. Pompey appointed Antipater, the father of Herod, as the first Roman Procurator. Later these ties allowed Herod to seek backing from Rome against the Hasmoneans in 40 BCE, when the senate recognized him as “king of the Jews.” His territories came to include the regions of Galilee, Gaulanitis (the Golan),Peraea and the Decapolis. Herod balanced his allegiance to Rome with the independence of his kingdom, often employing architectural projects to express his ambitions and control of nature to express his capacity to rule . His many palaces, placed strategically around the kingdom, feature dramatically designed landscapes and gardens. Upon his death, his heirs were unable to maintain order and Judea was annexed to Syria in 6 CE, although it was assigned its own procurator. By the time of Trajan, Judea was reduced in size and the Herodian palaces abandoned, preserving them over the millennia for archaeologists. Hadrian renamed the province Syria Palaestina after the Bar Kochba revolts (132-135) provoked him to erase the name of Judea.
The period for which we have the richest evidence of a garden culture in this region is during the reign of Herod the Great. A client king of Rome, Herod’s relationships with Mark Antony, Cleopatra, Augustus and Marcus Agrippa and other officials have been preserved in the texts of Flavius Josephus. These constitute a rare record of interactions between Rome and its territories, and provide a valuable context for understanding the trends of design in the early imperial period. The proximity of Judea to Alexandria, whose palaces and gardens lie beneath the modern city and its harbors, may also provide a suggestion of the late Hellenistic garden culture that Romans emulated. Evidence of gardens in the Hasmonean winter palaces at Jericho and the palaces of Hyracanus the Tobiad on the other side of the Jordan Valley provide rare cases where texts can illuminate archaeological evidence. These gardens require further investigation and both are threatened by local development. This geography of Judaea comprises a wide variety of biomes, from richly watered plains of the Galilee and the Jordan, to the semi arid Judean Hills, the humid, fertile coastal plain of the Mediterranean, and the deserts of the Dead Sea valley and the Negev.
Location Caesarea Maritima
Caesarea Maritima (Pleiades)
Location Description Ultimately the capital of the Roman provinces of Judaea and Syria Palestina, the city was built by Herod the Great. He acquired the old Hellenistic city of Strato’s Tower from Octavian as part of a territorial expansion after Actium, and turned the modest natural harbor here into a major port city, laid out on an orthogonal urban plan. Reminiscent of the basilaea of Alexandria, the southern area of the city was devoted to Herod’s seaside palace, in its early phase, and to public entertainment facilities by the time of the city’s opening in 12 BC. Josephus describes the port and the features of the city (AJ 15.9.6.331 and BJ 1.21.5. 408) including an “amphitheatron” and theater in the south, where archaeologists have discovered and restored a stadium and a theater. These are in the area of the archaeological remains of a palace, also noted but not located by Josephus. The city was a successful enterprise, and by the second and third centuries CE the stadium functions had moved inland and expansive villas were constructed over the remains of the stadium. By the Byzantine era, these villas were incorporated into a new praetorium. These palaces and villas have gardens, discovered in varying degrees of preservation, supplied with water through water channels, initially from the aqueduct and later from wells. Upon the destruction of this district of the city, the Arab inhabitants developed gardens amidst the ruins, irrigated by wells and water channels.
Garden Royal Garden
Keywords  pleasure garden walled garden  Garden Description Byzantine Law Court and Roof Garden
Architectural analysis and epigraphic finds excavated by Josef Patrich and the Combined Caesarea Excavations suggest that the buildings in the area immediately south of the harbor (Area CC) formed a governmental compound of Roman - Byzantine Caesarea, comprising a Revenue Office (skrinion), a Law Court and adjacent to them an archive or library for judicial and financial records and books. Earlier archaeologists (JECM) had identified this complex as an honorific U-shaped building; however, it is clearly the inverse. Constructed about 200 CE, the Law Court was a vast hall (13 x 18 m.), built on top of four vaults facing west. In the first phase, the hall faced west to the sea and was surrounded on three sides (N, E and S) by a reflection pool. To its east a square fountain was constructed. (Fig.1)
During the second phase, the pool was converted to a roof garden, filled in with the rich, red sandy soil, locally known as hamra (also noted in the upper courtyard at the promontory palace.) The soil was set on a surface of bipedal ceramic tiles (ca. 60 x 50 cm), which in turn were supported on suspensurae of flat sandstone blocks (each 20 x 20 cm and 15 cm thick) supporting the corners of four bipedal tiles. This arrangement formed a separating space between the roof of the vaults and the garden soil, preventing moisture from damaging the ceiling of the vaults (Fig. 2). This arrangement has no known parallels in Israel, but was used over vaults for the gardens of Tiberius on the Palatine in Rome, a form of nemora pensile, or hanging gardens.
During this phase the building looked out over an extended garden on the east side. Here the garden soil (hamra) extended beyond the eastern wall of the former reflection pool to include the square fountain. The garden was irrigated by a water tank (ca. 3 x 3 m.) erected on ground level between the hall and the fountain, the dimensions of which were reduced at this phase. The eastern wall of the reflection pool was partially dismantled to accommodate this tank.
During the third phase, in the 6th century, the entire garden, including the fountain, was covered by a mosaic floor.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the garden area (Combined Caesarea Excavations)   Images   Fig. 2: Reconstructed section of vaults and planting area showing roof garden construction (E. Clemence after J. Patrich)   Dates 324 CE - 638 CE
Bibliography  K.G. Holum, “Inscriptions from the imperial revenue office of Byzantine Caesarea Palaestinae” Journal of Roman Archaeology Supplement 14, 1995: 333-345. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 678401
TGN ID 7001363
Contributor Joseph Patrich ORCID: #
Publication date 09 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Herodian First Palace</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/jericho/herodian_first_palace/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/jericho/herodian_first_palace/</guid>
      <description>Province Judaea
Iudaea (province) (Pleiades)
Province Description Judaea, the Roman province, included parts of the areas of the Hasmonean and Herodium kingdoms, notably Biblical Judah, Samaria, and Edom. Its capital was Caesarea Maritima. Roman influence in the region began in 63 CE, when the Roman general Pompey the Great took over Syria from Mithridates and, coming into Jerusalem, occupied the Second Temple. Pompey appointed Antipater, the father of Herod, as the first Roman Procurator. Later these ties allowed Herod to seek backing from Rome against the Hasmoneans in 40 BCE, when the senate recognized him as “king of the Jews.” His territories came to include the regions of Galilee, Gaulanitis (the Golan),Peraea and the Decapolis. Herod balanced his allegiance to Rome with the independence of his kingdom, often employing architectural projects to express his ambitions and control of nature to express his capacity to rule . His many palaces, placed strategically around the kingdom, feature dramatically designed landscapes and gardens. Upon his death, his heirs were unable to maintain order and Judea was annexed to Syria in 6 CE, although it was assigned its own procurator. By the time of Trajan, Judea was reduced in size and the Herodian palaces abandoned, preserving them over the millennia for archaeologists. Hadrian renamed the province Syria Palaestina after the Bar Kochba revolts (132-135) provoked him to erase the name of Judea.
The period for which we have the richest evidence of a garden culture in this region is during the reign of Herod the Great. A client king of Rome, Herod’s relationships with Mark Antony, Cleopatra, Augustus and Marcus Agrippa and other officials have been preserved in the texts of Flavius Josephus. These constitute a rare record of interactions between Rome and its territories, and provide a valuable context for understanding the trends of design in the early imperial period. The proximity of Judea to Alexandria, whose palaces and gardens lie beneath the modern city and its harbors, may also provide a suggestion of the late Hellenistic garden culture that Romans emulated. Evidence of gardens in the Hasmonean winter palaces at Jericho and the palaces of Hyracanus the Tobiad on the other side of the Jordan Valley provide rare cases where texts can illuminate archaeological evidence. These gardens require further investigation and both are threatened by local development. This geography of Judaea comprises a wide variety of biomes, from richly watered plains of the Galilee and the Jordan, to the semi arid Judean Hills, the humid, fertile coastal plain of the Mediterranean, and the deserts of the Dead Sea valley and the Negev.
Location Jericho
Jericho (Pleiades)
Location Description In one of the most beautiful spots of the Eastern Mediterranean, five km west of Jericho, the biblical “city of Palms,” (Deut. 34:3) lie the remains of a royal complex of the late Second Temple Period (the end of the second century B.C. continuing through the mid-first century A.D). Despite their location in the desert some 200 m. below sea level (one of the lowest occupied elevations on earth) these palaces were set amidst an abundance of vegetation and enjoyed a copious supply of water brought from the surrounding hills via water channels. The palaces are dramatically situated along Wadi Qelt where the gorge opens abruptly onto the Jordan Valley floor. (Fig. 1) They were set amidst the large palm and balsam groves for which the valley was famed. Water channels give archaeological evidence of groves to the north of the palace, but literary evidence suggests that royal holdings from Jericho to Ein Gedi were extensive. None of the gardens have been fully excavated, but many have been examined and the presence of rich soil rather than pavement, as well as water channels and ceramic planting pots provide conclusive evidence for the many gardens discussed below.
Garden Royal Garden
Keywords  pleasure garden walled garden  Garden Description Herodian First Palace
Herod may have been a regular guest at the Hasmonean palace during his boyhood. Even after he effected his rule in 37 B.C., the Hasmoneans retained possession of their winter palace for a few years, according to Josephus. Artistobulus III was drowned there by Herod’s men when the royal court stayed at the palace as guests of Princess Alexandra, the mother of Aristobulus III and Herod’s wife, Mariamne.
His first palace, excavated in 1951 by J. Pritchard, was located to the south of Wadi Qelt, again, set amidst greenery. (Fig. 7a) The building was rectangular in shape and was built around three sides of a large peristyle garden. The planning of the palace shows a clear relationship to the courtyard; both the large rectangular triclinium and another reception room on the opposite side of the court’s axis, opened onto the peristyle offering the guests a good view of its gardens.
This first palace was “introverted” thus giving expression to Herod’s inferior status in Jericho at that time. The existence of any swimming pools near the building remains an open question, but a huge pool (180 x 150m) was found to the south near the modern settlement of Birket Musa. This pool may have been used for boating and water sports, as well as irrigation.
Maps Plans   Figure 1: Plan of the Hasmonean and Herodian Winter Palace Complex, Jericho (Gleason after Netzer)     Figure 7a: Plan of Herod’s first palace (Gleason after Netzer 2001).   &amp;ndash;&amp;gt;
Images   Axonometric reconstruction of Herod’s first palace (Yaniv Korman).   &amp;ndash;&amp;gt;
Dates 31 BCE - 4 BCE
Bibliography  G. Garbrecht, and E. Netzer, “Die Wasserversorgung des geschichtlichen Jericho und seiner koniglichen Anlagen,” in Mitteilungen (aus dem Leichtweiss-Institut fur Wasserbau) 115, Braunschweig/Jerusalem 1991 worldcat K. Gleason, “Garden Excavations at the Herodian Winter Palace in Jericho, 1985-1987&amp;quot;, Bulletin of the Anglo-Israel Archaeological Society, Vol. 7, 1987-8 Jstor K. Gleason, “A Garden Excavation in the Oasis Palace of Herod the Great at Jericho,” Landscape Journal 12.2 (1993):156-67wordcat J. Kelso, James L. and Dimitri Baramki, “Excavations at New Testament Jericho and Kirbet en-Nitla,” Annual of the American Schools of Oriental Research 29-30 (1949-51): 38-39 E. Netzer, The Palaces of the Hasmoneans and Herod the Great, Jerusalem: The Israel Exploration Society, 1999: 13-64 wordcat Nielsen, Inge, Hellenistic Palaces,1994, 195-201 wordcat E. Netzer, The Hasmonean and Herodian Palaces at Jericho: Final Reports of the 1973-1987 Excavations, Vol. 1, Jerusalem: Israel Exploration Society, 2001 : 287-298 worldcat E. Netzer, and Garbrecht G, “Water channels and a royal estate of the late Hellenistic period in Jericho’s eastern plains,” in D. Amit, J. Patrich and Y.; Hirschfeld, eds, The Aqueducts of Israel. 353-365. JRA Supplement 46, R.I. 2002 worldcat J. Pritchard, “The Excavation at Herodian Jericho, 1951,&amp;quot; The Annual of the American Schools of Oriental Research 32-3 (1952-4): 56-58. [worldcat] (https://www.worldcat.org/title/excavation-at-herodian-jericho-1951-for-1952-1954/oclc/256829094&amp;amp;referer=brief_results)  Pleiades ID 687917
TGN ID ?????
Contributor Kathryn L. Gleason (ORCID: 0000-0001-6260-8378
Publication date 09 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Herodian Second Palace</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/jericho/herodian_second_palace/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/jericho/herodian_second_palace/</guid>
      <description>Province Judaea
Iudaea (province) (Pleiades)
Province Description Judaea, the Roman province, included parts of the areas of the Hasmonean and Herodium kingdoms, notably Biblical Judah, Samaria, and Edom. Its capital was Caesarea Maritima. Roman influence in the region began in 63 CE, when the Roman general Pompey the Great took over Syria from Mithridates and, coming into Jerusalem, occupied the Second Temple. Pompey appointed Antipater, the father of Herod, as the first Roman Procurator. Later these ties allowed Herod to seek backing from Rome against the Hasmoneans in 40 BCE, when the senate recognized him as “king of the Jews.” His territories came to include the regions of Galilee, Gaulanitis (the Golan),Peraea and the Decapolis. Herod balanced his allegiance to Rome with the independence of his kingdom, often employing architectural projects to express his ambitions and control of nature to express his capacity to rule . His many palaces, placed strategically around the kingdom, feature dramatically designed landscapes and gardens. Upon his death, his heirs were unable to maintain order and Judea was annexed to Syria in 6 CE, although it was assigned its own procurator. By the time of Trajan, Judea was reduced in size and the Herodian palaces abandoned, preserving them over the millennia for archaeologists. Hadrian renamed the province Syria Palaestina after the Bar Kochba revolts (132-135) provoked him to erase the name of Judea.
The period for which we have the richest evidence of a garden culture in this region is during the reign of Herod the Great. A client king of Rome, Herod’s relationships with Mark Antony, Cleopatra, Augustus and Marcus Agrippa and other officials have been preserved in the texts of Flavius Josephus. These constitute a rare record of interactions between Rome and its territories, and provide a valuable context for understanding the trends of design in the early imperial period. The proximity of Judea to Alexandria, whose palaces and gardens lie beneath the modern city and its harbors, may also provide a suggestion of the late Hellenistic garden culture that Romans emulated. Evidence of gardens in the Hasmonean winter palaces at Jericho and the palaces of Hyracanus the Tobiad on the other side of the Jordan Valley provide rare cases where texts can illuminate archaeological evidence. These gardens require further investigation and both are threatened by local development. This geography of Judaea comprises a wide variety of biomes, from richly watered plains of the Galilee and the Jordan, to the semi arid Judean Hills, the humid, fertile coastal plain of the Mediterranean, and the deserts of the Dead Sea valley and the Negev.
Location Jericho
Jericho (Pleiades)
Location Description In one of the most beautiful spots of the Eastern Mediterranean, five km west of Jericho, the biblical “city of Palms,” (Deut. 34:3) lie the remains of a royal complex of the late Second Temple Period (the end of the second century B.C. continuing through the mid-first century A.D). Despite their location in the desert some 200 m. below sea level (one of the lowest occupied elevations on earth) these palaces were set amidst an abundance of vegetation and enjoyed a copious supply of water brought from the surrounding hills via water channels. The palaces are dramatically situated along Wadi Qelt where the gorge opens abruptly onto the Jordan Valley floor. (Fig. 1) They were set amidst the large palm and balsam groves for which the valley was famed. Water channels give archaeological evidence of groves to the north of the palace, but literary evidence suggests that royal holdings from Jericho to Ein Gedi were extensive. None of the gardens have been fully excavated, but many have been examined and the presence of rich soil rather than pavement, as well as water channels and ceramic planting pots provide conclusive evidence for the many gardens discussed below.
Garden Royal Garden
Keywords  pleasure garden walled garden  Garden Description Herodian Second Palace
The earthquake of 31 B.C. destroyed the Hasmonean palace complex, and the political changes that took place after Actium enabled Herod to gain full possession of the winter palaces. On top of the ruined palaces, he built a new complex (Fig 8). The two pools of the Pool Complex were unified to form a single, large pool (32 x 18m)! Gardens replaced the pavements around the pool, as evidenced by rows of ceramic planting pots found there. (Fig. 9) On the western side of the pool (A (B) 2), two rows of planting pots ran parallel to the pool. the distance between each pot was about two and a half meters apart while on the eastern side of the pool (A (B) 3) the pots were spaced about one meter apart. Colonnades were built around the larger of these pools and a hall was built on the western side (F), probably meant for the swimmers. A long, narrow Roman-style bath house was built to the west of this pool.
The main unit of the second palace included two wings. The northern wing, was elevated 5 meters above the southern wing and was built around a fairly large peristyle courtyard (34 x 28), flanked by rooms on three sides. The courtyard itself had an unusual structure. Its plan features a regular peristyle but the level of the open courtyard is c. 1 m. higher than that of the floors of the surrounding colonnades (Fig 10). Anyone walking around the courtyard would have seen, and perhaps even smelled, the flowering shrubs directly in front of them. Adjusted to the raised Peristyle garden was a triclinium, ornamented with wall panels and incorporated a window with a view onto the garden. Southern to the triclinium was a colonnaded balcony that overlooked the lower wing of the palace and a dramatic view of Wadi Qelt. The low wing of the palace (Fig 8, AK) incorporated the two Hasmonean swimming pools (one 20 x 20 m. and 7 x 7 m). Colonnades were built around the larger of the pools and a hall was built on the western side, probably meant for the swimmers. A long, narrow Roman-style bath house was built to the west of this pool.
Plans   Figure 1: Plan of the Hasmonean and Herodian Winter Palace Complex, Jericho (Gleason after Netzer)     Figure 8a: Gardens of Herod’s second palace. Light gray shading indicates gardens, dark gray shading indicates pools (Gleason after Netzer 2001a: Plan 47).   Images   Axonometric reconstruction of Herod’s second palace (Yaniv Korman).   &amp;ndash;&amp;gt;
  Figure 9: Planting pots such as this are known from around the Greek and Roman world, although this one is particularly elegant in shape. The ancient authors describe how such pots were used for the propagation of a variety of trees, shrubs, and vines. (K. Gleason).     Figure 10: The raised garden in the peristyle courtyard in Herod’s Second Palace (photo by E. Netzer).   Dates 31 BCE - 4 BCE
Bibliography  G. Garbrecht, and E. Netzer, “Die Wasserversorgung des geschichtlichen Jericho und seiner koniglichen Anlagen,” in Mitteilungen (aus dem Leichtweiss-Institut fur Wasserbau) 115, Braunschweig/Jerusalem 1991 worldcat K. Gleason, “Garden Excavations at the Herodian Winter Palace in Jericho, 1985-1987&amp;quot;, Bulletin of the Anglo-Israel Archaeological Society, Vol. 7, 1987-8 Jstor K. Gleason, “A Garden Excavation in the Oasis Palace of Herod the Great at Jericho,” Landscape Journal 12.2 (1993):156-67wordcat J. Kelso, James L. and Dimitri Baramki, “Excavations at New Testament Jericho and Kirbet en-Nitla,” Annual of the American Schools of Oriental Research 29-30 (1949-51): 38-39 E. Netzer, The Palaces of the Hasmoneans and Herod the Great, Jerusalem: The Israel Exploration Society, 1999: 13-64 wordcat Nielsen, Inge, Hellenistic Palaces,1994, 195-201 wordcat E. Netzer, The Hasmonean and Herodian Palaces at Jericho: Final Reports of the 1973-1987 Excavations, Vol. 1, Jerusalem: Israel Exploration Society, 2001 : 287-298 worldcat E. Netzer, and Garbrecht G, “Water channels and a royal estate of the late Hellenistic period in Jericho’s eastern plains,” in D. Amit, J. Patrich and Y.; Hirschfeld, eds, The Aqueducts of Israel. 353-365. JRA Supplement 46, R.I. 2002 worldcat J. Pritchard, “The Excavation at Herodian Jericho, 1951,&amp;quot; The Annual of the American Schools of Oriental Research 32-3 (1952-4): 56-58. [worldcat] (https://www.worldcat.org/title/excavation-at-herodian-jericho-1951-for-1952-1954/oclc/256829094&amp;amp;referer=brief_results)  Pleiades ID 687917
TGN ID #
Contributor Kathryn L. Gleason (ORCID: 0000-0001-6260-8378
Publication date 09 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Herodian Third Palace Corinthian Peristyle</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/jericho/herodian_third_palace_corinthian_peristyle/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/jericho/herodian_third_palace_corinthian_peristyle/</guid>
      <description>Province Judaea
Iudaea (province) (Pleiades)
Province Description Judaea, the Roman province, included parts of the areas of the Hasmonean and Herodium kingdoms, notably Biblical Judah, Samaria, and Edom. Its capital was Caesarea Maritima. Roman influence in the region began in 63 CE, when the Roman general Pompey the Great took over Syria from Mithridates and, coming into Jerusalem, occupied the Second Temple. Pompey appointed Antipater, the father of Herod, as the first Roman Procurator. Later these ties allowed Herod to seek backing from Rome against the Hasmoneans in 40 BCE, when the senate recognized him as “king of the Jews.” His territories came to include the regions of Galilee, Gaulanitis (the Golan),Peraea and the Decapolis. Herod balanced his allegiance to Rome with the independence of his kingdom, often employing architectural projects to express his ambitions and control of nature to express his capacity to rule . His many palaces, placed strategically around the kingdom, feature dramatically designed landscapes and gardens. Upon his death, his heirs were unable to maintain order and Judea was annexed to Syria in 6 CE, although it was assigned its own procurator. By the time of Trajan, Judea was reduced in size and the Herodian palaces abandoned, preserving them over the millennia for archaeologists. Hadrian renamed the province Syria Palaestina after the Bar Kochba revolts (132-135) provoked him to erase the name of Judea.
The period for which we have the richest evidence of a garden culture in this region is during the reign of Herod the Great. A client king of Rome, Herod’s relationships with Mark Antony, Cleopatra, Augustus and Marcus Agrippa and other officials have been preserved in the texts of Flavius Josephus. These constitute a rare record of interactions between Rome and its territories, and provide a valuable context for understanding the trends of design in the early imperial period. The proximity of Judea to Alexandria, whose palaces and gardens lie beneath the modern city and its harbors, may also provide a suggestion of the late Hellenistic garden culture that Romans emulated. Evidence of gardens in the Hasmonean winter palaces at Jericho and the palaces of Hyracanus the Tobiad on the other side of the Jordan Valley provide rare cases where texts can illuminate archaeological evidence. These gardens require further investigation and both are threatened by local development. This geography of Judaea comprises a wide variety of biomes, from richly watered plains of the Galilee and the Jordan, to the semi arid Judean Hills, the humid, fertile coastal plain of the Mediterranean, and the deserts of the Dead Sea valley and the Negev.
Location Jericho
Jericho (Pleiades)
Location Description In one of the most beautiful spots of the Eastern Mediterranean, five km west of Jericho, the biblical “city of Palms,” (Deut. 34:3) lie the remains of a royal complex of the late Second Temple Period (the end of the second century B.C. continuing through the mid-first century A.D). Despite their location in the desert some 200 m. below sea level (one of the lowest occupied elevations on earth) these palaces were set amidst an abundance of vegetation and enjoyed a copious supply of water brought from the surrounding hills via water channels. The palaces are dramatically situated along Wadi Qelt where the gorge opens abruptly onto the Jordan Valley floor. (Fig. 1) They were set amidst the large palm and balsam groves for which the valley was famed. Water channels give archaeological evidence of groves to the north of the palace, but literary evidence suggests that royal holdings from Jericho to Ein Gedi were extensive. None of the gardens have been fully excavated, but many have been examined and the presence of rich soil rather than pavement, as well as water channels and ceramic planting pots provide conclusive evidence for the many gardens discussed below.
Sublocation Herodian Entertainment Complex, Third Palace
Sublocation Description The third palace built by Herod in the late first century B.C. merits special mention with regard to the integration of water, gardens and landscape. This palace was sited along a straight section of Wadi Qelt to take advantage of its season flow of water each winter. This area was, however, lower than those on which the first and second palaces had been built, offering a more limited view of the surroundings. This shortcoming was offset by the erection of a viewing pavilion on top of an artificial tel. The overall building complex was rectilinear, with Wadi Qelt cutting through the center, and a bridge spanning the two halves. On the north side lay a complex of banqueting rooms, Roman style baths, reception rooms, peristyle courtyards and colonnaded walks. On the south lay a great sunken garden, the artificial tel and pavilion, and, off-axis, a shallow boating pool. (Fig. 11) The garden features are discussed individually below.
Garden Royal Garden
Keywords  pleasure garden walled garden  Garden Description Corinthian Peristyle
With porticoes on three sides and measuring 23 x 14.5m, this courtyard, known as area B55, is decorated with columns in the Corinthian order. (Fig. 16) The lower portions of these smooth stucco shafts alternate between red and black; above them the columns are of fluted white stucco while the Corinthian capitals are of stone. Thus far, no entablature or roof tiles have been discovered. A low stone wall, known as a pluteus, ran between the columns. Water entered the garden at the north end, under the pluteus from the aqueduct channel serving the adjacent baths. As with garden B64, an opus signinum walk runs along the exterior perimeter of the porticoes. The ridged surface of the garden lies 12cm below the surrounding walk, which is neatly finished with a curb. The ridges are of packed earth, 3 or 4cm in depth, with no trace of plaster or mortar; and whereas in garden B64 there is a covering layer of fertilized soil, in B55 the ridges are exposed. Beneath the packed surface, lies coarse gravel, perhaps equivalent to the subsoil or fill in B64. No perforated pots were found. The only evidence of ornamentation within the garden is a large boulder, centrally placed and apparently part of the garden scheme rather than fallen debris. Along the curb, layers of mineral deposit were excavated from very fine silt sand. In some respects, this courtyard has the appearance of a pool, although its surfaces are not sealed with the grey hydraulic plaster usually employed in water features elsewhere in the palace complex. The nature of this courtyard remains uncertain pending further excavation, but the mouth of a water channel on the north end and the accreted mineral deposit such either a water feature or displays of plants receiving heavy irrigation.
Plans   Figure 1: Plan of the Hasmonean and Herodian Winter Palace Complex, Jericho (Gleason after Netzer)     Figure 11: Plan of Herod’s Third Palace (K. Gleason after E. Netzer 2001a: Plan 48).     Figure 16a: Plan of Corinthian peristyle garden (B55) showing contouring (K. Gleason).   Dates 31 BCE - 4 BCE
Bibliography  G. Garbrecht, and E. Netzer, “Die Wasserversorgung des geschichtlichen Jericho und seiner koniglichen Anlagen,” in Mitteilungen (aus dem Leichtweiss-Institut fur Wasserbau) 115, Braunschweig/Jerusalem 1991 worldcat K. Gleason, “Garden Excavations at the Herodian Winter Palace in Jericho, 1985-1987&amp;quot;, Bulletin of the Anglo-Israel Archaeological Society, Vol. 7, 1987-8 Jstor K. Gleason, “A Garden Excavation in the Oasis Palace of Herod the Great at Jericho,” Landscape Journal 12.2 (1993):156-67wordcat J. Kelso, James L. and Dimitri Baramki, “Excavations at New Testament Jericho and Kirbet en-Nitla,” Annual of the American Schools of Oriental Research 29-30 (1949-51): 38-39 E. Netzer, The Palaces of the Hasmoneans and Herod the Great, Jerusalem: The Israel Exploration Society, 1999: 13-64 wordcat Nielsen, Inge, Hellenistic Palaces,1994, 195-201 wordcat E. Netzer, The Hasmonean and Herodian Palaces at Jericho: Final Reports of the 1973-1987 Excavations, Vol. 1, Jerusalem: Israel Exploration Society, 2001 : 287-298 worldcat E. Netzer, and Garbrecht G, “Water channels and a royal estate of the late Hellenistic period in Jericho’s eastern plains,” in D. Amit, J. Patrich and Y.; Hirschfeld, eds, The Aqueducts of Israel. 353-365. JRA Supplement 46, R.I. 2002 worldcat J. Pritchard, “The Excavation at Herodian Jericho, 1951,&amp;quot; The Annual of the American Schools of Oriental Research 32-3 (1952-4): 56-58. [worldcat] (https://www.worldcat.org/title/excavation-at-herodian-jericho-1951-for-1952-1954/oclc/256829094&amp;amp;referer=brief_results)  Pleiades ID 687917
TGN ID #
Contributor Kathryn L. Gleason (ORCID: 0000-0001-6260-8378
Publication date 09 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Herodian Third Palace Ionic Peristyle</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/jericho/herodian_third_palace_ionic_peristyle/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/jericho/herodian_third_palace_ionic_peristyle/</guid>
      <description>Province Judaea
Iudaea (province) (Pleiades)
Province Description Judaea, the Roman province, included parts of the areas of the Hasmonean and Herodium kingdoms, notably Biblical Judah, Samaria, and Edom. Its capital was Caesarea Maritima. Roman influence in the region began in 63 CE, when the Roman general Pompey the Great took over Syria from Mithridates and, coming into Jerusalem, occupied the Second Temple. Pompey appointed Antipater, the father of Herod, as the first Roman Procurator. Later these ties allowed Herod to seek backing from Rome against the Hasmoneans in 40 BCE, when the senate recognized him as “king of the Jews.” His territories came to include the regions of Galilee, Gaulanitis (the Golan),Peraea and the Decapolis. Herod balanced his allegiance to Rome with the independence of his kingdom, often employing architectural projects to express his ambitions and control of nature to express his capacity to rule . His many palaces, placed strategically around the kingdom, feature dramatically designed landscapes and gardens. Upon his death, his heirs were unable to maintain order and Judea was annexed to Syria in 6 CE, although it was assigned its own procurator. By the time of Trajan, Judea was reduced in size and the Herodian palaces abandoned, preserving them over the millennia for archaeologists. Hadrian renamed the province Syria Palaestina after the Bar Kochba revolts (132-135) provoked him to erase the name of Judea.
The period for which we have the richest evidence of a garden culture in this region is during the reign of Herod the Great. A client king of Rome, Herod’s relationships with Mark Antony, Cleopatra, Augustus and Marcus Agrippa and other officials have been preserved in the texts of Flavius Josephus. These constitute a rare record of interactions between Rome and its territories, and provide a valuable context for understanding the trends of design in the early imperial period. The proximity of Judea to Alexandria, whose palaces and gardens lie beneath the modern city and its harbors, may also provide a suggestion of the late Hellenistic garden culture that Romans emulated. Evidence of gardens in the Hasmonean winter palaces at Jericho and the palaces of Hyracanus the Tobiad on the other side of the Jordan Valley provide rare cases where texts can illuminate archaeological evidence. These gardens require further investigation and both are threatened by local development. This geography of Judaea comprises a wide variety of biomes, from richly watered plains of the Galilee and the Jordan, to the semi arid Judean Hills, the humid, fertile coastal plain of the Mediterranean, and the deserts of the Dead Sea valley and the Negev.
Location Jericho
Jericho (Pleiades)
Location Description In one of the most beautiful spots of the Eastern Mediterranean, five km west of Jericho, the biblical “city of Palms,” (Deut. 34:3) lie the remains of a royal complex of the late Second Temple Period (the end of the second century B.C. continuing through the mid-first century A.D). Despite their location in the desert some 200 m. below sea level (one of the lowest occupied elevations on earth) these palaces were set amidst an abundance of vegetation and enjoyed a copious supply of water brought from the surrounding hills via water channels. The palaces are dramatically situated along Wadi Qelt where the gorge opens abruptly onto the Jordan Valley floor. (Fig. 1) They were set amidst the large palm and balsam groves for which the valley was famed. Water channels give archaeological evidence of groves to the north of the palace, but literary evidence suggests that royal holdings from Jericho to Ein Gedi were extensive. None of the gardens have been fully excavated, but many have been examined and the presence of rich soil rather than pavement, as well as water channels and ceramic planting pots provide conclusive evidence for the many gardens discussed below.
Sublocation Herodian Entertainment Complex, Third Palace
Sublocation Description The third palace built by Herod in the late first century B.C. merits special mention with regard to the integration of water, gardens and landscape. This palace was sited along a straight section of Wadi Qelt to take advantage of its season flow of water each winter. This area was, however, lower than those on which the first and second palaces had been built, offering a more limited view of the surroundings. This shortcoming was offset by the erection of a viewing pavilion on top of an artificial tel. The overall building complex was rectilinear, with Wadi Qelt cutting through the center, and a bridge spanning the two halves. On the north side lay a complex of banqueting rooms, Roman style baths, reception rooms, peristyle courtyards and colonnaded walks. On the south lay a great sunken garden, the artificial tel and pavilion, and, off-axis, a shallow boating pool. (Fig. 6) The garden features are discussed individually below.
Garden Royal Garden
Keywords  pleasure garden walled garden  Garden Description Ionic Peristyle
This peristyle courtyard (19.1 x 18.7) lies adjacent to the banquet hall and near Roman baths constructed in opus reticulatum. It is referred to in excavation reports as area B64. The central garden is surrounded on three sides by a colonnade of cemented stone, stuccoed in white and red. Remains of plaster Ionic capitals and other stucco decoration were found during excavation, as well as frescoes with floral motifs of unusually high quality, perhaps made by Roman craftsmen. Rozenberg claimed that this courtyard was the most richly painted space in the palace An unusual feature of the peristyles in this complex is an opus signinum walk around the inner circumference of the peristyle, outside the columns flanking the garden.
The garden was first discovered in 1976 by E. Netzer, who excavated a trench through the center of the peristyle. The garden soil was poorly preserved, but ceramic planting pots appeared at the bottom of the garden. In 1985 and 1987, K. Gleason continued the excavations and found preserved garden soil layers beneath the destruction debris at the sides of the garden. (Fig. 13) The stratigraphy is reconstructed as follows:
The subsoil, probably fill, is composed of coarse, poorly cemented alluvial pebbles and cobbles. Above this, a thin layer of soil, in most places, plastered over, formed a rough surface over the courtyard, except at the north end, where the plaster tapers off onto a packed earth surface. The crude quality of the plaster and varying types of mortar suggest a working surface for the construction of the peristyle. When the garden was installed, trenches extending down into the subsoil levels were cut out of the plaster surface for the pots and planting pits. (Fig. 14) The flower pots at Jericho are unusual among Roman era pots. They are well-formed of local clay with a hole in the bottom and three holes in the side of the vessel, neatly punched before firing. Their similarity to local water-wheel pots is striking, except that in the planting pot the knob-like foot is open, like a bottle top, while closed in the water wheel pots. The Mishnah suggests that perforated pots, with holes in the bottom and sides, allowed the plants inside to make contact with the ground and thus allow plants or seeds in the pot to be considered like plants in the ground in most matters of agricultural law (Mishnah 8 in Kil’ayim), purity (eg Uktzin 1.9-10), and tithing (Gitin 21b-22a). The rabbis, at least during the redaction of the Mishnah, found that flower pots posed fascinating problems for interpretation.
The plantings were aligned in rows, roughly 1.5m apart. Between the rows, ridges were formed of small cobbles crudely plastered over, apparently to direct the flow of irrigation water. At the north end the situation appears to be somewhat different. The ridges characteristic of the plastered surface end approximately 2m from the walk in front of the apse. In this area only one pot was found, but late in excavation, after light rainfall, three planting pits became evident. These were filled with a light sandy loam, and two were free of flower-pot sherds. The fertilized garden soil was then laid over the whole area, 8-10cm deep and surrounding the pots, but only on the surface of the planting pits.
The plan reveals seven rows of up to eleven pots per row, although directly in front of the apse, tree pits were observed in place of the pots. This regular ordering of rows seems peculiar in such a public location, as Roman gardens of this period could be quite ornate in their layout. A garden at Pompeii laid out in such straight rows would be a market garden. However, the older, Hellenistic and Persian preference is for straight rows, and it is possible that this is a display garden for miniaturized plants (Langgut and Gleason).
Plans   Figure 1: Plan of the Hasmonean and Herodian Winter Palace Complex, Jericho (Gleason after Netzer)     Figure 11: Plan of Herod’s Third Palace (K. Gleason after E. Netzer 2001a: Plan 48).     Figure 13a: Plan of the Ionic Peristyle Courtyard B64 with the location of the planting pots (K. Wilczak and K. Gleason).   Images   Figure 12: Section extending from the Sunken Garden, through Garden B64, to the Southern Tell (K. Wilczak after Netzer 2001a: Ill. 478).     Figure 13b: Axonometric reconstruction of the Ionic Peristyle Courtyard B64 with the location of the planting pots (Yaniv Korman).     Figure 14: A section through the Ionic Peristyle Courtyard B64 at the second row from the north: (a) gravel subsoil; (b) working surface; (c) planting pot; (d) planting pit; (e) ridges; (f) contoured garden-soil surface; (g) sidewalk; (h) alluvial deposit; (i) fallen building debris; (j) modern surface in 1978–1985 (K. Gleason).     Figure 15: A planting pot No. 23 found in the Ionic Peristyle Courtyard B64 (K. Gleason).   Dates 31 BCE - 4 BCE
Bibliography  G. Garbrecht, and E. Netzer, “Die Wasserversorgung des geschichtlichen Jericho und seiner koniglichen Anlagen,” in Mitteilungen (aus dem Leichtweiss-Institut fur Wasserbau) 115, Braunschweig/Jerusalem 1991 worldcat K. Gleason, “Garden Excavations at the Herodian Winter Palace in Jericho, 1985-1987&amp;quot;, Bulletin of the Anglo-Israel Archaeological Society, Vol. 7, 1987-8 Jstor K. Gleason, “A Garden Excavation in the Oasis Palace of Herod the Great at Jericho,” Landscape Journal 12.2 (1993):156-67wordcat J. Kelso, James L. and Dimitri Baramki, “Excavations at New Testament Jericho and Kirbet en-Nitla,” Annual of the American Schools of Oriental Research 29-30 (1949-51): 38-39 E. Netzer, The Palaces of the Hasmoneans and Herod the Great, Jerusalem: The Israel Exploration Society, 1999: 13-64 wordcat Nielsen, Inge, Hellenistic Palaces,1994, 195-201 wordcat E. Netzer, The Hasmonean and Herodian Palaces at Jericho: Final Reports of the 1973-1987 Excavations, Vol. 1, Jerusalem: Israel Exploration Society, 2001 : 287-298 worldcat E. Netzer, and Garbrecht G, “Water channels and a royal estate of the late Hellenistic period in Jericho’s eastern plains,” in D. Amit, J. Patrich and Y.; Hirschfeld, eds, The Aqueducts of Israel. 353-365. JRA Supplement 46, R.I. 2002 worldcat J. Pritchard, “The Excavation at Herodian Jericho, 1951,&amp;quot; The Annual of the American Schools of Oriental Research 32-3 (1952-4): 56-58. [worldcat] (https://www.worldcat.org/title/excavation-at-herodian-jericho-1951-for-1952-1954/oclc/256829094&amp;amp;referer=brief_results) Langgut D. and Gleason K. 2020. Identification of the miniaturized garden of King Herod the Great: The fossil pollen evidence, Strata.  Pleiades ID 687917
TGN ID #
Contributor Kathryn L. Gleason (ORCID: 0000-0001-6260-8378
Publication date 09 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Herodian Third Palace Sunken Garden</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/jericho/herodian_third_palace_sunken_garden/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/jericho/herodian_third_palace_sunken_garden/</guid>
      <description>Province Judaea
Iudaea (province) (Pleiades)
Province Description Judaea, the Roman province, included parts of the areas of the Hasmonean and Herodium kingdoms, notably Biblical Judah, Samaria, and Edom. Its capital was Caesarea Maritima. Roman influence in the region began in 63 CE, when the Roman general Pompey the Great took over Syria from Mithridates and, coming into Jerusalem, occupied the Second Temple. Pompey appointed Antipater, the father of Herod, as the first Roman Procurator. Later these ties allowed Herod to seek backing from Rome against the Hasmoneans in 40 BCE, when the senate recognized him as “king of the Jews.” His territories came to include the regions of Galilee, Gaulanitis (the Golan),Peraea and the Decapolis. Herod balanced his allegiance to Rome with the independence of his kingdom, often employing architectural projects to express his ambitions and control of nature to express his capacity to rule . His many palaces, placed strategically around the kingdom, feature dramatically designed landscapes and gardens. Upon his death, his heirs were unable to maintain order and Judea was annexed to Syria in 6 CE, although it was assigned its own procurator. By the time of Trajan, Judea was reduced in size and the Herodian palaces abandoned, preserving them over the millennia for archaeologists. Hadrian renamed the province Syria Palaestina after the Bar Kochba revolts (132-135) provoked him to erase the name of Judea.
The period for which we have the richest evidence of a garden culture in this region is during the reign of Herod the Great. A client king of Rome, Herod’s relationships with Mark Antony, Cleopatra, Augustus and Marcus Agrippa and other officials have been preserved in the texts of Flavius Josephus. These constitute a rare record of interactions between Rome and its territories, and provide a valuable context for understanding the trends of design in the early imperial period. The proximity of Judea to Alexandria, whose palaces and gardens lie beneath the modern city and its harbors, may also provide a suggestion of the late Hellenistic garden culture that Romans emulated. Evidence of gardens in the Hasmonean winter palaces at Jericho and the palaces of Hyracanus the Tobiad on the other side of the Jordan Valley provide rare cases where texts can illuminate archaeological evidence. These gardens require further investigation and both are threatened by local development. This geography of Judaea comprises a wide variety of biomes, from richly watered plains of the Galilee and the Jordan, to the semi arid Judean Hills, the humid, fertile coastal plain of the Mediterranean, and the deserts of the Dead Sea valley and the Negev.
Location Jericho
Jericho (Pleiades)
Location Description In one of the most beautiful spots of the Eastern Mediterranean, five km west of Jericho, the biblical “city of Palms,” (Deut. 34:3) lie the remains of a royal complex of the late Second Temple Period (the end of the second century B.C. continuing through the mid-first century A.D). Despite their location in the desert some 200 m. below sea level (one of the lowest occupied elevations on earth) these palaces were set amidst an abundance of vegetation and enjoyed a copious supply of water brought from the surrounding hills via water channels. The palaces are dramatically situated along Wadi Qelt where the gorge opens abruptly onto the Jordan Valley floor. (Fig. 1) They were set amidst the large palm and balsam groves for which the valley was famed. Water channels give archaeological evidence of groves to the north of the palace, but literary evidence suggests that royal holdings from Jericho to Ein Gedi were extensive. None of the gardens have been fully excavated, but many have been examined and the presence of rich soil rather than pavement, as well as water channels and ceramic planting pots provide conclusive evidence for the many gardens discussed below.
Sublocation Herodian Entertainment Complex, Third Palace
Sublocation Description The third palace built by Herod in the late first century B.C. merits special mention with regard to the integration of water, gardens and landscape. This palace was sited along a straight section of Wadi Qelt to take advantage of its season flow of water each winter. This area was, however, lower than those on which the first and second palaces had been built, offering a more limited view of the surroundings. This shortcoming was offset by the erection of a viewing pavilion on top of an artificial tel. The overall building complex was rectilinear, with Wadi Qelt cutting through the center, and a bridge spanning the two halves. On the north side lay a complex of banqueting rooms, Roman style baths, reception rooms, peristyle courtyards and colonnaded walks. On the south lay a great sunken garden, the artificial tel and pavilion, and, off-axis, a shallow boating pool. (Fig. 6) The garden features are discussed individually below.
Garden Royal Garden
Keywords  pleasure garden walled garden  Garden Description Sunken Garden
The monumental ‘sunken garden’ (B6), which measures 37.27 x 113.67m, lies largely unexcavated on the south side of Wadi Qelt, in alignment with the buildings and gardens described above (Fig 17). First explored in 1950 by Kelso and Baramki and again by Netzer in 1979, its perimeter is known, although the northern side has eroded into the wadi. Kelso and Baramki found a retaining wall on the south side, set into the slope of the hill and presenting a “grand facade” of semicircular and squared niches separated by columns in antis (fig 18). Jewish Law would have prohibited the placement of statuary in these niches, but urns with plants may have provided a satisfactory alternative and Stibel suggests that it served as a luxurious nympheum. The facade is interrupted in the middle by a great hemicycle (Fig 19), which formed a small stepped theatre, with benches not for spectators but for plants in perforated ceramic pots of the same general size and description as those found in garden B64 and elsewhere in the winter palace complex (Fig 20). A water channel ran along the floor of the sunken garden across entire length of the facade and cavea. Double porticoes along the top of the retaining walls, preserved on the east and west sides, allowed visitors to promenade around the sunken garden and look into it; what they observed remains buried beneath a deep landslide. In 1978, Netzer cut a trial trench along the foot of the east retaining wall and discovered a perforated pot at this lower level. (Fig. 21 and 22) Gleason examined the stratigraphy of this sounding in 1985 and noted that the pot was set into a level of cultivated soil.
Elevated Pavilion
Above the east end of the sunken garden rises the artificial tel with its pavilion, another unusual feature of Herod’s palace. The pavilion was round, 16 m. in diameter, serving as a reception hall with four niches in each quarter. Below the hall, as seen in the northern palace at Masada, lay a Roman-style bathhouse for the pleasure of guests visiting the hall. The artificial mount was undoubtedly erected to offer splendid views of the landscape with its oasis estates of rare palms and balsam, and would, in turn, be a landmark visible from the road descending from Wadi Qelt and from across the plain.
Boating Pool
A huge pool (90 x 40 m.) built to the east of the sunken garden formed an integral part of the third palace. The pool probably served not only for swimming but also for boating and aquatic sports. In contrast to all the other wings of the third palace, which were built in alignment with a single grid system, this pool deviates by c. 30 to accommodate the slope of the hill, evidently to offer spectators a good view of the events. The difference in orientation was possibly obscured by trees and shrubs, was the case with the Pool Complex of the second palace.
Plans   Figure 1: Plan of the Hasmonean and Herodian Winter Palace Complex, Jericho (Gleason after Netzer)     Figure 11: Plan of Herod’s Third Palace (K. Gleason after E. Netzer 2001a: Plan 48).   Images   Figure 12: Section extending from the Sunken Garden, through Garden B64, to the Southern Tell (K. Wilczak after Netzer 2001a: Ill. 478).     Figure 17: view of the Third Palace showing the Sunken Garden with linear promenades(ambulationes, K. Gleason after J. Salzberg).     Fig 18: The Grand Facade of the Sunken Garden and Netzer’s Trench B3, view from the northwest (Netzer 2001a: Ill. 433).     Figure 19:Axonometric reconstruction of the Hemicycle and the Sunken Garden terrace showing the excavation areas.Light shading indicates the Kelso and Baramki excavations, dark shading indicates Netzer’s excavations (K.Gleason after J. Salzberg).     Figure 20:Section C-C through the benches of the Hemicycle: opus reticulatum walls set on clay subsoil (K. Gleason after Kelso and Baramki 1955:18).     Figure 21: Trench B6 (Netzer 2001a: Ill. 435).     Figure 22:Section D-D in Trench B6 showing garden soils near east end of Sunken Garden at location of flower pot. (K. Gleason).   Dates 31 BCE - 4 BCE
Bibliography  G. Garbrecht, and E. Netzer, “Die Wasserversorgung des geschichtlichen Jericho und seiner koniglichen Anlagen,” in Mitteilungen (aus dem Leichtweiss-Institut fur Wasserbau) 115, Braunschweig/Jerusalem 1991 worldcat K. Gleason, “Garden Excavations at the Herodian Winter Palace in Jericho, 1985-1987&amp;quot;, Bulletin of the Anglo-Israel Archaeological Society, Vol. 7, 1987-8 Jstor K. Gleason, “A Garden Excavation in the Oasis Palace of Herod the Great at Jericho,” Landscape Journal 12.2 (1993):156-67wordcat J. Kelso, James L. and Dimitri Baramki, “Excavations at New Testament Jericho and Kirbet en-Nitla,” Annual of the American Schools of Oriental Research 29-30 (1949-51): 38-39 E. Netzer, The Palaces of the Hasmoneans and Herod the Great, Jerusalem: The Israel Exploration Society, 1999: 13-64 wordcat Nielsen, Inge, Hellenistic Palaces,1994, 195-201 wordcat E. Netzer, The Hasmonean and Herodian Palaces at Jericho: Final Reports of the 1973-1987 Excavations, Vol. 1, Jerusalem: Israel Exploration Society, 2001 : 287-298 worldcat E. Netzer, and Garbrecht G, “Water channels and a royal estate of the late Hellenistic period in Jericho’s eastern plains,” in D. Amit, J. Patrich and Y.; Hirschfeld, eds, The Aqueducts of Israel. 353-365. JRA Supplement 46, R.I. 2002 worldcat J. Pritchard, “The Excavation at Herodian Jericho, 1951,&amp;quot; The Annual of the American Schools of Oriental Research 32-3 (1952-4): 56-58. [worldcat] (https://www.worldcat.org/title/excavation-at-herodian-jericho-1951-for-1952-1954/oclc/256829094&amp;amp;referer=brief_results)  Pleiades ID 687917
TGN ID #
Contributor Kathryn L. Gleason (ORCID: 0000-0001-6260-8378
Publication date 09 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Herod’s Tomb Garden</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/herodium/herods_tomb_garden/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/herodium/herods_tomb_garden/</guid>
      <description>Province Judaea
Iudaea (province) (Pleiades)
Province Description Judaea, the Roman province, included parts of the areas of the Hasmonean and Herodium kingdoms, notably Biblical Judah, Samaria, and Edom. Its capital was Caesarea Maritima. Roman influence in the region began in 63 CE, when the Roman general Pompey the Great took over Syria from Mithridates and, coming into Jerusalem, occupied the Second Temple. Pompey appointed Antipater, the father of Herod, as the first Roman Procurator. Later these ties allowed Herod to seek backing from Rome against the Hasmoneans in 40 BCE, when the senate recognized him as “king of the Jews.” His territories came to include the regions of Galilee, Gaulanitis (the Golan),Peraea and the Decapolis. Herod balanced his allegiance to Rome with the independence of his kingdom, often employing architectural projects to express his ambitions and control of nature to express his capacity to rule . His many palaces, placed strategically around the kingdom, feature dramatically designed landscapes and gardens. Upon his death, his heirs were unable to maintain order and Judea was annexed to Syria in 6 CE, although it was assigned its own procurator. By the time of Trajan, Judea was reduced in size and the Herodian palaces abandoned, preserving them over the millennia for archaeologists. Hadrian renamed the province Syria Palaestina after the Bar Kochba revolts (132-135) provoked him to erase the name of Judea.
The period for which we have the richest evidence of a garden culture in this region is during the reign of Herod the Great. A client king of Rome, Herod’s relationships with Mark Antony, Cleopatra, Augustus and Marcus Agrippa and other officials have been preserved in the texts of Flavius Josephus. These constitute a rare record of interactions between Rome and its territories, and provide a valuable context for understanding the trends of design in the early imperial period. The proximity of Judea to Alexandria, whose palaces and gardens lie beneath the modern city and its harbors, may also provide a suggestion of the late Hellenistic garden culture that Romans emulated. Evidence of gardens in the Hasmonean winter palaces at Jericho and the palaces of Hyracanus the Tobiad on the other side of the Jordan Valley provide rare cases where texts can illuminate archaeological evidence. These gardens require further investigation and both are threatened by local development. This geography of Judaea comprises a wide variety of biomes, from richly watered plains of the Galilee and the Jordan, to the semi arid Judean Hills, the humid, fertile coastal plain of the Mediterranean, and the deserts of the Dead Sea valley and the Negev.
Location Herodium
Herodium (Pleiades)
Location Description Herodium
Herod the Great’s primary residence and burial place appears to have been this large palace complex 15 km southwest of Jerusalem. Here his court was within easy reach of the city, and on clear days the palace and the Mt. of Olives are visible in both directions. Herodium was an entirely new administrative and residential complex, commemorating his military victory over Antigonus for control of Jerusalem in 40 BCE. Herodium was begun c. 23-20 BC and offered a Herod a range of facilities in which he could perhaps live and conduct business more freely here than in Jerusalem. (Jewish Antiquities, XV, 323-325) The palace has two primary residential areas: the fortified palace atop a natural, but raised hilltop; and an unfortified palace that spans a gentle valley below. (Fig. 1) (Josephus Jewish War I, 419-421; Jewish Antiquities, XV, 323-325).
Garden Royal Garden
Keywords  pleasure garden walled garden  Garden Description Herod’s Tomb Garden
In 2005, Netzer’s team found the long-sought tomb of Herod, positioned on a terrace constructed into the slope of the artificial hill. This terrace was constructed of chipped stone and construction debris, largely the light limestone of the area. To the front and sides of the tomb, a layer of rich brown loam, similar to that found in the other garden areas, clearly indicated a garden. (Fig. 4) A small pool with lead piping was found to the side of the terrace. Although the lead pipes had been robbed, the pool evidently watered the terraced gardens (fig 1B, 2, and 3)
Plans   Fig. 1:Plan of the complex at Herodium showing the Fortress Palace with its small peristyle garden (A), the Tomb Garden (B) and the Lower Palace with its central pool and cultivated grounds (C) (Yaniv Korman after Netzer)   Images   Fig. 2: A reconstruction drawing of the mausoleum garden at its later period, around 20 AD (Yaniv Korman)     Fig. 3: A reconstruction drawing of the mausoleum garden at its early period, around 15 BC (Yaniv Korman)   Dates 15 BCE - 60 CE
Bibliography  E. Netzer, “Greater Herodium” in Qedem, Monographs of the Institute of Archaeology, The Hebrew University of Jerusalem 13, 1981 (worldcat) E. Netzer The Palaces of the Hasmoneans and Herod the Great, Jerusalem: The Israel Exploration Society, 1999, 98-107 (worldcat) I. Nielsen, Inge, Hellenistic Palaces, 1994, 201-203. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 687916
TGN ID 8713913
Contributor Kathryn L. Gleason ORCID: 0000-0001-6260-8378
Ehud Netzer
Publication date 09 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lower Herodium</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/herodium/lower_herodium/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/herodium/lower_herodium/</guid>
      <description>Province Judaea
Iudaea (province) (Pleiades)
Province Description Judaea, the Roman province, included parts of the areas of the Hasmonean and Herodium kingdoms, notably Biblical Judah, Samaria, and Edom. Its capital was Caesarea Maritima. Roman influence in the region began in 63 CE, when the Roman general Pompey the Great took over Syria from Mithridates and, coming into Jerusalem, occupied the Second Temple. Pompey appointed Antipater, the father of Herod, as the first Roman Procurator. Later these ties allowed Herod to seek backing from Rome against the Hasmoneans in 40 BCE, when the senate recognized him as “king of the Jews.” His territories came to include the regions of Galilee, Gaulanitis (the Golan),Peraea and the Decapolis. Herod balanced his allegiance to Rome with the independence of his kingdom, often employing architectural projects to express his ambitions and control of nature to express his capacity to rule . His many palaces, placed strategically around the kingdom, feature dramatically designed landscapes and gardens. Upon his death, his heirs were unable to maintain order and Judea was annexed to Syria in 6 CE, although it was assigned its own procurator. By the time of Trajan, Judea was reduced in size and the Herodian palaces abandoned, preserving them over the millennia for archaeologists. Hadrian renamed the province Syria Palaestina after the Bar Kochba revolts (132-135) provoked him to erase the name of Judea.
The period for which we have the richest evidence of a garden culture in this region is during the reign of Herod the Great. A client king of Rome, Herod’s relationships with Mark Antony, Cleopatra, Augustus and Marcus Agrippa and other officials have been preserved in the texts of Flavius Josephus. These constitute a rare record of interactions between Rome and its territories, and provide a valuable context for understanding the trends of design in the early imperial period. The proximity of Judea to Alexandria, whose palaces and gardens lie beneath the modern city and its harbors, may also provide a suggestion of the late Hellenistic garden culture that Romans emulated. Evidence of gardens in the Hasmonean winter palaces at Jericho and the palaces of Hyracanus the Tobiad on the other side of the Jordan Valley provide rare cases where texts can illuminate archaeological evidence. These gardens require further investigation and both are threatened by local development. This geography of Judaea comprises a wide variety of biomes, from richly watered plains of the Galilee and the Jordan, to the semi arid Judean Hills, the humid, fertile coastal plain of the Mediterranean, and the deserts of the Dead Sea valley and the Negev.
Location Herodium
Herodium (Pleiades)
Location Description Herodium
Herod the Great’s primary residence and burial place appears to have been this large palace complex 15 km southwest of Jerusalem. Here his court was within easy reach of the city, and on clear days the palace and the Mt. of Olives are visible in both directions. Herodium was an entirely new administrative and residential complex, commemorating his military victory over Antigonus for control of Jerusalem in 40 BCE. Herodium was begun c. 23-20 BC and offered a Herod a range of facilities in which he could perhaps live and conduct business more freely here than in Jerusalem. (Jewish Antiquities, XV, 323-325) The palace has two primary residential areas: the fortified palace atop a natural, but raised hilltop; and an unfortified palace that spans a gentle valley below. (Fig. 1) (Josephus Jewish War I, 419-421; Jewish Antiquities, XV, 323-325).
Garden Royal Garden
Keywords  pleasure garden walled garden  Garden Description Lower Herodium
Lower Herodium (Fig. 1C) comprises several units. Here the central focus is the large pool, the water of which was supplied by a 6 km long aqueduct built by Herod from the spring at the modern village of Artas. The pool is set into a huge garden terrace 120 X 110 m. in size. It was constructed by blocking and leveling a whole section of a valley with up to 8 m of fill. A stepped retaining wall, like a dam, supports the terrace to the east of the garden, as well as two long halls, one on the garden level and the other below, looking down the valley. The garden itself is surrounded on three sides (north, west and south) by wide colonnades situated about 1.5m higher than the garden. The pool was probably used for swimming, for small boats, as a water reservoir, and as a central architectural focus at “the heart” of Lower Herodium. A tholos-type pavilion topped the circular stone foundation (13.5 m in diameter) exposed in the center of the pool. The majority of the buildings at Lower Herodium, still largely unexcavated, are laid out in a “U” shaped cluster around this large garden.
A limited examination of the courtyard area by K. Gleason in December 1985 supports the theory that the courtyard was planted, although it may have had substantial areas with plastered walks and seating areas, as one might expect around a pool. Immediately below the plaster surface, above the terrace fill, a rich, mottled loam with potsherds, suitable for cultivation was identified, suggesting either an earlier garden planted over the entire area, or simply a soil layer that permitted trees and shrubs to be planted within an overall scheme of trees, shrubs, and paved places for bathers to relax. Small test trenches did not reveal any planting pits; however, the rich soil was seen in the stratigraphy of earlier trenches throughout the site suggesting shaded smooth plastered surfaces and probable areas of garden beds.
Plans   Fig. 1:Plan of the complex at Herodium showing the Fortress Palace with its small peristyle garden (A), the Tomb Garden (B) and the Lower Palace with its central pool and cultivated grounds (C) (Yaniv Korman after Netzer)   Dates 30 BCE - 60 CE
Bibliography  E. Netzer, “Greater Herodium” in Qedem, Monographs of the Institute of Archaeology, The Hebrew University of Jerusalem 13, 1981 (worldcat) E. Netzer The Palaces of the Hasmoneans and Herod the Great, Jerusalem: The Israel Exploration Society, 1999, 98-107 (worldcat) I. Nielsen, Inge, Hellenistic Palaces, 1994, 201-203. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 687916
TGN ID 8713913
Contributor Kathryn L. Gleason ORCID: 0000-0001-6260-8378
Ehud Netzer
Publication date 09 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Masada</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/masada/masada/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/masada/masada/</guid>
      <description>Province Judaea
Iudaea (province) (Pleiades)
Province Description Judaea, the Roman province, included parts of the areas of the Hasmonean and Herodium kingdoms, notably Biblical Judah, Samaria, and Edom. Its capital was Caesarea Maritima. Roman influence in the region began in 63 CE, when the Roman general Pompey the Great took over Syria from Mithridates and, coming into Jerusalem, occupied the Second Temple. Pompey appointed Antipater, the father of Herod, as the first Roman Procurator. Later these ties allowed Herod to seek backing from Rome against the Hasmoneans in 40 BCE, when the senate recognized him as “king of the Jews.” His territories came to include the regions of Galilee, Gaulanitis (the Golan),Peraea and the Decapolis. Herod balanced his allegiance to Rome with the independence of his kingdom, often employing architectural projects to express his ambitions and control of nature to express his capacity to rule . His many palaces, placed strategically around the kingdom, feature dramatically designed landscapes and gardens. Upon his death, his heirs were unable to maintain order and Judea was annexed to Syria in 6 CE, although it was assigned its own procurator. By the time of Trajan, Judea was reduced in size and the Herodian palaces abandoned, preserving them over the millennia for archaeologists. Hadrian renamed the province Syria Palaestina after the Bar Kochba revolts (132-135) provoked him to erase the name of Judea.
The period for which we have the richest evidence of a garden culture in this region is during the reign of Herod the Great. A client king of Rome, Herod’s relationships with Mark Antony, Cleopatra, Augustus and Marcus Agrippa and other officials have been preserved in the texts of Flavius Josephus. These constitute a rare record of interactions between Rome and its territories, and provide a valuable context for understanding the trends of design in the early imperial period. The proximity of Judea to Alexandria, whose palaces and gardens lie beneath the modern city and its harbors, may also provide a suggestion of the late Hellenistic garden culture that Romans emulated. Evidence of gardens in the Hasmonean winter palaces at Jericho and the palaces of Hyracanus the Tobiad on the other side of the Jordan Valley provide rare cases where texts can illuminate archaeological evidence. These gardens require further investigation and both are threatened by local development. This geography of Judaea comprises a wide variety of biomes, from richly watered plains of the Galilee and the Jordan, to the semi arid Judean Hills, the humid, fertile coastal plain of the Mediterranean, and the deserts of the Dead Sea valley and the Negev.
Location Masada
Masada (Pleiades)
Location Description Masada, originally a Hasmonean defensive post, was the refuge for Herod’s family during the journey to Rome that led to his kingship. They nearly perished of thirst, but the winter rains arrived to fill the cisterns at the last possible moment. (Josephus, Jewish Antiquities XIV. 358-60; 391) Once Herod consolidated his power, he turned this barren desert mountaintop into a luxurious oasis palace overlooking the Dead Sea (Josephus Jewish War VII, 289-291.) (Fig. 1) The site is more famous as the last stand of the Zealots during the Jewish Revolt of AD 66 and remains of Roman forts surround the palace on the lower slopes and valley floor.
The earliest phases of Herodian building are seen in the Western Palace area. These buildings are architecturally similar to the Hasmonean palaces at Jericho and include the garden features of the southern area of the mountain top: water channels, cisterns, two swimming pools, and a columbarium. Gleason has studied the garden area briefly in 1990 and 1996 and found evidence of garden soil fertilized with domestic debris including potsherds. (Fig. 2) The sherd scatters are the main remaining evidence of this soil. It is possible that when the Zealots built the earthen fortification on the last night of the siege that the soils of the gardens may have been the quickest to remove. This or wind erosion appears to have removed any trace of the hilltop “being of rich soils…softer than any plain and given up to cultivation.” The potsherd types indicate that the garden area was cultivated by both Herod and the Zealots. There is no evidence of cultivation in the south area during the Byzantine period. Aerial photographs dating prior to the excavations may suggest that the gardens were laid out and managed in the manner of Nabataean desert agriculture in the region and future work at the site may shed further light on the layout of the garden.
The Northern or Hanging Palace, the latest of Herod’s constructions on the site, is a spectacular feature of architecture, engineering and landscape architecture. A series of platforms were created by alternately creating retaining walls and carving into the precipitous northern face of the mountain. On these platforms, he built a series of pavilions for dining, reception, baths and guest quarters. The contrast between the interior luxury of these rooms and the brilliant and utterly desolate landscape of the Dead Sea is sublime. Room xxx, in particular, sheltered guests amidst frescos of garden foliage (Fig. 3) and only steps away presented a spectacular overlook of the desert view. Herod’s reputation for “defying nature” (Josephus xx) is nowhere more refined than in this complex.
Garden Royal Garden
Keywords  pleasure garden walled garden agriculture  Plans   : Axonometric drawing of Masada (Gleason after Netzer 1999, fig. 124)   Images   Fig. 2: View of southern garden area with pools and columbarium.     Fig. 3:Fragments of garden paintings from the Northern Palace. Location of garden rooms is indicated with an asterix on Fig. 1. (Foerster, 1996).   Dates 30 BCE - 60 CE
Bibliography  G. Foerster, Masada VII: The Architectural Decoration. Jerusalem: Israel Exploration Society, 1996 E. Netzer, Masada V: The Architecture and Stratigraphy. Jerusalem: Israel Exploration Society, 1994 worldcat E. Netzer The Palaces of the Hasmoneans and Herod the Great, Jerusalem: The Israel Exploration Society, 1999, 98-107 (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 687968
TGN ID 7001381
Contributor Kathryn L. Gleason ORCID: 0000-0001-6260-8378
Ehud Netzer
Publication date 09 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Palace Fortress</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/herodium/palatial_fortress/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/herodium/palatial_fortress/</guid>
      <description>Province Judaea
Iudaea (province) (Pleiades)
Province Description Judaea, the Roman province, included parts of the areas of the Hasmonean and Herodium kingdoms, notably Biblical Judah, Samaria, and Edom. Its capital was Caesarea Maritima. Roman influence in the region began in 63 CE, when the Roman general Pompey the Great took over Syria from Mithridates and, coming into Jerusalem, occupied the Second Temple. Pompey appointed Antipater, the father of Herod, as the first Roman Procurator. Later these ties allowed Herod to seek backing from Rome against the Hasmoneans in 40 BCE, when the senate recognized him as “king of the Jews.” His territories came to include the regions of Galilee, Gaulanitis (the Golan),Peraea and the Decapolis. Herod balanced his allegiance to Rome with the independence of his kingdom, often employing architectural projects to express his ambitions and control of nature to express his capacity to rule . His many palaces, placed strategically around the kingdom, feature dramatically designed landscapes and gardens. Upon his death, his heirs were unable to maintain order and Judea was annexed to Syria in 6 CE, although it was assigned its own procurator. By the time of Trajan, Judea was reduced in size and the Herodian palaces abandoned, preserving them over the millennia for archaeologists. Hadrian renamed the province Syria Palaestina after the Bar Kochba revolts (132-135) provoked him to erase the name of Judea.
The period for which we have the richest evidence of a garden culture in this region is during the reign of Herod the Great. A client king of Rome, Herod’s relationships with Mark Antony, Cleopatra, Augustus and Marcus Agrippa and other officials have been preserved in the texts of Flavius Josephus. These constitute a rare record of interactions between Rome and its territories, and provide a valuable context for understanding the trends of design in the early imperial period. The proximity of Judea to Alexandria, whose palaces and gardens lie beneath the modern city and its harbors, may also provide a suggestion of the late Hellenistic garden culture that Romans emulated. Evidence of gardens in the Hasmonean winter palaces at Jericho and the palaces of Hyracanus the Tobiad on the other side of the Jordan Valley provide rare cases where texts can illuminate archaeological evidence. These gardens require further investigation and both are threatened by local development. This geography of Judaea comprises a wide variety of biomes, from richly watered plains of the Galilee and the Jordan, to the semi arid Judean Hills, the humid, fertile coastal plain of the Mediterranean, and the deserts of the Dead Sea valley and the Negev.
Location Herodium
Herodium (Pleiades)
Location Description Herodium
Herod the Great’s primary residence and burial place appears to have been this large palace complex 15 km southwest of Jerusalem. Here his court was within easy reach of the city, and on clear days the palace and the Mt. of Olives are visible in both directions. Herodium was an entirely new administrative and residential complex, commemorating his military victory over Antigonus for control of Jerusalem in 40 BCE. Herodium was begun c. 23-20 BC and offered a Herod a range of facilities in which he could perhaps live and conduct business more freely here than in Jerusalem. (Jewish Antiquities, XV, 323-325) The palace has two primary residential areas: the fortified palace atop a natural, but raised hilltop; and an unfortified palace that spans a gentle valley below. (Fig. 1) (Josephus Jewish War I, 419-421; Jewish Antiquities, XV, 323-325).
Garden Royal Garden
Keywords  pleasure garden walled garden  Garden Description Palace Fortress
The Palace Fortress is a cylindrical structure originally seven stories high (two vaulted corridors in the substructure and five stories of corridors each having its floors supported on wooden beams). In the open interior of the cylinder, palace quarters were designed with luxuriously appointed rooms facing onto a 41x18m courtyard (Fig 1A). These included a triclinium/reception hall, baths, and living quarters. This peristyle featured colonnaded corridors on three of its sides, the two shorter of which were decorated by exedra. The interior focal point for these rooms was a garden, which has been excavated to approximately its original surface. The soil of the garden is clearly amended with fertilizer and suitable for cultivation using water from the cisterns beneath the palace, but the garden features have not yet been excavated.
Plans   Fig. 1:Plan of the complex at Herodium showing the Fortress Palace with its small peristyle garden (A), the Tomb Garden (B) and the Lower Palace with its central pool and cultivated grounds (C) (Yaniv Korman after Netzer)   Dates 30 BCE - 60 CE
Bibliography  E. Netzer, “Greater Herodium” in Qedem, Monographs of the Institute of Archaeology, The Hebrew University of Jerusalem 13, 1981 (worldcat) E. Netzer The Palaces of the Hasmoneans and Herod the Great, Jerusalem: The Israel Exploration Society, 1999, 98-107 (worldcat) I. Nielsen, Inge, Hellenistic Palaces, 1994, 201-203. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 687916
TGN ID 8713913
Contributor Kathryn L. Gleason ORCID: 0000-0001-6260-8378
Ehud Netzer
Publication date 09 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Palace of John Hyrcanus I</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/jericho/palace_of_john_hyrcanus_i/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/jericho/palace_of_john_hyrcanus_i/</guid>
      <description>Province Judaea
Iudaea (province) (Pleiades)
Province Description Judaea, the Roman province, included parts of the areas of the Hasmonean and Herodium kingdoms, notably Biblical Judah, Samaria, and Edom. Its capital was Caesarea Maritima. Roman influence in the region began in 63 CE, when the Roman general Pompey the Great took over Syria from Mithridates and, coming into Jerusalem, occupied the Second Temple. Pompey appointed Antipater, the father of Herod, as the first Roman Procurator. Later these ties allowed Herod to seek backing from Rome against the Hasmoneans in 40 BCE, when the senate recognized him as “king of the Jews.” His territories came to include the regions of Galilee, Gaulanitis (the Golan),Peraea and the Decapolis. Herod balanced his allegiance to Rome with the independence of his kingdom, often employing architectural projects to express his ambitions and control of nature to express his capacity to rule . His many palaces, placed strategically around the kingdom, feature dramatically designed landscapes and gardens. Upon his death, his heirs were unable to maintain order and Judea was annexed to Syria in 6 CE, although it was assigned its own procurator. By the time of Trajan, Judea was reduced in size and the Herodian palaces abandoned, preserving them over the millennia for archaeologists. Hadrian renamed the province Syria Palaestina after the Bar Kochba revolts (132-135) provoked him to erase the name of Judea.
The period for which we have the richest evidence of a garden culture in this region is during the reign of Herod the Great. A client king of Rome, Herod’s relationships with Mark Antony, Cleopatra, Augustus and Marcus Agrippa and other officials have been preserved in the texts of Flavius Josephus. These constitute a rare record of interactions between Rome and its territories, and provide a valuable context for understanding the trends of design in the early imperial period. The proximity of Judea to Alexandria, whose palaces and gardens lie beneath the modern city and its harbors, may also provide a suggestion of the late Hellenistic garden culture that Romans emulated. Evidence of gardens in the Hasmonean winter palaces at Jericho and the palaces of Hyracanus the Tobiad on the other side of the Jordan Valley provide rare cases where texts can illuminate archaeological evidence. These gardens require further investigation and both are threatened by local development. This geography of Judaea comprises a wide variety of biomes, from richly watered plains of the Galilee and the Jordan, to the semi arid Judean Hills, the humid, fertile coastal plain of the Mediterranean, and the deserts of the Dead Sea valley and the Negev.
Location Jericho
Jericho (Pleiades)
Location Description In one of the most beautiful spots of the Eastern Mediterranean, five km west of Jericho, the biblical “city of Palms,” (Deut. 34:3) lie the remains of a royal complex of the late Second Temple Period (the end of the second century B.C. continuing through the mid-first century A.D). Despite their location in the desert some 200 m. below sea level (one of the lowest occupied elevations on earth) these palaces were set amidst an abundance of vegetation and enjoyed a copious supply of water brought from the surrounding hills via water channels. The palaces are dramatically situated along Wadi Qelt where the gorge opens abruptly onto the Jordan Valley floor. (Fig. 1) They were set amidst the large palm and balsam groves for which the valley was famed. Water channels give archaeological evidence of groves to the north of the palace, but literary evidence suggests that royal holdings from Jericho to Ein Gedi were extensive. None of the gardens have been fully excavated, but many have been examined and the presence of rich soil rather than pavement, as well as water channels and ceramic planting pots provide conclusive evidence for the many gardens discussed below.
Garden Royal Garden
Keywords  pleasure garden walled garden  Garden Description Palace of John Hyrcanus I
Erected on the southern margin of the royal estate around 120 B.C., north of Wadi Qelt, the palace has not yet been studied in its entirety, since at a later stage most of it was buried (Fig 2 area AA). At its center lay a courtyard measuring (25 x 18m) flanked by rooms on three sides, probably bedrooms and reception rooms. Although the inner courtyard lacked any archaeological evidence for vegetation, sections of walls and clay pipes suggest that the building was surrounded by orchards and gardens, some of which might have been formal.
Over the years, two swimming pools (probably one for men and one for women), each measuring 10 x 9 m. and 3 m. deep, were added to the palace building (Fig 2 area AB). Each pool had a broad flight of stairs along one of its sidewalls leading down to the bottom, and both had benches built into the tops of the side walls. The pools were probably surrounded by paved plazas with installations for the use of the bathers.
Plans   Figure 1: Plan of the Hasmonean and Herodian Winter Palace Complex, Jericho (Gleason after Netzer)     Figure 2: The plantations and Hasmonean palace buildings, Area AA represent the location of the the buried Palace.(K. Wilczak and K. Gleason, after Netzer 2001a: Plan 4; Netzer and Laureys-Chachy 2004: Plan 2)    Images   Figure 3: The palace of King Hyrcanus I in Jericho the palace, the garden and the swimming pools (Netzer 1999).   Dates 120 BCE - 103 BCE
Bibliography  G. Garbrecht, and E. Netzer, “Die Wasserversorgung des geschichtlichen Jericho und seiner koniglichen Anlagen,” in Mitteilungen (aus dem Leichtweiss-Institut fur Wasserbau) 115, Braunschweig/Jerusalem 1991 worldcat K. Gleason, “Garden Excavations at the Herodian Winter Palace in Jericho, 1985-1987&amp;quot;, Bulletin of the Anglo-Israel Archaeological Society, Vol. 7, 1987-8 Jstor K. Gleason, “A Garden Excavation in the Oasis Palace of Herod the Great at Jericho,” Landscape Journal 12.2 (1993):156-67wordcat J. Kelso, James L. and Dimitri Baramki, “Excavations at New Testament Jericho and Kirbet en-Nitla,” Annual of the American Schools of Oriental Research 29-30 (1949-51): 38-39 E. Netzer, The Palaces of the Hasmoneans and Herod the Great, Jerusalem: The Israel Exploration Society, 1999: 13-64 wordcat Nielsen, Inge, Hellenistic Palaces,1994, 195-201 wordcat E. Netzer, The Hasmonean and Herodian Palaces at Jericho: Final Reports of the 1973-1987 Excavations, Vol. 1, Jerusalem: Israel Exploration Society, 2001 : 287-298 worldcat E. Netzer, and Garbrecht G, “Water channels and a royal estate of the late Hellenistic period in Jericho’s eastern plains,” in D. Amit, J. Patrich and Y.; Hirschfeld, eds, The Aqueducts of Israel. 353-365. JRA Supplement 46, R.I. 2002 worldcat J. Pritchard, “The Excavation at Herodian Jericho, 1951,&amp;quot; The Annual of the American Schools of Oriental Research 32-3 (1952-4): 56-58. [worldcat] (https://www.worldcat.org/title/excavation-at-herodian-jericho-1951-for-1952-1954/oclc/256829094&amp;amp;referer=brief_results)  Pleiades ID 687917
TGN ID ?????
Contributor Kathryn L. Gleason (ORCID: 0000-0001-6260-8378
Publication date 09 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pool Complex of Alexander Janneaus</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/jericho/pool_complex_of_alexander_janneaus/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/jericho/pool_complex_of_alexander_janneaus/</guid>
      <description>Province Judaea
Iudaea (province) (Pleiades)
Province Description Judaea, the Roman province, included parts of the areas of the Hasmonean and Herodium kingdoms, notably Biblical Judah, Samaria, and Edom. Its capital was Caesarea Maritima. Roman influence in the region began in 63 CE, when the Roman general Pompey the Great took over Syria from Mithridates and, coming into Jerusalem, occupied the Second Temple. Pompey appointed Antipater, the father of Herod, as the first Roman Procurator. Later these ties allowed Herod to seek backing from Rome against the Hasmoneans in 40 BCE, when the senate recognized him as “king of the Jews.” His territories came to include the regions of Galilee, Gaulanitis (the Golan),Peraea and the Decapolis. Herod balanced his allegiance to Rome with the independence of his kingdom, often employing architectural projects to express his ambitions and control of nature to express his capacity to rule . His many palaces, placed strategically around the kingdom, feature dramatically designed landscapes and gardens. Upon his death, his heirs were unable to maintain order and Judea was annexed to Syria in 6 CE, although it was assigned its own procurator. By the time of Trajan, Judea was reduced in size and the Herodian palaces abandoned, preserving them over the millennia for archaeologists. Hadrian renamed the province Syria Palaestina after the Bar Kochba revolts (132-135) provoked him to erase the name of Judea.
The period for which we have the richest evidence of a garden culture in this region is during the reign of Herod the Great. A client king of Rome, Herod’s relationships with Mark Antony, Cleopatra, Augustus and Marcus Agrippa and other officials have been preserved in the texts of Flavius Josephus. These constitute a rare record of interactions between Rome and its territories, and provide a valuable context for understanding the trends of design in the early imperial period. The proximity of Judea to Alexandria, whose palaces and gardens lie beneath the modern city and its harbors, may also provide a suggestion of the late Hellenistic garden culture that Romans emulated. Evidence of gardens in the Hasmonean winter palaces at Jericho and the palaces of Hyracanus the Tobiad on the other side of the Jordan Valley provide rare cases where texts can illuminate archaeological evidence. These gardens require further investigation and both are threatened by local development. This geography of Judaea comprises a wide variety of biomes, from richly watered plains of the Galilee and the Jordan, to the semi arid Judean Hills, the humid, fertile coastal plain of the Mediterranean, and the deserts of the Dead Sea valley and the Negev.
Location Jericho
Jericho (Pleiades)
Location Description In one of the most beautiful spots of the Eastern Mediterranean, five km west of Jericho, the biblical “city of Palms,” (Deut. 34:3) lie the remains of a royal complex of the late Second Temple Period (the end of the second century B.C. continuing through the mid-first century A.D). Despite their location in the desert some 200 m. below sea level (one of the lowest occupied elevations on earth) these palaces were set amidst an abundance of vegetation and enjoyed a copious supply of water brought from the surrounding hills via water channels. The palaces are dramatically situated along Wadi Qelt where the gorge opens abruptly onto the Jordan Valley floor. (Fig. 1) They were set amidst the large palm and balsam groves for which the valley was famed. Water channels give archaeological evidence of groves to the north of the palace, but literary evidence suggests that royal holdings from Jericho to Ein Gedi were extensive. None of the gardens have been fully excavated, but many have been examined and the presence of rich soil rather than pavement, as well as water channels and ceramic planting pots provide conclusive evidence for the many gardens discussed below.
Garden Royal Garden
Keywords  pleasure garden walled garden  Garden Description Pool Complex of Alexander Janneaus
The ascent to the throne of Alexander Jannaeus in 103 B.C. triggered a significant development in the above palace. He constructed another conduit from the “Auja and Na’aran” springs to the north of the palace site, which improved the gardens and bathing facilities. Immediately to the east of the palace, he built a new complex of two swimming pools, each measuring 18 x 13 m., surrounded by paved plazas, and a pavilion to the south of the pools. These elements were surrounded by formal gardens, some of which were peripheral, while others were independent units. The largest of all (70 x 60 m.) was surrounded by colonnades. This splendid layout was built along an axis of symmetry, with the pavilion at one end and a peristyle courtyard at the other end. This may be the first archaeological evidence in the Hellenistic-Roman world of an architectural complex whose main function was to provide bathing and swimming facilities.
By 90 BCE, Jannaeus was experiencing political and military difficulties, and it seems that vacations in Jericho had become dangerous. To address security problems, he buried the palace of his father and on top of it he built an elevated, fortified palace surrounded by a moat. The new building offered the advantages of better views across the renowned estate of palm and balsam groves and greater exposure to breezes.
Plans   Figure 1: Plan of the Hasmonean and Herodian Winter Palace Complex, Jericho (Gleason after Netzer)     Figure 2: The plantations and Hasmonean palace buildings, Area AA represent the location of the the buried Palace.(K. Wilczak and K. Gleason, after Netzer 2001a: Plan 4; Netzer and Laureys-Chachy 2004: Plan 2)    Images   Figure 4:Axonometric reconstruction of the Hasmonean palace and cultivated areas (Netzer 1999).   Dates 103 BCE - 76 BCE
Bibliography  G. Garbrecht, and E. Netzer, “Die Wasserversorgung des geschichtlichen Jericho und seiner koniglichen Anlagen,” in Mitteilungen (aus dem Leichtweiss-Institut fur Wasserbau) 115, Braunschweig/Jerusalem 1991 worldcat K. Gleason, “Garden Excavations at the Herodian Winter Palace in Jericho, 1985-1987&amp;quot;, Bulletin of the Anglo-Israel Archaeological Society, Vol. 7, 1987-8 Jstor K. Gleason, “A Garden Excavation in the Oasis Palace of Herod the Great at Jericho,” Landscape Journal 12.2 (1993):156-67wordcat J. Kelso, James L. and Dimitri Baramki, “Excavations at New Testament Jericho and Kirbet en-Nitla,” Annual of the American Schools of Oriental Research 29-30 (1949-51): 38-39 E. Netzer, The Palaces of the Hasmoneans and Herod the Great, Jerusalem: The Israel Exploration Society, 1999: 13-64 wordcat Nielsen, Inge, Hellenistic Palaces,1994, 195-201 wordcat E. Netzer, The Hasmonean and Herodian Palaces at Jericho: Final Reports of the 1973-1987 Excavations, Vol. 1, Jerusalem: Israel Exploration Society, 2001 : 287-298 worldcat E. Netzer, and Garbrecht G, “Water channels and a royal estate of the late Hellenistic period in Jericho’s eastern plains,” in D. Amit, J. Patrich and Y.; Hirschfeld, eds, The Aqueducts of Israel. 353-365. JRA Supplement 46, R.I. 2002 worldcat J. Pritchard, “The Excavation at Herodian Jericho, 1951,&amp;quot; The Annual of the American Schools of Oriental Research 32-3 (1952-4): 56-58. [worldcat] (https://www.worldcat.org/title/excavation-at-herodian-jericho-1951-for-1952-1954/oclc/256829094&amp;amp;referer=brief_results)  Pleiades ID 687917
TGN ID ?????
Contributor Kathryn L. Gleason (ORCID: 0000-0001-6260-8378
Publication date 09 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Promontory Palace of Herod the Great</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/caesarea_maritima/promontory_palace_of_herod_the_great/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/caesarea_maritima/promontory_palace_of_herod_the_great/</guid>
      <description>Province Judaea
Iudaea (province) (Pleiades)
Province Description Judaea, the Roman province, included parts of the areas of the Hasmonean and Herodium kingdoms, notably Biblical Judah, Samaria, and Edom. Its capital was Caesarea Maritima. Roman influence in the region began in 63 CE, when the Roman general Pompey the Great took over Syria from Mithridates and, coming into Jerusalem, occupied the Second Temple. Pompey appointed Antipater, the father of Herod, as the first Roman Procurator. Later these ties allowed Herod to seek backing from Rome against the Hasmoneans in 40 BCE, when the senate recognized him as “king of the Jews.” His territories came to include the regions of Galilee, Gaulanitis (the Golan),Peraea and the Decapolis. Herod balanced his allegiance to Rome with the independence of his kingdom, often employing architectural projects to express his ambitions and control of nature to express his capacity to rule . His many palaces, placed strategically around the kingdom, feature dramatically designed landscapes and gardens. Upon his death, his heirs were unable to maintain order and Judea was annexed to Syria in 6 CE, although it was assigned its own procurator. By the time of Trajan, Judea was reduced in size and the Herodian palaces abandoned, preserving them over the millennia for archaeologists. Hadrian renamed the province Syria Palaestina after the Bar Kochba revolts (132-135) provoked him to erase the name of Judea.
The period for which we have the richest evidence of a garden culture in this region is during the reign of Herod the Great. A client king of Rome, Herod’s relationships with Mark Antony, Cleopatra, Augustus and Marcus Agrippa and other officials have been preserved in the texts of Flavius Josephus. These constitute a rare record of interactions between Rome and its territories, and provide a valuable context for understanding the trends of design in the early imperial period. The proximity of Judea to Alexandria, whose palaces and gardens lie beneath the modern city and its harbors, may also provide a suggestion of the late Hellenistic garden culture that Romans emulated. Evidence of gardens in the Hasmonean winter palaces at Jericho and the palaces of Hyracanus the Tobiad on the other side of the Jordan Valley provide rare cases where texts can illuminate archaeological evidence. These gardens require further investigation and both are threatened by local development. This geography of Judaea comprises a wide variety of biomes, from richly watered plains of the Galilee and the Jordan, to the semi arid Judean Hills, the humid, fertile coastal plain of the Mediterranean, and the deserts of the Dead Sea valley and the Negev.
Location Caesarea Maritima
Caesarea Maritima (Pleiades)
Location Description Ultimately the capital of the Roman provinces of Judaea and Syria Palestina, the city was built by Herod the Great. He acquired the old Hellenistic city of Strato’s Tower from Octavian as part of a territorial expansion after Actium, and turned the modest natural harbor here into a major port city, laid out on an orthogonal urban plan. Reminiscent of the basilaea of Alexandria, the southern area of the city was devoted to Herod’s seaside palace, in its early phase, and to public entertainment facilities by the time of the city’s opening in 12 BC. Josephus describes the port and the features of the city (AJ 15.9.6.331 and BJ 1.21.5. 408) including an “amphitheatron” and theater in the south, where archaeologists have discovered and restored a stadium and a theater. These are in the area of the archaeological remains of a palace, also noted but not located by Josephus. The city was a successful enterprise, and by the second and third centuries CE the stadium functions had moved inland and expansive villas were constructed over the remains of the stadium. By the Byzantine era, these villas were incorporated into a new praetorium. These palaces and villas have gardens, discovered in varying degrees of preservation, supplied with water through water channels, initially from the aqueduct and later from wells. Upon the destruction of this district of the city, the Arab inhabitants developed gardens amidst the ruins, irrigated by wells and water channels.
Garden Royal Garden
Keywords  pleasure garden walled garden  Garden Description Promontory Palace of Herod the Great
A seaside palace west of the theater at Caesarea Maritima has been identified by E. Netzer as the maritime palace Herod the Great built to supervise construction of the great harbor, and, later, to provide reception space for guests at spectacles and official functions. (Fig. 1) The view north from this promontory became increasingly impressive as the harbor was completed and thrived. The palace served as the official praetorium of his heirs and subsequent Roman officials. Lower Promontory Excavations in the 1970s by Netzer and Lee I. Levine in the lower area of the palace revealed a series of luxurious reception rooms and heated chambers centering on a large (35 x 18 m.) rock-cut swimming pool enclosed by a colonnade. Cuttings in the bedrock between the columns suggested to Netzer that planters had been built between the columns, offering a pluteus around the pool, as well as a planting area protected from the salt spray. (Fig. 2) Upper Palace Excavations by K. Gleason and B. Burrell for the University of Pennsylvania Museum (1990-1996), in collaboration with E. Netzer and Hebrew University; and by Y. Porath of the Israel Antiquities Authority (1993-1996), have revealed an upper, more public half of the palace connected to the stadium (also referred to as an amphitheater by Porath following Josephus) and the theater. The upper palace comprised a series of baths and reception rooms facing out onto a quadriportico (42 x 65 m.) Although the courtyard was paved in plastered crushed sandstone in later Roman phases, fragmentary areas of layers of rich red sand (hamra), popular today with gardeners, were used to level many areas of the courtyard and may indicate the presence of vegetation or a gardened area in the first Herodian period and possibly a gardened courtyard in the first phase of the upper palace’s peristyle courtyard, but soil pits and other planting features were not preserved in any detectable pattern. (Fig. 3) Pollen extracted from plaster on the kurkar columns of the surrounding colonnade included taxa likely to have been growing within the courtyard: Cypress (Cupressus&amp;ndash;either juniperus or sempervirens), hazelnut (Corylus, a non-native), and the herbaceous taxa, Brassicacaea, Salvia, and Cistus (Fig. 4). A fourth century AD well briefly supplied water for the courtyard. Curse tablets (defixiones) at the bottom of this well indicate the popular practice of wishing ill, rather than wishing well.
Foundations of garden architecture, water channels and garden soils of the late Byzantine period have also been found, best preserved in the eastern half of the site.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the Promontory Palace (J.H. Williams and A. Iamim): a) first phase (c. 22-15 BC) ; b) second phase (c. 15-4 BC)   Images   Fig. 2:Photograph of cuttings around pool for planters (K. Gleason.     Fig. 3:Photograph of Hamra soil in courtyard (K. Gleason).     Reconstruction drawing of the Promontory upper garden (Y. Korman)   Dates 37 BCE - 135 CE
Bibliography  D. Langgut, K. Gleason, and B. Burrell, “Pollen Analysis as Evidence for Herod’s Royal Garden at the Promontory Palace, Caesarea” Israel Journal of Plant Sciences 62 (2015): 111-121. http://www.tandfonline.com/action/showCitFormats?doi=10.1080/07929978.2014.975560; K. Gleason et al. “The promontory palace at Caesarea Maritima : preliminary evidence for Herod&amp;rsquo;s Praetorium” Journal of Roman Archaeology, 11 (1998) 23-52. (worldcat) B. Burrell, K. Gleason, and E. Netzer, “Uncovering Herod’s Seaside Palace” Biblical Archaeology Review 19.3(1993): 50-57; K. K. Gleason, “Ruler and Spectacle: Herod’s Palace at Caesarea” Caesarea Maritima: a Retrospective after Two Millennia. Eds., A. Raban and K. Holum, Leiden: J. Brill, 1996, pp. 208-27; (worldcat) L.I. Levine, and E. Netzer, Excavations at Caesarea Maritima, Qedem 21, 1986, pp. 158-160; Excavations at Caesarea Maritima (worldcat) E. Netzer, “Herod the Great’s Palace” In Caesarea Maritima: a Retrospective after Two Millennia. Eds. A. Raban and K. Holum, Leiden: J. Brill, 1996, pp. 193-207. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 678401
TGN ID 7001363
Contributor Kathryn L. Gleason ORCID: 0000-0001-6260-8378
Publication date 09 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ramat Hanadiv</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/ramat_hanadiv/ramat_hanadiv/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/ramat_hanadiv/ramat_hanadiv/</guid>
      <description>Province Judaea
Iudaea (province) (Pleiades)
Province Description Judaea, the Roman province, included parts of the areas of the Hasmonean and Herodium kingdoms, notably Biblical Judah, Samaria, and Edom. Its capital was Caesarea Maritima. Roman influence in the region began in 63 CE, when the Roman general Pompey the Great took over Syria from Mithridates and, coming into Jerusalem, occupied the Second Temple. Pompey appointed Antipater, the father of Herod, as the first Roman Procurator. Later these ties allowed Herod to seek backing from Rome against the Hasmoneans in 40 BCE, when the senate recognized him as “king of the Jews.” His territories came to include the regions of Galilee, Gaulanitis (the Golan),Peraea and the Decapolis. Herod balanced his allegiance to Rome with the independence of his kingdom, often employing architectural projects to express his ambitions and control of nature to express his capacity to rule . His many palaces, placed strategically around the kingdom, feature dramatically designed landscapes and gardens. Upon his death, his heirs were unable to maintain order and Judea was annexed to Syria in 6 CE, although it was assigned its own procurator. By the time of Trajan, Judea was reduced in size and the Herodian palaces abandoned, preserving them over the millennia for archaeologists. Hadrian renamed the province Syria Palaestina after the Bar Kochba revolts (132-135) provoked him to erase the name of Judea.
The period for which we have the richest evidence of a garden culture in this region is during the reign of Herod the Great. A client king of Rome, Herod’s relationships with Mark Antony, Cleopatra, Augustus and Marcus Agrippa and other officials have been preserved in the texts of Flavius Josephus. These constitute a rare record of interactions between Rome and its territories, and provide a valuable context for understanding the trends of design in the early imperial period. The proximity of Judea to Alexandria, whose palaces and gardens lie beneath the modern city and its harbors, may also provide a suggestion of the late Hellenistic garden culture that Romans emulated. Evidence of gardens in the Hasmonean winter palaces at Jericho and the palaces of Hyracanus the Tobiad on the other side of the Jordan Valley provide rare cases where texts can illuminate archaeological evidence. These gardens require further investigation and both are threatened by local development. This geography of Judaea comprises a wide variety of biomes, from richly watered plains of the Galilee and the Jordan, to the semi arid Judean Hills, the humid, fertile coastal plain of the Mediterranean, and the deserts of the Dead Sea valley and the Negev.
Location Ramat Hanadiv
Ramat Hanadiv(Pleiades)
Garden Villae Rusticae
Keywords  villae rusticae  Garden Description Probable garden soils have been identified in a partially excavated palatial complex from the Herodian period. (Fig. 1) The fortified residential complex is a huge square covering an area of over 5,000 square meters. Towers stood in the four corners of the precinct, which thus appears to have been what was called in the Hellenistic period a tetrapyrgion- type palace. Josephus also uses the term in describing the palace at Masada (Wars 7, 289). This is the best preserved example known to date in Palestine. The palace’s inhabitants were probably members of Jewish elite during and after Herod’s reign, as the complex was abandoned during the great Revolt.
The villa shows the range of indications of Hellenistic and Roman cultural influences of Herod’s time: a columbarium, areas of cultivated soils near the building, water channels, and a heated bathhouse of the Roman style. Amended cultivated soils have also been noted in other areas of the palace building complex, which will be investigated in future seasons.
Dates 15 BCE - 60 CE
Bibliography  Y. Hirschfeld, Ramat Hanadiv Excavations, Jerusalem 2000; S.T.A.M. Mols, Wooden Furniture in Herculaneum, Amsterdam (1999):139-40. worldcat  Pleiades ID 678357
Contributor [Yitzar Hirschfeld]
Publication date 09 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Latimer</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/britannia/latimer/latimer_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/britannia/latimer/latimer_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Latimer
Latimer (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Latimer
Keywords  archaeological garden fences (site elements) flower gardens orchards rural villas vegetable gardens villae rusticae  Garden Description Excavations at this country house in Buckinghamshire have produced evidence for gardens adjacent to the main residence in its latest phase dating to the beginning of the 4th century (Fig. 1). The house at the west is of the winged corridor type, fronted by a large courtyard bisected by a paved central drive with a banked edge. Between the outer courtyard wall and the house were areas used for gardening (G in Fig. 1). Just inside the outer yard wall on the south side of the drive traces of at least six bedding trenches cut into the natural subsoil and running parallel to each other were followed for at least 5 meters (b in Fig. 1). These have been interpreted by the excavator as the remains of vegetable gardens (Fig. 2). He also attributed a number of stake holes in this area to small fences bounding the vegetable gardens, and suggested the possibility of an orchard on the northern side of the drive as well as a formal flower garden nearer to the house between the projecting wings, for which there is no concrete archaeological evidence. Finally a small pit just inside the courtyard gateway may represent a pit dug to take one of a pair of trees flanking the entrance.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the residential building (A) with excavated bedding trenches (b) in its garden courtyard (G). Adapted from Branigan 1971, fig. 20.(Rights statement)   Images   Fig. 2: Reconstruction of the house and garden. Courtesy of K. Branigan.   Dates Evidence for gardens dating to the beginning of 4th century
Bibliography  K. Branigan, Latimer. Belgic, Roman, Dark Age and Early Modern Farm, Bristol, 1971, pp. 85-86, 184, figs. 14, 20 (worldcat) R.J. Zeepvat, “Roman Gardens in Britain,” in: A.E. Brown, ed., Garden Archaeology. Council for British Archaeology Research Report 78, London, 1991, p. 56, fig. 5.3. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 79555
TGN ID 1029792
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Twin Palaces of Alexandra Salome and Late Hasmonean Gardens</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/jericho/twin_palaces_of_alexandra_salome_and_late_hasmonean_gardens/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/judaea/jericho/twin_palaces_of_alexandra_salome_and_late_hasmonean_gardens/</guid>
      <description>Province Judaea
Iudaea (province) (Pleiades)
Province Description Judaea, the Roman province, included parts of the areas of the Hasmonean and Herodium kingdoms, notably Biblical Judah, Samaria, and Edom. Its capital was Caesarea Maritima. Roman influence in the region began in 63 CE, when the Roman general Pompey the Great took over Syria from Mithridates and, coming into Jerusalem, occupied the Second Temple. Pompey appointed Antipater, the father of Herod, as the first Roman Procurator. Later these ties allowed Herod to seek backing from Rome against the Hasmoneans in 40 BCE, when the senate recognized him as “king of the Jews.” His territories came to include the regions of Galilee, Gaulanitis (the Golan),Peraea and the Decapolis. Herod balanced his allegiance to Rome with the independence of his kingdom, often employing architectural projects to express his ambitions and control of nature to express his capacity to rule . His many palaces, placed strategically around the kingdom, feature dramatically designed landscapes and gardens. Upon his death, his heirs were unable to maintain order and Judea was annexed to Syria in 6 CE, although it was assigned its own procurator. By the time of Trajan, Judea was reduced in size and the Herodian palaces abandoned, preserving them over the millennia for archaeologists. Hadrian renamed the province Syria Palaestina after the Bar Kochba revolts (132-135) provoked him to erase the name of Judea.
The period for which we have the richest evidence of a garden culture in this region is during the reign of Herod the Great. A client king of Rome, Herod’s relationships with Mark Antony, Cleopatra, Augustus and Marcus Agrippa and other officials have been preserved in the texts of Flavius Josephus. These constitute a rare record of interactions between Rome and its territories, and provide a valuable context for understanding the trends of design in the early imperial period. The proximity of Judea to Alexandria, whose palaces and gardens lie beneath the modern city and its harbors, may also provide a suggestion of the late Hellenistic garden culture that Romans emulated. Evidence of gardens in the Hasmonean winter palaces at Jericho and the palaces of Hyracanus the Tobiad on the other side of the Jordan Valley provide rare cases where texts can illuminate archaeological evidence. These gardens require further investigation and both are threatened by local development. This geography of Judaea comprises a wide variety of biomes, from richly watered plains of the Galilee and the Jordan, to the semi arid Judean Hills, the humid, fertile coastal plain of the Mediterranean, and the deserts of the Dead Sea valley and the Negev.
Location Jericho
Jericho (Pleiades)
Location Description In one of the most beautiful spots of the Eastern Mediterranean, five km west of Jericho, the biblical “city of Palms,” (Deut. 34:3) lie the remains of a royal complex of the late Second Temple Period (the end of the second century B.C. continuing through the mid-first century A.D). Despite their location in the desert some 200 m. below sea level (one of the lowest occupied elevations on earth) these palaces were set amidst an abundance of vegetation and enjoyed a copious supply of water brought from the surrounding hills via water channels. The palaces are dramatically situated along Wadi Qelt where the gorge opens abruptly onto the Jordan Valley floor. (Fig. 1) They were set amidst the large palm and balsam groves for which the valley was famed. Water channels give archaeological evidence of groves to the north of the palace, but literary evidence suggests that royal holdings from Jericho to Ein Gedi were extensive. None of the gardens have been fully excavated, but many have been examined and the presence of rich soil rather than pavement, as well as water channels and ceramic planting pots provide conclusive evidence for the many gardens discussed below.
Garden Royal Garden
Keywords  pleasure garden walled garden  Garden Description Twin Palaces of Alexandra Salome and Late Hasmonean Gardens
The trend toward formal gardens and swimming pools at the palace complex gained new expression during the reign of Janneaus’ widow, 76 to 32 B.C.E. Two identical structures built at this time, sharing a common wall, appear to have housed her rival sons, John Hyrcanus II and Aristobulus II. Each half of the twin palaces, which were located to the south of the Pool complex, was built around a paved inner courtyard. (Fig. 5) The reception room and triclinium opened onto each of the courts via distyle in antis.
Alongside each of the twin palaces was a swimming pool surrounded by a garden and fence. Small reception halls appear to have been constructed next to the pools. In the eastern garden, we also exposed a garden-triclinium that was probably open to the sky, the floor of which was once covered by water; the benches were decorated with frescoes.
Apparently at the same time, changes were made in the Pool Complex, indicating a greater sensitivity to the garden areas. A wall separating the swimming pools from the peristyle garden to the north was demolished and replace by a row of columns. West of the pools, a large hall (11 x 6.5m) probably served for receptions.
After Alexandra’s death, during the period from 67-32, a large swimming pool (20 x 12.5) was added to the east of the twin palaces. At the same time, installations for bathing and ritual immersion were built over the small garden west of the Pool complex. Three long, narrow storerooms, probably for the storage of produce from the larger royal estate, were erected in the corresponding small garden to the east of the pools. (Fig. 6)
Plans   Figure 1: Plan of the Hasmonean and Herodian Winter Palace Complex, Jericho (Gleason after Netzer)     Figure 2: The plantations and Hasmonean palace buildings, Area AA represent the location of the the buried Palace.(K. Wilczak and K. Gleason, after Netzer 2001a: Plan 4; Netzer and Laureys-Chachy 2004: Plan 2)      Figure 5:Plan of the later Hasmonean palaces and their gardens. Light gray shading indicates gardens, dark gray shading indicates pools (Gleason after Netzer 2001a: Plan 8)   Images   Figure 6: Axonometric reconstruction of the Hasmonean palace prior to the earthquake of 32 BCE. (Netzer 1999).   Dates 76 BCE - 32 BCE
Bibliography  G. Garbrecht, and E. Netzer, “Die Wasserversorgung des geschichtlichen Jericho und seiner koniglichen Anlagen,” in Mitteilungen (aus dem Leichtweiss-Institut fur Wasserbau) 115, Braunschweig/Jerusalem 1991 worldcat K. Gleason, “Garden Excavations at the Herodian Winter Palace in Jericho, 1985-1987&amp;quot;, Bulletin of the Anglo-Israel Archaeological Society, Vol. 7, 1987-8 Jstor K. Gleason, “A Garden Excavation in the Oasis Palace of Herod the Great at Jericho,” Landscape Journal 12.2 (1993):156-67wordcat J. Kelso, James L. and Dimitri Baramki, “Excavations at New Testament Jericho and Kirbet en-Nitla,” Annual of the American Schools of Oriental Research 29-30 (1949-51): 38-39 E. Netzer, The Palaces of the Hasmoneans and Herod the Great, Jerusalem: The Israel Exploration Society, 1999: 13-64 wordcat Nielsen, Inge, Hellenistic Palaces,1994, 195-201 wordcat E. Netzer, The Hasmonean and Herodian Palaces at Jericho: Final Reports of the 1973-1987 Excavations, Vol. 1, Jerusalem: Israel Exploration Society, 2001 : 287-298 worldcat E. Netzer, and Garbrecht G, “Water channels and a royal estate of the late Hellenistic period in Jericho’s eastern plains,” in D. Amit, J. Patrich and Y.; Hirschfeld, eds, The Aqueducts of Israel. 353-365. JRA Supplement 46, R.I. 2002 worldcat J. Pritchard, “The Excavation at Herodian Jericho, 1951,&amp;quot; The Annual of the American Schools of Oriental Research 32-3 (1952-4): 56-58. [worldcat] (https://www.worldcat.org/title/excavation-at-herodian-jericho-1951-for-1952-1954/oclc/256829094&amp;amp;referer=brief_results)  Pleiades ID 687917
TGN ID ?????
Contributor Kathryn L. Gleason (ORCID: 0000-0001-6260-8378
Publication date 09 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Frocester Court</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/britannia/frocester-court/frocester_court_rural_vila/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jul 2020 08:32:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/britannia/frocester-court/frocester_court_rural_vila/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Frocester Court
Frocester Court (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Frocester Court
Keywords  archaeological garden ditches fences (site elements) kitchen gardens orchards paddock rural villas villae rusticae  Garden Description This Roman villa in Gloucestershire is situated about 14 miles west of the civitas capital Corinium Dobunnorum (Cirencester). The main residence is of the winged corridor type, fronted by a large courtyard which was bounded by the house on one side, by a wall on the two sides perpendicular to the house and by a fence on the fourth side opposite the house (Fig. 1). The yard measured 56 x 53 meters.
Excavated evidence indicates that this courtyard was designed as a formal garden in the early 4th century. The courtyard was bisected by a central drive 5 meters wide consisting of rubble with a layer of heavy metalling on top and bounded by kerb stones (P in Fig. 1). It led from the courtyard gate at the southeast and continued to the front of the house. The garden consisted of two planting beds near the house, a hedge and two long beds on either side of the drive (dark grey in Fig. 1) (Fig. 2). These beds had been dug into the stone and gravel and then filled with 20 centimeters of very dark soil. It is not known what plants grew here, although carbonized remains of box plants at the villa may reflect one type of greenery planted in the courtyard. The northeast part of the yard was paved with stone and gravel (dotted in Fig. 1), the southwest part, however, was not paved, suggesting that this part of the garden might have been used as an orchard or an area for trees or shrubs (O in Fig. 1). The formal garden was destroyed by 5th century cultivation. Northwest of the house, i.e. at the back, various ditches marked off a number of areas interpreted as possible paddocks and an area covered with a layer of very dark soil which has been interpreted as a kitchen garden.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the villa with its central path (P), planting beds for flowers and hedges (dark grey rectangles), a possible orchard (O) and a gravelled yard (dotted). Adapted from Zeepvat 1991, fig. 5.2. (Rights statement)   Images   Fig. 2: Reconstruction of the villa and its garden at Frocester Court. The closest wall should be a fence. Drawing courtesy of E. Price.   Dates Early 4th century - 5th century
Bibliography  R.J. Zeepvat, “Roman Gardens in Britain,” in: A.E. Brown, ed., Garden Archaeology. Council for British Archaaeology Research Report 78, London, 1991, pp. 53-56, fig. 5.2. (worldcat) E. Price, Frocester. A Romano-British Settlement, its Antecedents and Successors, Gloucester, 2000. [(worldcat)](A Romano-British Settlement, its Antecedents and Successors)  Pleiades ID 79471
TGN ID 4004114
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 10 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
