<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>orchards on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/orchards/</link>
    <description>Recent content in orchards on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 10:33:04 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/orchards/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Anonymous Gaul in Andematunnum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/andematunnum/andematunnum_tomb_garden_of_anonymous_gaul/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 10:33:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/andematunnum/andematunnum_tomb_garden_of_anonymous_gaul/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Province Description Location Andematunnum
Andematunnum (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Tomb Garden of Anonymous Gaul in Andematunnum
Keywords former reservoirs
inscription
literary garden
mausoleums
orchards
tombs
Garden Description A famous inscription from the territory of the Lingonian Gauls (Langres) known only from a manuscript of the tenth century records the will of a local hunting enthusiast who built for himself a lavish mausoleum (cella memoriae) and equipped it with orchards (pomaria) and a reservoir (lacus) put in the care of two freedmen who are instructed to devote the revenues from them to upkeep of the tomb complex, and three landscape gardeners (topiarii) and their apprentices, each to be supported annually by the testator’s grandson, Sex. Iulius Aquila, and his heirs. The will goes on to provide for annual banquets at the tomb site, to be funded by Aquila and his heirs (not explicitly from proceeds of the orchards), and to ensure that any deviations from the testator’s prescriptions be undertaken only in order that the complex be better adorned, better planted, and better perfected (nisi..ut melius colantur et conserantur perficianturque).
Maps Plans Images Dates unspecified
Bibliography  CIL 13.5708. EDCS-19800561 ILS 8379. FIRA III 49. J.-J. Hatt, La tombe gallo-romaine (Paris 1951) 65-84. (worldcat)  Periodo ID Pleiades ID 177441
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor John Bodel(ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 13 July 2020
Related articles </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Latimer</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/latimer/latimer_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/latimer/latimer_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Latimer
Latimer (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Latimer
Keywords archaeological garden
barrier walls
fences (site elements)
flower gardens
orchards
rural villas
vegetable gardens
villae rusticae
Garden Description Excavations at this country house in Buckinghamshire have produced evidence for gardens adjacent to the main residence in its latest phase dating to the beginning of the 4th century (Fig. 1). The house at the west is of the winged corridor type, fronted by a large courtyard bisected by a paved central drive with a banked edge. Between the outer courtyard wall and the house were areas used for gardening (G in Fig. 1). Just inside the outer yard wall on the south side of the drive traces of at least six bedding trenches cut into the natural subsoil and running parallel to each other were followed for at least 5 meters (b in Fig. 1). These have been interpreted by the excavator as the remains of vegetable gardens (Fig. 2). He also attributed a number of stake holes in this area to small fences bounding the vegetable gardens, and suggested the possibility of an orchard on the northern side of the drive as well as a formal flower garden nearer to the house between the projecting wings, for which there is no concrete archaeological evidence. Finally a small pit just inside the courtyard gateway may represent a pit dug to take one of a pair of trees flanking the entrance.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the residential building (A) with excavated bedding trenches (b) in its garden courtyard (G). Adapted from Branigan 1971, fig. 20.(Rights statement)   Images   Fig. 2: Reconstruction of the house and garden. Courtesy of K. Branigan.   Dates Evidence for gardens dating to the beginning of 4th century
Bibliography  K. Branigan, Latimer. Belgic, Roman, Dark Age and Early Modern Farm, Bristol, 1971, pp. 85-86, 184, figs. 14, 20 (worldcat) R.J. Zeepvat, “Roman Gardens in Britain,” in: A.E. Brown, ed., Garden Archaeology. Council for British Archaeology Research Report 78, London, 1991, p. 56, fig. 5.3. (worldcat)  Periodo ID Pleiades ID 79555
TGN ID 1029792
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 11 July 2020
Related articles </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>