<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/montreal/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:07:01 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/montreal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa de Séviac, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/montreal/gallia-aquitania_villa-de-se%CC%81viac_j.zhou/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:07:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/montreal/gallia-aquitania_villa-de-se%CC%81viac_j.zhou/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_Aquitania Gallia_Aquitania (Pleiades)
Province Description A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location Montréal, Gers
Montréal, Gers (Pleiades)
House Villa de Séviac
House Description Two kilometers southwest of the village, the villa sits on plateau overlooking the left bank of the Auzoue to the east and descending in a gentle slope to the brook Argentans to the north. An ancient road five meters wide runs along the east side. Known since 1867, the villa was partially excavated in 1911, then reopened and minutely studied since 1958.
Garden Keywords  fountains gutters (building drainage components) reception rooms piscinae mosaics (visual works)  Garden Description The dwelling goes back to the early empire and knew a period of splendor in late antiquity. In a unified construction program there was built, beginning in the fourth century, a grand villa with a main structure around a vast peristyle, with exterior façade galleries and baths adjacent to a second courtyard to the south. In the baths, however, numerous, complex modifications followed between the second and fifth centuries.
The main entrance was from the east, where the road was. An open passage way led into the peristyle (40 x 41 m). It had a central open area of 35 meters on a side. Its internal organization is not known. All or part of it may have been a garden, but there were also important layers of gravel (Monturet-Rivière, 1986, p. 15). It was bordered by a gutter lined with tegulae to catch the drip from the roofs. Straight ahead of the entrance but on the far side of the courtyard there was a narrow pool made of brick, possibly with a fountain. It had a polygonal apse on its east side. The pool was connected to the gutters. Beyond this pool, further to the west, across the west gallery and approximately in line with the entrance way and the pool, was a large room [S2], presumably a reception area.
To the south, as mentioned, were sumptuous baths with pavements in opus tesselatum depicting fruit trees. On the outside of the walls of the baths, painting simulated a garden fence with crisscross palings. (R. Monturet- H. Rivière 1987, p. 184, fig. 8, Demeures fig. 81, p. 205).
To the northeast, paleochristian places of worship were installed in the fifth and sixth centuries, apparently originally in one room of the villa.
The glory of Séviac is in its mosaics. Many, in excellent condition, are in their original places. The themes are geometric and vegetal; there is no mythological picture. This absence has suggested to several observers that the builder may have been Christian or, at least, did not wish to give offense to Christians. Moreover, the grape vine, an important Christian image, is prominent.
Figure 3 shows a “fruit pyramid” from room S25. On the support of a laurel bush growing in a giant seashell there is a green grape leaf with yellow veins and bunches of yellow grapes on either side. Higher up are two fruits, possibly a pear on the right and a citron on the left. From the top, two stylized acanthus leaves fall over the sides.
In the fruit tree mosaic in Figure 4, it is not clear what tree is depicted. The fruit look very like figs – also a Christian image &amp;ndash; but the leaves do not look at all like figs. Pears are another possibility. In fact, the artist may have been interested only in conveying abundance or a hoped-for paradise hereafter. Note the fleur-de-lys in the lower right corner.
Plans   Fig. 1: Topographic Plan of the Villa de Séviac, drawing by M. -P. R., based on the the 1/25000e map of the IGN.   Dates 1867CE
Excavation Dates 1911CE
Bibliography  Monturet, H. Rivière, J.P. Bost, P. Aragon-Launey, Les thermes sud de la villa gallo-romaine de Séviac, 10e suppl. Aquitania, 1986. (worldcat) J. Lapart, C. Petit, Le Gers, CAG, 32, 1993, p. 266-283. (worldcat) E. Morvillez, Forme et évolution des salles de réception des grandes demeures tardives du bassin Méditerranéen occidental, 1993, t. 1, 186-202.(worldcat) Catherine Balmelle, Les demeures aristocratiques d&amp;rsquo;Aquitaine, societe et culture de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquite tardive dans le sou-ouest de la Gaule, Ausonius, supple. d&amp;rsquo;Aquitania 10, Bordeaux 2001, p. 106-111, 386-88, 446 (with preceding bibliography). (worldcat) Jean Gugole with photographs by Jean-Bernard Laffitte, Mosaïques de Séviac, Serres Castet, Editions de Faucompret, 1996. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 246629
TGN ID Contributor Clopper Almon
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>