<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>statuettes on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/statuettes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in statuettes on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/statuettes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Peristyle garden in house of Julia Felix (II.iv.a).</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/region_ii_2/insula_iv/house/ii.iv.a/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/region_ii_2/insula_iv/house/ii.iv.a/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region II
House House of Julia Felix
Garden Peristyle garden in house of Julia Felix
Keywords  jet d&amp;rsquo;eau peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes statuettes (free-standing sculpture) triclinia  Garden Description A. Three separate gardens were located in this property. It occupies the entire insula and is one of the largest properties in the city. It was originally excavated in 1755-1757, stripped of its works of art and re-buried. In 1951-1952 it was re-excavated and restored but not published. Sixteen elegantly carved slender marble pillars support a portico which borders the peristyle garden (a) on the west.Fig.18, 5.29.59, Fig. 19, 5.32.50, Fig. 20, 5.25.59 An alcove (b) housed a summer triclinium (l. medius, 4.00 m.; l. imus and summus 3.00 m.) with marble faced couches that looked through the portico into the garden. Between the couches a niche supplied water that ran down small marble steps to a hole at the bottom. The water re-surfaced as a jet in the middle of the trilinium. A vine covered arbor stretched along the south and east side of the garden and beyond it in bays on the east wall were raised planting beds, alternating semicircular and square. These were covered with pumice and decorated with a band of Egyptian blue around the sides and top, the middle bay having four bands of Egyptian blue. The room (c) to the south of the triclinium had a garden representation (0.185 x 0.42 m.) on the north part of the west wall on the red middle zone. Four fish ponds connected to form a long channel down the center of the garden. The little marble bridges that crossed the channel and covered alcoves at the bottom of the pools provided shelter for the fish and eels. A number of statuettes were found during the two excavations of this site. More recently the pieces that were found are as follows: A marble satyr (0.475 m. preserved height; Pompeii inv. no. 8856) located at the north end of the pool, a seated terra-cotta figure of Pittacus of Mitylene (0.65 m. high; Pompeii inv. no. 2181-4) found at the edge of the pool, a small marble fountain statuette of a sea crab in a shell (0.19 m. wide; Pompeii inv. no. 1073/54). During the earlier excavation some of the items found were as follows: a satyr child (0.46 m. high; Muz. Naz. inv. no. 6108), a nude youth holding grapes in his right hand and a goose in his left (0.76 m. high; Muz. Naz. inv. no. 6342), a faun(Muz. Naz. inv. no. 6343), an old man covered with a cloth (0.49 m. high), a bird with a lizard in its beak (0.32 m. high), a marble mask of a smiling youth on a small column (0.54 m. high), and a marble relief (0.36m. long x 0.11 m. high) of an old man seated of a bench, perhaps this was a pinax. The heads of twelve marble herms, (one woman, one old man, three bearded men) were reported by PAH, but the post of only one is mentioned and only the feet of the thirteenth herm was found. A terra-cotta group of Caritas Romana was found in many pieces as well as multiple fragments of other terra-cotta statuettes which had been in the eleven niches in the peristyle portico. Chambalu believed the herms stood between these niches.
Plans   view form the portico     detail of the jet.     portico and garden   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography   Annali Dell&amp;rsquo;instituto Di Correspondenza Archeologica, 1830, p.50 worldcat
  Bonucci, Carlo.Pompei Descritta Da Carlo Bonucc, p.219 worldcat
  Bragantini, Irene. Pitture E Pavimenti Di Pompei. Roma: Ministero per i beni culturali e ambientali, Istituto centrale per il catalogo e la documentazione, 1981. Print.1:238 worldcat
  Chambalu,Die weiderverschüttete Besitzung der Julia Felix beim Amphitheater in Pompeji, Pp, 1895. Print. pp. 14-15 and plan of Weber (1757) after p. 20 worldcat
  Della Corte, Notizie degli scavi antichita (1958), p. 125, no. 238 (Pittakos inscription);worldcat
  Dwyer, Eugene J. Pompeian Oscilla Collections: (pls. 80-130) Mainz: Verlag Philipp von Zabern, 1981. Print. p. 279, no. 81worldcat
  F. Rakob, *Ein Grottentriklinium in Pompeji,*RM (1964), pp. 182-194;worldcat
  H. Döhl, Plastik aus Pompeji , tesi di libera d tingen 1976, pp. 8-10
  Idem, Pompeii (Novara), p. 111 worldcat
  Idem, Pomp. Sculpture, pp. 67, 128, and figs. 197, 212;
  Jashemski, Wilhelmina F, The Gardens of Pompeii, Herculaneum, and the Villas Destroyed by Vesuvius, New Rochelle: Aristide D. Caratzas, 1979. Print , 1:48, 110 and figs. 81 on p. 47, 82 on p. 48, 83 (marble statue at north end of pool), 84 (Pittacus), and 85 (sea-crab in shell) on p. 49; worldcat
  Jashemski, Wilhelmina F, and Stanley A. Jashemski, The Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the Villas Destroyed by Vesuvius. New Rochelle, NY: Caratzas, 1993. Print. pp. 86-88, 396worldcat
  Kapossy, Balázs. Brunnenfiguren Der Hellenistischen Und Römischen Zeit. Zürich, 1969. Print. pp 46, 50 worldcat
  Lorenz, Thuri. Galerien Von Griechischen Philosophen Und Dichterbildnissen Bei Den Römern. Mainz: Verlag Ph. von Zabern, 1965. Print. p. 39worldcat
  Maiuri, I giardini, Le Vie d’Italia, no.9 Sept 1961, p. 1139; worldcat
  Maiuri, Statuette fittilli di Pittaco di Mitilene, Archeologia Classica 4 (1952): 55-59; worldcat
  Maiuri, Pompei ed Ercolano:Fra case ed abitanti, pp. 74-75; worldcat
  Pompeianarum Antiquitatum Historia, vol. 1 pt. 1, pp. 13, 15, 16, 18, 19, 21, 28, 29, 30, 31, 34, 37, 39 (Apr. 13, 1755-Mar. 6, 1756);Ibid., vol. 1 pt. 2, pp. 98, 101; worlcat
  Richter, Greek Portraits, 3:34 and fig. 134; worlcat
  Richter, Portraits of the Greeks, 1:89a; worlcat
  Rohden, Hermann. Die Terracotten Von Pompeji. Stuttgart, 1880. Print. pp. 24, 47-48, 53, 57, 62 and plates 35.3, 36, 41.4, 47; worldcat
  Salsa Prina Ricotti, The Importance of Water in Roman Open Air Tricliniums, in Ancient Roman Villa Gardens, Dumbarton Oaks Colloquium on the History of Landscape Architecture, no. 10, Dumbarton Oaks, 1987, pp. 172-173; worlcat
  Sear, Frank B. Roman Wall and Vault Mosaics. Heidelberg: F.H. Kerle, 1977. Print. p.94 worlcat
  Zahn, Wilhelm.Die Schönsten Ornamente Und Merkwürdigsten Gemälde Aus Pompeji, Herkulanum Und Stabiae vol2.pl.100 (plan)worldcat
  Pleiades ID 955554415
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 2 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Small Garden House 4-6 in Pompeii Region II (II.iii.4-6). </title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/region_ii_2/insula_iii/house4_6/ii.iii.4-6a/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/region_ii_2/insula_iii/house4_6/ii.iii.4-6a/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region II
House House 4-6 in Pompeii Region II
Garden Small Garden House 4-6 in Pompeii Region II
Keywords  statuettes (free-standing sculpture) tufa villa  Garden Description A. A small garden (a) at the rear of this connected house and caupona may have originally contained the two small statuettes found at this site in 1953. The two pieces were a headless ithyphallic tufa statuette (0.33 m. high with base; Pompeii inv. no. 10017) and a marble statuette of Venus (0.51 m. high without base; Pompeii inv. no. 9926) with much of the red color preserved in the drapery. The Inventory Books list this house as II.vi.4.
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Jashemski, Wilhelmina F, and Stanley A. Jashemski, The Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the Villas Destroyed by Vesuvius. New Rochelle, NY: Caratzas, 1993. Print. pp. 84 worldcat  Pleiades ID 998787235
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 2 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
