<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>statuettes on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/statuettes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in statuettes on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 17:22:47 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/statuettes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>I.iii.25 A</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_25/i.iii.25_a/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 17:22:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iii/house_25/i.iii.25_a/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula III
House House 25
Garden I.iii.25 A
Keywords  archaeological garden peristyles (columnades) porticoes statues statuettes (free-standing sculpture) triclinia  Garden Description This house had an irregular plan and a small peristyle garden (a) enclosed on three sides by a low masonry wall. The wall was topped by four stuccoed brick columns which supported the portico. The excavation in 1869-72 showed that restoration was in progress at the time of the eruption. Inside the triclinium a small marble head of Bacchus from a herm (Mus. Naz. inv. no. 110 653) was found as well as a small marble ram (Mus. Naz. inv. no. 120 357), both probably garden decorations.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 6, p. 26; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1869-1872
Bibliography  Dohl, p. 1. Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 74. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., p. 57.(worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 2 (1870-1873), col. 461. Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 28. (worldcat) Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 78. Trendelenberg, BdI(1871), p. 172.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 29 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.ii.17 B</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_17/i.ii.17_b/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2020 15:01:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_17/i.ii.17_b/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 17
Garden I.ii.17 B
Keywords  archaeological garden atriums mural paintings (visual works) peristyles (columnades) pillars porticoes statues statuettes (free-standing sculpture) tablina  Garden Description The peristyle garden to the east of the atrium was excavated in 1873. It had a portico on the north and west supported by two pillars, one at the northwest corner and the other in the middle of the north side. A gutter sloped towards the southeast corner as it went around the east, north, and west edges of the garden. A shrine-like structure was built against the east wall with the marble veneered façade above the level of the floor of the niche. The niche contained a marble statuette of Venus, her left arm supported by a statuette (1.04 m. high; Mus Naz. inv. no. 109 608; Ruesch no. 1325). The wall behind the statue was painted to represent blue drapery and the ceiling had a shell-like fluting. Two small marble statuettes of toads (Mus. Nac. inv. no. 109 609, 109 610) found in the garden and probably the one of two doves (Mus. Naz. inv. no. 120 407) found in the tablinum decorated the flowerbeds. There was also a marble head of a man identified as Agrippa, found cemented in a cup (total height 0.285 m.; Mus. Nac. inv. no. 109 611; Reusch no. 1081). The marble statuette of Hercules wrapped in a lion skin (0.70 m. high; Mus. Nac. inv. no. 109 677) found in the atrium was probably a garden decoration. The large room on the north had a fine view of the garden and the east and south walls of the garden were decorated with garden paintings. These were separated by narrow panels with a painting of a candelabrum, according to Mau, and each painting featured a fence with an amphora upon it. Behind this there was a thicket with birds. On either side of the amphora there was an ibis, and a pheasant in the center. Fiorelli mentioned observing animals in the paintings. Jashemski notes that no trace of the paintings remained when she examined the site, and further, she has never seen a pheasant represented in any garden paintings. Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation dates 1873
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 22, no. 10. de Franciscis, Ritratto, p. 25 and figs. 10-11. (worldcat) Döhl, p.1. Dwyer, Pomp. Sculpture, pp. 124, 12. (worldcat) Fiorelli, Descr., p. 44. (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), cols. 46-47, 48, 55. Grimal, p. 445, no. 1.  Jashemski, Gardens, 1::124-125. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, pp. 23-24. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 313. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 233-235. Ibid. (1874), pp. 265-266. Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 265-266.  Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 76. Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “L’arte,” p. 6 and pl. 14 (Venus). Schefold, WandP, p. 10. (worldcat)  Sogliano, “Pitture,” p. 223, no. 691. (worldcat)  Sogliano, “Scavi,” p. 310. (worldcat) Viola, “Scavi” pp. 12 and 76, no. 1, p.77, nos. 5, 12, p.79, nos. 45, 46. (worldcat) Warscher, “Codex,” photo no. 32.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.ii.16</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_16/i.ii.16/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2020 14:27:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_16/i.ii.16/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 16
Garden I.ii.16
Keywords  aedicula lararium archaeological garden fountains pillars podiums (building divisions) porticoes puteal statues statuettes (free-standing sculpture)  Garden Description This house was excavated in 1873. The entranceway led directly to the portico which enclosed the garden on the north and east. In the northwest corner of the portico a masonry aedicula lararium formed an arched niche on top of a solid podium. A low wall connected the columns and pillars of the portico. There was an entrance to the garden on the east side and a gutter along the east and north edges of the garden. A terra-cotta statuette of a seated old man holding a scroll in his right hand and wearing a short sleeved tunic (0.60 m. high; Mus. Naz. Inv. No. 109 622; Ruesh no. 453) served as a fountain. This statue has been variously identified, but most likely was the Greek philosopher Antisthenes (ca. 445-360), a devoted follower of Socrates. A terra-cotta puteal was also found in the garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation dates 1873
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 22, no. 6. Curtius, &amp;ldquo;Miszellen zur Geschichte des greichischen Porträts,” RM (1944), p. 38. Dohl, p. 1. Dwyer, Pomp. Sculpture, p. 128. (worldcat) Fiorelli, Descr., p. 42. (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), col. 46, 177-179 and pl. 6. Ippel, AA (1939), pp 367-368. Jashemski, Gardens, 1:48. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 22-23. (worldcat) Kapossy, p. 47. Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “L’arte,” pl. 12. Pernice p. 34. Richter, Greek Portraits 3, pp. 33-34, fig. 133. (worldcat) Idem, Portraits of the Greeks, 2:181 and fig. no. 105. (worldcat) Viola, “Scavi” p. 12 and p. 79, no. 1. (worldcat) Von Rohden, pp. 21, 44-45 and pl. 32. Warscher, “Codex.”  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 25 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>