<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>mausoleums on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/mausoleums/</link>
    <description>Recent content in mausoleums on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 10:33:04 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/mausoleums/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Anonymous Gaul in Andematunnum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/andematunnum/andematunnum_tomb_garden_of_anonymous_gaul/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 10:33:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/andematunnum/andematunnum_tomb_garden_of_anonymous_gaul/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Andematunnum
Andematunnum (Pleiades)
Garden Tomb Garden of Anonymous Gaul in Andematunnum
Keywords  former reservoirs inscription literary garden mausoleums orchards tombs  Garden Description A famous inscription from the territory of the Lingonian Gauls (Langres) known only from a manuscript of the tenth century records the will of a local hunting enthusiast who built for himself a lavish mausoleum (cella memoriae) and equipped it with orchards (pomaria) and a reservoir (lacus) put in the care of two freedmen who are instructed to devote the revenues from them to upkeep of the tomb complex, and three landscape gardeners (topiarii) and their apprentices, each to be supported annually by the testator’s grandson, Sex. Iulius Aquila, and his heirs. The will goes on to provide for annual banquets at the tomb site, to be funded by Aquila and his heirs (not explicitly from proceeds of the orchards), and to ensure that any deviations from the testator’s prescriptions be undertaken only in order that the complex be better adorned, better planted, and better perfected (nisi..ut melius colantur et conserantur perficianturque).
Maps Images Dates unspecified
Bibliography  CIL 13.5708. EDCS-19800561 ILS 8379. FIRA III 49. J.-J. Hatt, La tombe gallo-romaine (Paris 1951) 65-84. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 177441
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 13 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
