<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>mosaic on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/mosaic/</link>
    <description>Recent content in mosaic on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2020 11:20:32 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/mosaic/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa Saint-Michel</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/beneharnum_lescar_pyr%C3%A9n%C3%A9es-atlantiques/beneharnum-lescar-pyre%CC%81ne%CC%81es-atlantiques_villa-saint-michel_y.sun/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/beneharnum_lescar_pyr%C3%A9n%C3%A9es-atlantiques/beneharnum-lescar-pyre%CC%81ne%CC%81es-atlantiques_villa-saint-michel_y.sun/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_Aquitania Gallia_Aquitania (Pleiades)
Province Description Ancient Roman colony (founded 118 BCE) and senatorial province located in modern southern France, along the Mediterranean. This province had stronger cultural and political ties to Italy than the rest of Gaul.
Location BENEHARNUM Lescar
Bene(h)arnum (Pleiades)
Location Description Today, Lescar is a small suburb of Pau, about ten kilometers to the northwest. In Roman times, however, it was the site of Beneharnum, a major city of Aquitania that gave its name to the Bearn region. Its center was at the edge of the high bluff rising above the valley of the Gave de Pau, a site now marked by the Romanesque church of Saint Julien. There are numerous Roman remains in the area, and the Office de Tourisme has organized a 5.5 kilometer, self-guided loop tour of them, including the site of the Villa Saint-Michel, about 200 meters south of Avenue Carrérot, on the east side of the chemin de Ferré. The site, however, is privately owned. Part of the villa was destroyed in building the owner&amp;rsquo;s house; the rest has been reburied and is under a lawn. A beautiful geometric mosaic and some artifacts, including a scythe blade, may be seen at the museum, which is in front of the west façade of Saint Julien..
Garden Villa Saint-Michel
Keywords  galleries (upper level spaces) mosaic  Garden Description From a high terrace about a kilometer east of the ancient Beneharnum, the residents of this suburban villa covering some 2000 square meters could look out over the valley of the Gave de Pau and on to the majestic, sharply outlined peaks of the Pyrenees on the horizon. Discovered in 1886, it was excavated by M. Bats and J. Seigne in 1968-70. The first phase of the construction was probably around the middle of the first century and included a courtyard.
A remodeling occurred around 100 – 150. The main entrance was from the north by a semicircular peristyle with 12 columns and a diameter of 18 meters. The carpet mosaic of the gallery depicted this colonnade projected upon the floor and with a garland of foliage suspended between each support.
The center of the villa was organized around a rectangular peristyle (33 x 26 m). Both the galleries and the central part were covered with mosaics, but in the southeast corner a floor of pebbles surrounded a masonry mass interpreted by Bats and Seigne as possibly a structure to hold planters. A gallery 45 meters long ran along the south façade of the villa and offered a splendid panorama over the valley of the Gave de Pau and on to the Pyrenees beyond.
Plans   Fig. 1: Villa Saint-Michel.    Dates Discovered in 1886, it was excavated by M. Bats and J. Seigne in 1968-70.
Bibliography  M. Bats and J. Seigne. La villa gallo-romaine de Saint-Michel à Lescar (Beneharnum), Bull. de la Société des Sciences, Lettres et Arts de Pau (Pau), 7, 1972, p. 19-66 ; G. Fabre, CAG, 64, 1994, n°203 ; Demeures, p. 363-365, plans p. 100.  Pleiades ID 981505 246237
TGN ID 300004031 300240727
Contributor Clopper Almon
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Combination of the House of the Opus Sectile with the House of the Opus Quadratum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_combination-of-the-house-of-the-opus-sectile-with-the-house-of-the-opus-quadratum_y.sun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_combination-of-the-house-of-the-opus-sectile-with-the-house-of-the-opus-quadratum_y.sun/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania (Pleiades)
Location AUGUSTORITUM - Limoges
Augustoritum (Pleiades)
Location Description The earliest traces of settlement in this area are at the oppidum of Villejoubert 25 kilometers east of the city. The Roman settlement of Limoges proper dates from about 15-10 B.C. and was named Augustoritum (Augustus’s ford) in honor of the emperor. It covered some 65 to 100 hectares and was laid out in a regular rectangular grid. The ancient wall dates from the end of the third century. The town took water from several sources, including the aqueduct of Aigoulène; there were drains for waste water disposal. There were several public fountains and baths, a theater, an arena, and temples. The city declined in the fourth century. Its Roman name was replaced by the Celtic name of the local people; and its regular street pattern, almost totally lost.
Garden Combination of the House of the Opus Sectile with the House of the Opus Quadratum
Keywords  pool mosaic  Garden Description In the first half of the second century, the combination of these two beautiful houses made for truly sumptuous quarters. The residence, opening off of a vast vestibule with a central pool, covered an area of 5500 square meters, the whole of the insula. In the first phase of the work, heating was installed in the two reception rooms. Enjoyment of the east garden [1] of around 500 square meters was enhanced by a double-asped, 1.2-meter-deep pool in its center. It disappeared in a fire between the third and fourth century. In a second phase of embellishment, not prior to the years 226-235, the luxury of the décor was heightened. The reception room [2] was paved with a rich carpet of geometric opus sectile framed by a border of white marble, while new marble plates suppressed the old. To room [3] was added a large apse to the north, also furnished with a luxurious pavement of opus sectile and ornamented with a mosaic on either a wall or perhaps a semidome. The semicircle of this apse was constructed at the expense of a service courtyard. This courtyard [4] was bordered on the east by a portico which sheltered under its roof a well with a monolithic puteal. All of this magnificence was destroyed by fire in the late third or early fourth century.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the Combination of House of the Opus Sectile with House of the Opus Quadratum.    Dates First Phase：first half of the second century
Second Phase：226-235 CE
Bibliography  J.P. Loustaud. Limoges antique, Travaux d’Archéologie Limousine, supplément 5, 2000, p. 198-202, plan p. 198. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 138203
TGN ID 7030318 7008410
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Five Mosaics</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-of-the-five-mosaics_y.sun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-of-the-five-mosaics_y.sun/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania (Pleiades)
Location AUGUSTORITUM - Limoges
Augustoritum (Pleiades)
Location Description The earliest traces of settlement in this area are at the oppidum of Villejoubert 25 kilometers east of the city. The Roman settlement of Limoges proper dates from about 15-10 B.C. and was named Augustoritum (Augustus’s ford) in honor of the emperor. It covered some 65 to 100 hectares and was laid out in a regular rectangular grid. The ancient wall dates from the end of the third century. The town took water from several sources, including the aqueduct of Aigoulène; there were drains for waste water disposal. There were several public fountains and baths, a theater, an arena, and temples. The city declined in the fourth century. Its Roman name was replaced by the Celtic name of the local people; and its regular street pattern, almost totally lost.
Garden House of the Five Mosaics
Keywords  mosaic  Garden Description Situated west of the forum, part of insula VI-5, this house had two successive stages. The first is called House of the Lion Emblema; the second, House with the OpusQuadratum. Each occupied about 2300 square meters.
The House of the Lion Emblema was organized around a central garden with peristyle [1] of 20 by 23 meters. The floor of the porticos is white concrete with calcite aggregates. The columns supporting the roof of the portico rest on a low wall covered by a coating painted red. To the north, in the axis of the garden, was the triclinium [2] (12.6 x 7.8 m) where were found two black-and-white carpet mosaics, with the emblema of the lion in the more northern one. South of the garden, it is worth noting, there was a bath. For no apparent reason, this beautiful house was destroyed and another, the House of the Opus Quadratum, was superimposed on the previous foundations, keeping practically the same plan. The garden with portico [1] of 440 square meters had in the northern part a foundation for a pool or perhaps for monumental stairs connecting the portico to the garden. The limestone columns were apparently Corinthean. The northern portico had a floor of opus signinum; the floors of the other galleries were bare. To the north, the reception room [3] was reduced in length to 9.8 by 7.8 meters, but flanked by symmetric rooms with larger mosaics than those of the preceeding phase. This room, lying in the axis of the possible pool or steps, was embellished by a luxurious paving with an opus quadratum motif made of marble rectangles. South of the garden, an important room [4] (12 meters on a side) serves as a vestibule for the main room and marks the end of this house, which was later connected to its neighbor In the center of the room was a pool with a rim and paving of white marble and a water jet in the center.
Bibliography  J.P. Loustaud. Limoges antique, Travaux d’Archéologie Limousine, supplément 5, 2000, p. 191-196, plans p. 191 and p. 194 (with bibliography of earlier works). (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 138203
TGN ID 7030318 7008410
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>