<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>COLONIA AUGUSTA TREVERORUM on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/categories/colonia-augusta-treverorum/</link>
    <description>Recent content in COLONIA AUGUSTA TREVERORUM on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/categories/colonia-augusta-treverorum/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Urban House East of Forum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/urban-house-east-of-forum/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/urban-house-east-of-forum/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location COLONIA AUGUSTA TREVERORUM (Trier, Germany)
COLONIA AUGUSTA TREVERORUM (Pleiades)
Garden Urban House East of Forum
Keywords  insulae atriums peristyles  Garden Description In only one of the excavated houses of the second and third century in two insulae east of the forum beneath the imperial baths can gardens be shown to have existed. This house was demolished when the imperial baths were erected in the last decade of the third century. It seems to have occupied an entire insula measuring 55 x 100 meters. (Fig. 1). An atrium (A on plan) was built in the west wing of the building in the first half of the second century. The atrium was later transformed into a garden with planting beds and a pool. Around the middle of the third century this garden was abandoned. The house also boasted a large peristyle courtyard on the east which may have been planted (G on plan), but for a garden there is no direct archaeological evidence.
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  W. Reusch, &amp;ldquo;Wandmalereien und Mosaikboden eines Peristylhauses im Bereich der Trierer Kaiserthermen,&amp;rdquo; Trierer Zeitschrift 29, 1966:187-235. (worldcat) W. Reusch, &amp;ldquo;Die Ausgrabungen im Westteil der Trierer Kaiserthermen&amp;rdquo;, Bericht der Römisch-Germanischen Kommission 51-52,1970-71:252-270, 281, Beilage 30. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 113319
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
