<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>atrium on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/atrium/</link>
    <description>Recent content in atrium on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 00:10:10 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/atrium/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>562.Insula or. I.2-3(B)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/insula_or._i/house_2-3/insula_or._i.2-3_b/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/insula_or._i/house_2-3/insula_or._i.2-3_b/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Insula Insula Orientalis I
House House 2-3
Garden B
Keywords  atrium peristyles stuccoing  Garden Description B. From the atrium the peristyle on the lower level was reached by way of a steeply sloping corridor. Stuccoed brick columns and a low wall 0.50 m. high enclosed the central area (b) and a large gutter collected water from the edges and conducted it to the cistern. A rectangular pool ca. 2.60 x 5.00 m. with the inside painted blue was located in the center of this area. At the rear of the pool an area paved with bipedales (tiles two feet long) covered the cellars below with an opening 1.70 x 2.20 to provide light. Jashemski noted that the paved and planted areas were reconstructed with a lattice fence between them, although she did not know of any evidence to support this interpretation.
Plans   Plan of the new excavations of Herculaneum (Maiuri, Herculaneum)     Herculaneum - insula orientalis I. 1-3-b   Images   Herculaneum - insula orientalis I. 2.3-2 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Maiuri, Herculaneum, pp.66-67 (worldcat) Maiuri, Ercolano, p. 353 (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, 1:50-51 and fig. 89 on p. 51 (worldcat)  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 20 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa dell’Alcova</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/tiffany_fong/casa_dellalcova/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/tiffany_fong/casa_dellalcova/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Garden Casa dell’Alcova
##Jashemski Catalogue 542.IV.3-4. 543.IV.3-4.
Keywords  atrium triclinium procoeton  Garden Description 542.IV.3-4. A. Two separate dwellings were united to form this house, excavated in 1928-1929. The northern house has three courtyards. The first (a) is directly off of the vestibule, the second is a covered atrium(b) with a small courtyard that collected roof water, and the third courtyard (c) in the rear supplied light and air to the adjoining rooms and the triclinium. This was too badly damaged to ascertain if it was a garden or even if it once held potted plants. It was compared to the better preserved courtyard in the Casa a Graticcio by Maiuri.
543.IV.3-4. B. The more elegant dwelling to the south had a long corridor on one side of the large triclinium leading to a small paved courtyard with pillars (e) which supplied light and air to the house. The pillars on the south and east stood on a low wall, 0.80 m. high, with a planting area 15 cm. wide in between. This gives the area the feeling of window boxes placed below large windows. There was a well in the southeast corner of this courtyard which received rain water and beyond the courtyard was a secluded alcove. This consisted of an apsed room preceded by a procoeton.
Plans Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1928-1929
Bibliography  Maiuri, Ercolano, pp. 51, 389-391 and fig. 322 (plan) on p. 389 (worldcat)     Idem, Maiuri, Herculaneum, pp. 31 (worldcat)     Idem, Ercolano, pp. 51, 392 and fig. 322 (plan) on p. 389.(worldcat)  -
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>