<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Europa on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/categories/europa/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Europa on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:07:01 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/categories/europa/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Barat-de-Vin, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/sorde-labbaye__landes/gallia_aquitania_barat-de-vin_j.zhou/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:07:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/sorde-labbaye__landes/gallia_aquitania_barat-de-vin_j.zhou/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_Aquitania Gallia_Aquitania (Pleiades)
Province Description A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location Sorde-L&amp;rsquo;Abbaye, Landes
Sorde-L&amp;rsquo;Abbaye, Landes (Pleiades)
House Barat-de-Vin
House Description Two kilometers east of Sorde-l’Abbaye, beside the ancient road from Dax to Pamplona sat this structure on a terrace above the former bed of the Gave. The ruins have been known since the second half of the nineteenth century. They were partially excavated by J. Lauffray between 1957 and 1966. He considered the structure a villa. Later, Boyrie–Fénié and Bost (1994) conjectured that it was a wayside inn. Balmelle is inclined, on the basis of architecture and décor, to the villa interpretation.
Garden Keywords  garden pavilions columns (architectural elements)  Garden Description There are two structures separated by thirty meters or more. It is thought that they may have been connected by a peristyle not yet found. The more southern, lower structure is remarkable for the height of the remaining walls, in some places more than three meters. The southeast wing of this structure includes a large gallery [XI] (41 x 5 m) that ran parallel to the stream. It had large bays separated by columns of green marble. This unit made a sort of belvedere which connected the baths on the northwest to a large pavilion at the southeast extremity. Both the pavilion and the baths belong to a phase of construction in the fourth century. There is a spring between the stream and the baths, which may account for their location. Two possible locations for gardens may be conjectured: (1) between the gallery and the stream, and (2) in a possible peristyle between the upper (eastern) and lower (southern) known structures.
Plans Dates Unspecified
Excavation Dates 1957CE-1966CE
Bibliography  J. Lauffray, Notes sur les fouilles gallo-romaines de Sorde-L’Abbaye, 1965 (no page numbers) B. Boyrie-Fénié, CAG, 40, 1994, p. 154-155, n°306. (worldcat) Catherine Balmelle, Les demeures aristocratiques d&amp;rsquo;Aquitaine, societe et culture de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquite tardive dans le sou-ouest de la Gaule, Ausonius, supple. d&amp;rsquo;Aquitania 10, Bordeaux 2001, p. 417-419. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 249908
TGN ID Contributor Clopper Almon
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Domus Campniac called “House of the Polylobed Impluvium”, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/vesunna_p%C3%A9rigueux_dordogne/gallia_aquitania_house_of_the_polylobed_impluvium_j.zhou/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:07:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/vesunna_p%C3%A9rigueux_dordogne/gallia_aquitania_house_of_the_polylobed_impluvium_j.zhou/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_Aquitania Gallia_Aquitania (Pleiades)
Province Description A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location Vesunna Périgueux, Dordogne Vesunna Périgueux, Dordogne (Pleiades)
House Domus Campniac called “House of the Polylobed Impluvium”
House Description Discovered by chance in 1889 in gardens near the Rue de Campniac, southeast of the Vésonne Tower sanctuary, these ruins were explored in 1908-09 by Charles Durand, who produced a rather accurate plan and description. This rich domus covering 2500 square meters was called at the time of its discovery the “House of the Polylobed Impluvium” because of the form of the pool which covered much of the court of the peristyle. Its final state, the only one thoroughly known, goes back to the beginning of the third century, though old probes indicated that there were without doubt earlier phases.
Garden Keywords  peristyles (columnades) colonnades aqueducts mosaics (visual works)  Garden Description The slightly trapezoidal courtyard (roughly 17.6 by 13.8 meters) is surrounded by a low wall, preserved up to 38 centimeters, which supported the colonnade. The floor of the galleries was a simple pebbled concrete.
The courtyard is fully occupied by two pools, one within the other but separated by a masonry structure of elaborate outline. The inner pool (5.4 x 8 m) had three semicircular apses on the long (north and south) sides and two on short (east and west) sides. The outside walls of the masonry structure were straight on the long sides but marked off rhythmically on the short side by three apses of the same dimension as those of the inner pool. (All apses are concave when seen from the water they touch.) The interior and exterior walls were made of brick and lined, like the bottom, with a soft limestone called Chancelade. The core of the masonry mass was mortared rubble. The central pool was probably fed by a lead pipe which must have come in from the southwest corner which has been destroyed. The drainage is unknown. The surrounding pool was connected to two channels, one going off to the west near the northwest corner and the other to the north near the northeast corner. According to the excavator, they served, respectively, to drain and fill the pool. The low wall supporting the colonnade was covered with stone plates held in place by a layer of red, possibly hydraulic, cement. What we have called the “central” pool was, in fact, not precisely in the center; the limb of the outer pool on the south side is about a meter wider than that on the north.
One can well imagine, following a hypothesis proposed after excavation, planters or space for plantings on the upper part of the masonry mass between the two pools.
Onto this courtyard totally devoted to water there opened on the south a large reception room [D] with a semicircular apse at its southern end. Its entrance was flanked by two symmetric rooms. On the north side of the courtyard, room [G] had a luxurious marble floor. The mosaics are datable to the Severin period.
Plans   Fig. 1: Detail plan of the house substructures of the Domus Campniac “House of the Polylobed Impluvium”.     Fig. 2: Plan of the Domus Campniac (“House of the Polylobed Impluvium”), according to Ch. Durand.   Dates Unspecified
Excavation Dates 1908CE-1909CE
Bibliography  Ch. Durand, Fouilles de Vésonne (Compte-rendu de 1909), Périgueux, 1910, p. 3-13 (worldcat) Ch. Durand, Fouilles de Vésonne (Compte-rendu de 1909), Périgueux, 1911, p. 5-42, pl. I-III. (worldcat) Cl. Girardy-Caillat, Périgueux antique, coll. Guides archéologiques de la France, Imprimerie Nationale, 1998. (worldcat) C. Balmelle, L’habitat dans le sud ouest de la Gaule romaine, Villes et agglomérations antiques du sud-ouest de la Gaule, 6e suppl. à Aquitania, Bordeaux 1992, p?. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 138650
TGN ID Contributor Clopper Almon
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Vesunna (Domus de Vésone ou de la rue des Bouquets), Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/vesunna_p%C3%A9rigueux_dordogne/gallia_aquitania_house_of_vesunna_j.zhou/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:07:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/vesunna_p%C3%A9rigueux_dordogne/gallia_aquitania_house_of_vesunna_j.zhou/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_Aquitania Gallia_Aquitania (Pleiades)
Province Description A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location Vesunna Périgueux, Dordogne Vesunna Périgueux, Dordogne (Pleiades)
House House of Vesunna (Domus de Vésone ou de la rue des Bouquets)
House Description The house was constructed around the middle of the first century on the remains of a building from the beginning of the history of the town in the Augustan age. It went through three principal phases and reached, at its maximum extent, an area of 4200 square meters. The chronology is proposed by Claudine Girady in Aquitania 2003. In all phases, the entrance was from a portico-bordered decumanus on the north. The zone along this route is known only partially and cannot be precisely followed through the phases.
Garden Keywords  porticoes reception rooms graffiti (casual notations) rinceaux lararia columns (architectural elements) nymphaea (garden structures) vases aqueducts  Garden Description Phase I. (Fig. 1) The first phase was a vast domus organized around a court or garden of 970 square meters closed on the south by a wall and bordered on the three other sides by porticoes 3.3 meters wide. Counting the porticoes, the space was 37.5 x 37.0 meters. The rooms, including a large reception room [10], wrapped in an L around the north and east sides. At least the east portico was paved, for the imprint of the stones was found. There were numerous graffiti on the paintings on the walls of the porticoes [6] around the courtyard or garden. Isolated letters, words, and even texts of several lines accompanied scenes of gladiatorial combats and contests between men and beasts. Among the decorative fragments from this phase are two interesting fragments found in room [5] of Phase III but coming from Phase 1 (when there was no room [5]), perhaps from room [4] or the walls around the garden. They show crisscrossed osier branches against a black background. Presumably, they were part of a picture of a garden fence. The mesh size, however, is different in different fragments. Alix Barbet has proposed that they came from a hortus conclusus, as shown in the illustration. This design was characteristic of the third stage of painting in Pompeii and elsewhere in Italy, but it is also found in Gaul, for instance at Vaison-la-Romaine, where an example found under the cathedral is now in the archaeological museum.
Phase II. (Fig. 2) Towards the end of the first century, the enclosing wall on the south was torn down to be rebuilt. Rooms were added along the west side, encroaching on the garden, which was reduced to 760 square meters. From fragments, we know that the decoration of this period included a life-sized scene of gladiatorial combats with at least a dozen human figures plus a number of animals, probably from scenes of hunting in the arena. The pictures were accompanied by inscriptions. A. Barbet, who has recently published this material, believes that the whole painting was some five meters high, with figures arranged in two or three bands. The painting must date from before the middle of the second century, when this phase of the house was destroyed. It is not totally clear where this grand composition was, for we know it only from fragments. Based on some Pompeian examples, however, Barbet tentatively places it on the south wall of the garden.
Phase Ⅲ. (Fig. 3,4,5,6) In the middle the second century, the whole house, except the garden, was filled in up to a height of about one meter. Along the west side, the walls were torn down; but along the east side, the walls were left in place. Thus, the lowest meter of these walls on the east side was buried with the paintings still on them. Paradoxically, it is this burying which has preserved the painting.
In the northern part of the house, two new courtyards with peristyles [62] and [32] were built. In the first was a large, 80-square-meter, rectangular pool, which one could enter by a large stairs. The courtyard was surrounded by a gallery 2.5 meters wide. On the south side was found a 1.5-meter-high base of a monument and steps going down to a well. In the pool were discovered the lower part of a statue of the mother goddess and two fragmentary altars, so that some have suggested a religious function for this part of the house. The smaller courtyard [32] with porticoes in a U had columns ornamented with foliage or shells.
Baths of modest proportions were constructed at the south end of the west wing. Two rooms of the east wing got hypocaust heating systems. The central garden was reduced to make room for a monumental south wing organized around a huge rectangular reception room [56] (8,25 x 7,15 m) on the central axis of the garden. In front of it, a platform projected into the garden and the room itself advanced across the portico. One entered from the portico by doors in the side of the room. The central bay opened onto the platform projecting into the garden; steps went down from the sides of the platform into the garden. A porch with two columns lent a monumental aspect to the room. It was flanked by two smaller rooms, [57] and [59].
The central garden was a slightly non-rectangular quadrilateral (23.60 x 20.60 m maximum) containing 460 square meters. It was 1.3 meters below the level of the stylobate of the galleries with Tuscan columns.connected by rails which surrounded it. In front on the platform on the south side was a well; another was in the north. In the center of the garden was a wall 60 centimeters thick enclosing a 15 x 11 meter rectangle. At its highest surviving point it stands 90 centimeters high, but is estimated to have been cut down by 30 centimeters. According to Claude Barrière, the first excavator, it had a top of limestone and an interior covering of the same material. He interpreted the wall as the outside of an ornamental pool. This interpretation accords well with the final phase of paintings on the outside of the wall, which shows carefully executed scenes of fish, crustaceans, and seashells.
But gradually doubts about this interpretation arose. The absence of water supply or drainage is surprising for so large a pool. Barrière indicated on a cross-section drawing traces of an internal paving with limestone along the inside of the wall. What was interpreted as the bottom of the pool was perhaps the base of walkway. There was no hydraulic cement and no opus signinum, moreover, the footings of the wall were shallow. The lack of of a proper bottom for a pool cannot be explained by the later installation of the circular pool in the middle which had a more than adequate bottom.
A new interpretation sees the structure filled with earth and functioning as a sort of huge raised bed for a garden. Later, a circular pool with an exterior diameter of 7.6 meters and deep foundations was installed in the center. This is the interpretation and state reflected in the plan of this phase. At the southeast corner of the rectangle there is block which could have supported steps leading up to the garden level. It must be noted, however, that this block concealed paintings on the wall, which must, therefore, have been done before the block was put there.
The décor of the walls of the garden were renewed several times; three phases of paintings on the central part correspond to three successive levels of the ground in the garden. Three phases have also been detected in the paintings which decorated the walls around the outside of the garden. It was possible to remove the paintings from one wall at the time of the discovery; meticulous study by Alix Barbet and her group have yielded a possible understanding of these very fragmentary remains. The other three walls of the garden were discovered in very unequal condition. The paintings, conserved up to a maximum height of 1.54 meters, show an alteration of herms and krater-fountains placed in semicircular excedras. (Five herms and four kraters are presumed.) The white marble vases imitate luxurious models. The underlying ocre-yellow plinth blends with the garden soil. It is bordered by a thick garland of green and black leaves and is datable, according to Barbet, to the second half of the second century at the latest.
At a later time still not well dated but probably in the course of the third century, the rectangular structure was trimmed down in height. The fragments of the paintings of the cut-off portion were left lying on the ground, and the area between the rectangle and the outer wall of the garden was filled in. Barrière showed that this filling occurred in two steps. After the second filling operation, the steps leading down from the platform on the south side had disappeared under the earth, and the rectangular wall was buried.
The round pool was restored and remained alone in the center of the garden, which was now on the same level as the rooms around it. In raking light, the trace of a lead pipe can be seen along a radius of the pool. It fed, no doubt, a water jet in the center of a circular fountain basin 1.4 meters in diameter in the pool. A fragment of the border of this basin was found.
At about the time of these last transformations in the third century, the baths also went out of use. It was abandoned at the end of the third century at the time of building the rampart and was pillaged for that construction. In particular, any stonework connected with the circular pool was carried away, leaving only its cement base with the imprint of the stones which were once above it. There are traces of a brief occupation in the fourth century.
To exhibit the remains to best advantage, the Museum of Vesunna has to show a condition which never actually existed. The rectangular wall has been shown exposed on both sides, while in the center the cement base of the circular pool is visible.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the House of Vesunna in the first phase.     Fig. 2: Plan of the House of Vesunna in the second phase (drawing by C. Girardy-Caillat).     Fig. 3: Plan of the House of Vesunna in the third phase (drawing by C. Girardy-Caillat) and the print of the garden (survey by A. Barbet, drawing by J.-F. Lefèvre).   Images   Fig. 4: Model of the third state with the hypothesis of a garden (credit to A.B.).     Fig. 5: Photo of the ornamental pond with the fish on the outside of the wall (credit to A.B.).     Fig. 6: Photo of the south, central and left part of the pool wall (credit A.B.).     Fig. 7: Photo of the partial restoration of the painting on the south wall of the garden.     Fig. 8: Drawing of the painting on the south wall on the west side of the garden, survey by A. Barbet, drawing by J.-F. Lefèvre.     Fig. 9: Drawing of the partial restoration of the painting on the south wall of the garden, drawing by J.-F. Lefevre, F. Ory.     Fig. 10: Photo of the paintings of fish on the outside of the wall.   Dates 1-3 Century CE
Excavation Dates 1960CE-1968CE, 1973CE-1977CE, 1992CE-1995CE
Bibliography  Cl Barrière, Domus Pompeia”: fouilles de la villa des bouquets à Périgueux, Document d’Archéologie et d’Histoire périgourdines, 2e suppl. Périgueux 1996. (worldcat) A. Bouet, Les collèges dans la ville antique, le cas des Subaediani, Revue Archéologique, 2001, p. 227-278.(worldcat) A. Barbet (en coll. Avec Cl. Girardy, J.-P. Bost), Peintures de Périgueux, édifice de la rue des Bouquets ou de la Domus de Vésone, Aquitania, XIX, 2003 p. 81-126. (avec bibliographie détaillée) (worldcat) A. Barbet, F. Monier, J.P. Bost, M. Sterneberg et alii, Peintures de Périgueux, édifice de la rue des Bouquets our la domus de Vésone II Les peintures fragmentaires, in Aquitania XX, 2004, p. 149-219. (worldcat) C. Girady-Caillat, Périgueux” in C. Girady-Caillat, Périgueux Antique, in the series Guides Archéologiques de la France, 1998. (worldcat) C. Girady-Caillat, Périgueux” in P. Garmy and L. Maurin, Enceintes romaines d&amp;rsquo;Aquitaine, Bordeaux, Dax, Périgueux, Bazas. Paris: MSH 1116, p. 128-154. (Documents d&amp;rsquo;Archéologie Française; 53). (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 138650
TGN ID Contributor Clopper Almon
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of “the Visitation”, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/vesunna_p%C3%A9rigueux_dordogne/gallia_aquitania_house_of_the_visitation_j.zhou/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:07:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/vesunna_p%C3%A9rigueux_dordogne/gallia_aquitania_house_of_the_visitation_j.zhou/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_Aquitania Gallia_Aquitania (Pleiades)
Province Description A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location Vesunna Périgueux, Dordogne Vesunna Périgueux, Dordogne (Pleiades)
House House of “the Visitation”
House Description This house, discovered during excavation in the 1980&amp;rsquo;s at the convent of the Visitation, is about 150 meters southeast of the amphitheater. It was bordered by a cardo on the west.
Garden Keywords  porticoes reception rooms  Garden Description In its first-century form, this rather luxurious house was organized around a courtyard with porticoes. The reception room was in the north gallery, its entrance from the gallery flanked by a pilaster on either side. The garden, in the center of the courtyard, measured at least 12 meters on a side and had a well. A rectangular pool, still incompletely exposed, ran along this north gallery and hooked around to run along the west gallery for several meters. Symmetry would suggest that it did the same on the east, but that is not presently known for certain. A large apse opens in front of the reception room.
At the end of the first century, the house underwent architectural modifications, but it was not raised to compensate for the rise in the level of the nearby street. The apse of the pool was filled in, while a small pool was added in the center of the garden. A new gallery was added on the west side of the courtyard. The house seems to have been destroyed by fire and abandoned from the end of the third century. By the second half of the fourth century, its site had become a quarry for materials.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the north part of Périgueux, drawing by V. Teillet, after C, Girardy-Caillat / Ministry of Culture.     Fig. 2: Plan of the Périgueux, House of “the Visitation”: domus de la visitation (zone 5), survey by F. Barron’s, 1987.   Dates Unspecified
Excavation Dates 1980&amp;rsquo;s CE
Bibliography  Cl. Girardy, Archéologie en Aquitaine 6, 1987, p. 19, 23-25. (worldcat) Cl. Girardy-Caillat, Périgueux antique, coll. Guides archéologiques de la France, Imprimerie Nationale, 1998, p.???-54.(worldcat) C. Balmelle, L’habitat dans le sud ouest de la Gaule romaine, Ville et agglomérations antiques du sud-ouest de la Gaule, 6e suppl. à Aquitania, Bordeaux 1992, p. 342-345. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 138650
TGN ID Contributor Clopper Almon
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb garden of C. Iulius Aemuli[a]nus, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/saintes/gallia-aquitania_tomb-garden-of-c.-iulius-aemulianus_j.zhou/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:07:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/saintes/gallia-aquitania_tomb-garden-of-c.-iulius-aemulianus_j.zhou/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_Aquitania Gallia_Aquitania (Pleiades)
Province Description A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location Saintes
Saintes (Pleiades)
House Garden Tomb garden of C. Iulius Aemuli[a]nus
Keywords  tombs  Garden Description A stone inscription found at Saintes in 1609, now lost and transmitted only in garbled form, seems to record the epitaph of C. Iulius Aemuli[a]nus, who consecrated for himself while still alive a burial place with a rather large (or “the larger”) garden as walled around and marked out, with its sacred places, approaches, and monuments (sepulcra cum hort[o] maior(e) ita uti intra cons[a]e[p]tum et termina[t]um [es]st cum [l]ocis sacris, aditibus, monumentis cons[e]cr[avit ?], according to Hirschfeld’s restoration of the text).
Plans Dates Unspecified
Excavation Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  CIL 13.1072 (worldcat; open access resource) J.-J. Hatt, La tombe gallo-romaine, Paris, 1951, p.71. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 138458
TGN ID Contributor John Bodel
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa at Glesia, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/saint-cricq-villeneuve_landes/gallia-aquitania_villa-at-glesia_j.zhou/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:07:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/saint-cricq-villeneuve_landes/gallia-aquitania_villa-at-glesia_j.zhou/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_Aquitania Gallia_Aquitania (Pleiades)
Province Description A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location Saint-Cricq-Villeneuve
Saint-Cricq-Villeneuve, Landes (Pleiades)
House Villa at Glesia
House Description On the right bank of the Midou, there was discovered in 1868 a large villa with much marble and numerous mosaics. A salvage excavation in 1976 only glimpsed the remains, and they are now known unfortunately only from a very schematic plan and sketchy descriptions.
Garden Keywords  mosaics (visual works) reception rooms  Garden Description The villa was built around a large courtyard (88.6 by 31.6 as read from the plan), which may have been a garden. It does not seem to have been surrounded in the usual way by porticoes, but one should not put much trust in the very simplified plan. There are, however, façade galleries on several sides. The separate baths, situated below the house near the river, were connected to the villa a series of flights of steps with landings between them. Along the southeast two-thirds of the southwest façade, a gallery runs between two reception rooms, a feature shared with the villa de Baptest at Moncrabeau, though in the present case, the gallery seems to have been double. Moreover, according to the descriptions of the excavations, each end of the exterior gallery (65 x 3.78 m) was terminated by an apse, a form found in other plans in this region and elsewhere. At the southeast end, in a feature characteristic of late antiquity, a trilobed room opened off of the reception room and extended beyond the basic rectangle of the house, as if to allow the enjoyment of the surrounding grounds.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the Villa at Glesia. Adapted from Dufourcet et al., 1890.   Dates 1868CE
Excavation Dates 1976CE
Bibliography  J. Quicherat, Rapport sur diverses communications concernant des mosaïques trouvées à Saint-Cricq (Landes, Revue des Sociétés Savantes, 5e série, I, 1870, p. 116-119. (worldcat) E. Morvillez, Forme et évolution des salles de réception des grandes demeures tardives du bassin Méditerranéen occidental, 1993, t. 1, p. 179-185.(worldcat) Catherine Balmelle, Les demeures aristocratiques d&amp;rsquo;Aquitaine, societe et culture de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquite tardive dans le sou-ouest de la Gaule, Ausonius, supple. d&amp;rsquo;Aquitania 10, Bordeaux 2001, p. 401-403, 445. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 249916
TGN ID Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa de Séviac, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/montreal/gallia-aquitania_villa-de-se%CC%81viac_j.zhou/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:07:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/montreal/gallia-aquitania_villa-de-se%CC%81viac_j.zhou/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_Aquitania Gallia_Aquitania (Pleiades)
Province Description A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location Montréal, Gers
Montréal, Gers (Pleiades)
House Villa de Séviac
House Description Two kilometers southwest of the village, the villa sits on plateau overlooking the left bank of the Auzoue to the east and descending in a gentle slope to the brook Argentans to the north. An ancient road five meters wide runs along the east side. Known since 1867, the villa was partially excavated in 1911, then reopened and minutely studied since 1958.
Garden Keywords  fountains gutters (building drainage components) reception rooms piscinae mosaics (visual works)  Garden Description The dwelling goes back to the early empire and knew a period of splendor in late antiquity. In a unified construction program there was built, beginning in the fourth century, a grand villa with a main structure around a vast peristyle, with exterior façade galleries and baths adjacent to a second courtyard to the south. In the baths, however, numerous, complex modifications followed between the second and fifth centuries.
The main entrance was from the east, where the road was. An open passage way led into the peristyle (40 x 41 m). It had a central open area of 35 meters on a side. Its internal organization is not known. All or part of it may have been a garden, but there were also important layers of gravel (Monturet-Rivière, 1986, p. 15). It was bordered by a gutter lined with tegulae to catch the drip from the roofs. Straight ahead of the entrance but on the far side of the courtyard there was a narrow pool made of brick, possibly with a fountain. It had a polygonal apse on its east side. The pool was connected to the gutters. Beyond this pool, further to the west, across the west gallery and approximately in line with the entrance way and the pool, was a large room [S2], presumably a reception area.
To the south, as mentioned, were sumptuous baths with pavements in opus tesselatum depicting fruit trees. On the outside of the walls of the baths, painting simulated a garden fence with crisscross palings. (R. Monturet- H. Rivière 1987, p. 184, fig. 8, Demeures fig. 81, p. 205).
To the northeast, paleochristian places of worship were installed in the fifth and sixth centuries, apparently originally in one room of the villa.
The glory of Séviac is in its mosaics. Many, in excellent condition, are in their original places. The themes are geometric and vegetal; there is no mythological picture. This absence has suggested to several observers that the builder may have been Christian or, at least, did not wish to give offense to Christians. Moreover, the grape vine, an important Christian image, is prominent.
Figure 3 shows a “fruit pyramid” from room S25. On the support of a laurel bush growing in a giant seashell there is a green grape leaf with yellow veins and bunches of yellow grapes on either side. Higher up are two fruits, possibly a pear on the right and a citron on the left. From the top, two stylized acanthus leaves fall over the sides.
In the fruit tree mosaic in Figure 4, it is not clear what tree is depicted. The fruit look very like figs – also a Christian image &amp;ndash; but the leaves do not look at all like figs. Pears are another possibility. In fact, the artist may have been interested only in conveying abundance or a hoped-for paradise hereafter. Note the fleur-de-lys in the lower right corner.
Plans   Fig. 1: Topographic Plan of the Villa de Séviac, drawing by M. -P. R., based on the the 1/25000e map of the IGN.   Dates 1867CE
Excavation Dates 1911CE
Bibliography  Monturet, H. Rivière, J.P. Bost, P. Aragon-Launey, Les thermes sud de la villa gallo-romaine de Séviac, 10e suppl. Aquitania, 1986. (worldcat) J. Lapart, C. Petit, Le Gers, CAG, 32, 1993, p. 266-283. (worldcat) E. Morvillez, Forme et évolution des salles de réception des grandes demeures tardives du bassin Méditerranéen occidental, 1993, t. 1, 186-202.(worldcat) Catherine Balmelle, Les demeures aristocratiques d&amp;rsquo;Aquitaine, societe et culture de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquite tardive dans le sou-ouest de la Gaule, Ausonius, supple. d&amp;rsquo;Aquitania 10, Bordeaux 2001, p. 106-111, 386-88, 446 (with preceding bibliography). (worldcat) Jean Gugole with photographs by Jean-Bernard Laffitte, Mosaïques de Séviac, Serres Castet, Editions de Faucompret, 1996. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 246629
TGN ID Contributor Clopper Almon
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa de Taron, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/taron-sadirac-villenave_pyr%C3%A9n%C3%A9es-atlantiques/gallia_aquitania_villa_de_taron_j.zhou/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:07:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/taron-sadirac-villenave_pyr%C3%A9n%C3%A9es-atlantiques/gallia_aquitania_villa_de_taron_j.zhou/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_Aquitania Gallia_Aquitania (Pleiades)
Province Description A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location Taron-Sadirac-Viellenave, Pyrénées-Atlantiques
Taron-Sadirac-Viellenave, Pyrénées-Atlantiques (Pleiades)
House Villa de Taron
House Description Vestiges of this villa in the valley of the Petit Lées are found in an area of some 2.5 hectares around the Romanesque church built over the southern part of the villa. It sat upon a terrace with a gentle slope towards the east. The church kept the same orientation as the villa under it, which is almost exactly true north-south and east-west. The remains of the villa were noted in the eighteenth century. Excavations conducted in 1995-96 by Ph. Vergain were able to ascertain an original construction in the first century.
Garden Keywords  mosaics (visual works) peristyles (columnades)  Garden Description According to Vergain, a remodeling in the third century created the peristyle which may have been planted as a garden. Four phases have been detected for late antiquity; the mosaic decorations come from the last.
Plans   Fig. 1: Taron. Plan R. Monturet, IRAA, Pau, according to Vergain et al. 1997, 154, fig. 3.     Fig. 2: Plan of the Villa de Taron (cat. n° 61).   Dates 18 Century CE
Excavation Dates 1995CE-1996CE
Bibliography  Philippe Vergain, &amp;ldquo;Taron&amp;rdquo; Bilan scientifique de la region Aquitaine 1995, Ministère de la culture Direction du patrimoine Sous-direction de l&amp;rsquo;archéologie 1996, p 115-116. Note：(worldcat) G. Fabre, CAG, 64, 1994, p. 88-89, n°108. (worldcat) Catherine Balmelle, Les demeures aristocratiques d&amp;rsquo;Aquitaine, societe et culture de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquite tardive dans le sou-ouest de la Gaule, Ausonius, supple. d&amp;rsquo;Aquitania 10, Bordeaux 2001, p. 420-421, plan p.449. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 249923
TGN ID Contributor Clopper Almon
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa du Palat, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/saint-emilion_gironde/gallia-aquitania_villa-du-palat_j.zhou/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:07:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/saint-emilion_gironde/gallia-aquitania_villa-du-palat_j.zhou/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_Aquitania Gallia_Aquitania (Pleiades)
Province Description A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location Saint-Emilion
Saint-Emilion, Gironde (Pleiades)
House Villa du Palat
House Description About half a kilometer southeast of the village of Saint-Emilion, on the west bank of the wet-weather branch La Fongaban, and about half way down the slope below plateau of the village, this aristocratic residence descended over several levels. It was reported in 1935, excavated by M. Gauthier in 1969-71 and then by C. Balmelle between 1981 and 1988.
The villa probably had a U shape, with the base of the U running southwest-to-northeast and the wings at either end extending to the southeast, probably crossing the branch. The interior of U was undoubtedly a garden. Only the southeast façade of the base of U has been uncovered; the rest of the construction continues under the road and on beyond in the vineyard on the other side. In the 17 known rooms, this sumptuous villa of late antiquity has no less than nine mosaic pavements of high quality. On the basis of stylistic criteria and ancient furnishings, its homogeneous construction is dated to the beginning of the fifth century – too late to have been built by Ausonius.
Garden Keywords  mosaics (visual works) colonnades porticoes fountains gutters (building drainage components) impluvia  Garden Description Across the 90-meter façade on the inside of the U ran a colonnade of marble Corinthian columns; between the colonnade and the rooms of the base wing was a portico 3.9 meters wide. In the center of this wing, a grand reception room opened for its full length (9.46 m) onto the portico and the garden on beyond. Its entrance from the portico was enlivened by a fountain with an octagonal pool lined with blue marble and decorated with a bottom mosaic with fish. A 13-centimeter wide gutter with a marble bottom ran around the outside of the pool, doubtless to catch the overflow. In the center, there was a marble footing with an octagonal base that no doubt supported a basin for the fountain that is now lost. On the threshold between the fountain and the portico ran a long, narrow mosaic showing a garland of laurel against a black background and sown with stylized leaves, rosettes, and lilies. In the middle, a crown of laurel surrounds a lily, and the lilies to either side open towards this central lily. A geometric carpet mosaic of the same width as the room seems to extend the room into the portico, for the floor of the portico on either side of this central room was a simple opus signinum.
In the presumed garden framed by the U-shaped gallery was an rectangular pool (60.3 x 6.93 m) with apses at either end. This pool is virtually the only thing visible at the site today. Its long axis ran parallel to the façade, and it was centered on reception room, so that it underscored nicely the lines of the façade. The sides were covered by a layer of rose-colored hydraulic mortar and topped by a parapet of limestone rounded above. The bottom was covered with reddish to yellowish brick tiles, giving a pleasant unity to the structure. The apses at either end were slightly narrower than the pool. The one on the south end was also paved with tile.
The pool was filled in at the end of the occupation of the house. Numerous fragments of polychrome mosaic, sometimes figured, were discovered in the fill. Also, some reworking of the apses has been observed, in both cases around the opening of the apse, but the purpose of the changes was unclear.
Plans   Fig. 1: Figure. 1. Plan of the Villa du Palat.     Fig. 2: Topographic plan of the situation of Saint-Emilion, drawing by M. -P. R., based on the the 1/25000e map of the IGN, 1636 Est.     Fig. 3: Plan of the archaeological remains before 1969, according to Oüy-Vernazobres, 1937.     Fig. 4: Plan of the villa after the excavations of 1981-87, by M.-P. R. after R. Monturet. According to Balmelle, Archéologie en Aquitaine, 1987, 44, fig.29.   Dates Unspecified
Excavation Dates 1969CE-1971CE，1981CE-1988CE
Bibliography  H. Sion, CAG 33/1, La Gironde, n° 286, pp. 197-207, plan fig. 120 p. 228. (worldcat) Catherine Balmelle, Les demeures aristocratiques d&amp;rsquo;Aquitaine, societe et culture de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquite tardive dans le sou-ouest de la Gaule, Ausonius, supple. d&amp;rsquo;Aquitania 10, Bordeaux 2001, p. 141-142 ; 403-405, 452 (with a bibliography of previous works). (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 140559
TGN ID Contributor Clopper Almon
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa of Arnesp, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/valentine_haute_garonne/gallia_aquitania_villa-of-arnesp_j.zhou/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:07:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/valentine_haute_garonne/gallia_aquitania_villa-of-arnesp_j.zhou/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_Aquitania Gallia_Aquitania (Pleiades)
Province Description A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location Valentine, Haute Garonne
Valentine, Haute Garonne (Pleiades)
House Villa of Arnesp
House Description This vast, 8,400 square meter villa sits at the edge of a natural terrace overlooking the right bank of the Garonne, which may have been closer then than now. It entrance was about fifty meters north of the Roman road running from Tolosa (Toulouse) to Lugdunum Convenae (Saint-Bertrand-de- Comminges). To the south, the high Pyrenees rise dramatically on the horizon. The construction is primarily of river-bed stones washed down from the mountains and showing a great variety of geological origin. There is also white marble from Saint-Béat and black and green marble from Campan and Sarrancolin, all a little south in the foothills of the Pyrenees. Water brought from thermal springs near the present village of Labarthe Rivière in the foothills played an important role in the life in the villa. Baths to the southwest have been exposed since the nineteenth century. Later, excavations directed by G. Fouet between 1949 and 1981 demonstrated occupation of the spot from the early empire. Partial publications suggest a date for the principal construction in the the fourth century and important remodeling in the fifth.
Garden Keywords  aqueducts lararia peristyles (columnades)  Garden Description The villa has a very linear and symmetric plan running north-south. On entering from the south, beyond the façade, one came into a long, rectangular court (52 x 21.45 m) bordered by two walkways which had walls towards the courtyard. There is no evidence that these walls supported columns, but they may have had windows or open arches or wooden columns or a trellis; we simply do not have enough of the walls vertically to know what sort or openings there were. Through the center of the courtyard ran a small, marble-lined channel, about a foot wide, bringing water from the south. Otherwise, the organization of the open space in the center of the courtyard is not known. At the northern end of the courtyard was a colonnade façade, behind which opened a semicircular peristyle of Tuscan columns with its straight side on the north. Its center was occupied by a large, D-shaped pool (14.2 x 9.5 m) with its circular part concentric with the peristyle. The pool was covered with marble and surrounded by colonnade and closed by a balustrade. On beyond was a long room running east-west with apses at either end. The next room to the north on the axis of the structures to the south was of unusal form and luxuriously decorated. Its fundamental form was an octagon inscribed in a square, but in the corners of the square cut off by the octagon were niches in the form of three sides of an octagon. Presumably there were statues or perhaps plants in them.
Behind this room, further north, extended a large peristyle thought to have been about 48 by 41 meters. The floors of the galleries were of opus signinum. The center of the peristyle was presumably a garden, but all of the area except about eighth in the southwest corner was destroyed by the construction of the canal and road in 1931. The water that had crossed the forecourt and filled the deep pool presumably irrigated also this area and then, beyond the gallery at the north end of the peristyle, descended to a lower area, where it may also have used to advantage in a garden. Near the point where it would have descended there was found, in the course of construction of the canal, a downspout in the shape of a lion’s head. It is now lost. Various items from the villa are in museum in the town of Valentine.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the Villa of Arnesp in Valentine (cat. n° 64).   Dates 4-5 Century CE
Excavation Dates 1949CE-1981CE
Bibliography  G. Fouet, La grande villa gallo-romaine de Valentine (Haute-Garonne) en 1970, Actes du 96e Congrès national des Sociétés Savantes, Toulouse 1971, Archéologie, 1976, p. 123-136. (worldcat) Catherine Balmelle, Les demeures aristocratiques d&amp;rsquo;Aquitaine, societe et culture de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquite tardive dans le sou-ouest de la Gaule, Ausonius, supple. d&amp;rsquo;Aquitania 10, Bordeaux 2001, p. 424-426, plan p. 450. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 249997
TGN ID Contributor Clopper Almon
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa of Gleyzia d’Augreilh, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/saint-sever_landes/gallia-aquitania_villa-of-gleyzia-daugreilh_j.zhou/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:07:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/saint-sever_landes/gallia-aquitania_villa-of-gleyzia-daugreilh_j.zhou/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_Aquitania Gallia_Aquitania (Pleiades)
Province Description A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location Saint-Sever, Landes
Saint-Sever, Landes (Pleiades)
House Villa of Gleyzia d’Augreilh
House Description This vast villa of at least 2700 square meters was situated on an alluvial terrace (36 m above sea level) on the left bank of the the Adour. It was noted and explored in the 19th century; modern excavation began in 1969 and has continued up to the present under the direction of Dr. Paul Dubedat. Occupation of the site may go back to the early empire, but the main phase of construction was in the fourth or fifth centuries.
The villa is a rare case in domestic architecture of two very large, twin, symmetrically placed peristyles of almost the same size.
Garden Keywords  loam mosaics (visual works) reception rooms  Garden Description The floors of the galleries surrounding all four sides of both peristyles were completely covered with mosaics. The eastern peristyle (31 x 25.5 m) was slightly larger (820 compared to 800 m2) and had geometric and plant motifs such as vines and stalks of acanthus leaves in the mosaics. The western peristyle gave access to baths.
The peristyles look like ideal places for gardens. They were not paved, and the soil throughout the area is rich bottom land. In his book, Dubedat says nothing about the courtyards in Gallo-Roman times; there is currently no direct evidence that they were planted.
Plans Dates The Early Empire
Excavation Dates 19th Century CE Modern excavation began in 1969 CE
Bibliography  Paul Dubedat, Bull.de la société de Borda (Dax), 95, 1970, p.13-31. (worldcat) Paul Dubedat, Bull.de la société de Borda (Dax), 112, 1987, p.312, 356. (worldcat) B. Boyrie-Fénié, CAG, 40, 1994, p.125-134, n°282. (worldcat) Catherine Balmelle, Les demeures aristocratiques d&amp;rsquo;Aquitaine, societe et culture de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquite tardive dans le sou-ouest de la Gaule, Ausonius, supple. d&amp;rsquo;Aquitania 10, Bordeaux 2001, p.407-409, plan p.448. (worldcat)* Paul Dubedat, *La villa gallo-romaine du Gleyzia d’Augreilh et Saint-Pé-de-Mazères*, Princi Negue, Pau, 2003. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 249911
TGN ID Contributor Clopper Almon
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa of La Garenne, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/nerac/gallia-aquitania_villa-of-la-garenne_j.zhou/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:07:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/nerac/gallia-aquitania_villa-of-la-garenne_j.zhou/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_Aquitania Gallia_Aquitania (Pleiades)
Province Description A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location Nérac
Nérac (Pleiades)
House Villa of La Garenne
House Description Despite its inauspicious entry into the rolls of archaeological sites, the villa remains truly a large and richly ornamented mansion. There were numerous pavements in polychrome opus tesselatum; much white and colored marble was used in the decoration. There were works in opus sectile and composite capitals with leafy swirls on their corners. There was a sculpture collection including a marble portrait of Marcus Aurelius and several mythological subjects.
Garden Keywords  statues reception rooms  Garden Description The villa was in two distinct parts. A bath complex and nymphaeum ran along the river bank. Some eighty meters back from the water and on a terrace was an enormous reception complex. In the center of it was a circular room about ten meters in diameter and on each side was a huge reception area about nine meters wide and 27 meters long with an apse at the end near the center. Between these two complexes was a large area divided by walls into three roughly rectangular areas. It appears possible that this walled-in area between the luxurious reception area and the river would have been developed as a garden. It is noteworthy that it is not a peristyle garden.
There were two phase of construction. The first seems to go back to the early empire. The second, which realigned slightly the upper complex, is dated by Balmelle to the early 5th century.
Plans Dates 1st Part: Early Empire 2nd Part: Early 5th Century CE
Excavation Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Catherine Balmelle, Les demeures aristocratiques d&amp;rsquo;Aquitaine, societe et culture de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquite tardive dans le sou-ouest de la Gaule, Ausonius, supple. d&amp;rsquo;Aquitania 10, Bordeaux 2001, p. 390-3. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505
TGN ID Contributor Clopper Almon
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa of Sorde-l’Abbaye, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/sorde-labbaye__landes/gallia_aquitania_villa_of_sorde-labbaye_j.zhou/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:07:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/sorde-labbaye__landes/gallia_aquitania_villa_of_sorde-labbaye_j.zhou/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_Aquitania Gallia_Aquitania (Pleiades)
Province Description A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location Sorde-L&amp;rsquo;Abbaye, Landes
Sorde-L&amp;rsquo;Abbaye, Landes (Pleiades)
House Villa of Sorde-l’Abbaye
House Description This villa covering 2000 square meters is in the center of the town, only a few meters from the bank of the Gave d’Oloron and inside the enclosure of the Abbey of Saint John, begun in 975. The abbey follows the orientation of the villa and covers part of it. The villa was noted in 1873 and excavated between 1957 and 1966 by J. Lauffray. At least three phases of work and embellishment have been detected.
Garden Keywords  mosaics (visual works) columns (architectural elements)  Garden Description It has two peristyles of very different sizes. The larger (30 x 22.5 m ), to the northwest, is trapezoidal in shape; the sides running in the north-south direction are parallel, but the other two are not. It had marble columns. One of the galleries (20.8 x 4.3 m) had a mosaic floor with stars formed by two squares and other geometric and figured motifs. They are tentatively dated at the end of the fourth or early years of the fifth century. The second, smaller peristyle in the southern part of the house (about 15 x 14 m on the outside and 8.5 x 7.2 m on the inside) was surrounded by galleries 2.3 meters wide. At an even later period, it connected the baths – along the south side near the river &amp;ndash; to the main body of the house. The geometric mosaic decoration are very late – sixth and even perhaps seventh century. Though without pools or other direct evidence, both peristyles are possible locations for gardens. Remarkably, the site was occupied, seemingly without interruption, until the beginning of the Middle Ages.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the Villa of Sorde-l’Abbaye after the excavations of 1958-1966 (n° 172&amp;amp;180.     Fig. 2: Plan of the Villa of Sorde-l’Abbaye (cat. n° 59).   Dates 1873CE
Excavation Dates 1957CE-1966CE
Bibliography  J. Lauffray, Sorde-L’Abbaye, ville romaine et médiévale d’après les recherches récentes, Les Amis de Sorde et du Pays d’Orthe, 1962, p. 24-31 (worldcat) B. Boyrie-Fénié, CAG, 40, 1994, p.125-134, n°282. (worldcat) Catherine Balmelle, Les demeures aristocratiques d&amp;rsquo;Aquitaine, societe et culture de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquite tardive dans le sou-ouest de la Gaule, Ausonius, supple. d&amp;rsquo;Aquitania 10, Bordeaux 2001, p. 414-417, plan p. 415 and 448. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 249908
TGN ID Contributor Clopper Almon
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>