<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/castelculier_lot-et-garonne/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2020 12:39:10 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/castelculier_lot-et-garonne/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa Lamarque, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/castelculier_lot-et-garonne/gallia_villa-lamarque-_yji/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2020 12:39:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/castelculier_lot-et-garonne/gallia_villa-lamarque-_yji/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania
Province Description&amp;ndash;&amp;gt; A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location CASTELCULIER
(Pleiades)
House Villa Lamarque
House Description The villa was noted in 1859 but forgotten until a farmer turned up first one and then another marble statue in the 1980’s. Soon afterwards, the prospect of a suburban subdivision over the site led to aerial exploration which, thanks to the fact that the barley growing over the walls turned yellow earlier than the rest of the field, yielded a rather precise plan of the whole villa, shown below. Urgent salvage excavations were undertaken between 1987 and 1998. Materials found are at the Centre de Recherche Archéologique d’Aiguillon, and detailed publication of this vast villa is awaited.
The restoration in the archaeological park covers just the area of the baths and is based on a late empire phase. Particularly noteworthy is the circular caldarium [14]; pieces of the mosaic that covered its dome have been found with fragments of fine gold and images of grapes and grape vines.
Garden Peristyle Garden; Courtyard Garden
Keywords  archaeological garden statues baths natationes peristyles (Roman courtyards) gutters (building drainage components) fountains porticos  Garden Description The baths have been carefully studied by phases, with no less than eight identified. The chronology covers the period from the early empire to the sixth century when the villa was abandoned. The first villa was built at the end of the first century. It was in the form of an L around a large rectangular pool or perhaps natatio with a surrounding gallery. The residential part was to the west. Then around the end of the second or beginning of the third century, the principal peristyle was built with rooms for daily life around it. The peristyle has been only partially excavated and may have contained a garden. An apparently very preliminary, undated report found in the Castelculier library mentioned that the “west” corner of the courtyard had been located and that there the courtyard was paved with concrete to within 20 cm of the walls, where there was a gutter to catch the drip from the peristyle roof. The concrete is obviously not favorable to the hypothesis that the area was a garden. However, the report goes on to note that over the concrete was a 15 cm thick layer dense with rocks, pieces of dressed limestone, and ceramic fragments from late antiquity. This layer might perhaps indicate that planters and statuary would have given the paved part of the courtyard the appearance of a garden. Also, a garden in the center remains a possibility.
In late antiquity, the residence occupied 1.5 hectares and included two vast courtyards. In the one to the south, a peristyle formed the heart of the residence; the monumental entrance of the villa has been identified in its east wing. The precise organization of the two spaces, however, is not known. The northern courtyard, partially excavated, with an entrance porch, brought together the agricultural buildings. A semicircular portico, with a central space that may have been planted, connected the south peristyle to the monumental baths with rooms characteristic of late antiquity. These rooms were several times remodeled.
Plans   Castelculier, Villa de Lamarque. Plan of the excavations (1995) by Ph. Jacques (after Fages 1995 [CAG, 47], 186, fig. 123)     Castelculier, Lamarque. Restored plan of state 1 and state 2 (after Fages 1995 [CAG, 47], 187, fig. 124)   Dates End of 1st Century CE
Excavation Dates 1987-1998
Bibliography  N/A, Gallia informations: préhistorie et historie, 1987-88 n° 1 p. 139-142, 1991, n° 1 p. 89-91. (worldcat) Ph. Jacques, Bilan scientifique, Aquitaine, 1994, p. 88-89 ; 1998 ; 100-103, 1998 (worldcat) Br. Fages, Carte archéologique de la Gaule, (47) Le Lot-et-Garonne, 1995, p. 184-195 (worldcat) Catherine Balmelle, Les demeures aristocratiques d&amp;rsquo;Aquitaine, societe et culture de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquite tardive dans le sou-ouest de la Gaule, Ausonius, supple. d&amp;rsquo;Aquitania 10, Bordeaux 2001, p. 89, 348-351, plan p. 448.. (worldcat) Francis Stephanus and Phillippe Jacques, an undated report on the salvage excavations, found in the library in Castelculier.  Pleiades ID 981505 249936
TGN ID []()
Contributor Clopper Almon (https://www.econ.umd.edu/facultyprofile/almon/clopper)
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>