<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dacia Traiana on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/categories/dacia-traiana/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Dacia Traiana on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 07:56:03 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/categories/dacia-traiana/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Ael(ius) Iul(ius) Iulianus, Decurion in Romula</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/dacia_traiana/romula/romula_tomb_garden_of_aelius_iulius_iulianus_decurion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 07:56:03 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/dacia_traiana/romula/romula_tomb_garden_of_aelius_iulius_iulianus_decurion/</guid>
      <description>Province Dacia Traiana
Province Description Location Romula
Romula (Pleiades)
Garden Tomb Garden of Ael(ius) Iul(ius) Iulianus, Decurion in Romula
Keywords  epitaphs inscription literary garden tombs  Garden Description A slab unearthed near Resça (Romula), Romania, in 1954 records a verse epitaph set up by Valeria Gemellina for her husband Ael(ius) Iul(ius) Iulianus, a decurion of the colony of Romula, some time probably in the later second or third century. In it she describes in pastoral terms well suited to the hexameter the setting of the “eternal home” (i.e. the tomb) she built for him (hanc Iuliano domum flendo fabricavi perennem): “See how Gemellina, along with her children, out of respect for her worthy husband built a resting place for him amidst the vines and shrubbery and the lush grass, where deep shade from an overhanging branch supplies the greenery” (ecce Gemellina pietate ducta marito / struxindolens digno sedem cum liberis una / inter pampinea virgulta et gramina laeta / umbra super rami virides ubi densa ministrat).
Maps Images Dates Later second century/third century
Excavation Dates 1954
Bibliography  AE 1957, 334.  Pleiades ID 981518
TGN ID 8712318
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 12 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dacia Traiana</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/dacia_traiana/dacia_traiana/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 19:24:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/dacia_traiana/dacia_traiana/</guid>
      <description>Province Dacia Traiana
Province Description Dacia occupied the region occupied by today by Romania, Moldava, and parts of Bulgaria, Serbia, Hungary and the Ukraine. Homeland of the Gatae tribe, it was conquered by the Romans under Trajan in 106 CE. After the Romans retreated from this region in 271-275 CE, they renamed an area of Moesia Superior “Dacia Aureliana”. This entry concerns only original province of Dacia.
The area was known to the Romans prior to its conquest, particularly for its position along the Hercynian Forest (Black Forest). Ruled by king Burebista (82–44 BC), Julius Caesar (De Bello Gallico book 6) describes the kingdom in 53 BC starting on the eastern edge of the Hercynian Forest (Black Forest). Strabo, in his Geography (c. 25 CE) writes:
 As for the southern part of Germany beyond the Albis, the portion which is just contiguous to that river is occupied by the Suevi; then immediately adjoining this is the land of the Getae, which, though narrow at first, stretching as it does along the Ister on its southern side and on the opposite side along the mountain-side of the Hercynian Forest (for the land of the Getae also embraces a part of the mountains), afterwards broadens out towards the north as far as the Tyregetae; but I cannot tell the precise boundaries.
 Both rulers were murdered in the same year, and the kingdom was broken into smaller entities. The states of Dacia recognized Rome’s supremacy under Augustus, and interaction is indicated by Augustus’ betrothal of his daughter to Cotiso. Horace (Occidit Daci Cotisonis agmen, Odes, III. 8. 18).
Dacia was of particular interest to the Romans for its supplies of lead, needed for the water pipes of the cities and villas.
Maps Dates 106 CE to 271-275 CE
Pleiades ID 981518
981518
TGN ID 7030323
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
