<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/saint-sever_landes/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:07:01 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/saint-sever_landes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa of Gleyzia d’Augreilh, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/saint-sever_landes/gallia-aquitania_villa-of-gleyzia-daugreilh_j.zhou/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:07:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/saint-sever_landes/gallia-aquitania_villa-of-gleyzia-daugreilh_j.zhou/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_Aquitania Gallia_Aquitania (Pleiades)
Province Description A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location Saint-Sever, Landes
Saint-Sever, Landes (Pleiades)
House Villa of Gleyzia d’Augreilh
House Description This vast villa of at least 2700 square meters was situated on an alluvial terrace (36 m above sea level) on the left bank of the the Adour. It was noted and explored in the 19th century; modern excavation began in 1969 and has continued up to the present under the direction of Dr. Paul Dubedat. Occupation of the site may go back to the early empire, but the main phase of construction was in the fourth or fifth centuries.
The villa is a rare case in domestic architecture of two very large, twin, symmetrically placed peristyles of almost the same size.
Garden Keywords  loam mosaics (visual works) reception rooms  Garden Description The floors of the galleries surrounding all four sides of both peristyles were completely covered with mosaics. The eastern peristyle (31 x 25.5 m) was slightly larger (820 compared to 800 m2) and had geometric and plant motifs such as vines and stalks of acanthus leaves in the mosaics. The western peristyle gave access to baths.
The peristyles look like ideal places for gardens. They were not paved, and the soil throughout the area is rich bottom land. In his book, Dubedat says nothing about the courtyards in Gallo-Roman times; there is currently no direct evidence that they were planted.
Plans Dates The Early Empire
Excavation Dates 19th Century CE Modern excavation began in 1969 CE
Bibliography  Paul Dubedat, Bull.de la société de Borda (Dax), 95, 1970, p.13-31. (worldcat) Paul Dubedat, Bull.de la société de Borda (Dax), 112, 1987, p.312, 356. (worldcat) B. Boyrie-Fénié, CAG, 40, 1994, p.125-134, n°282. (worldcat) Catherine Balmelle, Les demeures aristocratiques d&amp;rsquo;Aquitaine, societe et culture de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquite tardive dans le sou-ouest de la Gaule, Ausonius, supple. d&amp;rsquo;Aquitania 10, Bordeaux 2001, p.407-409, plan p.448. (worldcat)* Paul Dubedat, *La villa gallo-romaine du Gleyzia d’Augreilh et Saint-Pé-de-Mazères*, Princi Negue, Pau, 2003. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 249911
TGN ID Contributor Clopper Almon
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>