<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>epitaph on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/epitaph/</link>
    <description>Recent content in epitaph on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/epitaph/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Monumental Tomb Garden Complex</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_labicana/monumental_tomb_garden_complex/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_labicana/monumental_tomb_garden_complex/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Via Labicana Monumental Tomb Garden Complex
Sublocation Via Labicana
Sublocation Description An ancient Roman road connecting Rome and Labicum.
Garden Monumental Tomb Garden Complex
Keywords  courtyards ditches epitaphs funerary buildings sepulchral monuments tombs  Garden Description Two conjoining fragments of a cut marble slab found in the cemetery of Centocelle at the third mile of the Via Labicana, now in the Palazzo Ducale in Urbino, show part of a plan (not drawn to scale) of a large rectangular funerary garden (546 x 524.5 Roman feet, almost exactly 10 iugera, about 5.8 acres, in area) bounded on at least two sides by a private road that branched off near the end of a longer side to intersect a public thoroughfare 1,783 Roman feet (about 1/3rd of a Roman mile) long, beside which several rectangular tomb plots, some marked with border cippi at the (rear?) corners, are marked off in a reed bed. To judge from the stippling on the stone (incompletely marked on the most frequently reproduced drawing of the plan), a second reed bed occupying a triangular plot between the shorter length of private road and a ditch on the opposite side (a subsecivum) extended perpendicularly from the short side of the triangle at the hypotenuse in a narrow band equal in width to that of the reed bed beside the public road and the private road around the perimeter of the enclosure (see the photograph in Luni, fig. 6). De Rossi believed, on no firm evidence, that the property bounded by the public road and reed bed extending off the top of the plan was productive agricultural land attached to the tomb; if so, the territory was perhaps circumscribed by a band of reedbeds and private roads of uniform width bordering the property. But since we know neither the purpose nor the original extent of the plan, the significance of the undifferentiated area outside the enclosed tomb garden remains a matter of speculation: the only features labeled on the plan are the public road, the ditch, and the stippled reedbeds.
The enclosed tomb garden, accessible only by an entranceway at the upper left corner (according to the orientation of the plan) and by a narrow door next to an aedicular structure outside the enclosure in the lower left of the plan, is characterized by a strict formality of design. The garden proper consists of eight rectangular plots marked with stippling, possibly flower beds or lawns, regularly disposed amid perfectly aligned single or triple rows of equidistant circular dots, probably representing trees. A double row of dots separated from the others along the upper perimeter perhaps represents a pergola or elevated walkway. The lower third of the enclosure is dominated by a large tower-tomb monument (perhaps 15 meters square at the base) apparently similar in form to a mausoleum near S. Maria Capua Vetere sketched by Pirro Ligorio and known as “La Conocchia” (“The Distaff”). The tower-tomb sits in the center of a rectangular courtyard bordered by a single row of trees (interrupted by the rear wall of the tomb) that form an ambulatory around the perimeter. The longest side of the courtyard, along the bottom of the plan, gave access to connecting service rooms aligned perpendicularly behind the shorter sides of the courtyard and, in the lower left, a rectangular aedicular building outside the entrance, possibly a funerary shrine or perhaps the custodian’s quarters.
The plan has been dated as early as the Augustan age (by Huelsen, who favored De Rossi’s fanciful attribution of the tomb complex to “Turia”, fragments of whose well known epitaph were found, similarly cut for reuse in covering loculi, in the same cemetery of Centocelle [cf. CIL 6.37053 with 1527, 31670]), but the scale of the complex and the design of the monument seem more compatible with a date later in the first or second century.
The Centocelle plan provides uniquely valuable, if ambiguous, evidence for the arrangement of the planting and the disposition of the monument within a Roman tomb garden (our other surviving plan of a tomb-garden complex [see Claudia Peloris] focuses on the internal articulation of the buildings), but it can hardly be considered typical: not only is the central monument of a form and type not found elsewhere in the region of Rome (the only known parallel is at Capua), but the size of the plot dwarfs all others known in central Italy and is second in area only to the thirty-five iugera (almost twenty acres) of farm land dedicated by a Roman knight at Parma to supporting his funerary celebrations (see C. Praeconius P.f. Ventilius Magnus). If the round dots do indeed represent trees and the stippled areas flower beds, the size of the area laid out primarily, it seems, for amenity (even if the trees bore fruit and the flowers produced garlands and perfume) is far larger than that of other attested funerary gardens in Italy that served primarily a decorative purpose. Productive funerary gardens of comparable and smaller area that we can identify elsewhere in Rome and Italy were normally equipped with work buildings (aedificia) and retail outlets (bars and shops, tabernae) (see vol. 2, XXX). The spaces on the plan flanking the courtyard and identified as storerooms could well have housed farming and gardening tools, but the footprint of the structure in the lower left corner seems ill-suited to the design of a tavern. More probably a collective monument (perhaps of a funerary collegium) than a familial tomb, the complex raises more questions than it resolves about the characteristic form and function of the Roman tomb garden (see no. XXX, funerary collegium of the Cocceii).
Dates The plan was dated as early as the Augustan age, the scale and design seem more later in the frist or second century.
Bibliography   J. Bodel, Roman Tomb Gardens, Cambridge University Press, 2018, pp. 222-224. link
  Ch. Hülsen, Piante iconografiche incise in marmo, BMDAI(R) 5 (1890): 46-63 worldcat
  H. von Hesberg, Römische Grundrissplane auf Marmor, in Bauplanung und Bautheorie der Antike (Berlin 1984) 121-24;worldcat
  M. Luni, Iscrizioni pubbliche ed iscrizioni relative ad edifici, in 1756-1986. Il Museo Archeologico di Urbino I (Urbino 1986) 167 figs. 6-7. worldcat
  R. Volpe,Cento anni a Centocelle: dal volo di Wilbur Wright ai recenti scavi, in Atti del Convegno Nazionale di Archeologia Aerea “100 anni di Archeologia Aerea in Italia&amp;quot; (Roma 15-17 aprile 2009), Archeologia Aerea 4-5, 2010-2011, pp.41-46. Fig. 3 worldcat
  Pleiades ID 811119037
Contributor John Bodel
Publication date 01 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Anonymous</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_labicana/tomb_garden_of_anonymous/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_labicana/tomb_garden_of_anonymous/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Via Labicana Tomb Garden of Anonymous
Sublocation Via Labicana
Sublocation Description An ancient Roman road connecting Rome and Labicum.
Garden Tomb Garden of Anonymous
Keywords  epitaphs sepulchral monuments tombs  Garden Description A fragmentary marble slab found beside the Via Labicana near the cemetery of Centocelle and recording the end of an epitaph addressed in part to an Aurelius identifies a cepotaphium in the formulaic clause prohibiting misuse or alienation of the tomb property.
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  G.-L. Gregori, Horti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, Bullettino della Commissione Archeologica Comunale di Roma worldcat  Pleiades ID 60995119
Contributor John Bodel
Publication date 01 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Terentia</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_aurelia/tomb_garden_of_terentia/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_aurelia/tomb_garden_of_terentia/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Via Aurelia Tomb Garden of C. Nonius Minyas
Sublocation Via Aurelia
Sublocation Description An ancient Roman road begun ca. 241 B.C. by the censor C. Aurelius Cotta.
Garden Tomb Garden of Terentia
Keywords  epitaphs tombs  Garden Description A fragmentary (and probably reused) epitaph, probably of the first or second century CE, found in the catacombs of Calepodio beside the Via Aurelia identifies a cepota[phium] of Terentia.
Bibliography   J. Bodel, Roman Tomb Gardens, Cambridge University Press, 2018, pp. 225, 237. link
  G.-L. Gregori, Horti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, Bullettino della Commissione Archeologica Comunale di Roma worldcat
  Pleiades ID 283772837
Contributor John Bodel
Publication date 01 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Papias son of Adrastos</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/shamika_ghate/3._attouda_tomb_garden_of_papias_son_of_adrastos/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/asia/shamika_ghate/3._attouda_tomb_garden_of_papias_son_of_adrastos/</guid>
      <description>Province Asia Asia (Pleiades)
Province description The region of what is now modern Turkey became a part of the Roman Empire in 133 B.C. when king Attalos III of Pergamum bequeathed his kingdom to the Roman people. The province included the heartland of the Pergamene kingdom as well as the territories of Mysia, Lydia, Ionia, Caria, western Phrygia and the eastern Aegean islands. Under Augustus in 27 B.C. Asia was declared a senatorial province and the governance of a proconsul. The capital of the province was Ephesos, although Pergamon may have fulfilled this role initially. Under Diocletian (284-305 A.D.) the province was subdivided into smaller administrative units: Hellespontus, Asia, Lydia, Caria, Phrygia I and Phrygia II. Due to its excellent harbors on the west coast and its many navigable rivers, Asia’s water-borne trade with the rest of the Mediterranean flourished. In the second century A.D. Asia experienced great prosperity, to which the growth and architectural aggrandizement of many of its cities attest. In the area of Kibyra, bordering the regions of Lycia, Caria, Phrygia and Pisidia, numerous inscriptions refer to the large imperial estates of Roman families. Woolen textiles, marble, and timber constituted a significant part of the commodities exported from the province.
While the Romans might have looked to the Greeks for inspiration in philosophy, architecture, sculpture, and the fine arts, the non-Greek peoples of the eastern Mediterranean are their inspiration for luxury, fine-living, and the status conferred by displays of individual wealth (Athenaeus Deip. XV.690). Asia was a center for such splendor, first in the kingdoms of Lydia, Phrygia, and Lycia, and then continued by the Persian satraps, and later the Hellenistic kings. The Persian paradeisos is particularly well-attested in literature referencing Asia. That these gardens are known primarily from Roman-period literary sources indicates their continuing influence. For example, long after the gold of Lydia’s Pactolus River had disappeared, Lydia remained a literary topos, not only for copious wealth, but for a life of luxury set in a landscape of natural abundance. Athenaeus (Deipnosophistae 12.515d-f) wrote in the second century A.D. that
&amp;ldquo;The Lydians in their luxury planned parks and made them like gardens and so kept in the shade. For they thought it more dainty not to have the sun’s rays touch them at all…&amp;rdquo;
Other districts of Asia captured the Roman imagination: Pliny the Elder writes of an ancient plane tree (Sycamorus orientalis) in Lycia with a girth of sufficient circumference to house a grotto in its hollow trunk, ornamented with pumice and moss with provisions for 18 people to dine there (Pliny HN 12.9).
The paradeisoi of the Persian satraps are of particular influence on the introduction of horti and gardens of Rome. The paradeisos, from the Persian, paira daeza, or “enclosed place,” is a term that had evolved by the Hellenistic period to mean a large enclosed park with luxurious gardens as well as orchards, collections of trees, crops, and hunting areas (see Sardis below). It was at Sardis that the Greek Lysander visited Cyrus the Younger, a visit recorded by Clearchus and retold by Xenophon. It is an essential moment in garden history recounted for the Romans by Cicero, De Senectute. 17.59. These paradeisoi, in the sense of luxurious orchards, are said by the Romans to have been brought to Greece by Kimon (Aristot. apud Plut. Cim. 10; comp. Cic. de Off. 2.18Plutarch), and were adopted by Hellenistic kings throughout Greece and southern Italy during the late Hellenistic period. The hunting parks at Daskyleion and Celenae are also vividly described by Xenophon (See Anabasis 1.2.7, 2.4.14 and Oeconomicus 4.13). Xenophon also describes how paradeisoi were occupied or cut down by armies during the fourth and third centuries BC. Appreciation for these parks apparently continued, and Seleucus of Syria took over the royal paradeisos at Sardis (Plutarch, Demetrios 50.6). Years of instability followed, so it is difficult to know what the Romans themselves thought of paradeisoi in Asia in the second and first centuries B.C. Notable examples of paradeisoi, in some form, may have been visible to Romans visiting Asia, as well. For example, the Mausoleum at Halicarnassus is now thought by its excavators to have been set in a grove or park.
Thus, the paradeisos, the alsos, the gymnasium, and the quadriporticus are not forms the Romans suddenly “discovered.” They had had a long influence and were integrated into the Hellenistic architectural forms of the Italic landscape. In the second century B.C., however, when the Roman generals began to define themselves as rulers of an empire, they turned directly to the palaces and paradeisoi of the Hellenistic monarchs to establish their power, to display spoils of war, and to create the luxurious setting for life in Rome. They further adapted the evolving quadriporticus form for display to the public Despite the importance of Asia Minor in the history of the Roman landscape, archaeological evidence is scant. The excavators contacted for this essay indicated that parks, gardens, and other planted areas have yet to become a subject of research design for the region and finds appear to be few—primarily inscriptions and wall paintings. Most of the smaller domestic courtyards—often the most manageable to investigate - are paved. The larger palaestrae, gymnasia, and enclosed open spaces have not been investigated for landscape architectural and planting features, although recently an important campaign of work in the South Agora at Aphrodisias is setting an important precedent (see below). This catalog includes areas with dirt and incomplete paved surfaces, and notes sites where the excavators have some level of optimism about fruitful future study. The subject of designed landscapes, gardens, and planted areas in Asia Minor awaits archaeological investigation.
Location Attouda (Pleiades)
Garden Tomb Garden of Papias son of Adrastos
Keywords  marble slab epitaphs  Garden Description A marble slab found immured in a house wall at Hisarköy (Attouda) in Caria near the border with Phrygia records an epitaph set up by Papias, the son of Adrastos, grandson of Zeuxis, great grandson of Kounbarion, for himself and his heirs and sets aside a plot of unencumbered land six cubits square around it, from which it was permitted to derive revenue ([t“] mnhme€ƒ periÒria [di]°[ye]to pÆxiw ©é[ne]pikvlut€, nomØn ka‹ karpe€an énepikvlut€). The modest size of the allotment (less than ten m2) suggests that the productive plot was probably a garden.
Dates 2nd century BC
Bibliography  Monumenta Asiae Minoris Antiquae. Manchester and London, 1928-1993, VI, 83. (worldcat) J. Kubin’ska, Les monuments funéraires dans les inscriptions grecques de l’Asie Mineure. Warsaw, 1968, p. 145. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 638779
TGN ID 7002358
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 24 September 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
