<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>vestibules on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/vestibules/</link>
    <description>Recent content in vestibules on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2020 16:14:15 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/vestibules/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>I.ii.3</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_3/i.ii.3/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2020 16:14:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_3/i.ii.3/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Province Description Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Region I
Sublocation Description Insula Insula ii
House House 3
Garden I.ii.3
Keywords archaeological garden
tufa
vestibules \
viridarium
Garden Description The small viridarium (a) at the rear of the house had narrow, slightly raised beds along the walls on the north and east side. These beds were for the cultivation of flowers, according to Fiorelli. A small vestibule on the north side of the garden was decorated with remnants of tufa columns brought from another site.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Images Dates unspecified
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Descr.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Winden Am See</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/winden_am_see/winden_am_see_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 10:17:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/winden_am_see/winden_am_see_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Pannonia
Province Description Location Winden Am See
Winden Am See (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Winden Am See
Keywords archaeological garden
corridors
rural villas
vestibules
villae rusticae
Garden Description The modest house of this villa rustica is of the so-called corridor type, a type common in the region and already seen at Carnuntum (Fig. 1). It was built around 100 A.D. and occupied until the 4th century.
On the southeast of the house was a vestibule, from which a central corridor departed at a 90 degree angle. This corridor divided the house into two parts of equal width. Two walls at right angles to the house at the northeast enclosed an area in which the excavators found &amp;ldquo;fine garden soil.&amp;rdquo; This observation allows the reconstruction of a garden, probably a kitchen garden, next to the house (G in Fig. 1).
Maps Plans   Fig.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban Houses in Carnuntum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/carnuntum/carnuntum_urban_houses/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 08:57:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/carnuntum/carnuntum_urban_houses/</guid>
      <description>Province Pannonia
Province Description Location Carnuntum
Carnuntum (Pleiades)
Location Description The town of Carnuntum on the Danube River, like Aquincum, was promoted to colonial status in 194 A.D., after having been a municipium. Excavations in the modern zoological garden have revealed part of the town plan and its residential district.
Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Urban Houses in Carnuntum
Keywords arcades (structural assemblies)
archaeological garden
corridors
kitchen gardens
vestibules
Garden Description The regional house type found often in Pannonia, the so-called corridor house, is characterized by a vestibule or arcade on its narrow front and a central corridor running the length of the house, separating it into two parts. One of these houses (B on plan) on a street corner in Carnuntum exhibits this plan clearly (Fig. 1). South of the house, facing the street and separate from it, are various rooms which were interpreted as shops and workshops. North of the house is an open unpaved courtyard which is usually assumed to have been a garden, perhaps a kitchen garden (G on plan).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>