<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iv/houses_5&#43;25/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 14:06:54 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iv/houses_5+25/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>I.iv.5/25 C</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iv/houses_5&#43;25/i.iv.5&#43;25_c/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 14:06:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iv/houses_5&#43;25/i.iv.5&#43;25_c/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula IV
House House 5/25
Garden I.iv.5/25 C
Keywords  archaeological garden columns (architectural elements) exedrae (site elements) gutters (building drainage components) peristyles (columnades) porticoes puteal triclinia vestibules  Garden Description C. The north peristyle garden (f) belonged originally to a house whose entrance was on the Via dell’Abbondanza. It was accessed by a flight of steps from the central peristyle which lies about two meters below. A portico surrounded this garden on the south, east, and most of the north sides. Between the two middle columns on the east side there was a travertine puteal. A large exedra (g) proceeded by a vestibule offered a view of the garden from the west, as did the triclinium (h) from the east. The columns were made of brick and Sarno sandstone and faced with stucco, just like the ones in the central peristyle. They were unfluted except the ones opposite the entrances to the large excedra, the triclinium, and the atrium to the north. A gutter surrounded the garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iv, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 7, p. 29; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12; Niccolini, *Case*, vol.3, “*Topografia*,” pl.8 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates Bibliography  Breton, p. 481. Dwyer, Pomp. Sculpture, pp. 82, 83, 107-108. (worldcat) Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 67.(worldcat) “Giornale dei Soprastanti,” Feb 12-13, 1863. Idem, Desc., pp. 64-65. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 33-32. (worldcat) Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen,” p. 79. Overbeck-Mau, pp. 364-366.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 02 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.iv.5/25 B</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iv/houses_5&#43;25/i.iv.5&#43;25_b/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 14:06:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iv/houses_5&#43;25/i.iv.5&#43;25_b/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula IV
House House 5/25
Garden I.iv.5/25 B
Keywords  altars (religious fixtures) archaeological garden columns (architectural elements) gutters (building drainage components) lychnophoros oeci peristyles (columnades) porticoes puteal statues  Garden Description B. The center peristyle was separated from the south peristyle (d) by a long wall that had six windows and two doors. These offered a grand view into the southern peristyle. In an earlier period this peristyle must have been considered the most important component for each of the six windows corresponded to an intercolumniation in the southern peristyle. The twenty portico columns were fluted above, plain below, and faced with stucco over brick and Sarno limestone. The northeast corner had a portico with a marble puteal. This garden was bounded by a gutter and in this peristyle there was a white marble altar (0.255 high; Mus. Naz. inv. no. 110022). The middle peristyle was supposedly where the famous bronze statue of Apollo playing a cithara (1.58 m. high with base; Mus. Naz. inv. no. 5630; Reusch no. 831) was found on November 8, 1853. It probably came from the southeast corner of the southern peristyle for the middle peristyle was not excavated until five years after the Apollo was found. Niccolini (Case, vol.3, “L’arte” p. 8) was the first to mistakenly report the location where the bronze was discovered. Maiuri thought that the Apollo may have been adapted as a lychnophoros. Several smaller rooms looked out over the garden as well as a large oecus (e) on the east.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iv, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 7, p. 29; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12; Niccolini, *Case*, vol.3, “*Topografia*,” pl.8 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1848, 1853
Bibliography  Baset, p. 492. Brun, BdI (1863), p. 92-93. Döhl, p. 2. Dwyer, Pomp. Sculpture, pp. 79-81, 83-84, 88-89. (worldcat) Fiorelli, Scavi, p. 66.(worldcat) “Giornale dei Soprastanti,” April 7, 1859; 658-688. Idem, Desc., p. 62. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, 1:21-22 and fig. 28 on p. 21. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 31. (worldcat) Lugebil, BdI (1861), p. 261. MB, vol. 15, pl. 33. Maiuri, BdA, n.s. (1926), p. 350. Minervini, BullArchNap, n.s., 2 (Nov. 8, 1853):65. Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “L’arte,” pl. 5. Overbeck-Mau, pp. 363, 544-545. PAH, 2:583 (Nov 8, 1853). 586-587 (Dec. 5, 1853). 670 (Nov. 18, 1868). 671-673 (Nov. 3-Dec. 13, 1858). 685-688 (Sept. 14-Nov.30, 1859). Pernice, p. 30 and pl. 19.4.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 02 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Citharist; Casa Del Citarista; House of L. Popidius Secundus Agustianus and L. Popidus Ampliatus (I.iv.5/25)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iv/houses_5&#43;25/house_of_the_citharist/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 13:04:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_iv/houses_5&#43;25/house_of_the_citharist/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula IV
House House 5/25
Garden House of the Citharist; Casa Del Citarista; House of L. Popidius Secundus Agustianus and L. Popidus Ampliatus (I.iv.5/25)
Keywords  archaeological garden architraves (entablature) basins (vessels) columns (architectural elements) cisterns (plumbing components) fountains gutters (building drainage components) herms oscilla peltae piscinae porticoes predellas puteal statues statuettes (free-standing sculpture) tondi waterspouts  Garden Description A. Excavation took place at this large house intermittently from 1853 to 1869. There were three large parallel, adjacent gardens. A portico, supported by seventeen stuccoed columns made of brick and Sarno limestone, enclosed the center garden (a). The columns were red, fluted at the top and plain at the bottom. A gutter went around the perimeter of the garden. A semicircular basin was located at the west end of the garden around which six spectacular bronze animals were discovered in 1861. The bronzes were as follows: a boar with a fountain spouting from its mouth (0.56 m. high; Mus. Naz. inv. no. 4900); two dogs (0.51 and 0.25 m. high; for boar and dogs); a leaping stag with no trace of fountain fittings (0.61 high; Mus. Naz. inv. no. 4902; Reusch no. 823); a lion with an open mouth, possibly for a fountain, which originally stood on his hind legs (039m. high; Mus. Naz. inv. no. 4897; Reusch no. 820); a serpent with a spout in its mouth (0,51 high; Mus. Naz. inv. no. 4898; Reusch no. 822). The Museo Nazionale was said to have preserve the original placements of the statues. After careful study of this Dwyer concluded that the boar would have stood on the projecting spur of the fountain basin with the dogs attacking his from either side of the rim. The leaping lion would have been next to them and the serpent to their right. The stag would have stood on the rim of the basin at the extreme left. The entire group could have been seen from the large room (b) opening off the west portico, which was lacking one column to facilitate the view. (Eschebach incorrectly included this column on his plan.) Two double herms, each representing Bacchus and Ariadne, were found at the edge of the basin. Dwyer was not able to locate these. There eleven marble oscilla, six circular ones (tondi) (Mus. Naz. inv. nos. 6551, 6642, 6646, 6652, formerly 6667 but now at Pompeii, inv. no. 20486, one with inv. no. unknown). Five had the shape of a pelta (Mus. Naz. inv. no. 6660, 6661, 6664, 6665, formerly 6658 but now at Pompeii, inv. no. 20489). These white marble oscillae each had an iron hook at the top, but no rod, which indicates that were suspended from the architrave between the columns by a cord. Dwyer suggests that the peltae were probably alternated with the round shields. One oscillum had a maenad on one side; the rest had a faun or satyr on each side. A large rectangular pool (3.50 m. wide x 10.80 m. long; 1.40 m. deep) was excavated in February 1926 by Maruri. Two high steps (0.45 m. and 0.40 m.) descended into the pool on the west side. A much smaller semicircular pool had been built around these steps and into the larger pool which had been filled with rubble (Fig. 4). This was probably built after the earthquake when the entrance on the Via dell’Abbondanza was joined to the house. The cistern opening in the southwest corner of the garden had a lave puteal, but the one in the east portico had no puteal. To the northeast of garden (a) there was a large room (c) which contained garden representations painted on the black predella under both of the side panels on the south wall. These were recorded by Spinazzola in drawings (Fig. 4). Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula iv, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 7, p. 29; Fiorelli, *Scavi*, pl. 12; Niccolini, *Case*, vol.3, “*Topografia*,” pl.8 (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I.iv.5,25; 20.4.66, S.A.Jashemski (Rights Statement).     Fig. 4: I.iv.5; 64.25.57, S.A.Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1853-1869, 1926
Bibliography  Baset, p. 26.  Breton, pp. 489-490. Brun, BdI (1863), p. 91. Döhl, pp. 2-3. Dwyer, “Ocilla”, pp. 261-264, nos. 1-11. Elia, MonPittAnt, sec. 3, Pompei, fasc. 1 (1937), p. 4 and fig. 3.  Fiorelli, GiornSc (1861), pp.387, 388, 392-394, 397, 399-400. Fiorelli, Scavi, pp.66-67 and pl. 165, nn. 182-183. (worldcat) Idem, Desc., p. 62. (worldcat) Idem, Pomp. Sculpture,pp. 80-83, 89-97. Jashemski, Gardens, 1:21-22 and figs. 28 and 29 on pp. 21, 22. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, pp. 29–30. (worldcat) Idem, Gardens, vol.II, p. 394. (worldcat) Kapossy, pp. 48, 51, 52. Lugebil, BdI (1861), p. 240. Maiuri, NSc (1931), pp. 575-576. Mau-Kelsey, fig. 181 (plan) on p. 352. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p .79 and pl. 14. Overbeck-Mau, pp. 359-361 and fig. 179 (plan) on p. 360. PPP, 1:10.  PAH, 2: 685-688 (Sept. 17–Nov. 30, 1859). Pernice, p.14 and pl. 8.2. Schefold, WändP, p. 15.  Spinazzola, Scavi nuovi, figs. 646, 647 on p. 654, n. 336. (worldcat) Van Buren, MAAR 10 (1932) pls. I, 2. Ward-Perkins and Claridge, no. 83.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 02 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>