<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>villae rusticae on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/villae-rusticae/</link>
    <description>Recent content in villae rusticae on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 10:39:31 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/villae-rusticae/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Aviary (Maison de la Volière)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/xue_xia/karthago/house-of-the-aviary/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/xue_xia/karthago/house-of-the-aviary/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa Proconsularis Africa proconsularis (Pleiades)
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location Karthago
Karthago (Pleiades)
Location Description Founded by Tyrians from Phoenicia, Carthage became the capital of a powerful empire that came into conflict with the expanding power of Rome. In 146 BC Carthage was completely destroyed and re-founded as a Roman colony by Augustus who completed Cesar’s initial project. Augustus expanded the new city and encouraged settlements of veterans and civilians. The kingdom of Numidia was transformed into a province and Carthage was raised to the rank of capital. The city not only became the major port through which the wealth of the province flowed to Rome but also became a cultural capital that introduced the African elite to the rest of the empire, making it one of the wealthiest and most cosmopolitan cities in the Mediterranean world. Of the Roman period, the city plan is clearly recognizable. The plan takes as its central axis the summit of the acropolis of Byrsa that divided the city into four quarters of equal size except for the one situated to the northwest. The most remarkable monuments found in Carthage are the Baths of Antonius situated on the seashore at the foot of the hill of Borj Jedid and the villas that stretched along the Odeon’s hill. From the Christian era, several basilicas were found. The necropolis that surrounded the city has also provided important information on the city.
Garden House of the Aviary (Maison de la Volière)
Keywords  peristyles (columnades) peristyles (Roman courtyards) mosaics (visual works) cisterns (plumbing components) oeci  Garden Description Located on a hill overlooking Carthage, the house of the aviary is divided into two parts: the unit centered on the peristyle in the west, and the ensemble with the reception room in the east (Plan view, Fig. 1).
In the center of the peristyle in the western part of the house was an octagonal area enclosed by a low wall 50 cm high. P. Gauckler, the original excavator, recognized the area as a viridarium. The Aviary mosaic covers the floor space between the portico and the octagonal garden. In the center of each corner of the mosaic was a deep cavity in which a tree was planted. There was a cistern beneath the peristyle.
In the eastern part of the house, a low wall with six semi-circular niches that alternated with five square-shaped niches faced the oecus bordered by a portico. On the wall was laid out a large pool with small niches bordered on each side by two planters. On a higher level of the pool and the planters were three small cascades decorated with parietal mosaics and paintings depicting hunting and fishing scenes. Water coming from the huge cistern complex on the top of the hill ran through the cascades and fell into the pool. This arrangement can be compared to theater decor where nature is displayed. Hence, the oecus bordered by a portico was facing a frons scaenae composed by a pulpitum behind which were lined up the pool and two planters that could be compared to a proscaenium. The house dates from the end of the IInd-IVth century.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the House the Aviary. (Rights statement)   Images Dates The house dates from the end of the IInd-IVth century.
Bibliography  A. Ennabli, “La Maison de la Volière à Carthage: L’Architecture&amp;rdquo;, p. 132, in Mosaïque, Recueil d’hommage à Henri Stern, Paris, 1983. (worldcat) W. Ben Osman, “Etude des pavements de la Villa de la Volière”, p. 147, in Mosaïque, Recueil d’hommage à Henri Stern, Paris, 1983. (worldcat) Bullo, S. and F. Ghedini, Amplissimae atque ornatissimae domus: l&amp;rsquo;edilizia residenziale nelle citta della Tunisia roman, Rome: Edizioni Quasar, 2003, p. 125-128. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 314921
TGN ID 7016143
Contributor Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Winden Am See</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/winden_am_see/winden_am_see_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 10:17:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/winden_am_see/winden_am_see_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Pannonia
Location Winden Am See
Winden Am See (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Winden Am See
Keywords  archaeological garden corridors rural villas vestibules villae rusticae  Garden Description The modest house of this villa rustica is of the so-called corridor type, a type common in the region and already seen at Carnuntum (Fig. 1). It was built around 100 A.D. and occupied until the 4th century.
On the southeast of the house was a vestibule, from which a central corridor departed at a 90 degree angle. This corridor divided the house into two parts of equal width. Two walls at right angles to the house at the northeast enclosed an area in which the excavators found &amp;ldquo;fine garden soil.&amp;rdquo; This observation allows the reconstruction of a garden, probably a kitchen garden, next to the house (G in Fig. 1).
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the farmhouse with a garden plot (G) enclosed by walls. Adapted from Thomas 1964, fig. 107.(Rights statement.)   Dates 100 AD - 4th century
Bibliography  E.B. Thomas, Römische Villen in Pannonien, Budapest, 1964, pp. 201-210, figs. 107-10. (worldcat) A. Mócsy, Pannonia and Upper Moesia. A History of the Middle Danube Provinces of the Roman Empire, London, 1974, p. 173, fig. 32. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 197425
TGN ID 4008442
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Eisenstadt</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/eisenstadt/eisenstadt_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 09:31:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/eisenstadt/eisenstadt_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Pannonia
Location Eisenstadt
Eisenstadt (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Eisenstadt
Keywords  altars (religious fixtures) archaeological garden atriums peristyles (Roman courtyards) podiums (building divisions) porticoes villae rusticae  Garden Description The residence of this villa rustica was entered on the southeast by a portico (Fig. 1). After passing through a room interpreted as the atrium, one arrived in the open courtyard which had a peristyle on three sides (G on plan). On the northern edge of the courtyard was a podium (P on plan) near which votive altars to Diana and Silvanus were found, both gods of the woods and suitable subjects for a garden. This corner of the courtyard, thus, seems to have had religious character. In the middle of the courtyard was a square foundation, measuring 1.80 x 1.80 m., possibly the remains of a base for some kind of figure. The villa rustica was established in the early 2nd century and occupied probably until the 4th century.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the rural villa with a peristyle courtyard (G) and a podium (P) for sculpture. Adapted from Thomas 1964, fig. 73. (Rights statement.)   Dates Early 2nd century - 4th century
Bibliography  E.B. Thomas, Römische Villen in Pannonien, Budapest, 1964, pp. 137-151, fig. 73. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 197425
TGN ID 7003056
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Winkel-Seeb</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/winkel-seeb/winkel-seeb_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 10:34:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/winkel-seeb/winkel-seeb_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Winkel-Seeb
Winkel-Seeb (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Winkel-Seeb
Keywords  archaeological garden corridors pergolas porticoes terrace gardens villae rusticae well houses  Garden Description The residential and service parts of this villa rustica occupied an area of ca. 7 hectares. The lateral walls of the complex could be followed over a length of 395 meters, but it is assumed that they once extended up to the lake southeast of the farm. The house, measuring 56.70 x 82.40 meters, was of the winged corridor type (Fig. 12.1). The villa rustica was built in the first half of the 1st century A.C. and inhabited until its destruction in 250. The two protruding wings on either side of the entrance on the north extended to the dividing wall between the pars urbana and the pars rustica. These may have been built as covered porticoes or pergolas. The large terraced courtyard between them was possibly laid out as a garden or park (G in Fig. 1). Immediately north of the dividing wall was a well-house.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the rural villa with porticoes enclosing a possible garden (G) in front of the house. Plan adapted from Drack and Fellmann 1988, fig. 511. (Rights Statement)   Dates First half of 1st century A.C. - 250
Bibliography  W. Drack and R. Fellmann, Die Römer in der Schweiz, Stuttgart, 1988, pp. 550-555, figs. 511-512. (worldcat) Ch. Jacquat, Der römische Garten in Seeb, Zürich, 1988. (worldcat) W. Drack, Der römische Gutshof bei Seeb, Gem. Winkel. Berichte der Zürcher Denkmalpflege. Archäologische Monographien 8, Zürich, 1990. (worldcat) M. Carroll, Romans, Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 75, fig. 29. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 177667
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 20 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Wiesbaden-Biebrich</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/wiesbaden-biebrich/wiesbaden-biebrich_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 10:18:48 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/wiesbaden-biebrich/wiesbaden-biebrich_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Wiesbaden-Biebrich
Wiesbaden-Biebrich (Pleiades)
Location Description Biebrich, now part of Wiesbaden, is directly on the right bank of the Rhein south of the center of Wiesbaden.
Garden Rural Villa in Wiesbaden-Biebrich
Keywords archaeological garden \
 kitchen gardens villae rusticae  Garden Description Only the residential part of this farm has been excavated. The house with a width of 22 meters had two protruding wings at the south. To the west of the house was an area of irregular proportions enclosed by a wall, and this has been interpreted as a kitchen garden (G in Fig. 1).
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the rural villa with a possible walled garden (G) to the west. Adapted from Baatz and Herrmann 1989, fig. 471. (Rights Statement)   Dates unspecified
Bibliography  D. Baatz and F.-R. Herrmann, eds., Die Römer in Hessen, 2nd ed., Stuttgart, 1989, p. 495, fig. 471.  Pleiades ID 109461
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 20 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa in Vallon (Sur Dompierre, Canton de Fribourg, Switzerland)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vallon/vallon_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2020 17:12:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vallon/vallon_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Vallon
Vallon (Pleiades)
Garden Villa in Vallon (Sur Dompierre, Canton de Fribourg, Switzerland)
Keywords  arbors barns cisterns (plumbing components) ceramic tile ditches fences (site elements) hearths horrea kitchen gardens mosaics (visual works) orchards pedestals pillars piscinae porticoes sherds tesserae villae rusticae water supply systems  Garden Description Located 6km south-east of Avenches/ Aventicum, the capital of the Helvetian tribe, this site is situated on a small alluvial terrace at the bottom of a hillside. The area is bordered by a stream, the Laret, characterized by a flow, sometimes torrential, that has fluctuated during the past centuries. To the west, on the right bank, stands the rocky spur of Carignan (Fig. 1). Due to the relatively restrictive topography, human settlements favoured the left bank until the Middle Ages.
On the spur east of the stream, a building made of a light structure, apparently isolated, is constructed at the beginning of the 1st c. CE; it is bordered on its southern and northern sides by two roads. During the years 30/40 CE, a peripheral gallery on wooden pillars is placed around it. Its layout rather suggests an annex of a villa rustica or perhaps even a simple house in an urban context. Between 50 and 70 CE, it is surrounded by two other constructions, which together with the first building take on the characteristic shape of an “L”. The northern house is made of several habitation rooms; as it is bordered by a portico, it recalls the dwelling places of the medium-sized villae rusticae discovered in Switzerland. The southern building, surrounded by galleries, is laid out around a 100 m2 large kitchen, containing a large central hearth, which separates, to the south, the rooms designed for habitation, and the areas, to the north, apparently dedicated to utilitarian activities. At the back of the southern construction, a fourth building was erected, a barn (horreum) recognizable because of the network of pillars that supported an elevated floor.
A wall section, placed under a later separating wall, already indicates the existence of a division of the area between the northern and southern parts of the garden. The occupation layer is marked by a number of undated hollow structures. A ditch, boarded on the east by two big oval pits, distinguishes itself by its orientation which is parallel to the front of the central building, but its function still remains unknown: could it be an early garden arrangement? The only palynological analysis undertaken in a trench opened in the north building, suggest a tree canopy composed of a mixture of oaks, birches and hazel trees, in the second half of the 1st century CE; alders and willow trees could be found along the stream banks. An abundance of ferns and conifers grew in the surrounding areas. Herbaceous vegetation was intermingled with cereals. The information in our possession is too scarce to allow us to interpret it as a garden. Traces of equidistant posts or peg holes appear to form the outline of structures that are still difficult to explain (light arbour-like construction?). This open space is confined by a small bank to the south. Below it, the area is crossed by two long perpendicular depressions that could have a natural origin (paleochannel?), re-used as rubbish disposals at the beginning of our era. The south-east oriented channel, originally interpreted as a clay extraction pit, was cleared over a distance of approximately thirty meters. It was seven to eight meters wide, 1,2 meters deep and contained, in its lower part, several conduits made from pine trees (fig. 3). These timber elements were not assembled but stored in a humid environment before being used. The preparation and preservation of wood for plumbing systems, suggests the existence, from the first Antique settlements, of a very elaborate running water supply system, its use in domestic and/or handicraft or farming activities still needs to be clarified. Dendrochronology reveals two time series, dated to the autumn/winter 3/4 CE and 32/33 CE. These dates, that are contemporary with the first building stages of the villa, are very early for Switzerland and are close to Avenche’s first dated constructions.
The edges of the channel, which are gradually filled in, are bordered by two small fences in the last quarter of the Ist century; these fittings may be the result of a wish to stabilize the banks of the channel, clearly still under water at that time. Later on, the channel is filled in by a new rubbish disposal that seals the fences. We know nothing about the appearance of the area (courtyard or garden?) which extended between the channel and the southern building.
The profound architectural developments that took place in the three habitation buildings from the years 150/160 CE, had repercussions on the gardens (fig. 2). The occupation layer of the courtyards to the west of the buildings is raised by bringing in a large amount of ballast material. The subdivision of the garden zone is not precisely known. To the west of the constructed area, in the northern area bordered by the waterway, a pedestal indicates the presence of a statuary decoration that will be removed by the next generation. A long masonry wall, decorated with pillars presumably sculpted, is the only partition element brought to light. It marks the boundaries of an area interpreted as an ornamental garden, onto which the northern building and the northern part of the central building open. Divided into two zones, the oriental part of the northern garden is covered with tiles, revealing in its northern corner a fountain; it is replaced, in its western part, by soil around which a fence was probably built. It communicates directly with a second ornamental garden situated on the side of the central building, maybe destined for the private use of the family and close relatives. Here too, the remains are sparse: a patch stretches along the separation wall with the northern garden. A path followed the central building. Others must have crossed beds of plants edged with vertical ceramic elements. In other places, wooden posts formed rows that are still difficult to elucidate but that may indicate the outline of arbours. In the same place were found meander shaped ditches which do not follow the exact same orientation as the buildings (fig. 4). Were they hedges that were part of a vegetal maze? Despite the absence of palynological facts, they can be compared to the ditches excavated in the gardens of the Fishbourne Villa (England) or to those in the pars urbana of Dietikon’s villae (canton of Zurich).
At the end of the first archaeological excavations (1985-2000), we favoured the hypothesis of a subdivision of the area to the west of the buildings into three juxtaposed courtyards which echoed the tripartition of the constructions. They contained two ornamental gardens, in the north and in the center, and a courtyard that sheltered a kitchen garden and an orchard at the front of the southern building, dedicated to utilitarian activities (fig. 5). The recent research does not support a division of the area into three distinctive courtyards (2006/2010). The second garden, which presents a regular incline to the south, does not show any tangible boundary. Did it occupy the whole area in the front of the south building, or were they garden arrangements (hedges) dividing it? (fig. 6) Traces of vegetation being very hard to spot on the surface of the ground of the gardens, no definitive conclusion can be drawn.
The recent discovery of the lower part of a pool in front of the south building has also casts doubts on its utilitarian function. The structure itself, laid on a foundation of stakes made from oak and alder wood dated by dendrochonology to the years after 160 CE, has been almost entirely retrieved. The interpretation of this structure is still under discussion: it could be a cistern but it is more likely to be an ornamental pool that could have been enhanced by a parietal mosaic composed of the many glass tesserae that were found nearby. The structure, standing against the south building, would be oriented not towards the construction itself, but towards the courtyard where no garden arrangement has been uncovered.
Whereas the courtyards have offered very few traces for the Early Roman Period, the Late Antique Period marks a turning point in the history of Vallon’s gardens. Following a fire, the buildings are reorganized and areas dedicated to handicraft activities appear in the porticoes. A new function is attributed to the courtyards. The rubble of the partially demolished north and central buildings is discarded in the northern garden and the northern part of the second courtyard. To the south of themeander shaped ditches, is built a construction consisting of posts and sill plates, equipped with a ground hearth made out of ceramic tiles. The late occupation of the gardens seems to be linked to the salvage and transformation of building materials collected in the edifices. Other post structures (constructions? enclosures?) almost cover the whole area in the front of the southern building. The archaeological objects found (pottery fragments, over a hundred coins) suggest that this occupation partly covers the IVth century and does not go further than the beginning of the Vth century.
After the disappearance of the Antique site, the land continues to be occupied during the Early Middle Ages. The discovery of channels supports the hypothesis that the areas between the new buildings or on their sides, were well enough built to see the creation of an ornamental garden. However, the remains are too disrupted to allow further discussion.
Maps   Fig. 1: Vallon location map. (Rights Statement)     Fig. 2 : map of the habitation zone in the second half of the IInd century of our era.(Rights Statement)   Images   Fig. 3 : pine wood conduits preserved in one of the channels. Photo Fribourg State Archaeological Service. (Rights Statement)     Fig. 4 : ditches uncovered in the courtyard in front of the central building (2006). Photo Fribourg State Archaeological Service. (Rights Statement)     Fig. 5 : scale model of the habitation area in the second half of the IInd century. Built before the research in the gardens was resumed, it presents a considerable partitioning of the various open spaces. Photo Fribourg State Archaeological Service. (Rights Statement)     Fig. 6 : watercolour of the habitation area integrating the first results obtained by excavating the gardens. Please note the less significant partition between the different courtyards. The cistern at the front of the south building (to the right) is highly hypothetical; it seems rather to be an ornamental pool. Watercolour: Bernard Reymond, Yverdon-les-Bains (Switzerland). (Rights Statement)   Dates Beginning of the 1st c. CE - beginning of the Vth century
Excavation Dates 1985-2000, 2006/2010
Bibliography No bibliography listed Pleiades ID 981525
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor Michel Fuchs (ORCID: 0000-0001-8176-8393)
Jacques Monnier (ORCID: N/A)
Publication date 18 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Orbe</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/orbe/orbe_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2020 13:44:42 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/orbe/orbe_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Orbe
Orbe (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Orbe
Keywords archaeological garden \
 corridors terrace gardens villae rusticae  Garden Description This large palatial house belonged to a villa rustica revealed by excavation and aerial photography. The enclosed farmyard is calculated to have been approximately 420 x 650 meters in size. The house itself, built in the mid-1st century AD and in use until the 4th century, was 200 meters long (Fig. 1). This winged corridor house had two large open courtyards between the protruding wings at the front. These were very likely gardens (G in Fig. 1). Twenty-five meters in front of the house at the east was a long terrace wall 400 meters long running north-south. There may have been gardens or a park (G in Fig. 1) between the house and this terrace wall.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the rural villa (A) with two large courtyard gardens (G) and a possible walled garden (G) to the east of the main house. The dotted lines are structures known only from aerial photography. Adapted from Drack and Fellmann 1988, fig. 423. (Rights Statement)   Dates House: mid-1st century CE - 4th century
Bibliography  D. Weidmann, &amp;ldquo;L&#39;établissement romain d&amp;rsquo;Orbe/Boscéaz,&amp;rdquo; Archäologie der Schweiz 2, 1978: 84-86. (worldcat) W. Drack and R. Fellmann, Die Römer in der Schweiz, Stuttgart, 1988, pp. 463-465, figs. 422-423. (worldcat) R. Fellmann, La Suisse gallo-romaine. Cinq siècles d’histoire, Lausanne, 1992, pp. 152-153, fig. 112. (worldcat) Th. Luginbühl, J. Monnier, Y. Dubois, Vie de palais et travail d’esclave. La villa romaine d’Orbe-Boscéaz. Document du Musée cantonal d’archéologie et d’histoire, Lausanne, 2001, pp. 34-36, 53-55, figs. 28-29, 40, 49-51. [(worldcat)](Vie de palais et travail d’esclave. La villa romaine d’Orbe-Boscéaz)  Pleiades ID 177598
TGN ID 7007438
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 17 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Oberentfelden</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/oberentfelden/oberentfelden_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 17:46:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/oberentfelden/oberentfelden_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Oberentfelden
Oberentfelden (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Oberentfelden
Keywords  archaeological garden bathhouses (water recreation structures) kitchen gardens nymphaea (garden structures) peristyles (columnades) villae rusticae  Garden Description The enclosed area of this villa rustica was 160 meters wide and at least 460 meters long; the eastern limits of the complex have not yet been found. The main residence and bath complex (A and B in Fig. 1), dating to the beginning of the 2nd century, stood on sloping land eight meters higher than the rest of the farmyard. At the eastern end of the service area (pars rustica) was a large peristyle building with a nymphaeum at the western end (D in Fig. 1). The open courtyard within this peristyle may have been a garden. Small kitchen gardens have been reconstructed between the various outbuildings and smaller houses (C in Fig. 1) in the pars rustica. Gardens here are possible, but it remains a matter of speculation whether these areas were actually planted.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the rural villa (A) with a bath (B), a nymphaeum (D) and various outbuildings and houses (C). Plan adapted from Drack and Fellmann 1988, fig. 418.   Dates 2nd century
Bibliography  W. Drack and R. Fellmann, Die Römer in der Schweiz, Stuttgart, 1988, pp. 457-459, fig. 418. (worldcat) R. Fellmann, La Suisse gallo-romaine. Cinq siècles d’histoire, Lausanne, 1992, pp. 152, 154, fig. 105. (worldcat) M. Carroll, Romans, Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 75, fig. 34. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 177596
TGN ID 8703779
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 17 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Hummetroth</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/hummetroth/hummetroth_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 11:47:11 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/hummetroth/hummetroth_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Hummetroth
Hummetroth (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Hummetroth
Keywords  apsed triclinium bathhouses (water recreation structures) corridors hypocausts porticoes reception rooms terrace gardens villae rusticae  Garden Description The enclosed farmyard, including the residential area (pars urbana) and the service zone with outbuildings and working areas (pars rustica), covered an area of 3.5 hectares. The house of this villa rustica of the 2nd century is of the winged corridor type with two protruding wings framing a large courtyard in front of the house at the south (Fig. 1).
The courtyard was divided into two zones by a terrace(?) wall, and in both zones a garden has been reconstructed (G in Fig. 1). Entering the house from the south, one passed through a large reception room to an apsed triclinium with hypocaust heating. A bath complex lay to the southwest, entered by the portico next to the garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the rural villa with a large terraced courtyard garden (G) to the south. Plan adapted from Baatz and Herrmann 1989, fig. 303a.   Dates 2nd century
Bibliography  D. Baatz and F.-R. Herrmann, eds., Die Römer in Hessen, 2nd ed., Stuttgart,1989, pp. 360-361, fig. 303a-b. (worldcat) M. Carroll, Romans,Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 74, fig. 29. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981525
TGN ID 7165467
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 16 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Friedberg Pfingstweide</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/friedberg-pfingstweide/friedberg-pfingstweide_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 18:12:31 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/friedberg-pfingstweide/friedberg-pfingstweide_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Friedberg Pfingstweide
Friedberg Pfingstweide (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Friedberg Pfingstweide
Keywords  archaeological garden bathhouses (water recreation structures) villae rusticae  Garden Description This villa rustica was situated on the northern slope of a valley through which a stream ran. The enclosed area of the farm occupied an area of 3.4 hectares (180 x 190 meters), and it was divided into a residential part (pars urbana) and a service area (pars rustica) by a road running east-west (Fig. 1). The front of the house (H in Fig. 1) faced north and had a view of the valley and the lower lying service area of the farm.
Built in the early 2nd century, the house was of the winged corridor type with a large open courtyard enclosed by the protruding wings of the house. The courtyard was divided into two zones that were possibly gardens (G in Fig. 1) and have been reconstructed as such. The farm was destroyed by fire in the first half of the 3rd century.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the villa (H) with a bath building (B) and with two possible garden enclosures (G) joined to the house at the north. Adapted from Baatz and Herrmann 1989, fig. 246.   Dates Early 2nd century - first half of 3rd century
Bibliography  D. Baatz and F.-R. Herrmann, eds., Die Römer in Hessen, 2nd ed., Stuttgart, 1989, pp. 307-309, fig. 246. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981525
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 16 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Ferpicloz</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ferpicloz/ferpicloz_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 15:32:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ferpicloz/ferpicloz_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Ferpicloz
Ferpicloz (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Ferpicloz
Keywords archaeological garden \
 porticoes villae rusticae  Garden Description The house of this villa rustica was of the winged corridor type (A in Fig. 1) with a porticoed facade (Fig. 1). Attached to the eastern end of the house, measuring 37 x 46 meters, was a wall running east-west which has been interpreted as the protective wall of a garden (G in Fig. 1).
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the rural villa (A) with a possible garden (G) protected by a wall to the east of the main building. The shoreline of the lake is dotted. Adapted from Drack and Fellmann 1988, fig. 369. (Rights Statement)   Dates unspecified
Bibliography  W. Drack and R. Fellmann, Die Römer in der Schweiz, Stuttgart, 1988, pp. 394-395, fig. 369. (worldcat) R. Fellmann, La Suisse gallo-romaine. Cinq siècles d’histoire, Lausanne, 1992, p. 157, fig. 116.3. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981525
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 15 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Dietikon</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/dietikon/dietikon_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 13:09:50 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/dietikon/dietikon_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Dietikon
Dietikon (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Dietikon
Keywords  archaeological garden axial plan corridors pergolas piscinae porticoes villae rusticae  Garden Description This villa rustica complex was built on a site at the bottom of a valley near and parallel to the river Limmat. Dietikon was situated on an important land and water traffic route from the Bündner Alps to Vindonissa and further north to the Rhine. Recent excavations supply valuable evidence for a garden in front of the entrance to a rural residence, giving insight into the appearance of other similar villas at which, for one reason or another, no physical remains of gardens have been retrieved. The excavations revealed a first villa with timber buildings dating to the Tiberian period, or early 1st century AD. Around the middle of the 1st century AD these first buildings were replaced by an axially-constructed stone-built villa complex with an enclosure, covering a total surface of 13 hectares (Fig. 1 and 4).
In the residential part of the farm (pars urbana) was a large corridor villa with two protruding wings enclosing a courtyard area on three sides. This area was planted as an ornamental garden in the mid-1st century (Fig 2, G in Fig. 2). On either side of the central path, garden zones were bordered by bedding trenches, 20-25 centimeters deep and 20-40 centimeters wide. The line of plantings flanking the path are curved to form two niches (Fig. 3). In Dietikon, digging of planting trenches would have been necessary because the massive layers of construction debris deposited to level this area for the building would have hampered a successful growing of garden plants. The archaeobotanical analysis of several soil samples revealed little of relevance, but box hedges have been suggested as the vegetation in the bedding trenches, forming a low living edge to these formal garden beds, and possibly climbing plants such as ivy along the porticoed façade. Shallow pits in the plots surrounded by the hedges may be the remains of bedding pits for trees or shrubs. A timber pergola in the courtyard ran parallel to the northeast wing of the house. To the west of the courtyard garden was a timber-lined pool fed by a stream, interpreted as a fishpond. Bedding trenches for hedges surrounded it.
In the late 1st century, around AD 70, the timber-lined pool in the west was replaced by a masonry pool lined with water-proof plaster on the same spot (Fig. 5). This was possibly fed by water from a small stream. At the same time, the timber pergola was dismantled, its place taken by a large masonry pool, 3 x 22 meters in plan. The planting pattern of the courtyard garden was retained (Fig. 5) until after the middle of the 2nd century when the pools were destroyed and the garden leveled.
Plans   Fig. 1: Overall plan of the site during the 2nd half of the 1st century and 1st half 2nd century AD. Plan courtesy of Christa Ebnöther.     Fig. 2: Plan of the main building with its garden, phase 1, ca. 50-70 AD. Plan courtesy of Christa Ebnöther.     Fig. 3: Plan of the main building showing the curved plantings flanking the path. (Rights Statement)   Images   Fig. 4: Reconstructed perspective drawing. (Rights Statement)     Fig. 5: Photo of the masonry pool with planting pattern of the courtyard garden retained. (Rights Statement)   Dates Garden: Late 1st century (~70 CE) - Middle of the 2nd century
First buildings: Early 1st century CE - Middle of 1st century CE
Stone-built villa: Middle of the 1st century CE
Bibliography  C. Ebnöther, &amp;ldquo;Die Gartenanlage in der pars urbana des Gutshofes von Dietikon ZH,&amp;rdquo; Archäologie der Schweiz 14, 1991:250-256. (worldcat) C. Ebnöther, Der römische Gutshof in Dietikon. Monographien der Kantonsarchäologie Zürich 25, Zürich, 1995, pp. 36-45, 49-50, figs. 21, 36-37,41-42. (worldcat) L. Flutsch, U. Niffeler, F. Rossi, eds., La Suisse du Paléolithique à l’aube du Moyen-Age (SPM) V. Epoque romaine/Età Romana, Basel, 2002, p. 143, fig. 140. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981525
TGN ID 7007345
Contributor Christa Ebnöther
Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 15 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Bad Kreuznach</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/bad_kreuznach/bad_kreuznach_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 12:39:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/bad_kreuznach/bad_kreuznach_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Bad Kreuznach
Bad Kreuznach (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Bad Kreuznach
Keywords  apsed triclinium colonnades cryptoportici fountains gutters (building drainage components) lararia mosaics (visual works) peristyles (Roman courtyards) porticoes villae rusticae  Garden Description This villa, almost 6000 square meters in size, gives eloquent testimony to the wealth and status of the owner of the rural estate. The estate was built in the second half of the 2nd century and occupied until its destruction around 275.
The three-storied villa with more than 50 rooms on the ground floor alone, many decorated with mosaics and imported marble revetment, was centered on a colonnaded garden courtyard (G in Fig. 1). Many of the sandstone columns from the peristyle, as well as fragments of sculpture from the garden, were found in the courtyard. The house was built into a hill, and the courtyard was terraced on two levels. Around the edges of the garden was a ground level gutter. From the apsed triclinium on the south, with a mosaic floor and a marble fountain in the middle, there was an excellent view of the garden.
At the northeast of the villa was a garden (G in Fig. 1) with a lararium. On the southwest there was a garden (G in Fig. 1) with a fountain. The northern facade had a cryptoporticus below and a porticoed corridor on the story above. The service area of the villa rustica lay in front of the villa to the north.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the rural villa with gardens (G) in the central courtyard and in the corners of the house. Plan adapted from Cüppers 1990, fig. 204.(Rights statement)   Dates Second half of 2nd century - around 275
Bibliography  G. Rupprecht, &amp;ldquo;Die Kreuznacher Mosaikbodenvilla. Kurzbericht (Stand: April 1977),&amp;rdquo; Saalburg Jahrbuch 34, 1977:78-87. G. Rupprecht, &amp;ldquo;Leben auf dem Land,&amp;rdquo; Archäologie in Deutschland 4, 1986: 36-39. (worldcat) Heinz Cüppers, Die Römer in Rheinland-Pfalz, Stuttgart, 1990, pp.321-323, fig. 204. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981525
TGN ID 7012371
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 15 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural villa at Voerendaal</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/voerendaal/voerendaal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:58:07 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/voerendaal/voerendaal/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Province Description Location Voerendaal
Voerendaal (Pleiades)
Garden Rural villa at Voerendaal
Keywords  villae rusticae porticoes piscinae hedges courtyards  Garden Description The stone-built structures of this villa rustica near the Meuse river, the largest excavated thus far in the Netherlands, were erected in the early 2nd century and repeatedly enlarged until the abandonment of the farm around 300 A.D. (Plan 1). The total area of the farm, including the cultivated land, is calculated to have been ca. 150 hectares. The main residence (A on plan) lay in the northern half of the complex which measured 167 x 214 m. (3.5 hectares) in size. The porticoed facade in its final state was 190 m. long.
In front of the house to the south was a large area (17 x 37 m.), enclosed by a stone wall on two sides and villa porticoes on the other sides. This has been interpreted as a formal garden (G on plan) with low plantings, hedges and a pool (P on plan; Image 1 [NO IMAGE INCLUDED]). The main road leading from the gate in the south to the house in the north cut through this enclosed area. The excavators postulate a vegetable garden behind the house for easy, daily access. The boundaries of the farm complex were planted with a row of trees or a hedge, the planting pits of which had survived. The many carbonized grains of wheat and chaff found in and around a large building in the northeastern part of the courtyard enclosure suggest that wheat grown in the fields of the farm was processed here. The main crop at Voerendaal was spelt; very little emmer or bread wheat was present in the organic remains.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the rural villa with a possible walled garden (G) and its pool (P) south of the house (A). Hedges (rows of dots) enclosed the farmyard. Adapted from Willems 1992, Fig. 307. (Rights statement).   Images Dates Early second century CE to ca. 300 CE
Bibliography  W.J.H. Willems, &amp;ldquo;Die kaiserzeitliche Villa von Voerendaal&amp;rdquo;, in Spurensicherung. Archäologische Denkmalpflege in der Euregio Maas-Rhein, Mainz, 1992, pp. 526-534, figs. 307-308. worldcat P. Van Ossel, Établissements ruraux de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquité tardive dans le nord de la Gaule, Paris, 1992, pp. 363-365, fig. 155. worldcat  Pleiades ID 109442
TGN ID 7272601
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rustic villa at Rheinbach-Flerzheim</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/rheinbach-flerzheim/rheinbach-flerzheim/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:57:12 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/rheinbach-flerzheim/rheinbach-flerzheim/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Province Description Location Rheinbach-Flerzheim
Garden Rustic villa at Rheinbach-Flerzheim
Keywords  villae rusticae hedges bathhouses (water recreation structures) kitchen gardens piscinae  Garden Description There was no division between the residential and service parts of this modest farm. The house, with its bath (A and B on plan), and the outbuildings were built of stone at the beginning of the 2nd century (Plan 1). The winged corridor type house of this villa rustica was 37 m. long and 20 m. wide, and it had a bath attached to the back.
Enclosing the farm complex was a hedge or row of trees, the planting trenches of which were uncovered in excavations (gray wavy border on plan). Based on the palaeobotanical evidence of carbonised plant remains and pollen, a kitchen garden near the house and fruit trees on the property have been reconstructed. In front of the entrance to the main residence at the south were the remains of a small pool lined with clay. This has been taken as evidence for an ornamental garden surrounding the pool. On a farm of this modest size and simplicity, however, an ornamental garden seems rather unlikely. The farm was occupied until the mid-5th century.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the farmyard with its house (A) and bath (B) enclosed by a hedge (grey line). The open circles are wells. Adapted from Carroll 2001, fig. 38. (Rights statement).   Images Dates Second century CE to mid-fifth century CE
Bibliography  M. Gechter, &amp;ldquo;Der römische Gutshof von Rheinbach-Flerzheim,&amp;rdquo; in Spurensicherung. Archäologische Denkmalpflege in der Euregio Maas-Rhein, Mainz, 1992, pp. 249-54, 452-60. worldcat M. Carroll, Romans, Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 79, fig. 38. worldcat  Pleiades ID 981524
TGN ID 7192890
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 25 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Niederzier Hambach 59</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/niederzier-hambach/niederzier-hambach59/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:55:45 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/niederzier-hambach/niederzier-hambach59/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Province Description Location Niederzier-Hambach
Niederzier-Hambach (Pleiades)
Location Description In the Hambacher Forst region, which lies approximately 30-35 km. west of the former capital city Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium (mod. Cologne), a number of modest villae rusticae have been excavated.
Garden Niederzier Hambach 59
Keywords  villae rusticae ditches fences (site elements) hedges water wells orchards cherry (plant)  Garden Description This farm, known as Hambach 59, was built in the late 1st century A.D. and inhabited until its destruction in the 4th century (Plan 1). The farmhouse, 19.50 x 26 m. in size (A on plan), occupied a position in the northern part of the complex, and looked out on the rest of the farm to the south where various outbuildings and stables stood. There was no division between the residential part and the service area of the farm.
The farmyard was enclosed by a hedge (dotted lines on plan) and took up an area of approximately 1.5 hectares. Outside of the enclosed farmyard to the north were four large plots, presumably for orchards and cultivated fields, which were marked off by ditches or fences (outlined in black on plan). Two of these plots were approximately one hectare in size. The reconstruction of the vegetation on the farm is based on the palaeobotanical analysis of deposits from the four wells in front of the house. The material includes charred fruits and seeds as well as unburnt plant remains and pollen. Cherry pits are evidence for sweet cherry trees. Oak pollen, as well as the water-logged remains of the buds and bud scales of the oak tree, suggest that a shady oak may have grown near one of the wells in the courtyard. Walnut pollen was found in such large quantities in the wells, that one can safely assume the presence of walnut trees near the house. The same applies for lime trees attested by their pollen in the sediments. The remains of coriander and linseed in the wells suggest that these plants may have grown in the vegetable garden in the immediate vicinity of the house. The hedge surrounding the farm compound may have consisted of a combination of hazelnut, elderberry, raspberry and brambleberry, which were all present as pollen, shells, and seeds in the sediments. Box is attested by the pollen in the wells, but it is uncertain where this plant grew on the site.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the farm with hedges (dotted lines) and fences (solid lines) enclosing orchards, fields and the farmyard with its house (A). Plan adapted from Gaitzsch 1990, fig. on p. 238. (Rights statement).   Images Dates Late first century CE until the fourth century CE.
Bibliography  W. Gaitzsch, &amp;ldquo;Der römische Gutshof im &amp;lsquo;Gewährhau’ bei Niederzier,&amp;rdquo; in H. Hellenkemper, H. Koschik and B. Trier, eds., Archäologie in Nordrhein-Westfalen, Cologne, 1990, pp. 235-41. worldcat K.-H. Knörzer and J. Meurers-Balke, &amp;ldquo;Die Wirtschafts- und Nutzflächen eines römischen Gutshofes,&amp;rdquo; in H. Hellenkemper, H. Koschick and B.Trier, eds., Archäologie in Nordrhein-Westfalen, pp. 242-46. worldcat W. Gaitzsch, &amp;ldquo;Antikes Landleben im Modell einer villa rustica,&amp;rdquo; Archäologie im Rheinland 1990, Cologne, 1991, pp. 46-49.  Pleiades ID 109210
TGN ID 7128518
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 24 July 2020
Related articles Niederzier-Hambach 69.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Niederzier Hambach 69</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/niederzier-hambach/niederzier-hambach69/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:55:45 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/niederzier-hambach/niederzier-hambach69/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Province Description Location Niederzier-Hambach
Niederzier-Hambach (Pleiades)
Location Description In the Hambacher Forst region, which lies approximately 30-35 km. west of the former capital city Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium (mod. Cologne), a number of modest villae rusticae have been excavated.
Garden Niederzier Hambach 69
Keywords  villae rusticae fences (site elements) ditches hedges kitchen gardens orchards water wells cherry (plant)  Garden Description This villa rustica was situated west of Cologne in the same region as Hambach 59. It was built in the late 1st century A.D. and inhabited until the 4th century (Plan 1). The farm had a calculated overall area, including the cultivated land, of 50 hectares. The farm compound itself was one hectare in size. The modest house (A on plan) stood just inside the western border of the complex. Elsewhere on the property were various stables, barns, a pond and several wells.
To the east of the house was an area marked off by a narrow ditch (B on plan). This was probably a bedding trench for a protective hedge around a vegetable garden (G on plan). Palaeobotanical material, all of it carbonized, from deposits in wells and pits provide information on the field crops. Considerable amounts of charred chaff in a well in the eastern part of the farmyard suggest that a threshing area for the grain grown on the farm may have been situated near the well. The botanical remains indicate that spelt wheat was the main crop, followed by barley. The farmyard has hedge borders, the planting trenches for which were excavated. Within this area, fruit trees, oaks and alders as well as elderberry bushes possibly were planted.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the farm house (A) and the farmyard enclosed by a hedge (grey line). A vegetable garden (G) may have lain within another hedge (B). Adapted from Gaitzsch 1986, fig. 5. (Rights statement).   Dates Late first century CE until the fourth century CE.
Bibliography  K.-H. Knörzer, &amp;ldquo;Veränderungen der Unkrautvegetation auf rheinischen Bauernhöfen seit der Römerzeit,&amp;rdquo; Bonner Jahrbuch 184, 1984: 491-503. worldcat W. Gaitzsch, &amp;ldquo;Grundformen römischer Landsiedlungen im Westen der CCAA,&amp;rdquo; Bonner Jahrbuch 186, 1986: 397-427, fig. 5. worldcat  Pleiades ID 109210
TGN ID 7128518
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 24 July 2020
Related articles Niederzier-Hambach 59.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa at Neerhaaren-Rekem</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/neerhaaren-rekem/neerharen-rekem/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:54:58 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/neerhaaren-rekem/neerharen-rekem/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Neerhaaren-Rekem
Neerhaaren-Rekem (Pleiades)
Garden Rural villa at Neerhaaren-Rekem
Keywords- rural villas  villae rusticae arbors pergolas piscinae  Garden Description The facade of this modest house of a villa rustica near the Meuse river measured 24 m. in length and had two protruding wings joined by a portico (Plan 1). The house was built in the late 1st century A.D. There is evidence for an arbor or pergola next to the house in the form of two rows of postholes arranged diagonally and converging in front of the entrance on the west (circles on plan). Between the rows of posts, each measuring ca. 15 m. in length, and around which some kind of vines or other climbing plants may have been trained to grow, was a small pool.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the farm house at Neerhaaren-Rekem with a possible arbor leading to the door and a pool (grey) between the posts of the arbor. Plan adapted from De Boe, De Bie and Van Impe 1992, fig. 288. Rights statement.   Images Dates Late first century CE
Bibliography  G. De Boe, M. De Bie, and L. Van Impe, &amp;ldquo;Heerharen-Rekem. Die komplexe Besiedlungsgeschichte einer vor den Kiesbaggern geretteten Fundstätte,&amp;rdquo; in Spurensicherung. Archäologische Denkmalpflege in der Euregio Maas-Rhein, Mainz, 1992, pp. 490-493, fig. 288. worldcat P. Van Ossel, Établissements ruraux de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquité tardive dans le nord de la Gaule, Paris, 1992, pp. 297-300, fig. 105. worldcat  Pleiades ID 109193
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Sudeley/Spoonley Wood</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/sudeley/sudeley_spoonley_wood_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 18:57:34 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/sudeley/sudeley_spoonley_wood_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Sudeley/Spoonley Wood
Sudeley/Spoonley Wood (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Sudeley/Spoonley Wood
Keywords  archaeological garden axial plan terrace gardens rural villas villae rusticae  Garden Description The main residence of this rural estate in Gloucestershire, excavated in 1882, is of the winged corridor type (Fig. 1). From the north and south corners of the house, walls ran in a westerly direction to enclose an open courtyard (G in Fig. 1) approximately 65 meters wide and 45 meters deep from the outer boundary to the main entrance of the house. A paved path was axially arranged in the courtyard to connect the entrance to the courtyard with that of the residential building. The western third of the courtyard is marked off by low scarps which may be remains of garden terraces (T in Fig. 1). Finds from the site indicate a 3rd/4th century date for the complex.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the villa with a path (stippled) leading through a courtyard garden (G) and garden. (Rights statement)   Images Dates 3rd/4th century for the complex.
Excavation Dates 1882
Bibliography  Ancient and Historical Monuments in the County of Gloucester Vol. 1. Royal Commission on Historical Monuments of England, London, 1976, pp. 113-114, fig. on p. 114. (worldcat) C. Taylor, The Archaeology of Gardens. Shire Archaeology Series 30, Aylesbury, 1983, pp. 30-31, fig. 1. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 79693
TGN ID 7030316
Contributor Maureen Carroll
ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Byzantine Law Court and Roof Garden</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/judaea/caesarea_maritima/byzantine_law_court_and_roof_garden/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/judaea/caesarea_maritima/byzantine_law_court_and_roof_garden/</guid>
      <description>Province Judaea
Iudaea (province) (Pleiades)
Province Description Judaea, the Roman province, included parts of the areas of the Hasmonean and Herodium kingdoms, notably Biblical Judah, Samaria, and Edom. Its capital was Caesarea Maritima. Roman influence in the region began in 63 CE, when the Roman general Pompey the Great took over Syria from Mithridates and, coming into Jerusalem, occupied the Second Temple. Pompey appointed Antipater, the father of Herod, as the first Roman Procurator. Later these ties allowed Herod to seek backing from Rome against the Hasmoneans in 40 BCE, when the senate recognized him as “king of the Jews.” His territories came to include the regions of Galilee, Gaulanitis (the Golan),Peraea and the Decapolis. Herod balanced his allegiance to Rome with the independence of his kingdom, often employing architectural projects to express his ambitions and control of nature to express his capacity to rule . His many palaces, placed strategically around the kingdom, feature dramatically designed landscapes and gardens. Upon his death, his heirs were unable to maintain order and Judea was annexed to Syria in 6 CE, although it was assigned its own procurator. By the time of Trajan, Judea was reduced in size and the Herodian palaces abandoned, preserving them over the millennia for archaeologists. Hadrian renamed the province Syria Palaestina after the Bar Kochba revolts (132-135) provoked him to erase the name of Judea.
The period for which we have the richest evidence of a garden culture in this region is during the reign of Herod the Great. A client king of Rome, Herod’s relationships with Mark Antony, Cleopatra, Augustus and Marcus Agrippa and other officials have been preserved in the texts of Flavius Josephus. These constitute a rare record of interactions between Rome and its territories, and provide a valuable context for understanding the trends of design in the early imperial period. The proximity of Judea to Alexandria, whose palaces and gardens lie beneath the modern city and its harbors, may also provide a suggestion of the late Hellenistic garden culture that Romans emulated. Evidence of gardens in the Hasmonean winter palaces at Jericho and the palaces of Hyracanus the Tobiad on the other side of the Jordan Valley provide rare cases where texts can illuminate archaeological evidence. These gardens require further investigation and both are threatened by local development. This geography of Judaea comprises a wide variety of biomes, from richly watered plains of the Galilee and the Jordan, to the semi arid Judean Hills, the humid, fertile coastal plain of the Mediterranean, and the deserts of the Dead Sea valley and the Negev.
Location Caesarea Maritima
Caesarea Maritima (Pleiades)
Location Description Ultimately the capital of the Roman provinces of Judaea and Syria Palestina, the city was built by Herod the Great. He acquired the old Hellenistic city of Strato’s Tower from Octavian as part of a territorial expansion after Actium, and turned the modest natural harbor here into a major port city, laid out on an orthogonal urban plan. Reminiscent of the basilaea of Alexandria, the southern area of the city was devoted to Herod’s seaside palace, in its early phase, and to public entertainment facilities by the time of the city’s opening in 12 BC. Josephus describes the port and the features of the city (AJ 15.9.6.331 and BJ 1.21.5. 408) including an “amphitheatron” and theater in the south, where archaeologists have discovered and restored a stadium and a theater. These are in the area of the archaeological remains of a palace, also noted but not located by Josephus. The city was a successful enterprise, and by the second and third centuries CE the stadium functions had moved inland and expansive villas were constructed over the remains of the stadium. By the Byzantine era, these villas were incorporated into a new praetorium. These palaces and villas have gardens, discovered in varying degrees of preservation, supplied with water through water channels, initially from the aqueduct and later from wells. Upon the destruction of this district of the city, the Arab inhabitants developed gardens amidst the ruins, irrigated by wells and water channels.
Garden Royal Garden
Keywords  pleasure garden walled garden  Garden Description Byzantine Law Court and Roof Garden
Architectural analysis and epigraphic finds excavated by Josef Patrich and the Combined Caesarea Excavations suggest that the buildings in the area immediately south of the harbor (Area CC) formed a governmental compound of Roman - Byzantine Caesarea, comprising a Revenue Office (skrinion), a Law Court and adjacent to them an archive or library for judicial and financial records and books. Earlier archaeologists (JECM) had identified this complex as an honorific U-shaped building; however, it is clearly the inverse. Constructed about 200 CE, the Law Court was a vast hall (13 x 18 m.), built on top of four vaults facing west. In the first phase, the hall faced west to the sea and was surrounded on three sides (N, E and S) by a reflection pool. To its east a square fountain was constructed. (Fig.1)
During the second phase, the pool was converted to a roof garden, filled in with the rich, red sandy soil, locally known as hamra (also noted in the upper courtyard at the promontory palace.) The soil was set on a surface of bipedal ceramic tiles (ca. 60 x 50 cm), which in turn were supported on suspensurae of flat sandstone blocks (each 20 x 20 cm and 15 cm thick) supporting the corners of four bipedal tiles. This arrangement formed a separating space between the roof of the vaults and the garden soil, preventing moisture from damaging the ceiling of the vaults (Fig. 2). This arrangement has no known parallels in Israel, but was used over vaults for the gardens of Tiberius on the Palatine in Rome, a form of nemora pensile, or hanging gardens.
During this phase the building looked out over an extended garden on the east side. Here the garden soil (hamra) extended beyond the eastern wall of the former reflection pool to include the square fountain. The garden was irrigated by a water tank (ca. 3 x 3 m.) erected on ground level between the hall and the fountain, the dimensions of which were reduced at this phase. The eastern wall of the reflection pool was partially dismantled to accommodate this tank.
During the third phase, in the 6th century, the entire garden, including the fountain, was covered by a mosaic floor.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the garden area (Combined Caesarea Excavations)   Images   Fig. 2: Reconstructed section of vaults and planting area showing roof garden construction (E. Clemence after J. Patrich)   Dates 324 CE - 638 CE
Bibliography  K.G. Holum, “Inscriptions from the imperial revenue office of Byzantine Caesarea Palaestinae” Journal of Roman Archaeology Supplement 14, 1995: 333-345. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 678401
TGN ID 7001363
Contributor Joseph Patrich ORCID: #
Publication date 09 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Promontory Palace of Herod the Great</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/judaea/caesarea_maritima/promontory_palace_of_herod_the_great/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/judaea/caesarea_maritima/promontory_palace_of_herod_the_great/</guid>
      <description>Province Judaea
Iudaea (province) (Pleiades)
Province Description Judaea, the Roman province, included parts of the areas of the Hasmonean and Herodium kingdoms, notably Biblical Judah, Samaria, and Edom. Its capital was Caesarea Maritima. Roman influence in the region began in 63 CE, when the Roman general Pompey the Great took over Syria from Mithridates and, coming into Jerusalem, occupied the Second Temple. Pompey appointed Antipater, the father of Herod, as the first Roman Procurator. Later these ties allowed Herod to seek backing from Rome against the Hasmoneans in 40 BCE, when the senate recognized him as “king of the Jews.” His territories came to include the regions of Galilee, Gaulanitis (the Golan),Peraea and the Decapolis. Herod balanced his allegiance to Rome with the independence of his kingdom, often employing architectural projects to express his ambitions and control of nature to express his capacity to rule . His many palaces, placed strategically around the kingdom, feature dramatically designed landscapes and gardens. Upon his death, his heirs were unable to maintain order and Judea was annexed to Syria in 6 CE, although it was assigned its own procurator. By the time of Trajan, Judea was reduced in size and the Herodian palaces abandoned, preserving them over the millennia for archaeologists. Hadrian renamed the province Syria Palaestina after the Bar Kochba revolts (132-135) provoked him to erase the name of Judea.
The period for which we have the richest evidence of a garden culture in this region is during the reign of Herod the Great. A client king of Rome, Herod’s relationships with Mark Antony, Cleopatra, Augustus and Marcus Agrippa and other officials have been preserved in the texts of Flavius Josephus. These constitute a rare record of interactions between Rome and its territories, and provide a valuable context for understanding the trends of design in the early imperial period. The proximity of Judea to Alexandria, whose palaces and gardens lie beneath the modern city and its harbors, may also provide a suggestion of the late Hellenistic garden culture that Romans emulated. Evidence of gardens in the Hasmonean winter palaces at Jericho and the palaces of Hyracanus the Tobiad on the other side of the Jordan Valley provide rare cases where texts can illuminate archaeological evidence. These gardens require further investigation and both are threatened by local development. This geography of Judaea comprises a wide variety of biomes, from richly watered plains of the Galilee and the Jordan, to the semi arid Judean Hills, the humid, fertile coastal plain of the Mediterranean, and the deserts of the Dead Sea valley and the Negev.
Location Caesarea Maritima
Caesarea Maritima (Pleiades)
Location Description Ultimately the capital of the Roman provinces of Judaea and Syria Palestina, the city was built by Herod the Great. He acquired the old Hellenistic city of Strato’s Tower from Octavian as part of a territorial expansion after Actium, and turned the modest natural harbor here into a major port city, laid out on an orthogonal urban plan. Reminiscent of the basilaea of Alexandria, the southern area of the city was devoted to Herod’s seaside palace, in its early phase, and to public entertainment facilities by the time of the city’s opening in 12 BC. Josephus describes the port and the features of the city (AJ 15.9.6.331 and BJ 1.21.5. 408) including an “amphitheatron” and theater in the south, where archaeologists have discovered and restored a stadium and a theater. These are in the area of the archaeological remains of a palace, also noted but not located by Josephus. The city was a successful enterprise, and by the second and third centuries CE the stadium functions had moved inland and expansive villas were constructed over the remains of the stadium. By the Byzantine era, these villas were incorporated into a new praetorium. These palaces and villas have gardens, discovered in varying degrees of preservation, supplied with water through water channels, initially from the aqueduct and later from wells. Upon the destruction of this district of the city, the Arab inhabitants developed gardens amidst the ruins, irrigated by wells and water channels.
Garden Royal Garden
Keywords  pleasure garden walled garden  Garden Description Promontory Palace of Herod the Great
A seaside palace west of the theater at Caesarea Maritima has been identified by E. Netzer as the maritime palace Herod the Great built to supervise construction of the great harbor, and, later, to provide reception space for guests at spectacles and official functions. (Fig. 1) The view north from this promontory became increasingly impressive as the harbor was completed and thrived. The palace served as the official praetorium of his heirs and subsequent Roman officials. Lower Promontory Excavations in the 1970s by Netzer and Lee I. Levine in the lower area of the palace revealed a series of luxurious reception rooms and heated chambers centering on a large (35 x 18 m.) rock-cut swimming pool enclosed by a colonnade. Cuttings in the bedrock between the columns suggested to Netzer that planters had been built between the columns, offering a pluteus around the pool, as well as a planting area protected from the salt spray. (Fig. 2) Upper Palace Excavations by K. Gleason and B. Burrell for the University of Pennsylvania Museum (1990-1996), in collaboration with E. Netzer and Hebrew University; and by Y. Porath of the Israel Antiquities Authority (1993-1996), have revealed an upper, more public half of the palace connected to the stadium (also referred to as an amphitheater by Porath following Josephus) and the theater. The upper palace comprised a series of baths and reception rooms facing out onto a quadriportico (42 x 65 m.) Although the courtyard was paved in plastered crushed sandstone in later Roman phases, fragmentary areas of layers of rich red sand (hamra), popular today with gardeners, were used to level many areas of the courtyard and may indicate the presence of vegetation or a gardened area in the first Herodian period and possibly a gardened courtyard in the first phase of the upper palace’s peristyle courtyard, but soil pits and other planting features were not preserved in any detectable pattern. (Fig. 3) Pollen extracted from plaster on the kurkar columns of the surrounding colonnade included taxa likely to have been growing within the courtyard: Cypress (Cupressus&amp;ndash;either juniperus or sempervirens), hazelnut (Corylus, a non-native), and the herbaceous taxa, Brassicacaea, Salvia, and Cistus (Fig. 4). A fourth century AD well briefly supplied water for the courtyard. Curse tablets (defixiones) at the bottom of this well indicate the popular practice of wishing ill, rather than wishing well.
Foundations of garden architecture, water channels and garden soils of the late Byzantine period have also been found, best preserved in the eastern half of the site.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the Promontory Palace (J.H. Williams and A. Iamim): a) first phase (c. 22-15 BC) ; b) second phase (c. 15-4 BC)   Images   Fig. 2:Photograph of cuttings around pool for planters (K. Gleason.     Fig. 3:Photograph of Hamra soil in courtyard (K. Gleason).     Reconstruction drawing of the Promontory upper garden (Y. Korman)   Dates 37 BCE - 135 CE
Bibliography  D. Langgut, K. Gleason, and B. Burrell, “Pollen Analysis as Evidence for Herod’s Royal Garden at the Promontory Palace, Caesarea” Israel Journal of Plant Sciences 62 (2015): 111-121. http://www.tandfonline.com/action/showCitFormats?doi=10.1080/07929978.2014.975560; K. Gleason et al. “The promontory palace at Caesarea Maritima : preliminary evidence for Herod&amp;rsquo;s Praetorium” Journal of Roman Archaeology, 11 (1998) 23-52. (worldcat) B. Burrell, K. Gleason, and E. Netzer, “Uncovering Herod’s Seaside Palace” Biblical Archaeology Review 19.3(1993): 50-57; K. K. Gleason, “Ruler and Spectacle: Herod’s Palace at Caesarea” Caesarea Maritima: a Retrospective after Two Millennia. Eds., A. Raban and K. Holum, Leiden: J. Brill, 1996, pp. 208-27; (worldcat) L.I. Levine, and E. Netzer, Excavations at Caesarea Maritima, Qedem 21, 1986, pp. 158-160; Excavations at Caesarea Maritima (worldcat) E. Netzer, “Herod the Great’s Palace” In Caesarea Maritima: a Retrospective after Two Millennia. Eds. A. Raban and K. Holum, Leiden: J. Brill, 1996, pp. 193-207. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 678401
TGN ID 7001363
Contributor Kathryn L. Gleason ORCID: 0000-0001-6260-8378
Publication date 09 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Latimer</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/latimer/latimer_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/latimer/latimer_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Latimer
Latimer (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Latimer
Keywords archaeological garden \
 fences (site elements) flower gardens orchards rural villas vegetable gardens villae rusticae  Garden Description Excavations at this country house in Buckinghamshire have produced evidence for gardens adjacent to the main residence in its latest phase dating to the beginning of the 4th century (Fig. 1). The house at the west is of the winged corridor type, fronted by a large courtyard bisected by a paved central drive with a banked edge. Between the outer courtyard wall and the house were areas used for gardening (G in Fig. 1). Just inside the outer yard wall on the south side of the drive traces of at least six bedding trenches cut into the natural subsoil and running parallel to each other were followed for at least 5 meters (b in Fig. 1). These have been interpreted by the excavator as the remains of vegetable gardens (Fig. 2). He also attributed a number of stake holes in this area to small fences bounding the vegetable gardens, and suggested the possibility of an orchard on the northern side of the drive as well as a formal flower garden nearer to the house between the projecting wings, for which there is no concrete archaeological evidence. Finally a small pit just inside the courtyard gateway may represent a pit dug to take one of a pair of trees flanking the entrance.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the residential building (A) with excavated bedding trenches (b) in its garden courtyard (G). Adapted from Branigan 1971, fig. 20.(Rights statement)   Images   Fig. 2: Reconstruction of the house and garden. Courtesy of K. Branigan.   Dates Evidence for gardens dating to the beginning of 4th century
Bibliography  K. Branigan, Latimer. Belgic, Roman, Dark Age and Early Modern Farm, Bristol, 1971, pp. 85-86, 184, figs. 14, 20 (worldcat) R.J. Zeepvat, “Roman Gardens in Britain,” in: A.E. Brown, ed., Garden Archaeology. Council for British Archaeology Research Report 78, London, 1991, p. 56, fig. 5.3. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 79555
TGN ID 1029792
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Gorhambury</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/gorhambury/gorhambury_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 10:45:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/gorhambury/gorhambury_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Gorhambury
Gorhambury (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Gorhambury
Keywords  arbors archaeological garden axial plan loam villae rusticae  Garden Description At this site in Hertfordshire near the town of Verulamium (St. Albans) excavations have revealed a multi-phased Roman farm, characterized in late Iron Age and Roman times by an outer courtyard with various service buildings and an inner courtyard in which the farm house stood (Fig. 1).
An avenue 20 meters wide led axially from the gate at the eastern end of the inner courtyard a cross to the front of the house (H in Fig. 1). On either side of the avenue was a line of circular pits spaced 4-6 meters apart (A in Fig. 1). These were filled with fine, homogeneous loam and have been interpreted as planting holes for trees or shrubs. Alternatively, the rows of holes have been interpreted as the postholes of a covered walkway or arbour leading to the house, supporting climbing plants. This feature of the courtyard is contemporary with the first masonry house built around A.D. 100, and represents an attempt to design the compound fronting the house in a more formal way. After 175 the avenue leading to the rebuilt house seems not to have been flanked by trees or an arbour, and numerous trackways leading into both courtyards from the north and south suggest that the entrance to the main residence was no longer strictly axial.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the farm with two ditched enclosures surrounding the house (H) and an avenue of trees or an arbor (A) leading to it. Adapted from Neal, Wardle, and Hunn. (Rights statement)   Images Dates around A.D. 100 - 175
Bibliography  A. Selkirk, “Gorhambury,” Current Archaeology 87, 1983: 120-121, fig. on p. 116. D.S. Neal, A. Wardle and J. Hunn, Excavation of the Iron Age, Roman and Medieval Settlement at Gorhambury, St. Albans. English Heritage Report 14, London, 1990, p. 44, fig. 56. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 79485
TGN ID 7030316
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Frocester Court</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/frocester-court/frocester_court_rural_vila/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jul 2020 08:32:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/frocester-court/frocester_court_rural_vila/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Frocester Court
Frocester Court (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Frocester Court
Keywords  archaeological garden ditches fences (site elements) kitchen gardens orchards paddock rural villas villae rusticae  Garden Description This Roman villa in Gloucestershire is situated about 14 miles west of the civitas capital Corinium Dobunnorum (Cirencester). The main residence is of the winged corridor type, fronted by a large courtyard which was bounded by the house on one side, by a wall on the two sides perpendicular to the house and by a fence on the fourth side opposite the house (Fig. 1). The yard measured 56 x 53 meters.
Excavated evidence indicates that this courtyard was designed as a formal garden in the early 4th century. The courtyard was bisected by a central drive 5 meters wide consisting of rubble with a layer of heavy metalling on top and bounded by kerb stones (P in Fig. 1). It led from the courtyard gate at the southeast and continued to the front of the house. The garden consisted of two planting beds near the house, a hedge and two long beds on either side of the drive (dark grey in Fig. 1) (Fig. 2). These beds had been dug into the stone and gravel and then filled with 20 centimeters of very dark soil. It is not known what plants grew here, although carbonized remains of box plants at the villa may reflect one type of greenery planted in the courtyard. The northeast part of the yard was paved with stone and gravel (dotted in Fig. 1), the southwest part, however, was not paved, suggesting that this part of the garden might have been used as an orchard or an area for trees or shrubs (O in Fig. 1). The formal garden was destroyed by 5th century cultivation. Northwest of the house, i.e. at the back, various ditches marked off a number of areas interpreted as possible paddocks and an area covered with a layer of very dark soil which has been interpreted as a kitchen garden.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the villa with its central path (P), planting beds for flowers and hedges (dark grey rectangles), a possible orchard (O) and a gravelled yard (dotted). Adapted from Zeepvat 1991, fig. 5.2. (Rights statement)   Images   Fig. 2: Reconstruction of the villa and its garden at Frocester Court. The closest wall should be a fence. Drawing courtesy of E. Price.   Dates Early 4th century - 5th century
Bibliography  R.J. Zeepvat, “Roman Gardens in Britain,” in: A.E. Brown, ed., Garden Archaeology. Council for British Archaaeology Research Report 78, London, 1991, pp. 53-56, fig. 5.2. (worldcat) E. Price, Frocester. A Romano-British Settlement, its Antecedents and Successors, Gloucester, 2000. [(worldcat)](A Romano-British Settlement, its Antecedents and Successors)  Pleiades ID 79471
TGN ID 4004114
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 10 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Eccles</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/eccles/eccles_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 17:53:24 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/eccles/eccles_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Eccles
Eccles (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Eccles
Keywords  archaeological garden ditches drains horticultural containers piscinae rural villas villae rusticae water baths  Garden Description This country estate in modern Kent possessed a large ornamental pool (P in Fig. 1) in the area in front of the main residence (A in Fig. 1) and to the east of the attached bath house (Fig. 1). The masonry pool measuring 25 x 3.50 meters lay parallel to the house frontage. From the pool ran a masonry drain. Although no traces of bedding trenches or plantings have been detected in the yard around the pool, it might be assumed that the pool was a centerpiece of a garden (G in Fig. 1). Interestingly, in the backfill of a ditch under the southeast wing of the villa at least thirty planting pots were retrieved in excavations. The vessels had three knife-cut triangular holes in the lower body and a round hole through the base (Fig. 2, nest page). The pots were misfired and almost certainly manufactured in kilns near the villa in the decade after A.D. 50. Although the planting pots were not found in context in pits within a garden, it is clear that they were being produced locally for use at Eccles or other gardens nearby. Excavations have established that the estate was continually occupied from the middle of the 1st century until the 4th century. In its final 4th century form, the villa complex measured 89 x 116 meters, including its wings and the courtyard.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the villa with the main house (A), a possible garden (G) and a large pool (P). Adapted from Detsicas 1983, fig. 25. (Rights statement)   Images   Fig. 2: Clay planting pot with cut-out holes. Adapted from Detsicas 1981, fig. 26.2. (Rights statement)   Dates Middle of 1st century - 4th century
Bibliography  A. Detsicas, The Cantiaci, Gloucester, 1983, pp. 103-107, fig. 20. (worldcat) R.J. Zeepvat, “Fishponds in Roman Britain,” in: M. Aston, ed., Medieval Fish, Fisheries and Fishponds in England. British Archaeological Reports, Brit. Ser. 182, Oxford, 1988, p. 18, fig. 2. (worldcat) A. Detsicas, “A group of pottery from Eccles, Kent,” in Roman Pottery Research in Britain and Northwest Europe, British Archaeological Reports, Int. Ser. 123, Oxford, 1981, pp. 441-445.  Pleiades ID 79448
TGN ID 1029144
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rustic villa at Blankenheim-Hülchrath</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/blankenheim-hulchrath/blankenheim-hulchrath/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/blankenheim-hulchrath/blankenheim-hulchrath/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Blankenheim-Hülchrath
Blankenheim-Hülchrath (Pleiades)
Garden Rustic villa at Blankenheim-Hülchrath
Keywords  rural villas villae rusticae  Garden Description This villa rustica was built on a slope so that the residential building (A on Plan 1) overlooked the rest of the lower lying farmyard (Image 1). The entire complex covered an area 120 m. in width and 250 m. in length (3 hectares). The house was separated from a large open area behind and to the southwest of it by a wall. This has been interpreted as a utilitarian garden (G on Plan 1), and it may well be that an orchard and a vegetable garden were located here near the house.
To the northeast of the house was an open courtyard flanked by outbuildings and separated from the service area of the farm by a terrace wall. This open courtyard may have been a garden (G on Plan 1), perhaps of a more decorative nature. Without any physical evidence for gardens, however, this remains speculation.
Maps Plans   Plan 1: Plan of the rural villa (A) with possible gardens (G) in the courtyard adjacent to the house and in the enclosed area southwest of it. Adapted from Horn 1987, fig. 306. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  H. G. Horn, ed., Die Römer in Nordrhein-Westfalen, Stuttgart, 1987, pp. 361-63, figs. 306-308. (worldcat) P. Van Ossel, Établissements ruraux de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquité tardive dans le nord de la Gaule. Suppl. Gallia 51, Paris, 1992, pp. 192-193, fig. 5. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981524
TGN ID 6002234
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Darenth</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/darenth/darenth_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 12:08:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/darenth/darenth_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Darenth
Darenth (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Darenth
Keywords  archaeological garden kitchen gardens piscinae rural villas villae rusticae waterspouts  Garden Description Excavations at this site of a Roman villa in Kent uncovered a large rectangular masonry pool in the courtyard, which was enclosed by buildings on the north, west, and east (Fig. 1). The villa buildings took up an area of 150 x 225 meters in total, including the courtyard with a width of 26.5 meters. Occupation at the site began after A.D. 100 and continued until the closing decades of the 4th century.
This pool (P in Fig. 1), measuring 25.6 x 3.36 meters, lay at right angles to the center of the main residence and bisected an enclosed courtyard, possibly a garden (G in Fig. 1) in front of the house. The pool would have been a decorative element in the courtyard. Within the pool at the end nearest the house was found a small bronze water-spout in the form of the head of a lioness. At the other end was a semi-circular pool with provision for the inflow and outflow of water.
South of the western range of rooms was a large, open space measuring 14.6 x 58.4 meters, enclosed by walls. There was no paving in this area, nor was there any evidence for partitions. It has been suggested that this might have been a kitchen garden (G in Fig. 1).
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the villa with the main house (A), garden areas (G), and a large pool (P). Adapted from Detsicas 1983, fig. 20. (Rights statement)   Dates After 100 CE - Closing decades of the 4th century
Bibliography  A. Detsicas, The Cantiaci, Gloucester, 1983, pp. 103-107, fig. 20. (worldcat) B. Philp, Excavations in the Darent Valley, Kent, Gloucester, 1984, pp. 89-92, figs. 24, 33. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 79413
TGN ID 7027349
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Bancroft</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/bancroft/bancroft_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2020 18:04:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/bancroft/bancroft_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Bancroft
Garden Rural Villa in Bancroft
Keywords  archaeological garden bathhouses (water recreation structures) drains gazebos horticultural containers piscinae villae rusticae  Garden Description Excavations between 1983 and 1986 at this site in Buckinghamshire revealed a Roman villa of the winged corridor type, which was built in the late 3rd century and rebuilt and enlarged in the mid-4th century (Fig.1).
From the two projecting wings of the house at the northeast and southeast two walls ran eastward, forming an enclosed courtyard 35.5 meters in width and ca. 42 meters in length in front of the 4th century house. In the centre of the yard was a stone-built rectangular fishpond (P in Fig. 1), 2.6 x 13 meters in size and 50-80 centimeters deep which was continually fed by a drain running from an overflow in the cold plunge bath at the south end of the house. An overflow at the east end of the pool may have led to a nearby stream. Although traces of plantings or planting beds were not preserved in the gravelly subsoil, a shallow rectangular depression just west of the fishpool, filled with dark humic soil, may represent a flowerbed through which the water pipe feeding the pool ran. The courtyard therefore was at least partially planted as a garden (G in Fig. 1). Adjacent to the courtyard enclosure at the south was an octagonal structure with stone walls, interpreted as a possible gazebo (A in Fig. 1).
The villa complex that preceded the winged corridor house is also of interest in regard to gardens. The earlier aisled house of late 1st to late 2nd century date was part of a series of buildings and enclosures that included a walled area to the northeast measuring 27 x 18.3 meters in size. Inside this enclosure was a deposit of dark humic soil between 4 and 6 centimeters deep. Environmental analysis of soil samples from the enclosure suggests that the area was used as a kitchen garden with plants such as brassicas, celery, mustard, coriander, summer savory and caper spurge. Three ceramic vessels with at least one hole pierced through the side or the base, possibly planting pots, may have been associated with this phase of the villa garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the villa with its garden courtyard (G), a central pool (P), and a possible gazebo (A). Adapted from Zeepvat 1991, fig. 5.4.(Rights statement.)   Dates Roman villa&amp;hellip; built in the late 3rd century and rebuilt and enlarged in the mid-4th century.
Excavation Dates 1983-1986
Bibliography  R. J. Williams and R. J. Zeepvat, Bancroft. The late Bronze Age and Iron Age Settlement and Roman Villa and Temple-Mausoleum. Buckinghamshire Archaeological Society Monograph Series 7, Aylesbury, 1994, pp. 154, 163, 188-191, figs. 66, 80, 83, 85, 93, 101-103, pls. 57-59. (worldcat) R.J. Zeepvat, “Roman Gardens in Britain,” in: A. E. Brown, ed., Garden Archaeology. Council for British Archaeology Research Report 78, London, 1991, pp. 56-58, fig. 5.4. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 79312
TGN ID 7030316
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 07 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>