<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>villae rusticae on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/villae-rusticae/</link>
    <description>Recent content in villae rusticae on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 10:17:25 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/villae-rusticae/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Winden Am See</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/winden_am_see/winden_am_see_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 10:17:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/winden_am_see/winden_am_see_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Pannonia
Province Description Location Winden Am See
Winden Am See (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Winden Am See
Keywords archaeological garden
corridors
rural villas
vestibules
villae rusticae
Garden Description The modest house of this villa rustica is of the so-called corridor type, a type common in the region and already seen at Carnuntum (Fig. 1). It was built around 100 A.D. and occupied until the 4th century.
On the southeast of the house was a vestibule, from which a central corridor departed at a 90 degree angle. This corridor divided the house into two parts of equal width. Two walls at right angles to the house at the northeast enclosed an area in which the excavators found &amp;ldquo;fine garden soil.&amp;rdquo; This observation allows the reconstruction of a garden, probably a kitchen garden, next to the house (G in Fig. 1).
Maps Plans   Fig.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Eisenstadt</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/eisenstadt/eisenstadt_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 09:31:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/eisenstadt/eisenstadt_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Pannonia
Province Description Location Eisenstadt
Eisenstadt (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Eisenstadt
Keywords altars (religious fixtures)
archaeological garden
atriums
peristyles (Roman courtyards)
podiums (building divisions)
porticoes
rural villas
villae rusticae
Garden Description The residence of this villa rustica was entered on the southeast by a portico (Fig. 1). After passing through a room interpreted as the atrium, one arrived in the open courtyard which had a peristyle on three sides (G on plan). On the northern edge of the courtyard was a podium (P on plan) near which votive altars to Diana and Silvanus were found, both gods of the woods and suitable subjects for a garden. This corner of the courtyard, thus, seems to have had religious character. In the middle of the courtyard was a square foundation, measuring 1.80 x 1.80 m., possibly the remains of a base for some kind of figure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Winkel-Seeb</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/winkel-seeb/winkel-seeb_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 10:34:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/winkel-seeb/winkel-seeb_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Province Description Location Winkel-Seeb
Winkel-Seeb (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Winkel-Seeb
Keywords archaeological garden
barrier walls
corridors
pergolas
porticoes
rural villas
terrace gardens
villae rusticae
well houses
Garden Description The residential and service parts of this villa rustica occupied an area of ca. 7 hectares. The lateral walls of the complex could be followed over a length of 395 meters, but it is assumed that they once extended up to the lake southeast of the farm. The house, measuring 56.70 x 82.40 meters, was of the winged corridor type (Fig. 12.1). The villa rustica was built in the first half of the 1st century A.C. and inhabited until its destruction in 250. The two protruding wings on either side of the entrance on the north extended to the dividing wall between the pars urbana and the pars rustica. These may have been built as covered porticoes or pergolas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Wiesbaden-Biebrich</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/wiesbaden-biebrich/wiesbaden-biebrich_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 10:18:48 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/wiesbaden-biebrich/wiesbaden-biebrich_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Province Description Location Wiesbaden-Biebrich
Wiesbaden-Biebrich (Pleiades)
Location Description Biebrich, now part of Wiesbaden, is directly on the right bank of the Rhein south of the center of Wiesbaden.
Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Wiesbaden-Biebrich
Keywords archaeological garden
barrier walls
kitchen gardens
rural villas
villae rusticae
Garden Description Only the residential part of this farm has been excavated. The house with a width of 22 meters had two protruding wings at the south. To the west of the house was an area of irregular proportions enclosed by a wall, and this has been interpreted as a kitchen garden (G in Fig. 1).
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the rural villa with a possible walled garden (G) to the west. Adapted from Baatz and Herrmann 1989, fig. 471. (Rights Statement)   Images Dates unspecified
Bibliography  D. Baatz and F.-R. Herrmann, eds., Die Römer in Hessen, 2nd ed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa in Vallon (Sur Dompierre, Canton de Fribourg, Switzerland)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vallon/vallon_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2020 17:12:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vallon/vallon_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Province Description Location Vallon
Vallon (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Villa in Vallon (Sur Dompierre, Canton de Fribourg, Switzerland)
Keywords arbors
barns
barrier walls
ceramic tile
ditches
fences (site elements)
hearths
horrea
kitchen gardens
mosaics (visual works)
orchards
pedestals
pillars
piscinae
porticoes
rural villas
sherds
tesserae
villae rusticae
water supply systems
Garden Description Located 6km south-east of Avenches/ Aventicum, the capital of the Helvetian tribe, this site is situated on a small alluvial terrace at the bottom of a hillside. The area is bordered by a stream, the Laret, characterized by a flow, sometimes torrential, that has fluctuated during the past centuries. To the west, on the right bank, stands the rocky spur of Carignan (Fig. 1). Due to the relatively restrictive topography, human settlements favoured the left bank until the Middle Ages.
On the spur east of the stream, a building made of a light structure, apparently isolated, is constructed at the beginning of the 1st c.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Orbe</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/orbe/orbe_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2020 13:44:42 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/orbe/orbe_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Province Description Location Orbe
Orbe (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Orbe
Keywords archaeological garden
barrier walls
corridors
rural villas
terrace gardens
villae rusticae
Garden Description This large palatial house belonged to a villa rustica revealed by excavation and aerial photography. The enclosed farmyard is calculated to have been approximately 420 x 650 meters in size. The house itself, built in the mid-1st century AD and in use until the 4th century, was 200 meters long (Fig. 1). This winged corridor house had two large open courtyards between the protruding wings at the front. These were very likely gardens (G in Fig. 1). Twenty-five meters in front of the house at the east was a long terrace wall 400 meters long running north-south. There may have been gardens or a park (G in Fig. 1) between the house and this terrace wall.
Maps Plans   Fig.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Oberentfelden</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/oberentfelden/oberentfelden_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 17:46:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/oberentfelden/oberentfelden_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Province Description Location Oberentfelden
Oberentfelden (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Oberentfelden
Keywords archaeological garden
bathhouses (water recreation structures)
kitchen gardens
nymphaea (garden structures)
peristyles (columnades)
rural villas
villae rusticae
Garden Description The enclosed area of this villa rustica was 160 meters wide and at least 460 meters long; the eastern limits of the complex have not yet been found. The main residence and bath complex (A and B in Fig. 1), dating to the beginning of the 2nd century, stood on sloping land eight meters higher than the rest of the farmyard. At the eastern end of the service area (pars rustica) was a large peristyle building with a nymphaeum at the western end (D in Fig. 1). The open courtyard within this peristyle may have been a garden. Small kitchen gardens have been reconstructed between the various outbuildings and smaller houses (C in Fig.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Hummetroth</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/hummetroth/hummetroth_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 11:47:11 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/hummetroth/hummetroth_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Province Description Location Hummetroth
Hummetroth (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Hummetroth
Keywords apsed triclinium
bathhouses (water recreation structures)
corridors
hypocausts
porticoes
reception rooms
rural villas
terrace gardens
villae rusticae
Garden Description The enclosed farmyard, including the residential area (pars urbana) and the service zone with outbuildings and working areas (pars rustica), covered an area of 3.5 hectares. The house of this villa rustica of the 2nd century is of the winged corridor type with two protruding wings framing a large courtyard in front of the house at the south (Fig. 1).
The courtyard was divided into two zones by a terrace(?) wall, and in both zones a garden has been reconstructed (G in Fig. 1). Entering the house from the south, one passed through a large reception room to an apsed triclinium with hypocaust heating. A bath complex lay to the southwest, entered by the portico next to the garden.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Friedberg Pfingstweide</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/friedberg-pfingstweide/friedberg-pfingstweide_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 18:12:31 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/friedberg-pfingstweide/friedberg-pfingstweide_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Province Description Location Friedberg Pfingstweide
Friedberg Pfingstweide (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Friedberg Pfingstweide
Keywords archaeological garden
bathhouses (water recreation structures)
rural villas
villae rusticae
Garden Description This villa rustica was situated on the northern slope of a valley through which a stream ran. The enclosed area of the farm occupied an area of 3.4 hectares (180 x 190 meters), and it was divided into a residential part (pars urbana) and a service area (pars rustica) by a road running east-west (Fig. 1). The front of the house (H in Fig. 1) faced north and had a view of the valley and the lower lying service area of the farm.
Built in the early 2nd century, the house was of the winged corridor type with a large open courtyard enclosed by the protruding wings of the house. The courtyard was divided into two zones that were possibly gardens (G in Fig.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Ferpicloz</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ferpicloz/ferpicloz_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 15:32:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ferpicloz/ferpicloz_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Province Description Location Ferpicloz
Ferpicloz (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Ferpicloz
Keywords archaeological garden
barrier walls
porticoes
rural villas
villae rusticae
Garden Description The house of this villa rustica was of the winged corridor type (A in Fig. 1) with a porticoed facade (Fig. 1). Attached to the eastern end of the house, measuring 37 x 46 meters, was a wall running east-west which has been interpreted as the protective wall of a garden (G in Fig. 1).
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the rural villa (A) with a possible garden (G) protected by a wall to the east of the main building. The shoreline of the lake is dotted. Adapted from Drack and Fellmann 1988, fig. 369. (Rights Statement)   Images Dates unspecified
Bibliography  W. Drack and R. Fellmann, Die Römer in der Schweiz, Stuttgart, 1988, pp.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Dietikon</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/dietikon/dietikon_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 13:09:50 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/dietikon/dietikon_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Province Description Location Dietikon
Dietikon (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Dietikon
Keywords archaeological garden
axial plan
corridors
pergolas
piscinae
porticoes
rural villas
villae rusticae
Garden Description This villa rustica complex was built on a site at the bottom of a valley near and parallel to the river Limmat. Dietikon was situated on an important land and water traffic route from the Bündner Alps to Vindonissa and further north to the Rhine. Recent excavations supply valuable evidence for a garden in front of the entrance to a rural residence, giving insight into the appearance of other similar villas at which, for one reason or another, no physical remains of gardens have been retrieved. The excavations revealed a first villa with timber buildings dating to the Tiberian period, or early 1st century AD. Around the middle of the 1st century AD these first buildings were replaced by an axially-constructed stone-built villa complex with an enclosure, covering a total surface of 13 hectares (Fig.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Bad Kreuznach</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/bad_kreuznach/bad_kreuznach_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 12:39:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/bad_kreuznach/bad_kreuznach_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Province Description Location Bad Kreuznach
Bad Kreuznach (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Bad Kreuznach
Keywords apsed triclinium
colonnades
cryptoportici
fountains
gutters (building drainage components)
lararia
mosaics (visual works)
peristyles (Roman courtyards)
porticoes
rural villas
villae rusticae
Garden Description This villa, almost 6000 square meters in size, gives eloquent testimony to the wealth and status of the owner of the rural estate. The estate was built in the second half of the 2nd century and occupied until its destruction around 275.
The three-storied villa with more than 50 rooms on the ground floor alone, many decorated with mosaics and imported marble revetment, was centered on a colonnaded garden courtyard (G in Fig. 1). Many of the sandstone columns from the peristyle, as well as fragments of sculpture from the garden, were found in the courtyard. The house was built into a hill, and the courtyard was terraced on two levels.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa at Neerhaaren-Rekem</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/neerhaaren-rekem/neerharen-rekem/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:54:58 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/neerhaaren-rekem/neerharen-rekem/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Neerhaaren-Rekem
Neerhaaren-Rekem (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural villa at Neerhaaren-Rekem
Keywords rural villas
villae rusticae
arbors
pergolas
piscinae
Garden Description The facade of this modest house of a villa rustica near the Meuse river measured 24 m. in length and had two protruding wings joined by a portico (Plan 1). The house was built in the late 1st century A.D. There is evidence for an arbor or pergola next to the house in the form of two rows of postholes arranged diagonally and converging in front of the entrance on the west (circles on plan). Between the rows of posts, each measuring ca. 15 m. in length, and around which some kind of vines or other climbing plants may have been trained to grow, was a small pool.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the farm house at Neerhaaren-Rekem with a possible arbor leading to the door and a pool (grey) between the posts of the arbor.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Sudeley/Spoonley Wood</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/sudeley/sudeley_spoonley_wood_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 18:57:34 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/sudeley/sudeley_spoonley_wood_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Sudeley/Spoonley Wood
Sudeley/Spoonley Wood (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Sudeley/Spoonley Wood
Keywords archaeological garden
axial plan
barrier walls
terrace gardens
rural villas
villae rusticae
Garden Description The main residence of this rural estate in Gloucestershire, excavated in 1882, is of the winged corridor type (Fig. 1). From the north and south corners of the house, walls ran in a westerly direction to enclose an open courtyard (G in Fig. 1) approximately 65 meters wide and 45 meters deep from the outer boundary to the main entrance of the house. A paved path was axially arranged in the courtyard to connect the entrance to the courtyard with that of the residential building. The western third of the courtyard is marked off by low scarps which may be remains of garden terraces (T in Fig. 1). Finds from the site indicate a 3rd/4th century date for the complex.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Latimer</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/latimer/latimer_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/latimer/latimer_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Latimer
Latimer (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Latimer
Keywords archaeological garden
barrier walls
fences (site elements)
flower gardens
orchards
rural villas
vegetable gardens
villae rusticae
Garden Description Excavations at this country house in Buckinghamshire have produced evidence for gardens adjacent to the main residence in its latest phase dating to the beginning of the 4th century (Fig. 1). The house at the west is of the winged corridor type, fronted by a large courtyard bisected by a paved central drive with a banked edge. Between the outer courtyard wall and the house were areas used for gardening (G in Fig. 1). Just inside the outer yard wall on the south side of the drive traces of at least six bedding trenches cut into the natural subsoil and running parallel to each other were followed for at least 5 meters (b in Fig.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Gorhambury</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/gorhambury/gorhambury_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jul 2020 10:45:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/gorhambury/gorhambury_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Gorhambury
Gorhambury (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Gorhambury
Keywords arbors
archaeological garden
axial plan
loam
villae rusticae
Garden Description At this site in Hertfordshire near the town of Verulamium (St. Albans) excavations have revealed a multi-phased Roman farm, characterized in late Iron Age and Roman times by an outer courtyard with various service buildings and an inner courtyard in which the farm house stood (Fig. 1).
An avenue 20 meters wide led axially from the gate at the eastern end of the inner courtyard a cross to the front of the house (H in Fig. 1). On either side of the avenue was a line of circular pits spaced 4-6 meters apart (A in Fig. 1). These were filled with fine, homogeneous loam and have been interpreted as planting holes for trees or shrubs. Alternatively, the rows of holes have been interpreted as the postholes of a covered walkway or arbour leading to the house, supporting climbing plants.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Eccles</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/eccles/eccles_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 17:53:24 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/eccles/eccles_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Eccles
Eccles (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Eccles
Keywords archaeological garden
ditches
drains
horticultural containers
piscinae
rural villas
villae rusticae
water baths
Garden Description This country estate in modern Kent possessed a large ornamental pool (P in Fig. 1) in the area in front of the main residence (A in Fig. 1) and to the east of the attached bath house (Fig. 1). The masonry pool measuring 25 x 3.50 meters lay parallel to the house frontage. From the pool ran a masonry drain. Although no traces of bedding trenches or plantings have been detected in the yard around the pool, it might be assumed that the pool was a centerpiece of a garden (G in Fig. 1). Interestingly, in the backfill of a ditch under the southeast wing of the villa at least thirty planting pots were retrieved in excavations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rustic villa at Blankenheim-Hülchrath</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/blankenheim-hulchrath/blankenheim-hulchrath/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/blankenheim-hulchrath/blankenheim-hulchrath/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Blankenheim-Hülchrath
Blankenheim-Hülchrath (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rustic villa at Blankenheim-Hülchrath
Keywords rural villas
villae rusticae
Garden Description This villa rustica was built on a slope so that the residential building (A on Plan 1) overlooked the rest of the lower lying farmyard (Image 1). The entire complex covered an area 120 m. in width and 250 m. in length (3 hectares). The house was separated from a large open area behind and to the southwest of it by a wall. This has been interpreted as a utilitarian garden (G on Plan 1), and it may well be that an orchard and a vegetable garden were located here near the house.
To the northeast of the house was an open courtyard flanked by outbuildings and separated from the service area of the farm by a terrace wall. This open courtyard may have been a garden (G on Plan 1), perhaps of a more decorative nature.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Darenth</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/darenth/darenth_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 12:08:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/darenth/darenth_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Darenth
Darenth (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Darenth
Keywords archaeological garden
kitchen gardens
piscinae
rural villas
villae rusticae
waterspouts
Garden Description Excavations at this site of a Roman villa in Kent uncovered a large rectangular masonry pool in the courtyard, which was enclosed by buildings on the north, west, and east (Fig. 1). The villa buildings took up an area of 150 x 225 meters in total, including the courtyard with a width of 26.5 meters. Occupation at the site began after A.D. 100 and continued until the closing decades of the 4th century.
This pool (P in Fig. 1), measuring 25.6 x 3.36 meters, lay at right angles to the center of the main residence and bisected an enclosed courtyard, possibly a garden (G in Fig. 1) in front of the house. The pool would have been a decorative element in the courtyard.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Bancroft</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/bancroft/bancroft_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2020 18:04:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/bancroft/bancroft_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Bancroft
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Bancroft
Keywords archaeological garden
barrier walls
bathhouses (water recreation structures)
drains
gazebos
horticultural containers
piscinae
rural villas
villae rusticae
Garden Description Excavations between 1983 and 1986 at this site in Buckinghamshire revealed a Roman villa of the winged corridor type, which was built in the late 3rd century and rebuilt and enlarged in the mid-4th century (Fig.1).
From the two projecting wings of the house at the northeast and southeast two walls ran eastward, forming an enclosed courtyard 35.5 meters in width and ca. 42 meters in length in front of the 4th century house. In the centre of the yard was a stone-built rectangular fishpond (P in Fig. 1), 2.6 x 13 meters in size and 50-80 centimeters deep which was continually fed by a drain running from an overflow in the cold plunge bath at the south end of the house.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>