<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/fishbourne/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 18:05:37 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/fishbourne/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Roman Palace in Fishbourne</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/fishbourne/fishbourne_roman_palace/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 18:05:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/fishbourne/fishbourne_roman_palace/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Fishbourne
Fishbourne (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Roman Palace in Fishbourne
Keywords archaeological garden
basins (vessels)
colonnades
loam
palaces
piscinae
presence chambers
terrace gardens
vegetable gardens
Garden Description Fishbourne Roman Palace was accidentally discovered during the digging of a water main trench in 1960. The discovery led to nine seasons of excavations (1961-69) that showed the site had developed from a military base at the time of the Roman invasion in AD 43 to a sumptuous palace by the end of the first century CE. Carefully excavated by Barry Cunliffe, using techniques of environmental archaeology, the garden excavations at the palace have long served as a model in the development of Roman garden archaeology, although the findings did not initially prompt the investigation of other gardens in Britain. Today the site has been developed for display and education.
The palace contains gardens within its internal courtyards, as well in a larger area to the south, where terraces and other landscape architectural features lay between the residence and the deep water channel (Fig 1.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>