<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>piscinae on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/piscinae/</link>
    <description>Recent content in piscinae on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2020 15:00:54 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/piscinae/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>I.ii.17 A</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_17/i.ii.17_a/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2020 15:00:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_17/i.ii.17_a/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 17
Garden I.ii.17 A
Keywords  archaeological garden mural paintings (visual works) piscinae tablina  Garden Description At the rear of the house was a very small garden entered from the tablinum. Excavated in 1872, much of the garden was occupied by two small raised pools, according to Mau. (Fig. 3) Attached to the west wall was a masonry pool 0.58 m. deep on the inside and 0.73 m. high on the outside. The other pool was to the south and there was a garden painting on the rear wall.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, *Scavi*, pl. 1; Niccolini, *Case*, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I.ii.17; 10.13.59, S.A. Jashemski (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation dates 1872
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Descr., p. 44. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 23. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 264-265. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. Gen.,” p. 76. Viola, “Scavi” p. 12. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 25 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of L. Vousius Faustus and M. Vousius Faustus (I.ii.10)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_10/house_of_l._vousius_faustus_and_m._volusius_faustus-i.ii.10/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2020 18:18:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_10/house_of_l._vousius_faustus_and_m._volusius_faustus-i.ii.10/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 10
Garden House of L. Vousius Faustus and M. Vousius Faustus (I.ii.10)
Keywords  aedicules archaeological garden biclinia drains lararia mural paintings (visual works) piscinae triclinia  Garden Description The garden at the rear of the house, excavated in 1873, is almost totally destroyed. According to Mau, most of the garden was occupied by a large pool (5.40 X 2.90 m.) which was sloped toward the west from where it drained into the street through a pipe. The pool was surrounded by a low wall about 0.55 m. high leaving only a narrow space between the pool and the walls. In the northwest corner were the two beds of a masonry biclinium which sloped toward the wall, as was customary. Rainwater falling on them was carried away by a terra-cotta drain which emptied into the pool. A square niche under the north couch provided a storage space. On the wall above this couch was a rectangular niche lararium with a roughly made aedicula facade (Fig. 3, 2.19.72). At the east end of this couch was a masonry table. Fiorelli reports a planting bed attached to the rear (east) wall. There was a view from the triclinium through the large window in the east wall, across the pool to the garden painting on the rear wall.
Garden Painting
When this garden was excavated in 1873, the excavators reported three panels on the east wall with garden paintings. The center panel had a body of water with swimming fish with assorted animals in the background that included a grazing deer and a springing leopard. The two panels on either side each had a large crater-shaped fountain surrounded by thick growth. Large red flowers and yellow apples could be identified to the left of each fountain and the right, pomegranates (Punica granatum L.). Jashemski examined this painting in 1964 to find it had been covered by a growth of ivy which had destroyed most of the painting. A section of a large pomegranate bush was all that was left intact at the time. She describes the leaves, painted in blue-green with darker shading and a few yellow leaves and the fruit, deep yellow with reddish-orange shading, as being rendered in an impressionistic manner. At the right of the entrance to the garden area was a cistern opening. Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Images   Fig. 3: I.ii.10; 2.19.72, S. A. Jashemski.   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1873
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 22, no. 6. Fiorelli, Descr., p. 42. (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), col. 57.  Jashemski, Gardens, 1:1 10-1 1 1. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 22. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 313. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 197-198. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. Gen.,” p. 76. Schefold, WandP, p. 9 (describes this painting as a paradeisos, with sea, deer, panther, and nymphaeum). (worldcat)  Sogliano, “Pitture,” p. 224, no. 694. (worldcat)  Soprano, p.305, no. 23. Viola, “Scavi” p. 11. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 24 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.ii.6</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_6/i.ii.6/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2020 12:44:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_6/i.ii.6/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 6
Garden I.ii.6
Keywords  archaeological garden atriums graffiti (casual notations) gutters (building drainage components) inscription peristyles (columnades) piscinae porticoes puteal  Garden Description The west portico of the small peristyle garden at the rear of the house was entered through two doors directly from the atrium. The garden was enclosed on four sides by a portico supported by eight stuccoed brick columns. On the foreside, the two first columns on the left had a larger intercolumniation corresponding to the wide opening opposite the atrium. Between these columns stood a terra-cotta puteal covered with white stucco. A gutter around the edges of the garden was shown in the plan. The round pool in the center of the garden no longer exists, and only stumps of the columns remain today. One of the graffiti on the walls of the portico noted that on November 17 Puteolana gave birth to three males and two females (XV K(alendas) NOV(embres) PVTEOLANA PEPERIT MASCL(os) III FEMEL[as] II) (CIL IV.3890). Perhaps they were either piglets or puppies. Pigs were more common in ancient cities than is commonly realized.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Descr., p. 39. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, 1: 104-105 (for the graffito). (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 21. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 199. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. Gen.,” p. 76. Pernice, p. 18. Viola, “Scavi,” p 11. (worldcat) Warscher, “Codex.”  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 24 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban House or Schola in Aquincum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/aquincum/aquincum_urban_house_or_schola/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jul 2020 16:44:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/aquincum/aquincum_urban_house_or_schola/</guid>
      <description>Province Pannonia
Province Description Location Aquincum
Aquincum (Pleiades)
Location Description This town on the Danube river acquired the rank of municipium under Hadrian in 124 A.D. In the year 194 it was granted colonial status.
Garden Urban House or Schola in Aquincum
Keywords  archaeological garden bathhouses (water recreation structures) fountains peristyles (Roman courtyards) piscinae statues statuettes (free-standing sculpture)  Garden Description Very few houses of Mediterranean type have been discovered, and only one can be said with certainty to have had a garden (Fig. 1, G in Fig. 1). The peristyle courtyard was a prominent feature of this house of irregular plan and substantial size near the southern city wall. The house dates to the 3rd century, and it is thought to have been a clubhouse or schola for young men (collegium iuventutis), complete with a bath suite. In the middle of the courtyard, framed on four sides by a low wall supporting columns, was a square masonry pool (Fig. 2). In the center of the pool was a fountain consisting of a small marble satyr standing on a column of the same material. This decorative element and the unpaved ground strongly suggest the existence of a garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of a building with a peristyle garden courtyard (G) and a pool in its center. Adapted from Polenz and Póczy 1986, fig. 47.(Rights statement.)   Images   Fig. 2: The excavated courtyard building with its peristyle garden. Photo courtesy of M. Carroll.)   Dates 3rd century
Bibliography  A. Mócsy, Pannonia and Upper Moesia. A History of the Middle Danube Provinces of the Roman Empire, London, 1974, p. 166, pl. 16b. (worldcat) H. Polenz and K. Póczy, Das römische Budapest. Neue Ausgrabungen und Funde in Aquincum, Münster, 1986, p. 124, fig. 47, pl. 10. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 1971301
TGN ID 8713146
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Structures under the Collège Lumière in Vesontio</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vesontio/vesontio_structures_under_the_colle%CC%80ge_lumie%CC%80re/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 09:48:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vesontio/vesontio_structures_under_the_colle%CC%80ge_lumie%CC%80re/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Vesontio
Vesontio (Pleiades)
Location Description The defensibility offered by this unique geography made Caesar hasten to occupy Vesontio in 58 BC. The town came to have all the usual Roman structures– forum, baths, aqueduct, and amphitheater (on the other side of the Doubs, to the northwest.) But the most visible remnant is the Porte Noire (Black Gate) [3], a triumphal arch built by Marcus Aurelius at the southeastern end of the cardo maximus, today Grande Rue and still the center of city life.
Archaeology in a downtown area is always a matter of seizing opportunities as they are presented by new construction, remembering and recording what was found, and coming back years later to complete the picture. A good example of this process is at our second site, [2] on the map. In 1973, the Neptune Mosaic was discovered in rue de Lorraine, one of the largest floor decorations in all Gaul. The extent of the mosaic under nearby buildings made full excavation impossible. More than thirty years later, in 2004, construction of a gymnasium for the Collège Lumière (a middle school) gave archaeologists access to much more of the site, about 3000 square meters, for a salvage excavation. As expected, the continuation of the Neptune mosaic was found; moreover, three other mosaics of high quality, along with columns, sculpted blocks, peristyles, and monumental pools came to light. The results of this excavation have not been published; we are grateful to the excavators for sharing their preliminary results.
Garden Structures under the Collège Lumière in Vesontio
Keywords  colonnades kraters mosaics (visual works) opus signinum peristyles (Roman courtyards) piscinae porticoes reception rooms rinceaux terrazzo  Garden Description The results of the 2004 excavation at the Collège Lumière are still under study and the data are therefore still partial. This zone, close to the river and the artisinal quarter has, in the past, yielded most of the mosaics recorded for Besançon. The ancient structures discovered on 3000 square meters relate to a Gallo-Roman urbanization extending from the Augustan period to the third century and superimposed on a rather dense Gallic occupation of the first century BC. Two phases of construction from the late Augustan period up through the end of the first century, have thus far not permitted the confirmation of the possible presence of a garden. On the other, later constructions dating from the beginning and last third of the second century are rich in peristyles with open space suitable for a garden.
At the beginning of the second century, in a third phase, a structure of large dimension (at least 2500 m2) but undetermined purpose was built on fill and leveling of the abandoned earlier buildings. It will simplify descriptions to let “north” denote the direction that is actually northeast, the direction towards the river. In these terms, large rooms (the largest reaching 126 sq. m.) and corridors were bordered on the south by an open area, possibly a garden, with porticos on at least the north and west sides, and by one peristyle to the west and by another to the east. The walls of the porticos around these peristyles were decorated with painted plaster. The west peristyle (at least 22 x 20 m) is the most complete. Only one wall, the east wall of the west peristyle, is common to these second century structures and the preceding ones of first century. It may thus represent a property line. Originally, it opened over a large threshold between the largest of the rooms and the western peristyle. It was subsequently first reduced and then completely closed.
The fourth phase, a remodeling at the end of the second century, is the best preserved, but its purpose remains unclear. It has yielded a series of elements that allow us to follow the architectural reasoning of the builders. It kept the basic plan of the third state: a peristyle to the east, one to the west, and a large garden to the south. The rooms, however, are considerably rearranged. Three grand reception rooms (of 200, 85, and 65 m2 ) with floors decorated with luxurious mosaics are organized in a very regular fashion in relation to the two peristyles and garden by corridors or galleries. The floors of these numerous spaces of circulation were a terrazzo in an opus signinum matrix, except for the gallery of garden, which had a mosaic.
The largest of the rooms, decorated by the Neptune mosaic, opened on its north side through a colonnade onto the south of the east peristyle and through another colonnade on the opposite side to the garden on the south. The spacing of the columns was the same (4.6 m) on both colonnades. The excavated part of the east peristyle showed that it was 22.3 meters wide; if it was square, it would have had an area of about 500 square meters. Another large room decorated with the rinceaux mosaic (so called for the bands of scrolled foliage) also opens onto the east peristyle. The gallery that borders the garden was widened into the garden in front of the Neptune room; against the wall of this extension there was a pool at least 1.5 meters wide and probably about 13 meters long. Several paving stones of the bottom have survived. The last room, the one with the Medusa mosaic, would seem to have opened onto the garden. The garden was about .95 meters lower than the house and was reached by descending four steps. The north portico of the west peristyle was enlarged in this final phase; the interval between columns reached 6.7 meters. The presence of the closed wall that may have been a property line obliges us to ask Did this west peristyle really belong to the structure to the east or was it part of a different edifice that may have extended to the west outside the limits of the excavation?
A fragment of a little ornamental stone krater was found in the material that filled the east peristyle after its abandonment. From late antiquity is the foundation of a pool or cistern of about 3.5 by 2.5 meters. Its stones have been removed, and only the opus signinum mortar bearing the imprint of the stones has been found. This structure pierced through all the archaeological levels and into the natural earth.
Plans Images not available (?)  Fig. 1: Plan of the domus, now under the Collège Lumière.  Dates Gardens: Beginning and last third of second century
Excavation Dates 2004
Bibliography  C. Gaston and C. Munier “Une luxueuse domus de la find du IIe siècle à Besançon, college Lumière (Doubs, F)&amp;rdquo;&amp;rdquo; in Premières Journées archéologiques frontalières de l&amp;rsquo;Arc jurassien: Mandeure, sa campagne et ses relations d&amp;rsquo;Avenches à Luxeuil et d&amp;rsquo;Augst à Besançon. Ed, Cécile Bélet-Gonda, Presses Univ. Franche-Comté (2007), 103-112.  Pleiades ID 177657
TGN ID 7008356
Contributor Claudine Monier (ORCID: N/A)
Christophe Gaston (ORCID: https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6865-5108)
Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 20 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House in the Rue du Palais de Justice in Vesontio</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vesontio/vesontio_house_in_the_rue_du_palais_de_justice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2020 16:58:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vesontio/vesontio_house_in_the_rue_du_palais_de_justice/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Vesontio
Vesontio (Pleiades)
Location Description The defensibility offered by this unique geography made Caesar hasten to occupy Vesontio in 58 BC. The town came to have all the usual Roman structures– forum, baths, aqueduct, and amphitheater (on the other side of the Doubs, to the northwest.) But the most visible remnant is the Porte Noire (Black Gate) [3], a triumphal arch built by Marcus Aurelius at the southeastern end of the cardo maximus, today Grande Rue and still the center of city life.
Archaeology in a downtown area is always a matter of seizing opportunities as they are presented by new construction, remembering and recording what was found, and coming back years later to complete the picture. A good example of this process is at our second site, [2] on the map. In 1973, the Neptune Mosaic was discovered in rue de Lorraine, one of the largest floor decorations in all Gaul. The extent of the mosaic under nearby buildings made full excavation impossible. More than thirty years later, in 2004, construction of a gymnasium for the Collège Lumière (a middle school) gave archaeologists access to much more of the site, about 3000 square meters, for a salvage excavation. As expected, the continuation of the Neptune mosaic was found; moreover, three other mosaics of high quality, along with columns, sculpted blocks, peristyles, and monumental pools came to light. The results of this excavation have not been published; we are grateful to the excavators for sharing their preliminary results.
Garden House in the Rue du Palais de Justice in Vesontio
Keywords archaeological garden \
 domus fountains hypocausts mosaics (visual works) opus sectile (visual works) opus signinum oeci peristyles (columnades) piscinae porticoes terrazzo water wells  Garden Description In 2000-2001, at the time of construction a new judiciary facility, an area of 2000 square meters was excavated at the center of this loop. The results are in large part unpublished. On land that had been occupied since the end of the second century BC, two houses of perishable materials were built in the eastern part of the site in the beginning of the first century AD. They were abandoned at the beginning of the Flavian epoch, and replaced by two imposing domus that lasted up to the middle of the third century. They stood on opposite sides of a property line wall (tinted in purple in Fig. 1) that was parallel to a cardo running in a northwest-to-southeast direction some hundred meters away. The two houses had slightly different orientations. The eastern house doubtless opened onto a southwest-northeast street passing 50 meters beyond the eastern limit of the excavation but partially brought to light in 1989-90 during excavations when a new parking facility was being built for the city hall. In this house, two independent structures (oecus) (tinted pink in the figure) with floors once decorated with mosaics since disappeared are wrapped about and connected by a portico (yellow tint) of complex plan with galleries 3 meters wide and opening onto an open space (green tint) covering 110 square meters. The counterpart of this portico is in part visible on the other side of the larger room. An incompletely known peristyle borders this oecus to the east (on the lower right edge of the plan). Its gallery was decorated with a terrazzo floor of opus signinum with accents of crustae, thin stone slices of which an opus sectile is made. In this phase, the north domus had a peristyle of 75 square meters with galleries on three sides. To the west (lower left corner of the plan), there was a large open space of nearly 500 square meters, which may have been a garden. At its west end, the wall of an incomplete building ran by a well and a masonry square 2.16 meters on a side which may have been the base of a shrine or monument. These structures were aligned with the property line wall. There was as yet no pool.
In the second half of the second century, the “garden” was restructured. The building on the west side was abandoned, the shrine or monument was kept, and a large pool put in at the eastern end supported against the wall of a terrace supporting the house to the east and consequently having the same orientation. This rectangular pool (21.2 x 3.5 m) had on the garden side a semicircular apse 6.9 meters in diameter. As part of the same architectural ensemble, a portico formed the retro-scene of the pool. Its opus signinum floor was 80 centimeters above the surface of the pool. Another, wider portico ran along the north side of the area. A shim-shaped gap existed between it and the property-line wall because of the difference in orientation. The monumental character of the pool and the north portico suggests that this garden may have been independent of both houses and was possibly a public space or belonged to a house further west, outside the limits of excavation.
At the beginning of the third century, the two domus were transformed. In particular, polychrome mosaics were installed in the east house and rooms with hypocausts in the north house. The little shrine or monument at the western end of the garden was eliminated, but the pool was reconstructed without alteration. The paving stones that had been in a pool were in part removed and used to build a 3.8 x 2.9 meter platform which served as the base, presumably, of a quadrangular fountain in the north house in an open space which replaced the peristyle, which was then destroyed.
Images Images not available (?) FIGURES:
 Fig. 1: Houses at the Palais de Justice Fig. 2: Axonometric representation  Dates Beginning of the Flavian epoch - middle of the third century
Excavation Dates 2000-2001
Bibliography  C. Gaston, “Un bassin monumental et une fontaine dans les fouille du Palais de Justice de Besancon,” Revue Archéologique de l&amp;rsquo;Est, t. 52, 2003, p.417-428. Christophe Gaston: “Données récentes sur l&amp;rsquo;achitecture antique à Besançon,” Archéopages/Inrap. No. 8, Nov. 2002, p. 28-35. Laurent Vaxelaire, Philippe Barral, “Besançon: de l’oppidum à la ville romaine” in La naissance de la ville dans l’Antiquité, M. Reddé et al. ed., Paris, 2003, p. 254-256.  Pleiades ID 177657
TGN ID 7008356
Contributor Claudine Monier (ORCID: N/A)
Christophe Gaston (ORCID: https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6865-5108)
Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 19 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa in Vallon (Sur Dompierre, Canton de Fribourg, Switzerland)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vallon/vallon_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2020 17:12:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vallon/vallon_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Vallon
Vallon (Pleiades)
Garden Villa in Vallon (Sur Dompierre, Canton de Fribourg, Switzerland)
Keywords  arbors barns cisterns (plumbing components) ceramic tile ditches fences (site elements) hearths horrea kitchen gardens mosaics (visual works) orchards pedestals pillars piscinae porticoes sherds tesserae villae rusticae water supply systems  Garden Description Located 6km south-east of Avenches/ Aventicum, the capital of the Helvetian tribe, this site is situated on a small alluvial terrace at the bottom of a hillside. The area is bordered by a stream, the Laret, characterized by a flow, sometimes torrential, that has fluctuated during the past centuries. To the west, on the right bank, stands the rocky spur of Carignan (Fig. 1). Due to the relatively restrictive topography, human settlements favoured the left bank until the Middle Ages.
On the spur east of the stream, a building made of a light structure, apparently isolated, is constructed at the beginning of the 1st c. CE; it is bordered on its southern and northern sides by two roads. During the years 30/40 CE, a peripheral gallery on wooden pillars is placed around it. Its layout rather suggests an annex of a villa rustica or perhaps even a simple house in an urban context. Between 50 and 70 CE, it is surrounded by two other constructions, which together with the first building take on the characteristic shape of an “L”. The northern house is made of several habitation rooms; as it is bordered by a portico, it recalls the dwelling places of the medium-sized villae rusticae discovered in Switzerland. The southern building, surrounded by galleries, is laid out around a 100 m2 large kitchen, containing a large central hearth, which separates, to the south, the rooms designed for habitation, and the areas, to the north, apparently dedicated to utilitarian activities. At the back of the southern construction, a fourth building was erected, a barn (horreum) recognizable because of the network of pillars that supported an elevated floor.
A wall section, placed under a later separating wall, already indicates the existence of a division of the area between the northern and southern parts of the garden. The occupation layer is marked by a number of undated hollow structures. A ditch, boarded on the east by two big oval pits, distinguishes itself by its orientation which is parallel to the front of the central building, but its function still remains unknown: could it be an early garden arrangement? The only palynological analysis undertaken in a trench opened in the north building, suggest a tree canopy composed of a mixture of oaks, birches and hazel trees, in the second half of the 1st century CE; alders and willow trees could be found along the stream banks. An abundance of ferns and conifers grew in the surrounding areas. Herbaceous vegetation was intermingled with cereals. The information in our possession is too scarce to allow us to interpret it as a garden. Traces of equidistant posts or peg holes appear to form the outline of structures that are still difficult to explain (light arbour-like construction?). This open space is confined by a small bank to the south. Below it, the area is crossed by two long perpendicular depressions that could have a natural origin (paleochannel?), re-used as rubbish disposals at the beginning of our era. The south-east oriented channel, originally interpreted as a clay extraction pit, was cleared over a distance of approximately thirty meters. It was seven to eight meters wide, 1,2 meters deep and contained, in its lower part, several conduits made from pine trees (fig. 3). These timber elements were not assembled but stored in a humid environment before being used. The preparation and preservation of wood for plumbing systems, suggests the existence, from the first Antique settlements, of a very elaborate running water supply system, its use in domestic and/or handicraft or farming activities still needs to be clarified. Dendrochronology reveals two time series, dated to the autumn/winter 3/4 CE and 32/33 CE. These dates, that are contemporary with the first building stages of the villa, are very early for Switzerland and are close to Avenche’s first dated constructions.
The edges of the channel, which are gradually filled in, are bordered by two small fences in the last quarter of the Ist century; these fittings may be the result of a wish to stabilize the banks of the channel, clearly still under water at that time. Later on, the channel is filled in by a new rubbish disposal that seals the fences. We know nothing about the appearance of the area (courtyard or garden?) which extended between the channel and the southern building.
The profound architectural developments that took place in the three habitation buildings from the years 150/160 CE, had repercussions on the gardens (fig. 2). The occupation layer of the courtyards to the west of the buildings is raised by bringing in a large amount of ballast material. The subdivision of the garden zone is not precisely known. To the west of the constructed area, in the northern area bordered by the waterway, a pedestal indicates the presence of a statuary decoration that will be removed by the next generation. A long masonry wall, decorated with pillars presumably sculpted, is the only partition element brought to light. It marks the boundaries of an area interpreted as an ornamental garden, onto which the northern building and the northern part of the central building open. Divided into two zones, the oriental part of the northern garden is covered with tiles, revealing in its northern corner a fountain; it is replaced, in its western part, by soil around which a fence was probably built. It communicates directly with a second ornamental garden situated on the side of the central building, maybe destined for the private use of the family and close relatives. Here too, the remains are sparse: a patch stretches along the separation wall with the northern garden. A path followed the central building. Others must have crossed beds of plants edged with vertical ceramic elements. In other places, wooden posts formed rows that are still difficult to elucidate but that may indicate the outline of arbours. In the same place were found meander shaped ditches which do not follow the exact same orientation as the buildings (fig. 4). Were they hedges that were part of a vegetal maze? Despite the absence of palynological facts, they can be compared to the ditches excavated in the gardens of the Fishbourne Villa (England) or to those in the pars urbana of Dietikon’s villae (canton of Zurich).
At the end of the first archaeological excavations (1985-2000), we favoured the hypothesis of a subdivision of the area to the west of the buildings into three juxtaposed courtyards which echoed the tripartition of the constructions. They contained two ornamental gardens, in the north and in the center, and a courtyard that sheltered a kitchen garden and an orchard at the front of the southern building, dedicated to utilitarian activities (fig. 5). The recent research does not support a division of the area into three distinctive courtyards (2006/2010). The second garden, which presents a regular incline to the south, does not show any tangible boundary. Did it occupy the whole area in the front of the south building, or were they garden arrangements (hedges) dividing it? (fig. 6) Traces of vegetation being very hard to spot on the surface of the ground of the gardens, no definitive conclusion can be drawn.
The recent discovery of the lower part of a pool in front of the south building has also casts doubts on its utilitarian function. The structure itself, laid on a foundation of stakes made from oak and alder wood dated by dendrochonology to the years after 160 CE, has been almost entirely retrieved. The interpretation of this structure is still under discussion: it could be a cistern but it is more likely to be an ornamental pool that could have been enhanced by a parietal mosaic composed of the many glass tesserae that were found nearby. The structure, standing against the south building, would be oriented not towards the construction itself, but towards the courtyard where no garden arrangement has been uncovered.
Whereas the courtyards have offered very few traces for the Early Roman Period, the Late Antique Period marks a turning point in the history of Vallon’s gardens. Following a fire, the buildings are reorganized and areas dedicated to handicraft activities appear in the porticoes. A new function is attributed to the courtyards. The rubble of the partially demolished north and central buildings is discarded in the northern garden and the northern part of the second courtyard. To the south of themeander shaped ditches, is built a construction consisting of posts and sill plates, equipped with a ground hearth made out of ceramic tiles. The late occupation of the gardens seems to be linked to the salvage and transformation of building materials collected in the edifices. Other post structures (constructions? enclosures?) almost cover the whole area in the front of the southern building. The archaeological objects found (pottery fragments, over a hundred coins) suggest that this occupation partly covers the IVth century and does not go further than the beginning of the Vth century.
After the disappearance of the Antique site, the land continues to be occupied during the Early Middle Ages. The discovery of channels supports the hypothesis that the areas between the new buildings or on their sides, were well enough built to see the creation of an ornamental garden. However, the remains are too disrupted to allow further discussion.
Maps   Fig. 1: Vallon location map. (Rights Statement)     Fig. 2 : map of the habitation zone in the second half of the IInd century of our era.(Rights Statement)   Images   Fig. 3 : pine wood conduits preserved in one of the channels. Photo Fribourg State Archaeological Service. (Rights Statement)     Fig. 4 : ditches uncovered in the courtyard in front of the central building (2006). Photo Fribourg State Archaeological Service. (Rights Statement)     Fig. 5 : scale model of the habitation area in the second half of the IInd century. Built before the research in the gardens was resumed, it presents a considerable partitioning of the various open spaces. Photo Fribourg State Archaeological Service. (Rights Statement)     Fig. 6 : watercolour of the habitation area integrating the first results obtained by excavating the gardens. Please note the less significant partition between the different courtyards. The cistern at the front of the south building (to the right) is highly hypothetical; it seems rather to be an ornamental pool. Watercolour: Bernard Reymond, Yverdon-les-Bains (Switzerland). (Rights Statement)   Dates Beginning of the 1st c. CE - beginning of the Vth century
Excavation Dates 1985-2000, 2006/2010
Bibliography No bibliography listed Pleiades ID 981525
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor Michel Fuchs (ORCID: 0000-0001-8176-8393)
Jacques Monnier (ORCID: N/A)
Publication date 18 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Dietikon</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/dietikon/dietikon_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 13:09:50 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/dietikon/dietikon_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Dietikon
Dietikon (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Dietikon
Keywords  archaeological garden axial plan corridors pergolas piscinae porticoes villae rusticae  Garden Description This villa rustica complex was built on a site at the bottom of a valley near and parallel to the river Limmat. Dietikon was situated on an important land and water traffic route from the Bündner Alps to Vindonissa and further north to the Rhine. Recent excavations supply valuable evidence for a garden in front of the entrance to a rural residence, giving insight into the appearance of other similar villas at which, for one reason or another, no physical remains of gardens have been retrieved. The excavations revealed a first villa with timber buildings dating to the Tiberian period, or early 1st century AD. Around the middle of the 1st century AD these first buildings were replaced by an axially-constructed stone-built villa complex with an enclosure, covering a total surface of 13 hectares (Fig. 1 and 4).
In the residential part of the farm (pars urbana) was a large corridor villa with two protruding wings enclosing a courtyard area on three sides. This area was planted as an ornamental garden in the mid-1st century (Fig 2, G in Fig. 2). On either side of the central path, garden zones were bordered by bedding trenches, 20-25 centimeters deep and 20-40 centimeters wide. The line of plantings flanking the path are curved to form two niches (Fig. 3). In Dietikon, digging of planting trenches would have been necessary because the massive layers of construction debris deposited to level this area for the building would have hampered a successful growing of garden plants. The archaeobotanical analysis of several soil samples revealed little of relevance, but box hedges have been suggested as the vegetation in the bedding trenches, forming a low living edge to these formal garden beds, and possibly climbing plants such as ivy along the porticoed façade. Shallow pits in the plots surrounded by the hedges may be the remains of bedding pits for trees or shrubs. A timber pergola in the courtyard ran parallel to the northeast wing of the house. To the west of the courtyard garden was a timber-lined pool fed by a stream, interpreted as a fishpond. Bedding trenches for hedges surrounded it.
In the late 1st century, around AD 70, the timber-lined pool in the west was replaced by a masonry pool lined with water-proof plaster on the same spot (Fig. 5). This was possibly fed by water from a small stream. At the same time, the timber pergola was dismantled, its place taken by a large masonry pool, 3 x 22 meters in plan. The planting pattern of the courtyard garden was retained (Fig. 5) until after the middle of the 2nd century when the pools were destroyed and the garden leveled.
Plans   Fig. 1: Overall plan of the site during the 2nd half of the 1st century and 1st half 2nd century AD. Plan courtesy of Christa Ebnöther.     Fig. 2: Plan of the main building with its garden, phase 1, ca. 50-70 AD. Plan courtesy of Christa Ebnöther.     Fig. 3: Plan of the main building showing the curved plantings flanking the path. (Rights Statement)   Images   Fig. 4: Reconstructed perspective drawing. (Rights Statement)     Fig. 5: Photo of the masonry pool with planting pattern of the courtyard garden retained. (Rights Statement)   Dates Garden: Late 1st century (~70 CE) - Middle of the 2nd century
First buildings: Early 1st century CE - Middle of 1st century CE
Stone-built villa: Middle of the 1st century CE
Bibliography  C. Ebnöther, &amp;ldquo;Die Gartenanlage in der pars urbana des Gutshofes von Dietikon ZH,&amp;rdquo; Archäologie der Schweiz 14, 1991:250-256. (worldcat) C. Ebnöther, Der römische Gutshof in Dietikon. Monographien der Kantonsarchäologie Zürich 25, Zürich, 1995, pp. 36-45, 49-50, figs. 21, 36-37,41-42. (worldcat) L. Flutsch, U. Niffeler, F. Rossi, eds., La Suisse du Paléolithique à l’aube du Moyen-Age (SPM) V. Epoque romaine/Età Romana, Basel, 2002, p. 143, fig. 140. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981525
TGN ID 7007345
Contributor Christa Ebnöther
Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 15 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House in Insula 13 in Aventicum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_house_in_insula_13/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 10:06:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_house_in_insula_13/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Aventicum
Aventicum (Pleiades)
Location Description The town was established in the Augustan period as the civitas capital of the Helvetii. At this time the orthogonal street grid was laid out. Most probably in AD 71, it became Colonia Pia Flavia Constans Emerita Helvetiorum Foederata. The town was destroyed or badly damaged around AD 260, and it was progressively abandoned thereafter.
Garden House in Insula 13 in Aventicum
Keywords  archaeological garden bathhouses (water recreation structures) corridors fountains garden pavilions gutters (building drainage components) insulae peristyles (Roman courtyards) piscinae reception rooms  Garden Description Recent excavations in Insula 13 on the northwestern edge of the town have uncovered the remains of two large and luxurious houses separated from each other by a narrow corridor. They date to the late 1st century and were occupied until the middle of the 3rd century. Both buildings had a length of 60 meters, spanning the length of the insula. The eastern house included a private bath suite and an apsed reception room on the southwest.
The most remarkable feature of the building was a T-shaped garden courtyard (G in Fig. 1) surrounded by a peristyle on all sides (Fig. 1). A ground line gutter ran around the edge of the courtyard. In the southern part of the garden was a large pool paved with limestone slabs and measuring 6 x 12 meters On the northern edge of the pool was a rectangular fountain. To the north of this was a square structure measuring 5.40 x 5.40 meters which may have been a garden pavilion.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of a courtyard house in Insula 13 with a peristyle garden (G) and pool (grey). Plan adapted from Carroll 2001, fig. 20. (Rights statement)   Dates Houses: Late 1st century - Middle of 3rd century
Bibliography  J. Morel, &amp;ldquo;Chronique archéologique 1993,&amp;rdquo; Bull. de l&amp;rsquo;Association Pro Aventico 35, 1993: 19-21, figs. 8, 11. J. Morel, “L’habitat,” in : A. Hochuli-Gysel, ed., Avenches, capitale des Helvètes, Archéologie Suisse 24.1, 2001: 45-46, figs. 58, 60. (worldcat) M. Carroll, Romans, Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 55, fig. 20. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 177495
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 15 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden and Pool of Cingius Iustinus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/dalmatia/salona/salona_tomb_garden_and_pool_of_cingius_iustinus/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 16:52:02 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/dalmatia/salona/salona_tomb_garden_and_pool_of_cingius_iustinus/</guid>
      <description>Province Dalmatia
Location Salona
Salona (Pleiades)
Sublocation Garden Tomb Garden and Pool of Cingius Iustinus
Keywords  piscinae tombs epitaphs  Garden Description A rock cut inscription at Salonae marks the spot where some time in the late second or third century Cingius Iustinus made a fishpond or pool (piscina) in the garden of his wife Aelia Licinia for her and for himself (fecit piscinam in horto Aeliae Liciniae coiugi incomparabili et sibi). No tomb is mentioned, but the dedication D(is) M(anibus) identifies the text as an epitaph and thus points to a funerary context.
Maps Plans Images Dates Late second or third century (CE)
Bibliography  CIL 3.2279  Pleiades ID 197488
TGN ID 7017320
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 14 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Palatial House in Insula 7 in Aventicum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_palatial_house_in_insula_7/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 14:48:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_palatial_house_in_insula_7/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Aventicum
Aventicum (Pleiades)
Location Description The town was established in the Augustan period as the civitas capital of the Helvetii. At this time the orthogonal street grid was laid out. Most probably in AD 71, it became Colonia Pia Flavia Constans Emerita Helvetiorum Foederata. The town was destroyed or badly damaged around AD 260, and it was progressively abandoned thereafter.
Garden Palatial House in Insula 7 in Aventicum
Keywords  archaeological garden axial plan bathhouses (water recreation structures) drains exedrae (site elements) mosaics (visual works) palaces peristyles (Roman courtyards) piscinae presence chambers  Garden Description The remains of a palatial house (Palais de Derrière la Tour) were recently uncovered in excavations on the western edge of the city in an area characterized by luxurious domestic dwellings (Fig. 1). The house in its final state, from the Severan period to the middle of the 3rd century, had a peristyle courtyard measuring 42 x 69 meters. North of the courtyard was a reception room 12 x 18 meters in plan with a mosaic floor.
The courtyard was on two levels, divided on the north by a terrace wall with two small exedrae, possibly pools. An axially arranged central pathway between the reception room on the north and an apsed triclinium on the south further divided the courtyard into an eastern and a western half. Steps led up to the triclinium and to the northern wing of the house. A ground level gutter ran around the courtyard, and a covered drain crossed it beneath the central path. It can reasonably be assumed that the courtyard was designed as a garden (G in Fig. 1) with garden elements such as the path and the exedral pools. With the addition on the northeast of another wing terminating in a bath complex, the building ultimately had a length of around 200 meters. The excavators believe that the building in its latest phase had official character.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the courtyard house or palace on the western fringe of Insula 7, with a garden courtyard (G) with two small apsidal pools on one side. Plan adapted from Morel 1995, fig. 4. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Severnan Period - Middle of 3rd century
Bibliography  J. Morel, “Avenches VD, Derrière la Tour et insula 7 : Fouilles 1989/1990,” Annuaire de la Société Suisse de Préhistoire et d’Archéologie 74, 1991: 214-220, fig. 2. (worldcat) J. Morel, “Avenches, Palais de Derrière la Tour,” Bull. de l’Association Pro Aventico 37, 1995: 206-209, fig. 4.(worldcat) J. Morel, “L’habitat,” in : A. Hochuli-Gysel, ed., Avenches, capitale des Helvètes, Archéologie Suisse 24.1 2001: 47-49, fig. 62.(worldcat)  Pleiades ID 177495
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 14 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural villa at Voerendaal</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/voerendaal/voerendaal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:58:07 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/voerendaal/voerendaal/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Province Description Location Voerendaal
Voerendaal (Pleiades)
Garden Rural villa at Voerendaal
Keywords  villae rusticae porticoes piscinae hedges courtyards  Garden Description The stone-built structures of this villa rustica near the Meuse river, the largest excavated thus far in the Netherlands, were erected in the early 2nd century and repeatedly enlarged until the abandonment of the farm around 300 A.D. (Plan 1). The total area of the farm, including the cultivated land, is calculated to have been ca. 150 hectares. The main residence (A on plan) lay in the northern half of the complex which measured 167 x 214 m. (3.5 hectares) in size. The porticoed facade in its final state was 190 m. long.
In front of the house to the south was a large area (17 x 37 m.), enclosed by a stone wall on two sides and villa porticoes on the other sides. This has been interpreted as a formal garden (G on plan) with low plantings, hedges and a pool (P on plan; Image 1 [NO IMAGE INCLUDED]). The main road leading from the gate in the south to the house in the north cut through this enclosed area. The excavators postulate a vegetable garden behind the house for easy, daily access. The boundaries of the farm complex were planted with a row of trees or a hedge, the planting pits of which had survived. The many carbonized grains of wheat and chaff found in and around a large building in the northeastern part of the courtyard enclosure suggest that wheat grown in the fields of the farm was processed here. The main crop at Voerendaal was spelt; very little emmer or bread wheat was present in the organic remains.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the rural villa with a possible walled garden (G) and its pool (P) south of the house (A). Hedges (rows of dots) enclosed the farmyard. Adapted from Willems 1992, Fig. 307. (Rights statement).   Images Dates Early second century CE to ca. 300 CE
Bibliography  W.J.H. Willems, &amp;ldquo;Die kaiserzeitliche Villa von Voerendaal&amp;rdquo;, in Spurensicherung. Archäologische Denkmalpflege in der Euregio Maas-Rhein, Mainz, 1992, pp. 526-534, figs. 307-308. worldcat P. Van Ossel, Établissements ruraux de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquité tardive dans le nord de la Gaule, Paris, 1992, pp. 363-365, fig. 155. worldcat  Pleiades ID 109442
TGN ID 7272601
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rustic villa at Rheinbach-Flerzheim</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/rheinbach-flerzheim/rheinbach-flerzheim/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:57:12 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/rheinbach-flerzheim/rheinbach-flerzheim/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Province Description Location Rheinbach-Flerzheim
Garden Rustic villa at Rheinbach-Flerzheim
Keywords  villae rusticae hedges bathhouses (water recreation structures) kitchen gardens piscinae  Garden Description There was no division between the residential and service parts of this modest farm. The house, with its bath (A and B on plan), and the outbuildings were built of stone at the beginning of the 2nd century (Plan 1). The winged corridor type house of this villa rustica was 37 m. long and 20 m. wide, and it had a bath attached to the back.
Enclosing the farm complex was a hedge or row of trees, the planting trenches of which were uncovered in excavations (gray wavy border on plan). Based on the palaeobotanical evidence of carbonised plant remains and pollen, a kitchen garden near the house and fruit trees on the property have been reconstructed. In front of the entrance to the main residence at the south were the remains of a small pool lined with clay. This has been taken as evidence for an ornamental garden surrounding the pool. On a farm of this modest size and simplicity, however, an ornamental garden seems rather unlikely. The farm was occupied until the mid-5th century.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the farmyard with its house (A) and bath (B) enclosed by a hedge (grey line). The open circles are wells. Adapted from Carroll 2001, fig. 38. (Rights statement).   Images Dates Second century CE to mid-fifth century CE
Bibliography  M. Gechter, &amp;ldquo;Der römische Gutshof von Rheinbach-Flerzheim,&amp;rdquo; in Spurensicherung. Archäologische Denkmalpflege in der Euregio Maas-Rhein, Mainz, 1992, pp. 249-54, 452-60. worldcat M. Carroll, Romans, Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 79, fig. 38. worldcat  Pleiades ID 981524
TGN ID 7192890
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 25 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa at Neerhaaren-Rekem</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/neerhaaren-rekem/neerharen-rekem/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:54:58 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/neerhaaren-rekem/neerharen-rekem/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Neerhaaren-Rekem
Neerhaaren-Rekem (Pleiades)
Garden Rural villa at Neerhaaren-Rekem
Keywords- rural villas  villae rusticae arbors pergolas piscinae  Garden Description The facade of this modest house of a villa rustica near the Meuse river measured 24 m. in length and had two protruding wings joined by a portico (Plan 1). The house was built in the late 1st century A.D. There is evidence for an arbor or pergola next to the house in the form of two rows of postholes arranged diagonally and converging in front of the entrance on the west (circles on plan). Between the rows of posts, each measuring ca. 15 m. in length, and around which some kind of vines or other climbing plants may have been trained to grow, was a small pool.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the farm house at Neerhaaren-Rekem with a possible arbor leading to the door and a pool (grey) between the posts of the arbor. Plan adapted from De Boe, De Bie and Van Impe 1992, fig. 288. Rights statement.   Images Dates Late first century CE
Bibliography  G. De Boe, M. De Bie, and L. Van Impe, &amp;ldquo;Heerharen-Rekem. Die komplexe Besiedlungsgeschichte einer vor den Kiesbaggern geretteten Fundstätte,&amp;rdquo; in Spurensicherung. Archäologische Denkmalpflege in der Euregio Maas-Rhein, Mainz, 1992, pp. 490-493, fig. 288. worldcat P. Van Ossel, Établissements ruraux de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquité tardive dans le nord de la Gaule, Paris, 1992, pp. 297-300, fig. 105. worldcat  Pleiades ID 109193
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban House on Gertrudenstrasse</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_gertrudenstrasse/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:51:27 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_gertrudenstrasse/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Garden Urban house on Gertrudenstrasse (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords  urban villas villae urbanae peristyles (Roman courtyards) apsed pools piscinae  Garden Description This Mediterranean-type house just inside the western city wall had a peristyle courtyard ca. 9 x 14 m. in size, in the middle of which was a pool (3 x 8 m.) with apsidal ends (P on Plan 1).
The courtyard was unpaved, and the presence of a source of water suggests that it was designed as a garden (G on Plan 1). Although the house was only partially excavated, evidence for several rebuildings from the second half of the 1st to the 4th century was retrieved. The peristyle courtyard was retained throughout, indicating the importance attached to the garden by generations of owners.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the partially preserved house with a peristyle courtyard garden (G) and pool (P) on Gertrudenstraße. Adapted from Thomas 1993, fig. 3. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Middle of the first century CE until the fourth century CE
Bibliography  R. Thomas, Römische Wandmalerei in Köln, Mainz, 1993, pp. 321-327, figs. 138-39. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108751
TGN ID 7004446
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 12 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roman Palace in Fishbourne</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/fishbourne/fishbourne_roman_palace/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 18:05:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/fishbourne/fishbourne_roman_palace/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Location Fishbourne
Fishbourne (Pleiades)
Garden Roman Palace in Fishbourne
Keywords  archaeological garden basins (vessels) colonnades loam palaces piscinae presence chambers terrace gardens vegetable gardens  Garden Description Fishbourne Roman Palace was accidentally discovered during the digging of a water main trench in 1960. The discovery led to nine seasons of excavations (1961-69) that showed the site had developed from a military base at the time of the Roman invasion in AD 43 to a sumptuous palace by the end of the first century CE. Carefully excavated by Barry Cunliffe, using techniques of environmental archaeology, the garden excavations at the palace have long served as a model in the development of Roman garden archaeology, although the findings did not initially prompt the investigation of other gardens in Britain. Today the site has been developed for display and education.
The palace contains gardens within its internal courtyards, as well in a larger area to the south, where terraces and other landscape architectural features lay between the residence and the deep water channel (Fig 1.). The main garden of the palace is located in the large central courtyard, and dates to the late 1st century CE. Only the northern half has been excavated, while the remainder lies beneath the gardens of adjacent houses. The garden is bisected by a wide path leading between the entrance to the villa and a large audience hall. Lining the path, bedding trenches in alternating rectangular and semi-circular patterns survived as patterns of dark gray loam against an ochre-colored clay and gravel subsoil. Similar cuttings were found along the colonnades.
Pollen samples were taken in the garden areas in the hope that traces of pollen had survived from flowers and shrubs that had grown in the garden. Unfortunately, only a small quantity of pollen from weeds of cultivation, such as plantain and daisy, remained. As no positive archaeobotanical evidence for specific plants survived on site, literary sources were used to select plants that would have survived in the conditions of this northern province. Pliny the Younger refers to clipped box lining the edges of the pathways in the gardens of his Tuscan estate. This lime-loving shrub would have been very appropriate in the deliberately marled loam of these trenches, so, in 1968, it was planted and has thrived. Figure 2 shows the excavated trenches, and figure 3 shows the replanted box.
On the eastern side of the formal garden, alternating tree-pits and post holes were found. The pattern suggested an original arrangement of trees or shrubs planted against a trellis. Again, Pliny the Younger mentions espaliered apples in his gardens, and these have been successfully established at Fishbourne. Less successful was the effort to establish Italian cypress in the location of a large tree-pit found towards the western side of the garden.
Beneath the surface of the garden, the excavators discovered lines of ceramic pipes. They ran from the remains of the base of what is assumed to have been a water storage tank in the northwest corner of the formal garden. One line of pipes probably fed a pool in the entrance hall while others supplied small semi-circular basins set in recesses in the box hedging. Half a marble basin was found in the 1960&amp;rsquo;s.
There is circumstantial evidence for there having been a vegetable garden in the angle between the ends of the north and west wings of the palace where there is a dark, humus-rich soil containing heavily abraded pottery, suggesting that the soil had been intensively cultivated. It also had its own water supply, provided through wooden pipes with iron collars.
Limited excavations to the south of the palace revealed an artificial terrace which bore evidence of landscaping, including a pool, a gravel path, possible bedding trenches and what may have been the base for a column or statue. Excavations to the east of the palace in the mid 1980&amp;rsquo;s uncovered evidence for semi-formal gardens.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the Roman Palace showing the position of the gardens. Courtesy of David Rudkin for Fishbourne Roman Palace.   Images   Fig. 2: View of formal garden excavation. Photo courtesy of David Rudkin for Fishbourne Roman Palace.     Fig. 3: View of replanted formal garden. Photo courtesy of David Rudkin for Fishbourne Roman Palace.   Dates Late 1st century CE - unspecified
Excavation Dates 1961-69, mid 1980s
Bibliography  Barry Cunliffe, Excavations at Fishbourne, 1961-1969, Vols I &amp;amp; II, The Society of Antiquaries, London, 1971.(worldcat) B. W. Cunliffe, A.G. Down, and D. Rudkin, Excavations at Fishbourne 1969-1988, Chichester, 1996.(worldcat) B. Cunliffe, Fishbourne Roman Palace, Tempus, 1998. (worldcat) Amina-Aïcha Malek, A Sourcebook of Garden Archaeology, Bern: Peter Lang, 2012.(worldcat)  Pleiades ID 79466
TGN ID 7032567
Contributor Kathryn Gleason (ORCID:0000-0001-6260-8378)
Publication date 09 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Atrium House</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_atrium/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 07:38:05 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_atrium/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Garden Atrium House (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords  urban villas villae urbanae atrium houses atriums tablina colonnades peristyles (Roman courtyards) apsed pools piscinae  Garden Description West of the House of Dionysos stood the so-called &amp;ldquo;atrium house&amp;rdquo; which covered an area of 1400 sq. m. (Plan 1). It was built around the middle of the 1st century A.D.
Entering from the colonnaded street at the west, one passed through a room reconstructed as an atrium, continuing along a corridor around the tablinum, and arrived at a peristyle courtyard with a semicircular pool. This courtyard, approximately 10 x 13 m. in size, was almost certainly a garden (Plan 1, G). A ground level gutter ran around the edge of the unpaved courtyard. This part of the house remained unchanged until the destruction of the building in the 4th century.
Maps Plans   Plan 1: Plan of the so-called &amp;#39;atrium house&amp;#39; with an apsidal pool (P) in its garden courtyard (G). Adapted from Precht 1971, fig. 2. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Middle of the first century CE until the fourth century CE
Bibliography  G. Precht, &amp;ldquo;Die Ausgrabungen um den Kölner Dom. Vorbericht über die Untersuchungen,&amp;rdquo; Kölner Jahrbuch 12, 1971:55-56, fig. 2, pl. 7.2. (worldcat) H. Hellenkemper, &amp;ldquo;Architektur als Beitrag zur Geschichte der CCAA,&amp;rdquo; in H. Temporini, ed., Aufstieg und Niedergang der Römischen Welt II.4, Berlin, 1974, p. 810, figs. 20-21. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108751
TGN ID 7004446
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 09 July 2020
Related articles House of Dionysos (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of Dionysius</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_dionysius/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 20:22:59 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_dionysius/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Garden House of Dionysius (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords  urban villas villae urbanae triclinia insulae peristyles (Roman courtyards) apsed pools axial plan piscinae  Garden Description The largest urban villa excavated thus far in Cologne is the House of Dionysos (3400 sq. m.), named after the early 3rd century mosaic floor decorated with Dionysiac motifs in the triclinium (Image 1??). The house occupies part of an insula in the northeastern corner of the city, bordered on the south by a street leading to the harbor.
The original house, erected after A.D. 50, was rebuilt under Vespasian and included a peristyle garden courtyard measuring 23 x 27 m. (G on Plan 1). The garden was surrounded on three sides by a peristyle, 3.35 m. in width. A ground level gutter ran around the edge of the garden. At this time, a masonry pool with a paved floor occupied a position in the eastern part of the garden. A piece of lead pipe and a bronze opening were found associated with the pool. This was later replaced in the second half of the 2nd century by an apsed pool (4.20 x 5.40 m.) in the western half of the garden which drained into the gutter at the west. The pool was axially arranged between the entrance to the house on the east and the dining room on the west, from which a view through a wide doorway onto the garden was afforded. The triclinium was unheated, leading the excavator to interpret it as a summer triclinium. The connection with the garden would, in this case, be quite understandable. An axial planting pattern in the garden with a path leading from the entrance of the house to the pool is possible. There is, however, no evidence for the planting pattern or the type of vegetation in this garden. The house was inhabited until the 4th century.
Maps Plans   Plan 1: Plan of the House of Dionysos, built around a central courtyard garden (G) with a pool (grey). Plan adapted from Fremersdorf 1956, fig. 27. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Reign of Vespasian until the end of the fourth century CE
Bibliography  F. Fremersdorf, Das römische Haus mit dem Dionysosmosaik vor dem Südportal des Kölner Doms, Berlin, 1956. (worldcat) M. Carroll, Romans, Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 55, fig. 20. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108751
TGN ID 7004446
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Eccles</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/eccles/eccles_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 17:53:24 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/eccles/eccles_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Eccles
Eccles (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Eccles
Keywords  archaeological garden ditches drains horticultural containers piscinae rural villas villae rusticae water baths  Garden Description This country estate in modern Kent possessed a large ornamental pool (P in Fig. 1) in the area in front of the main residence (A in Fig. 1) and to the east of the attached bath house (Fig. 1). The masonry pool measuring 25 x 3.50 meters lay parallel to the house frontage. From the pool ran a masonry drain. Although no traces of bedding trenches or plantings have been detected in the yard around the pool, it might be assumed that the pool was a centerpiece of a garden (G in Fig. 1). Interestingly, in the backfill of a ditch under the southeast wing of the villa at least thirty planting pots were retrieved in excavations. The vessels had three knife-cut triangular holes in the lower body and a round hole through the base (Fig. 2, nest page). The pots were misfired and almost certainly manufactured in kilns near the villa in the decade after A.D. 50. Although the planting pots were not found in context in pits within a garden, it is clear that they were being produced locally for use at Eccles or other gardens nearby. Excavations have established that the estate was continually occupied from the middle of the 1st century until the 4th century. In its final 4th century form, the villa complex measured 89 x 116 meters, including its wings and the courtyard.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the villa with the main house (A), a possible garden (G) and a large pool (P). Adapted from Detsicas 1983, fig. 25. (Rights statement)   Images   Fig. 2: Clay planting pot with cut-out holes. Adapted from Detsicas 1981, fig. 26.2. (Rights statement)   Dates Middle of 1st century - 4th century
Bibliography  A. Detsicas, The Cantiaci, Gloucester, 1983, pp. 103-107, fig. 20. (worldcat) R.J. Zeepvat, “Fishponds in Roman Britain,” in: M. Aston, ed., Medieval Fish, Fisheries and Fishponds in England. British Archaeological Reports, Brit. Ser. 182, Oxford, 1988, p. 18, fig. 2. (worldcat) A. Detsicas, “A group of pottery from Eccles, Kent,” in Roman Pottery Research in Britain and Northwest Europe, British Archaeological Reports, Int. Ser. 123, Oxford, 1981, pp. 441-445.  Pleiades ID 79448
TGN ID 1029144
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Darenth</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/darenth/darenth_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 12:08:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/darenth/darenth_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Darenth
Darenth (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Darenth
Keywords  archaeological garden kitchen gardens piscinae rural villas villae rusticae waterspouts  Garden Description Excavations at this site of a Roman villa in Kent uncovered a large rectangular masonry pool in the courtyard, which was enclosed by buildings on the north, west, and east (Fig. 1). The villa buildings took up an area of 150 x 225 meters in total, including the courtyard with a width of 26.5 meters. Occupation at the site began after A.D. 100 and continued until the closing decades of the 4th century.
This pool (P in Fig. 1), measuring 25.6 x 3.36 meters, lay at right angles to the center of the main residence and bisected an enclosed courtyard, possibly a garden (G in Fig. 1) in front of the house. The pool would have been a decorative element in the courtyard. Within the pool at the end nearest the house was found a small bronze water-spout in the form of the head of a lioness. At the other end was a semi-circular pool with provision for the inflow and outflow of water.
South of the western range of rooms was a large, open space measuring 14.6 x 58.4 meters, enclosed by walls. There was no paving in this area, nor was there any evidence for partitions. It has been suggested that this might have been a kitchen garden (G in Fig. 1).
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the villa with the main house (A), garden areas (G), and a large pool (P). Adapted from Detsicas 1983, fig. 20. (Rights statement)   Dates After 100 CE - Closing decades of the 4th century
Bibliography  A. Detsicas, The Cantiaci, Gloucester, 1983, pp. 103-107, fig. 20. (worldcat) B. Philp, Excavations in the Darent Valley, Kent, Gloucester, 1984, pp. 89-92, figs. 24, 33. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 79413
TGN ID 7027349
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Bancroft</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/bancroft/bancroft_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2020 18:04:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/bancroft/bancroft_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Bancroft
Garden Rural Villa in Bancroft
Keywords  archaeological garden bathhouses (water recreation structures) drains gazebos horticultural containers piscinae villae rusticae  Garden Description Excavations between 1983 and 1986 at this site in Buckinghamshire revealed a Roman villa of the winged corridor type, which was built in the late 3rd century and rebuilt and enlarged in the mid-4th century (Fig.1).
From the two projecting wings of the house at the northeast and southeast two walls ran eastward, forming an enclosed courtyard 35.5 meters in width and ca. 42 meters in length in front of the 4th century house. In the centre of the yard was a stone-built rectangular fishpond (P in Fig. 1), 2.6 x 13 meters in size and 50-80 centimeters deep which was continually fed by a drain running from an overflow in the cold plunge bath at the south end of the house. An overflow at the east end of the pool may have led to a nearby stream. Although traces of plantings or planting beds were not preserved in the gravelly subsoil, a shallow rectangular depression just west of the fishpool, filled with dark humic soil, may represent a flowerbed through which the water pipe feeding the pool ran. The courtyard therefore was at least partially planted as a garden (G in Fig. 1). Adjacent to the courtyard enclosure at the south was an octagonal structure with stone walls, interpreted as a possible gazebo (A in Fig. 1).
The villa complex that preceded the winged corridor house is also of interest in regard to gardens. The earlier aisled house of late 1st to late 2nd century date was part of a series of buildings and enclosures that included a walled area to the northeast measuring 27 x 18.3 meters in size. Inside this enclosure was a deposit of dark humic soil between 4 and 6 centimeters deep. Environmental analysis of soil samples from the enclosure suggests that the area was used as a kitchen garden with plants such as brassicas, celery, mustard, coriander, summer savory and caper spurge. Three ceramic vessels with at least one hole pierced through the side or the base, possibly planting pots, may have been associated with this phase of the villa garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the villa with its garden courtyard (G), a central pool (P), and a possible gazebo (A). Adapted from Zeepvat 1991, fig. 5.4.(Rights statement.)   Dates Roman villa&amp;hellip; built in the late 3rd century and rebuilt and enlarged in the mid-4th century.
Excavation Dates 1983-1986
Bibliography  R. J. Williams and R. J. Zeepvat, Bancroft. The late Bronze Age and Iron Age Settlement and Roman Villa and Temple-Mausoleum. Buckinghamshire Archaeological Society Monograph Series 7, Aylesbury, 1994, pp. 154, 163, 188-191, figs. 66, 80, 83, 85, 93, 101-103, pls. 57-59. (worldcat) R.J. Zeepvat, “Roman Gardens in Britain,” in: A. E. Brown, ed., Garden Archaeology. Council for British Archaeology Research Report 78, London, 1991, pp. 56-58, fig. 5.4. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 79312
TGN ID 7030316
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 07 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>