<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>mosaics on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/mosaics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in mosaics on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 09:48:09 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/mosaics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Structures under the Collège Lumière in Vesontio</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vesontio/vesontio_structures_under_the_colle%CC%80ge_lumie%CC%80re/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 09:48:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vesontio/vesontio_structures_under_the_colle%CC%80ge_lumie%CC%80re/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Province Description Location Vesontio
Vesontio (Pleiades)
Location Description The defensibility offered by this unique geography made Caesar hasten to occupy Vesontio in 58 BC. The town came to have all the usual Roman structures– forum, baths, aqueduct, and amphitheater (on the other side of the Doubs, to the northwest.) But the most visible remnant is the Porte Noire (Black Gate) [3], a triumphal arch built by Marcus Aurelius at the southeastern end of the cardo maximus, today Grande Rue and still the center of city life.
Archaeology in a downtown area is always a matter of seizing opportunities as they are presented by new construction, remembering and recording what was found, and coming back years later to complete the picture. A good example of this process is at our second site, [2] on the map. In 1973, the Neptune Mosaic was discovered in rue de Lorraine, one of the largest floor decorations in all Gaul.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House in the Rue du Palais de Justice in Vesontio</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vesontio/vesontio_house_in_the_rue_du_palais_de_justice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2020 16:58:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vesontio/vesontio_house_in_the_rue_du_palais_de_justice/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Province Description Location Vesontio
Vesontio (Pleiades)
Location Description The defensibility offered by this unique geography made Caesar hasten to occupy Vesontio in 58 BC. The town came to have all the usual Roman structures– forum, baths, aqueduct, and amphitheater (on the other side of the Doubs, to the northwest.) But the most visible remnant is the Porte Noire (Black Gate) [3], a triumphal arch built by Marcus Aurelius at the southeastern end of the cardo maximus, today Grande Rue and still the center of city life.
Archaeology in a downtown area is always a matter of seizing opportunities as they are presented by new construction, remembering and recording what was found, and coming back years later to complete the picture. A good example of this process is at our second site, [2] on the map. In 1973, the Neptune Mosaic was discovered in rue de Lorraine, one of the largest floor decorations in all Gaul.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa in Vallon (Sur Dompierre, Canton de Fribourg, Switzerland)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vallon/vallon_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2020 17:12:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/vallon/vallon_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Province Description Location Vallon
Vallon (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Villa in Vallon (Sur Dompierre, Canton de Fribourg, Switzerland)
Keywords arbors
barns
barrier walls
ceramic tile
ditches
fences (site elements)
hearths
horrea
kitchen gardens
mosaics (visual works)
orchards
pedestals
pillars
piscinae
porticoes
rural villas
sherds
tesserae
villae rusticae
water supply systems
Garden Description Located 6km south-east of Avenches/ Aventicum, the capital of the Helvetian tribe, this site is situated on a small alluvial terrace at the bottom of a hillside. The area is bordered by a stream, the Laret, characterized by a flow, sometimes torrential, that has fluctuated during the past centuries. To the west, on the right bank, stands the rocky spur of Carignan (Fig. 1). Due to the relatively restrictive topography, human settlements favoured the left bank until the Middle Ages.
On the spur east of the stream, a building made of a light structure, apparently isolated, is constructed at the beginning of the 1st c.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Bad Kreuznach</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/bad_kreuznach/bad_kreuznach_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 12:39:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/bad_kreuznach/bad_kreuznach_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Province Description Location Bad Kreuznach
Bad Kreuznach (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Bad Kreuznach
Keywords apsed triclinium
colonnades
cryptoportici
fountains
gutters (building drainage components)
lararia
mosaics (visual works)
peristyles (Roman courtyards)
porticoes
rural villas
villae rusticae
Garden Description This villa, almost 6000 square meters in size, gives eloquent testimony to the wealth and status of the owner of the rural estate. The estate was built in the second half of the 2nd century and occupied until its destruction around 275.
The three-storied villa with more than 50 rooms on the ground floor alone, many decorated with mosaics and imported marble revetment, was centered on a colonnaded garden courtyard (G in Fig. 1). Many of the sandstone columns from the peristyle, as well as fragments of sculpture from the garden, were found in the courtyard. The house was built into a hill, and the courtyard was terraced on two levels.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Palatial House in Insula 7 in Aventicum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_palatial_house_in_insula_7/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 14:48:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/aventicum/aventicum_palatial_house_in_insula_7/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Province Description Location Aventicum
Aventicum (Pleiades)
Location Description The town was established in the Augustan period as the civitas capital of the Helvetii. At this time the orthogonal street grid was laid out. Most probably in AD 71, it became Colonia Pia Flavia Constans Emerita Helvetiorum Foederata. The town was destroyed or badly damaged around AD 260, and it was progressively abandoned thereafter.
Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Palatial House in Insula 7 in Aventicum
Keywords archaeological garden
axial plan
bathhouses (water recreation structures)
drains
exedrae (site elements)
mosaics (visual works)
palaces
peristyles (Roman courtyards)
piscinae
presence chambers
Garden Description The remains of a palatial house (Palais de Derrière la Tour) were recently uncovered in excavations on the western edge of the city in an area characterized by luxurious domestic dwellings (Fig. 1). The house in its final state, from the Severan period to the middle of the 3rd century, had a peristyle courtyard measuring 42 x 69 meters.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>