<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>praetoriums on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/praetoriums/</link>
    <description>Recent content in praetoriums on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:57:44 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/praetoriums/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Legionary Houses at Castra Vetera (Germania Inferior)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/castra_vetera/ger_inf_castra_vetera/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:57:44 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/castra_vetera/ger_inf_castra_vetera/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Province Description Location Castra Vetera
Castra Vetera (Pleiades)
Garden Legionary houses at Castra Vetera (Germania inferior)
Keywords  castra praetoriums atriums peristyles (Roman courtyards) tablina pedestals Pliny the Younger  Garden Description In the Neronian fort of the 5th and 15th legions near the civilian settlement of Colonia Ulpia Traiana were two vast buildings on either side of the headquarters building (principia). These were the residences, or praetoria, of the two legionary commanders. The western palatial complex was 76-77 m. in width and 97 m. in length (over 7400 sq. m.) (Plan 1). It was entered from the east through a vestibule and an atrium. The villa had several peristyle courtyards, including one long peristyle courtyard with apsidal ends which has been interpreted as a garden (G on plan). Between the atrium and the apsidal courtyard was a large room, possibly a tablinum or a dining room. This courtyard measured 18.80 x 83 m. and had an open area 10.80 m. wide, surrounded on all sides by a covered columned walkway, 3.50 m. in width.
The partially excavated eastern villa was 78.50 m. wide and 109 m. in length. It too had several peristyle courtyards and one long courtyard 19 x 74.60 m. in size. The open area between the covered walkways was 5.80 m. wide. In front of each of the columns surrounding the courtyard were buttress-like foundations which the excavator interpreted as possible bases for statues. The excavator referred to the long courtyards in these houses as &amp;ldquo;hippodrome gardens&amp;rdquo;, and compared them to known stadium or hippodrome gardens at Pliny&amp;rsquo;s Tuscan villa, on the Palatine in Rome (Domus Augustana) and at Hadrian&amp;rsquo;s villa at Tivoli. The comparison is unacceptable, however, since both ends of the courtyards in the legionary camp are apsidal, unlike a stadium or hippodrome which has one straight end. The long garden courtyards at Xanten may have had more in common with the long, apsidal gardens referred to by Pliny as gestatio in modum circi (Epist. 5.6.17). It can be considered reasonably certain that the courtyards in both legionary villas were not foreseen for races or athletic activities, but for gardens as an ideal place for promenades.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the western *praetorium* in the double legionary base with its long apsidal garden (G). Adapted from Lehner 1930, fig. 39. (Rights statement).   Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  H. Lehner, Vetera. Die Ergebnisse der Ausgrabungen des Bonner Provinzialmuseums bis 1929. Römisch-Germanische Forschungen 4, Berlin, 1930, pp. 52-60, figs. 38-41. worldcat  Pleiades ID 108867
TGN ID 7004944
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 25 July 2020
Related articles The Houses of Insula 7 in Colonia Ulpia Traiana</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>