<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>pilasters on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/tags/pilasters/</link>
    <description>Recent content in pilasters on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 00:10:10 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/tags/pilasters/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>II.ix.6.B</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_ix/ii.ix.6b/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/insula_ix/ii.ix.6b/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient city of Campania destroyed by the volcanic eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D. 79, Pompeii was named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Sublocation Region II
Insula Insula IX
Keywords  peristyles porticoes pilasters puteals lararia opus signinum doliums  Garden Description B. This vineyard section of the property was excavated in 1984 by Dr. De Caro. A small peristyle garden (b) was enclosed on the east and south by a three column portico with a pilaster on the southwest corner. A low wall joined the pilaster and the west column on the south side with a terra-cotta puteal incorporated into it. The north and east sides of the garden had a gutter. The south part of this vineyard had a small house with a garden painting on the west wall. The excavators found the painting to be badly damaged but a section showing a lattice fence 0.68 m. high with leaves and flowers behind remained on the right two-thirds of the building. All of the painting above the fence had been lost. A huge lararium was built against the north portion of the wall which partially covered the image of a Frejus type statuette of Venus 0.87 m. high. An entrance from the east portico¬ led directly to the vineyard which had been in production at the time of the eruption. At the front of the house on the west end a treading floor for the grapes had been built. The floor was raised, enclosed by a low wall 18 cm. high, and paved with opus signinum. The juice would run into a pair of dolium buried in the soil at the east edge of the floor. Fig. 81, 16.11.70, Fig. 82, 7.14.71; Fig. 83, 7.16.71; Fig. 84, 7.28.71; Fig. 85, 9.25.71, Fig. 86, 9.26.71, Fig. 87, 49.10.64, Fig. 88, 54.20.64.
Plans   Fig. 75, Plan of Region II, insula ix   Images   Fig. 81, 16.11.70 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 82, 7.14.71 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 83, 7.16.71 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 84, 7.28.71 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 85, 9.25.71 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 86, 9.26.71 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 87, 49.10.64 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Fig. 88, 54.20.64. (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)   Pleiades ID 456321707
TGN ID 7004658
Excavation Dates 1984
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, pp. 97-98, 333 (worldcat)  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 10 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
