<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_latina/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_latina/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Memorial Tomb Garden of Ortorius Heleis and Ortoria Eutychis</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_latina/memorial_tomb_garden_of_ortorius_heleis_and_ortoria_eutychis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_latina/memorial_tomb_garden_of_ortorius_heleis_and_ortoria_eutychis/</guid>
      <description>Province italia
Location via latina
via latina (Pleiades)
Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Memorial Tomb Garden of Ortorius Heleis and Ortoria Eutychis
Keywords  tombs  Garden Description An inscribed marble plaque found in the early 1930s covering a drain near Ponte Lungo in the region of the Via Tuscolana south of Rome records the epitaph of a Greek-speaking couple, Ortorios Heleis and Ortoria Eutychis, evidently devotees of the cult of Isis, who some time during the second or early third century built for their ten-year old son Markos Ortorios Eleutheros “an eternal bridal chamber” (aionion nymphona) and “for themselves, in expectation of their death, and for their freedmen and their descendants, a memorial tomb garden” ([mne]meion kepotaphon). The inscription, which includes a prayer to Osiris to grant the boy cool water in the afterlife, dwells on the son’s untimely death and his parents bereavement.
Maps Plans Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  J. M. C. Toynbee, Death and Burial in the Roman World, Print book : English : Hopkins pb. ed., 96 and n. 312. worldcat G.-L. Gregori, Horti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, Article : Italian, BCom 92 (1987-88) [1989] 180 n. 37. worldcat  Pleiades ID 93042695
TGN ID 6006328
Contributor Pier Giorgio Monti (ORCID: 0000-0001-7719-0920)
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
