<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>epitaphs on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/epitaphs/</link>
    <description>Recent content in epitaphs on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/epitaphs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of (Cl)oelia Tyche and (C)loelia Faustina</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/unknown_provenance/tomb_garden_of_cloelia_tyche_and_cloelia_faustina/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/unknown_provenance/tomb_garden_of_cloelia_tyche_and_cloelia_faustina/</guid>
      <description>Province italia
Location Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Tomb Garden of (Cl)oelia Tyche and (C)loelia Faustina
Keywords  tombs epitaphs  Garden Description The lower right portion of a marble slab found in the vicinity of the Via del Mare outside Rome records an epitaph of the late first or second century dedicated to a mother, [Cl]oelia Tyche, and sister, [C]loelia Faustina, and their freedmen and freedwomen, and declaring that the property, which comprised “a tomb monument and building and garden enclosed by a wall” (hoc monimentum et aedificium et hortum, ita uti maceria clusum est), would not pass to the heir.
Maps Plans Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  G. Vergantini, La collezione epigrafica dei Musei Capitolini: Inediti – revisioni –contributi al riordino, (Tituli 6), edited by S. Panciera (Rome 1987) 152-53 n. 72, Tav. XXXIX, 4. worldcat G.-L. Gregori, Horti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, BCom 92 (1987-88) [1989] 176 n. 4. worldcat  Pleiades ID TGN ID Contributor Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Anonymous</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/unknown_provenance/tomb_garden_of_anonymous/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/unknown_provenance/tomb_garden_of_anonymous/</guid>
      <description>Province italia
Location Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Tomb Garden of Attia Quintilla
Keywords  tombs epitaphs  Garden Description A fragmentary opisthographic slab of unknown urban provenance, now in the Lapidario Profano ex Lateranense of the Vatican Museums, records an anonymous epitaph dedicating to the dedicator and his household a tomb garden (cepotafi[um]) and tomb monument with a building.
Maps Plans Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  G.-L. Gregori, Horti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, BCom 92 (1987-88) [1989] 177 n. 10. worldcat  Pleiades ID TGN ID Contributor Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Attia Quintilla</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/unknown_provenance/tomb_garden_of_attia_quintilla/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/unknown_provenance/tomb_garden_of_attia_quintilla/</guid>
      <description>Province italia
Location Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Tomb Garden of Attia Quintilla
Keywords  tombs epitaphs  Garden Description A handsome marble funerary altar of unknown but presumably urban provenance, now in the Louvre, decorated on the front with Erotes holding garlands and on the sides with storks and other birds records the epitaph of Attia T. f. Quintilla set up by her father, Attius Phlegon, her mother Attia Quinta (probably both ex-slaves), and her brother Attius T. f. Quintianus. Along with the monument, which can be dated to the first or early second century, Quintilla’s parents and brother also dedicated to her and to their descendants and the freedmen and freedwomen of their household “a field or garden (agrum sive hortum) with a building, enclosed by a wall”.The building, a substantial structure of some thirteen rooms, seems to comprise, on the ground floor, a series of three work rooms opening off a central corridor that leads directly through the house from front to back, a two-room suite separately accessible from the front porch (perhaps the residence of the gardner and overseer of the tomb), and a stairway to the upper floor. The upper floor presents a more seigneural aspect: in addition to two large rooms and a pair of small functional rooms corresponding to those on the first floor, the residential space includes a narrow rectangular room or balcony over the entranceway and a two-room suite and a separate room built out above the rear service court and overlooking the garden. A broad passageway eleven feet wide along the side of the building seems to allow for a wagon to be backed into position for loading directly from the garden. The dimensions of the rooms inscribed along most of the interior walls indicate that the three building plans are not drawn to the same scale, and it is not clear how the two structures were situated in relation to each other. The configuration of the aedificium and garden suggests the arrangements of a working kitchen garden with related workspaces on the ground floor and a residential and dining area on the upper floor, perhaps for the use of family members celebrating communal meals at the tomb site during the annual Parentalia and other festivals of the dead. The cepotaphium dedicated by C. Cominius Abascantus at Puteoli in 148 CE provided for the town magistrates and officers of the Augustales to dine annually at the site in a dining room above his tomb (no. XXX).
Maps Plans Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  W. Altmann, Die römischen Grabaltäre der Kaiserzeit, (Berlin 1905) 168 no. 214; S. worldcat S. Ducroix, Catalogue analytique des inscriptions latines sur pierre conservées au Musée du Louvre, (Paris 1975) 96 no. 314. worldcat D. Boschung, Antike Grabaltäre aus den Nekropolen Roms, (Acta Bernensia X) (Bern 1987) 107 no. 329, Taf. worldcat G.-L. Gregori, Horti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, BCom 92 (1987-88) [1989] 177 n. 9. worldcat  Pleiades ID TGN ID Contributor Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of C. Hostius Pamphilus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/unknown_provenance/tomb_garden_of_c._hostius_pamphilus/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/unknown_provenance/tomb_garden_of_c._hostius_pamphilus/</guid>
      <description>Province italia
Location Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Tomb Garden of C. Hostius Pamphilus
Keywords  tombs epitaphs  Garden Description A travertine slab of unknown urban provenance, now in the Mus-ei Capitolini, records an epitaph of the mid first century BCE of a freedman doctor, C. Hostius C.l. Pamphilus, who bought a tomb (thirteen by twenty-four feet in area) for himself and his wife Nelpia M. l. Hymnis, and for their freedmen and their descendants. A crude verse (almost a septenarius) following the dedication declares “this is our eternal home, this our farm, these our gardens (horti), this our monument”. It is unclear whether horti here refers to a tomb garden or, perhaps more probably, to a suburban estate, as normally in contemporary fashionable usage. The ambivalence of the term in any case draws a link, conceptual as well as topographical, between productive rural property (fundus) and a burial monument conceived of as a home for the deceased. If horti refers to a tomb garden proper, it would be among the earliest attested in the environs of Rome.
Maps Plans Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  M. Mattei, Testimonianze epigrafiche e attestazioni letterarie relative all’area degli Horti Lamiani, in Le tranquille dimore degli dei, edited by M. Cima and E. La Rocca (Venice 1986) 153-54 fig. 103. worldcat G.-L. Gregori, Horti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, BCom 92 (1987-88) [1989] 178 n. 21, 179 fig. 2; J. worldcat Bodel, Monumental Villas and Villa Monuments, JRA 10 (1997) 26. worldcat  Pleiades ID TGN ID Contributor Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Claudia Peloris</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/unknown_provenance/tomb_garden_of_claudia_peloris/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/unknown_provenance/tomb_garden_of_claudia_peloris/</guid>
      <description>Province italia
Location Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Tomb Garden of Claudia Peloris
Keywords  tombs epitaphs  Garden Description A marble plaque now in the archaeological museum of Perugia but probably of urban origin records the epitaph of a freedwoman of Octavia, the daughter of the deified emperor Claudius, Claudia Peloris, and her husband, also an imperial freedman and procurator of the Augusti, Ti. Claudius Eutychus, who left to her sisters and freedwomen and their descendants charge of a building (aedificium) and tomb monument (monumentum). An inscribed plan at the center of the plaque depicting different sections of a building and tomb complex (evidently the ones specified in the text) shows, at the right, a walled tomb enclosure, with the monument built into the rear wall and a corridor leading off the left side of the forecourt to a stair descending perpendicularly to an undergound burial chamber below; at the left, the ground floor of a two storey building (the set of rooms depicted at the top of the plan represents the second floor) with a roughly rectangular walled garden (70 X 76 X 65 X 65 Roman feet, some 410 square meters), opening off the rear (Fig. XXX). The building, a substantial structure of some thirteen rooms, seems to comprise, on the ground floor, a series of three work rooms opening off a central corridor that leads directly through the house from front to back, a two-room suite separately accessible from the front porch (perhaps the residence of the gardner and overseer of the tomb), and a stairway to the upper floor. The upper floor presents a more seigneural aspect: in addition to two large rooms and a pair of small functional rooms corresponding to those on the first floor, the residential space includes a narrow rectangular room or balcony over the entranceway and a two-room suite and a separate room built out above the rear service court and overlooking the garden. A broad passageway eleven feet wide along the side of the building seems to allow for a wagon to be backed into position for loading directly from the garden. The dimensions of the rooms inscribed along most of the interior walls indicate that the three building plans are not drawn to the same scale, and it is not clear how the two structures were situated in relation to each other. The configuration of the aedificium and garden suggests the arrangements of a working kitchen garden with related workspaces on the ground floor and a residential and dining area on the upper floor, perhaps for the use of family members celebrating communal meals at the tomb site during the annual Parentalia and other festivals of the dead. The cepotaphium dedicated by C. Cominius Abascantus at Puteoli in 148 CE provided for the town magistrates and officers of the Augustales to dine annually at the site in a dining room above his tomb (no. XXX).
Maps Plans Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Ch. Hülsen, Piante iconografiche incise in marmo, MDAI(R) 5 (1890) 46-52 and Tav. III; H. von Hesberg. worldcat H. von Hesberg, Römische Grundrissplane auf Marmor, in Bauplanung und Bautheorie der Antike (Berlin 1983) 124-26. worldcat G.-L. Gregori, Horti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, BCom 92 (1987-88) [1989] 181 fig. 3, 184. worldcat  Pleiades ID TGN ID Contributor Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of P. Sullius Zoticus and Sullia Nice</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/unknown_provenance/tomb_garden_of_p._sullius_zoticus_and_sullia_nice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/unknown_provenance/tomb_garden_of_p._sullius_zoticus_and_sullia_nice/</guid>
      <description>Province italia
Location Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Tomb Garden of (Cl)oelia Tyche and (C)loelia Faustina
Keywords  tombs epitaphs  Garden Description A marble slab of unknown urban provenance broken at the bottom and long lost records an epitaph of the first or second century erected by P. Sullius Zoticus and his wife Sullia Nice to themselves, their children, their freedmen and freedwomen and their descendants; to “another wife” of Zoticus, Iulia Tatiane; and (it seems) to a Sullius Istefanus. The epitaph concludes with provision for a fine to be paid to the treasury of the pontiffs and the Vestal Virgins by any who attempt to alienate the tomb and surrounding property, which comprised “a garden with cistern enclosed by a surrounding wall” (in conti[nenti] / hortulu(m) maceria clus[um] / at cisterna(m) perten[dentem]).
Maps Plans Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  G.-L. Gregori, Horti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, BCom 92 (1987-88) [1989] 177 n. 11. worldcat  Pleiades ID TGN ID Contributor Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Iul(ia) Victorin(a) in Scarbantia</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/scarbantia/scarbantia_tomb_garden_of_iulia_victorina/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 10:08:21 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/scarbantia/scarbantia_tomb_garden_of_iulia_victorina/</guid>
      <description>Province Pannonia
Location Scarbantia
Scarbantia (Pleiades)
Garden Tomb Garden of Iul(ia) Victorin(a) in Scarbantia
Keywords  epitaphs literary garden stelae tombs viridarium  Garden Description A limestone funerary stele of probably third century date unearthed in 1973 near Scarbantia at Winder am See (Burgenland) and now in the Burgenländische Landesmuseum at Eisenstadt records an epitaph set up by Septimius Alcides, a veteran of the legio XIII Gemina Iulia, for his wife, Iul(ia) Victorin(a), dead at thirty, for whom he built at his own expense a funerary pleasure garden (viridarium).
Maps Dates 3rd century
Bibliography  AE 1973, 433. Epigraphische Datenbank Heidelberg HD011378.  Pleiades ID 197501
TGN ID 4008442
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 22 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Fl(avius) Dalmatius in Savaria</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/savaria/savaria_tomb_garden_of_flavius_dalmatius/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 09:49:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/savaria/savaria_tomb_garden_of_flavius_dalmatius/</guid>
      <description>Province Pannonia
Location Savaria
Savaria (Pleiades)
Garden Tomb Garden of Fl(avius) Dalmatius in Savaria
Keywords  epitaphs inscription literary garden tombs  Garden Description A limestone slab found near the monastery of St. Martin in Szombathely (Savaria), Hungary, in 1845 and subsequently transferred to the National Museum in Budapest records the epitaph of a high ranking equestrian official (vir perfectissimus), Fl(avius) Dalmatius, and his wife Aur(elia) Iulia, who some time during the third or fourth century built a tomb on their villa estate and composed for it a verse inscription in which Dalmatius hopes for commemoration from a future owner of the property: “Whoever will be master of this house and garden after me, gather the nearby roses for me, put out the white lilies which the green garden will grow for me: these are the gifts of the blessed” (Quisquis {h}e(ris) post me d(o)m(inus) Laris huius et (h)orti, / vicinas mihi carpe rosas, mihi lilia pone / [ca]ndeda{s} q(uae) viridis dabit (h)ortulus: ista (sc. munera) beat(or)um). A freedman Volussius and freedwoman Sabatia saw to the erection of the inscription and monument. On the basis of the final platitude, with its reference to “the blessed” (beati), Diehl considered Dalmatius and his wife to be Christians. For Adamik, on the other hand, commemoration with flowers, a practice condemned by Christian writers as idolatrous, points to a pagan context. The phrasing of the hexameters reveals familiarity also with Roman literary conventions of funerary commemoration (cf. Martial 1.61.3, quiquis eris nostri post me regnator agelli&amp;hellip;).Whatever the religious beliefs of Dalmatius and his wife, the equipping of their tomb with a funerary garden to support commemorative celebrations at the site is fully in keeping with the literary pretensions of their epitaph in representing the couple as fully assimilated and sophisticated Romans.
Maps Dates 3rd or 4th century
Bibliography  CIL 3.4185. CLE 578. ILCV 296. A. Mócsy and T. Szentléleky, Die römischen Steindenkmäler von Savaria. Amsterdam, 1971, p. 117, no. 161, photo 143. (worldcat) T. Adamik,Archaeologiai Ertesítö 110, 1983:3-9 = AE 1984:722.  Pleiades ID 197498
TGN ID 4008442
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 22 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Ti. Claudios Lykos</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/macedonia/thessaloniki/thessaloniki_tomb_garden_of_tib_claudios_lykos/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 09:07:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/macedonia/thessaloniki/thessaloniki_tomb_garden_of_tib_claudios_lykos/</guid>
      <description>Province Macedonia
Location Thessaloniki
Thessaloniki (Pleiades)
Garden Tomb Garden of Ti. Claudios Lykos
Keywords  tombs sarcophagi epitaphs  Garden Description A limestone sarcophagus found at Thessaloniki and first reported in 1962 preserves an epitaph set up in 147 A.D. by Ti. Claudios Lykos, a local town counselor (bouleutÆw), for himself, his loving wife Meinoukia (Minucia) Theoprepes, and his two daughters Roda and Theoprepes. As Robert correctly observed (Bull. Épigr. 1963:134), the garbled inscription—a product, it seems, of two drafts of the text being confused by the carver—nonetheless makes clear that Lykos had built a tomb garden complex, which he calls a ≤r“on, comprising “a field, house, garden, and, burial place” (égrÒw, oﬁk€a, k∞pow, tÒpow), in which were situated various sarcophagi (lhnÒi) and statues (éndriãntew) and which he attempted to prevent from future alienation. Two other inscriptions found in the same complex identify Lykos as granting, in one case, a cinerary urn (kaÊstra), in the other, in 167 A.D., a burial place (tÒpow) to others for their monuments. A secondary inscription on the cover of Lykos’s sarcophagus attests its reuse later in the third century. Robert and Kubińska considered the “house” (oﬁk€a) to be that of a gardener appointed to oversee the garden complex, but the traditional formulaic pairing of field and house, garden and tomb attested elsewhere (at the tomb gardens of C. Hostius Pamphilus at Rome [cross-ref, XXX] and of C. [Ma?]rcius C. l. Cleon at Bari [cross-ref XXX]) suggests that it is Lykos’s own house that is meant and, perhaps, that the tomb garden is located on its property. For the conventional “tomb” (tãfow, sepulchrum, monumentum) Lykos substitutes “burial place” (tÒpow, Latin locus, as in l(ocus) d(atus) d(ecreto) d(ecurionum), a formula for awarding honorific burials with which Lykos the decurion was assuredly familiar), but his conformity to the traditional conceptual juxtapositions is apparent. To judge from the presence of statues and more than one sarcophagus, and from the granting of burial space to others, Lykos’s funerary garden was a substantial complex.
Maps Images Dates 147 CE, 167 CE
Bibliography : IG X 2,1.608; J. Kubińska, Les monuments funéraires dans les inscriptions grecques de l’Asie Mineure. Warsaw, 1968, p. 146; P. Petsas, “AgrÒw, oﬁk€a, k∞pow, tÒpow,” in J. H. Dell, ed. Macedonian Studies in Honor of Charles F. Edson. Thessaloniki, 1981, pp. 295-98; Bull. Épigr. 1963, 134; 1984, 252.
Pleiades ID 491741
TGN ID 7011182
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 16 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cemetery Garden of Metrodorus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/dalmatia/salona/salona_cemetery_garden_of_metrodorus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 10:10:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/dalmatia/salona/salona_cemetery_garden_of_metrodorus/</guid>
      <description>Province Dalmatia
Location Salona
Salona (Pleiades)
Sublocation Garden Cemetery Garden of Metrodorus
Keywords  tombs epitaphs sarcophagi (coffins)  Garden Description A sarcophagus found at Salona in 1824, transported to the museum in Split, and subsequently lost bore an inscription recording the donation by Aur(elius) Aprilianus to Aur(elius) Amurus and Aur(elia) Quinta of a sarcophagus “which is in the garden of Metrodorus” and specifying that it was put into position while they were still alive (Aur(elius) Aprilianus se vivo donavet arcam Aur(elio) Amuro et Aur(eliae) Quinte que est in orto Metrodori. Vivi sibi posuerunt…). The find spot of the sarcophagus is not known, but Wilkes plausibly associates the garden of Metrodorus with a walled cemetery a hundred meters outside the city gate on the north side of the road leading west from town, which comprises a number of individual familial plots marked out by dividing walls within an area enclosed by a massive masonry perimeter built of blocks more than four meters long. The garden of Metrodorus was perhaps home also to the monument of Iulia Mutiana erected “among the sarcophagi in the middle in the garden, near the road, overlooking the old (?) courtyard (or seed bed)” (see the preceding entry): the two inscriptions belong broadly to the same period (the latter second or third century) and might well be contemporary with each other.
Maps Plans Images Dates Late second or third century (CE)
Bibliography  CIL 3.2207 M. Abramic´, VAHD 52, 1935-49:1-18 J. J. Wilkes, Dalmatia. London, 1969, pp. 360-61, fig. 16.  Pleiades ID 197488
TGN ID 7017320
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 15 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden with Monument of Julia Mutiana</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/dalmatia/salona/salona_tomb_garden_with_monument_of_julia_mutiana/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 17:06:21 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/dalmatia/salona/salona_tomb_garden_with_monument_of_julia_mutiana/</guid>
      <description>Province Dalmatia
Location Salona
Salona (Pleiades)
Sublocation Garden Tomb Garden and Pool of Cingius Iustinus
Keywords  tombs epitaphs  Garden Description An inscription reported among those of Salona records an epitaph set up by Iulia Mutiana for herself and her husband Aur(elius) Pateas in a place granted her by A. Aelius Marullinus “among the sarcophagi in the middle in the garden, near the road, overlooking the old (?) courtyard (or seed bed)” (inter arcas in medio in horto at viam prospicientem in areolam vet(erem ?)). The specification of a location within the garden, the mention of (other) sarcophagi, and the concession of Marullinus suggest that the cemetery was extensive and perhaps public. The term areola used to describe the area overlooked by Mutiana’s monument generally means “courtyard” in architectural contexts (e.g. CIL 6.9077), “garden plot” or “seed bed” in agricultural ones (e.g. Columella 5.12.3, 10.362, 11.2.75). It is difficult to know which sense is to be preferred here. Whatever its character, Mommsen questioned the description of the areola as “old” (vet(erem)) and proposed an alternative reading “behind” (ret(ro)), unnecessarily, it seems. Nomenclature and circumstance (inhumation burial) point to a date in the second half of the second or the third century.
Maps Plans Images Dates Second half of the second or the third century (CE)
Bibliography  CIL 3.2397.  Pleiades ID 197488
TGN ID 7017320
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 14 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden and Pool of Cingius Iustinus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/dalmatia/salona/salona_tomb_garden_and_pool_of_cingius_iustinus/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 16:52:02 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/dalmatia/salona/salona_tomb_garden_and_pool_of_cingius_iustinus/</guid>
      <description>Province Dalmatia
Location Salona
Salona (Pleiades)
Sublocation Garden Tomb Garden and Pool of Cingius Iustinus
Keywords  piscinae tombs epitaphs  Garden Description A rock cut inscription at Salonae marks the spot where some time in the late second or third century Cingius Iustinus made a fishpond or pool (piscina) in the garden of his wife Aelia Licinia for her and for himself (fecit piscinam in horto Aeliae Liciniae coiugi incomparabili et sibi). No tomb is mentioned, but the dedication D(is) M(anibus) identifies the text as an epitaph and thus points to a funerary context.
Maps Plans Images Dates Late second or third century (CE)
Bibliography  CIL 3.2279  Pleiades ID 197488
TGN ID 7017320
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 14 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Ael(ius) Iul(ius) Iulianus, Decurion in Romula</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/dacia_traiana/romula/romula_tomb_garden_of_aelius_iulius_iulianus_decurion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 07:56:03 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/dacia_traiana/romula/romula_tomb_garden_of_aelius_iulius_iulianus_decurion/</guid>
      <description>Province Dacia Traiana
Province Description Location Romula
Romula (Pleiades)
Garden Tomb Garden of Ael(ius) Iul(ius) Iulianus, Decurion in Romula
Keywords  epitaphs inscription literary garden tombs  Garden Description A slab unearthed near Resça (Romula), Romania, in 1954 records a verse epitaph set up by Valeria Gemellina for her husband Ael(ius) Iul(ius) Iulianus, a decurion of the colony of Romula, some time probably in the later second or third century. In it she describes in pastoral terms well suited to the hexameter the setting of the “eternal home” (i.e. the tomb) she built for him (hanc Iuliano domum flendo fabricavi perennem): “See how Gemellina, along with her children, out of respect for her worthy husband built a resting place for him amidst the vines and shrubbery and the lush grass, where deep shade from an overhanging branch supplies the greenery” (ecce Gemellina pietate ducta marito / struxindolens digno sedem cum liberis una / inter pampinea virgulta et gramina laeta / umbra super rami virides ubi densa ministrat).
Maps Images Dates Later second century/third century
Excavation Dates 1954
Bibliography  AE 1957, 334.  Pleiades ID 981518
TGN ID 8712318
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 12 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
