<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gallia on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/categories/gallia/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Gallia on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/categories/gallia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>House of the Masks (Maison aux Masques)</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/house_of_the_masks_maison_aux_masques/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/house_of_the_masks_maison_aux_masques/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location LUGDUNUM (Lyon, France)
LUGDUNUM (Pleiades)
Garden House of the Masks (Maison aux Masques)
Keywords  peristyle opus stigninumboth porticoes stylobate plynth pilasters  Garden Description The two known wings of the house were organized around a peristyle (8x 12 m), probably in a U, though the west wall has not been found but has been drawn on the accompanying plan by extension of wall further south. Two of the three galleries were open. The open area of the peristyle court was ornamented by a rectangular pool (5.4 x 2.6 m) covered with opus signinumboth inside and outside; it had a drain in the northeast corner. The surface of the water in the pool would have been above the level of pounded earth floor of the courtyard. Porticoes 2.8 meters wide around three sides of the courtyard also had pounded earth floors; the stylobate was blocks of limestone while the columns were of circular brick covered with plaster painted red in the lower part, white in the upper, and touched with green highlights. The porticoes were terminated at the west end by engaged columns. The painted plaster is preserved in place in the southwest corner of the peristyle. A red plinth sets off tuffs of green foliage; above are black panels bordered with decorative strings. At a later phase, a wall was built between the last two columns of the of the portico; in the space thus created were found bases for shelves. Near the peristyle were found little theatrical masks in terra cotta which had served as oscilla. An ostrich egg, an exotic import, was perhaps also hung in the peristyle. Onto the south portico opened a reception room [B 20] (8.6 x 6.2 m) rhythmically divided by four pilasters and two columns. Onto the east portico opened an even larger room [B 12] (10.5 x 6.5 m). Both reception rooms had concrete floors with limestone accents. There were also two small courtyards &amp;ndash;one in the south wing, one in the east &amp;ndash;both indicated on the plan.
Maps Not Available
Plans Not Available
Images   perspective drawing of porticoes   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  A. Desbat, Les fouilles de la rue des Farges à Lyon, Groupe lyonnais de recherche en archéologie gallo-romaine, Lyon, 1984, p. 45-49 (worldcat) A. Desbat, Jadis, rue des Farges, archéologie d’un quartier de Lyon antique, exposition au Musée de la Civilisation Gallo-Romaine de Lyon, 1985. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 167717
TGN ID 6003548
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 12 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/fliessem-otrang-villa-rural/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/fliessem-otrang-villa-rural/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location FLIESSEM-OTRANG (Germany)
FLIESSEM-OTRANG (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa
Keywords  villae rusticae mosaic porticoes courtyard  Garden Description This villa rustica was built on the slope of a hill about 30 kilometers north of Colonia Augusta Treverorum, close to the Roman road from Trier to Cologne, now B 51/E29. It is a kilometer or two south of the village of Fliessem. The original core of the villa is of second century date, but the building was enlarged considerably in the third century to take up an area of 4225 square meters (Fig. 1). It was occupied until around AD 400. The house (A on plan) occupied a position at the eastern end of the property, and in its final state it measured 60 x 60 meters and had 66 rooms, many of them decorated with mosaic floors. On the northern and southern sides were porticoes, and from the southern portico with its pavilions a view of the valley below was afforded.
The entrance to the house on the west was flanked by two protruding pavilions framing an open courtyard. Immediately to the west of this was another open courtyard enclosed by a wall. It might be expected, even if the evidence is sparse, that a garden or park was laid out at least in front of the entrance at the west (G on plan).
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  H. Mylius, &amp;ldquo;Die Rekonstruktion der römischen Villen von Nennig und Fliessem,&amp;rdquo; Bonner Jahrbuch 129, 1924:120-128, fig. 3, pl. 7; E. M. Wightman, Roman Trier and the Treveri, London, 1970, pp. 143-145, fig. 15; H. Cüppers, ed., Die Römer in Rheinland-Pfalz, Stuttgart,1990, pp. 367-371, figs. 264-265. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/1075378207) E. M. Wightman, Roman Trier and the Treveri, London, 1970, pp. 143-145, fig. 15 [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/1001859813) H. Cüppers, ed., Die Römer in Rheinland-Pfalz, Stuttgart,1990, pp. 367-371, figs. 264-265. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/924024101)  Pleiades ID 108982
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 12 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/nennig-villa-rural/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/nennig-villa-rural/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location NENNIG (Germany)
NENNIG (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa
Keywords  peristyle corridors bath building  Garden Description The villa of this rural estate of the third century and its grounds are the only parts of the complex which have been investigated (Fig. 1). The farm lay about 40 km. south of Trier on a gentle slope above the Moselle river. The villa is of the winged corridor type with a facade of over 45 meters in length, taking up an area of 4200 square meters. In the villa were two peristyle courtyards, but both were paved with slabs of red sandstone rather than having been laid out as gardens.
Parks were laid out on the grounds of the villa. A peristyle corridor 250 meters in length and 8.80 meters in width led from the villa to the bath building on the southwest, although it was not directly connected to either building. From the open-sided corridor one could enjoy the view of the almost certainly landscaped grounds, and of the terrain sloping down to the river. It is assumed that there was another peristyle corridor on the northeast. A grotto on the grounds of the villa belonged to the park.
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  P. Steiner, Die römische Villa von Nennig, Saarbrücken, 1955. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/1073267042) H. Mylius, &amp;ldquo;Die Rekonstruktion der römischen Villen von Nennig und Fliessem,&amp;rdquo; Bonner Jahrbuch 129, 1924:110-120, fig. 1, pls. 4-5. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/1075378207)  Pleiades ID 109198
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 12 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/veirherrenborn-rural-villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/veirherrenborn-rural-villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location VEIRHERRENBORN (Germany)
VEIRHERRENBORN (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa
Keywords  courtyard paddock  Garden Description The house stood in the middle of a farm complex 75 meters wide and 120 meters long. It dates to the early second century. The house (A on the plan, Fig. 1) is of the winged corridor type, measuring 19.30 x 22.40 meters.
On the west and east, in front of and behind the house, were open courtyards enclosed by a wall. The western courtyard has been interpreted as a garden (G on plan); the eastern one may have been a paddock.
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  H. Cüppers, ed., Die Römer in Rheinland-Pfalz, Stuttgart, 1990, p. 653, fig. 594. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/924024101)  Pleiades ID 109198
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 12 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/weitersbach-rural-villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/weitersbach-rural-villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location WELSCHBILLIG (Germany)
WELSCHBILLIG (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa
Keywords  palace portico herms  Garden Description This palatial villa, which has been interpreted as an imperial summer palace, lay within the confines of an imperial domain about 12 km. northwest of Colonia Augusta Treverorum. It was built during the reign of the emperor Valentinian I (364-375) or Gratian (367-383) who resided in the capital. Very little remains of the actual villa, although foundation walls of other buildings and a possible portico have been found.
The grounds of the villa were almost certainly landscaped in some form, as is suggested by a large decorative pool that may have been a decorative focus in a garden. It measured 18 x 60 meters and had three symmetrically arranged apses on the long sides. (Fig. 1) The walls of the pool were constructed of cut stone blocks and the bottom was paved with stone slabs. On top of the edges of the pool was an open-worked stone balustrade pierced at regular intervals by 112 limestone herms. The herms represent gods, Greeks, Romans, philosophers, generals and idealized figures such as putti, as well as Phrygians, Nubians and Germans. These were thrown into the pool in the 5th century, landing perhaps on layers of sediment at the bottom. As a result, the herms, of which 71 were retrieved in excavations, are in excellent condition. At the northern end of the pool was a rectangular building through which ran a drain from the pool. (Fig. 2, View of Model)
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  H. Wrede, Die spätantike Hermengalerie von Welschbillig. Römisch-Germanische Forschungen 32, Berlin, 1972 [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/223360098) H. Cüppers, ed., Die Römer in Rheinland-Pfalz, Stuttgart, 1990, pp. 665-667, figs. 607-609. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/924024101) P. Van Ossel, Établissements ruraux de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquité tardive dans le nord de la Gaule, Paris, 1992, pp. 277-278, fig. 90. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/445007864)  Pleiades ID 109456
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 12 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/welschbillig-rural-villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/welschbillig-rural-villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location WEITERSBACH (Germany)
WEITERSBACH (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa
Keywords  vegetable garden  Garden Description The enclosed farm compound measured 79 x 125/132 meters (less than one hectare). In the middle of the yard stood a house (A on plan) of the winged corridor type dating to the period between the end of the 1st and the later fourth century. (Fig. 1)
Southeast of the house was an open area of 900 square meters. enclosed by a wall. There were no traces of any building activity within this enclosure, leading the excavators to interpret the area as a utilitarian (vegetable) garden (G on plan).
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  E. Gose, &amp;ldquo;Jahresbericht&amp;rdquo;, Trierer Zeitschrift 24/26,1956-58: 511-525, figs. 106, 113. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/223360098) H. Cüppers, ed., Die Römer in Rheinland-Pfalz, Stuttgart, 1990, pp. 663-665, fig. 606. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/924024101) P. Van Ossel, Établissements ruraux de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquité tardive dans le nord de la Gaule, Paris, 1992, pp. 273-276, fig. 82. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/445007864)  Pleiades ID 109456
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 12 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa des Tuillières</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/villa_des_tuilli%C3%A8res/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/villa_des_tuilli%C3%A8res/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location SELONGEY (Côte d&amp;rsquo;Or, France)
SELONGEY (Pleiades)
Garden Villa des Tuillières
Keywords  courtyard porticos/porticus hypocausts  Garden Description The villa des Tuillières near Selongey was on a Roman road connecting Lyon and Trier. The villa was detected by aerial photography in 1973 and almost completely excavated by the private Association Archéologique de Fontaine-Française in advance of the construction of the motorway A 26/31 Langres – Dijon between 1976 and 1988.
At Selongey, the first Roman evidence was a timber-framed building with clay walls. It can be dated to Claudian or Neronian times. The construction type of this &amp;lsquo;proto-villa&amp;rsquo; continued well-known Late Celtic traditions. Some small, typical Roman stone buildings were erected during Flavian times. In the second century AD, under Hadrian or Antoninus, these first structures were razed to the ground and the complex was re-organized by the construction of a small main building and a huge isolated building for agricultural purposes. The huge stone-built villa complex, with its strict axial arrangement of all buildings around a central courtyard of 1.5 hectares, was constructed at the beginning of the third century AD under the reign of Severus.
During the first half of the 3rd century AD the complex of the villa comprised several buildings, which were arranged around a central courtyard (Fig. 1). The north-western wing of the villa complex was formed by the main building (Fig. 1, B) and the thermae in its classical form (Fig. 1, C) while buildings for agriculture (Fig. 1, A and D) and Iron working activities (Fig. 1, E) were arranged at the other sides of the courtyard. The main part of the villa opened with a long porticus south-east to the courtyard (Fig. 1, B No. 5). At both ends of the porticus small pavilions formed the angles of the main building (Fig. 1 B no. 1). The entrance was situated in the center of the porticus; it gave access to a central hall (Fig. 2, VIII) and to the representative rooms such as the main building which were heated by a hypocaust. The rooms for domestic activities such as the kitchen and service rooms were located to the back.
Two cellars under the rooms X and XIII were used for storage purposes. The cellar under room X yielded the most important archaeological objects of the villa, about 2600 fragments of burnt ivory objects. They made it possible to reconstruct a wooden casket with several application made from ivory. Cellar X obviously contained the treasury of the villa; cellar XIII, food for human alimentation.
The villa was destroyed during the barbarian invasion into Gaul in 256-8 AD, which followed the main Roman roads. The most recent coin found in the villa was an antoninianus of Valerius, coined in Rome AD 254. Because the rescue excavation focused mainly on the building structures, and the open space of the inner courtyard was not completely excavated, the direct garden evidence is faint. Herb gardens and fruit tree gardens can be assumed near the back of the main building. The presence of gardens is indicated by the rich archaeobotanical evidence. The destruction of the villa by fire preserved plant remains. Archaeobotanical analysis of the plant material revealed huge amounts of carbonized cereals and grape pips from building D. The assemblage is dominated by naked wheat (Triticum aestivum s.l./durum/turgidum), hulled barley (Hordeum vulgare) and pips of cultivated grape (Vitis vinifera vinifera). The botanical assemblages from building D contained thousands of grape pips, but also fragmented Vitis stalks and carbonized underdeveloped complete grapes. A possible explanation is that the agricultural building D of the villa complex was not only used to dry and store cereal grain, but also contained a wine pressing area (Fig. 1 D indicated in grey, Fig. 2, rooms II-XII). Archaeobotanical evidence from the villa &amp;lsquo;des Tuillières&amp;rsquo; at Selongey, Côte d&amp;rsquo;Or, and from the villa &amp;lsquo;Tête de Fer&amp;rsquo; near Avallon also point clearly to local viticulture during the third century AD.
Furthermore, there is evidence of lentil (Lens culinaris) and broad bean (Vicia faba), which were most probably cultivated either in the gardens of the villa or on small fields in the vicinity. Carbonized scales from walnuts and uncarbonized fruit stones from peach (Prunus persica) and damson (Prunus insititia) indicate cultivation of fruit trees in the gardens while hazel (Corylus avellana) and sloe (Prunus spinosa) were most probably fruits collected from the wild.
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  J.C. Beal with the collaboration of d&amp;rsquo;A. et A. Ruellet, La resserre de Selongey (Côte d&amp;rsquo;Or): une collection d&amp;rsquo;objets de bois et d&amp;rsquo;ivoire dans la villa des Tuillières,» Revue Archéologique de l&amp;rsquo;Est xx E. Gauthier, M. Joly, « Vignoble et viticulture dans le centre-est de la Gaule au Ier siècle « .in: F. Favory/A. Vignot (eds.), Actualités de la Recherche en Histoire et Archéologie agraires. Actes du colloque international AGER V, Besançon 2000. Collection Annales Littéraires No. 764, Série Environnement, sociétés et archéologie 5(2003) :191-208, Besançon; A. Olivier, A. Ruellet, « Selongey, « La villa » In: Archéologie de Bourgogne. La Côte d&amp;rsquo;Or » Dijon, Musée Archéologique/Errance, Paris, 1990, pp. 77-78; A. Ruellet, « La villa des Tuillières à Selongey, » in L&amp;rsquo;autoroute au pays des Lingons. Archéologie et autoroute A31. Sociétés des autoroutes Paris-Rhin-Rhône, Dijon, 1989, pp. 34-39: A. and A. Ruellet, J.-C. Beal, « La villa de Selongey. » in Il était une fois la Côte d&amp;rsquo;Or. 20 ans de recherches archéologiques [exhibition catalogue Dijon, Musée archéologique], Paris, pp. 95-104; J. Wiethold, &amp;ldquo;’How to trace the &amp;lsquo;Romanisation&amp;rsquo; of central Gaule by archaeobotanical analysis?” in F. Favory/A. Vignot (eds.), Actualités de la Recherche en Histoire et Archéologie agraires. Actes du colloque international AGER V, Besançon 2000. Collection Annales Littéraires No. 764, Série Environnement, sociétés et archéologie 5(2003) : 269-282.  Ch.W. Martin, Note sur les fouilles exécutées en 1876 sur l’emplacement de la station romaine de Ste-Marguerite-sur-Mer (Seine inférieure), in Bulletin de la Société des Antiquaires de Normandie, 1861, p. 319-326. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/1026569500) abbé J. Loth, Fouilles de Ste-Marguerite-sur-Mer, in Bulletin de la Commission des antiquités de la Seine-Inférieure, Rouen, 1870, p. 68-75. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/812701053) &amp;lt;! &amp;ndash; In the process of being finalized: J.P. Darmon, Recueil &amp;ldquo;Erin Mckay&amp;rdquo; emckay2@towson.eduise II, 5???, 1994 (ou 5 ???), n°:894-902, p.111-114; ???, in CAG Seine-maritime; 76, 20???, p. 497-500 (with detailed bibliography). &amp;ndash;&amp;gt;  Pleiades ID 177578
TGN ID 6003548
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 12 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Arsenal (Maison de l’Arsenal)</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/house-of-the-arsenal-maison-de-larsenal/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/house-of-the-arsenal-maison-de-larsenal/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location DIVODURUM MEDIOMATRICORUM (Metz, France)
DIVODURUM MEDIOMATRICORUM (Pleiades)
Sublocation Description In the valley of the Moselle, Divodurum Mediomatricorum, a former Gallic oppidum on the hill of Ste-Croix, became an urban center in the Augustan period. It had an amphitheater, an aqueduct, several baths, and a sewer network with a large collector.
Garden HHouse of the Arsenal (Maison de l’Arsenal)
Keywords  courtyard porticoes hypocausts  Garden Description A large house (40 x 40 m) of the second century covered the site of three adjacent buildings going back to the years 60-80 (Fig 1). It was built around a central courtyard [1] 18 meters on a side, bordered by porticos on the east, south, and west. The courtyard, doubtless treated as a garden, had a rectangular pool that has been partially excavated. On the axis of the pool, on the north side and seemingly opening directly onto the courtyard was a large, 60-square-meter room [2] heated by hypocausts.
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Ph. Brunella, D. Meckenbenner, Cl. Lefebvre, P. Thion, Metz, cinq années de recherches archéologiques 1982-1987, Dalph, Gumra, 1990, p.33-36, fig.36. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108927
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Arsenal (Maison de l’Arsenal)</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/villa-de-larry-/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/villa-de-larry-/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location DIVODURUM MEDIOMATRICORUM (Liéhon, France)
DIVODURUM MEDIOMATRICORUM (Pleiades)
Garden Villa de Larry
Keywords  courtyard porticoes hedge pergola cistern fountain  Garden Description The site is on the Lorraine plateau, which has been densely occupied and cultivated since protohistoric times. The villa was on the divide between the headwaters of the Seille on the west and the Neid on the east and only 2.3 kilometers from the Roman road connecting Metz, Sarrebourg, and Strasbourg. The combination of the pars urbana and the pars rustica occupied more than 7 hectares, and the pars rustica alone had at least twelve buildings. The site of pars urbana now lies under the airport runway, so all vestiges were destroyed in the construction. The pars rustica lies outside the airport property in cultivated fields. It remains buried but intact and has been (2006- 2007) the subject of further investigation by ground-penetrating radar and other techniques not requiring excavation.
In 2003, in connection with the extension of the north runway of the Metz-Nancy-Lorraine airport, the excavation of the pars urbana within the perimeter of the airport made it possible to trace the evolution of this aristocratic villa. The site was occupied since the beginning of the first century, at first by a wooden building. At the end of the first century, the residence was still only a simple villa with a masonry portico and lateral pavilions covering, in all, about 520 square meters. Nearby were the farm buildings.
At its architectural apogee between 190 and 250, the buildings of the pars urbana enclosed about 5000 square meters. The residential habitable areas - the great rooms, the lateral pavilions, the galleries, the triclinia, the balnea major and minor, the bedrooms and service areas were arranged around the central courtyard and garden areas. The buildings covered a total of more than 1.3 hectares. The rest, more than two-thirds of the pars urbana, were courtyards and gardens.
For ease of description, we will assume that the top of the plan (Fig. 1) is the north side, though in fact it is the northwest side. In these terms, the north side of the central courtyard was open for just over half its length onto a 90-meter-long courtyard or garden along the north side of the pars urbana. This court was bordered on the north by a closed gallery which marked the separation from the pars rustica. In the southeast corner of this large court, in an area of 92 square meters (shaded green and marked with a V and a 1 in Fig. 1, there were discovered definite traces of a pleasure garden, namely, planting trenches and pits for a hedge or row of bushes which marked its limits (Fig. 2). The planting trenches were preserved to a depth of 5 to 15 centimeters. The soil in them was a gray sandy silt, while surrounding soil was the geological clay of the area. The row of bushes was placed parallel to the large, heated reception room just to the south. Detail and a possible hypothetical reconstruction of the layout of this garden are shown in Fig. 3. Moreover, traces of five pairs of post holes in the soil were discovered east of the inner façade of the entry porch and in alignment with it. They may be related to a pergola (8.4 x 2 m) (Fig. 1 and detail in Fig. 4).
Two walkways, now much despoiled of their stones, formed a T (indicated by dotted lines in Fig. 1) and connected this entry porch to the two lateral pavilions which framed the forecourt. Likewise, a large court bordered the western part of the west wing and northwest pavilion. It was enclosed by a wall on the south and west defining an area of 3265 square meters. Erosion of the ancient surface of the soil, however, destroyed any other horticultural traces. In all, the three large courtyards, enclosed or bordered by residential buildings covered 7,100 square meters.
In the eastern part of the pars urbana, an intermediary enclosed space (shaded green and marked with a V and a 3 in Fig. 1) between the northeast pavilion and the gallery of the balneum, was occupied by a garden with a surface of 196 square meters, where two trees were planted in the center. A second interior court (shaded green and marked with a V and a 4 in Fig.1), occupied 504 square meters in the southeast corner of the villa between the southern apartments and the balneum. A deep subterranean structure about five or six meters in diameter may have been a cistern or pool. These two interior gardens related to the baths covered 700 square meters. Finally, the bottom of a horticultural pot was discovered under the porch of the south facade of the villa.
Traces of wooden pipes with iron hoops were discovered running underground across the large central courtyard and to the south of the pars urbana to bring water from capped springs to the central pool, to the baths, and almost certainly to fountains that were not found. A corresponding network of drains and sewers was also found. Just east of the entry porch was a canal for draining off the rainwater from the roof of the entry porch.
In the fourth century, the villa was in large part ruined; the pools were filled in, the courtyards in the center and to the north occupied by wooden structures erected from the end of the fourth century to the sixth century.
The Villa de Larry site is an example of the villa of a country estate where the gardens integrated the architecture of the buildings. The art of gardening bore witness to the will of the builders and proprietors to master nature and the plant world, imposing on them harmonious and regular forms with plans inspired by the imperial prototypes of Rome.
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  J.-D. Laffite, A. Bressoud, M. Mondy, A. Lefèbvre, M. Feller, I. Dechanez-Clerc, J.-J. Bigot, É. Rouger, LIÉHON (Moselle) « Larry » - Aéroport Metz-Nancy Lorraine, rapport de fouille préventive 2003, INRAP GEN/ SRA DRAC Lorraine, Metz, 2005, 9 vol., 1378 p., 207 figures, 61 plates. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108927
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House on the Place des Halles (La maison des Halles)</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/house_on_the_place_des_halles_la_maison_des_halles/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/house_on_the_place_des_halles_la_maison_des_halles/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location &amp;ndash; missing in Pleiades &amp;ndash; VINDINUM a.k.a. Subdinnum (Le Mans, France)
VINDINUM a.k.a. Subdinnum (Pleiades)
Sublocation Description On the left bank of the Sarthe, where it is joined by the Isaac creek, the Roman town was the successor to a Celtic oppidum. A wall of the late empire enclosed nine hectares.
Garden House on the Place des Halles (La maison des Halles)
Keywords  domus courtyard  Garden Description LUG 6.1.1: Le Mans. House on the Place des Halles. From CAG.
This domus was on the Place des Halles, the former site of the covered market place. It was excavated in 1987-88 south of the principal street. In a part of the ancient city inhabited since the first century, the house occupied a surface (33 x 54 m) of 1782 square meters. Two-story wings of the house surround on three sides a courtyard [1] that may have been a garden. The residential wing, to the south, of careful construction, had four principal rooms with floors of smooth concrete. The existence of a second court farther south, on the other façade of the residential wing has been supposed, but its nature is unknown.
Maps Plans   Restored section of the entire domus by P. André   Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Service Régional de l’Archéologie des Pays de la Loire, La Sarthe, 72, CAG p. 318-319, plan p. 318. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 109236
TGN ID 6003548
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House on the rue de la Harpe ( *Domus* rue de la Harpe)</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/house_on_the_rue_de_la_harpe_domus_rue_de_la_harpe/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/house_on_the_rue_de_la_harpe_domus_rue_de_la_harpe/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location MEDIOLANUM AULERCORUM (Evreux, France)
MEDIOLANUM AULERCORUM (Pleiades)
Garden House on the Place des Halles (La maison des Halles)
Keywords  peristyles porticos fountain courtyards  Garden Description Excavations of a 1400 square meter site in 1989 at 45 rue de la Harpe partially uncovered five habitations of the southern quarter of the city. They were occupied between the first and third century until a final destruction around 275 – 280. Among them, one had a peristyle [1] of which three porticos are know; it was quite likely planted. The same house had another paved court with a fountain [2]. Further south, the corner of another courtyard with porticos (4 x 3 columns) was found.
Maps None Available
Plans   Reconstruction of the four house spaces that make up House on the Rue de la Harpe.   Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  D. CLIQUET, L’Eure, 27, CAG p.136-137, restitution p.136. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 109153
TGN ID 6003548
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House with Garden, rue des Capucins</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/house-with-garden-rue-des-capucins/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/house-with-garden-rue-des-capucins/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location DUROCORTORUM (Reims, France)
DUROCORTORUM (Pleiades)
Sublocation Description Durocortorum was mentioned by Caesar as the center of the Remi, a Celtic tribe that sided with the Romans against the Belgians. It then became a federated city, nominally independent. Under Augustus, it became the capital of Gallia Belgica. Many vestiges indicate that it was densely settled and unusually extensive. A network of water supply and sewers has been found; an aqueduct brought water from 40 kilometers. The cardo and decumanus are still identifiable today by vestiges of four gates with arches, the northern one still standing; they cardo and decumanus intersect at the present Place Royale. Today, the city is known for its magnificent Gothic cathedral and its fine champagnes.
Garden House with Garden, rue des Capucins
Keywords  domus atrium  Garden Description A salvage excavation by F. Berthelot in 1987 revealed part of this poorly preserved house covering some 800 square meters in downtown Reims, about 300 meters from the right bank of the Vesle. (Fig 1) It is near an ancient street which is known for a ten meter stretch. The site was occupied in Julio-Claudian times, but the domus seems to date from the end of the first or beginning of the second century. Its total area must have exceeded 1000 square meters. It was divided into two parts. To the northeast were the rooms for daily life organized around a space (14 x 8 m) that would seem to be an atrium; there was a square (3.5 m) structure in the middle, now worn down beyond recognition, and no other indication of the nature of the space. To the southwest, a space free of construction may have been a garden. It was 12 meters wide and at least 20 meters long; its southwest limit is not known exactly. The northwest wall has buttresses on the outside.
BEL 2.1.1: Reims, House with Garden
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  F. Berthelot, L’archéologie urbaine à Reims, in L’archéologie en Champagne-Ardenne, 1960-1990, Bulletin de la société archéologique champenoise, t. 85, 1992, 4, p. 283-287.  A. Balmelle, R. Neiss, Les maisons de l’élite à Durocortorum, in Archéologie urbaine à Reims, Bulletin de la société archéologique champenoise, t. 96, 2003, 4, p. 73. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108945
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>La Villa des Rouaux</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/la-villa-des-rouaux/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/la-villa-des-rouaux/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location DIVODURUM MEDIOMATRICORUM (Peltre, France)
DIVODURUM MEDIOMATRICORUM (Pleiades)
Garden Villa de Larry
Keywords   courtyard
  porticoes
  hedge
  pergola
  cistern
  fountain
  Garden Description The villa des Rouaux runs along the south side of most of the village of Peltre, which is five kilometers southeast of of Metz. The historical and archaeological context is that of the periphery of Divodurum, principal city of the Mediomatrici, where a dense fabric of Roman rural sites has been found. This villa was 600 meters from the Roman road connecting Metz and Strasbourg.
In 2004, an open air excavation on 2.5 hectares permitted the study of the remains of five buildings organized around a vast rectangular courtyard with the long axis in the northwest-southeast direction. In the southwest-northeast direction, the courtyard was some 70 meters wide. The exact extent in the direction of the long axis remains unknown, but comparison with the complete plans of similar sites suggests that it could have been 200 to 300 meters.
The estate began from a wooden structure built at the end of the Gaulic period [1]. (Numbers refer to plan Fig. 1) It was replaced in the course of the Tiberian period by a building of durable materials. This second phase was then extensively remodeled in the Flavian period to give it an affluent, indeed, a monumental aspect by adding a long portico [2] framed by two pavilions [3]. A bath wing [4] and other touches were added later. In parallel with this evolution of the main edifice, annexes [5] were constructed to define a long rectangular court beginning from the façade of the main building. It was not possible to determine the precise chronology of the construction of this court, but it was, in any event, already in place when the living quarters were enlarged in the next phase.
In this next phase, the space of the estate was structured by building several low, separating walls, perhaps dividing the whole into the classic pars urbana and pars rustica.The pars urbana, of which the central element was the main dwelling, included also surrounding spaces, well defined by the low walls. In front, a pleasure courtyard [6] or garden was developed in harmony with the façade. A pool [7] occupied a good part of the area.
Several fragments of statues of white Grecian marble attest the presence of a rich décor with at least two divinities of which one was Harpocrates (Fig. 2 a Hellenized version of the child Horus). On either side of the main dwelling were smaller courtyards with technical functions. The one on the west [8] encloses the bath wing, which seems to have been added after the expansion of the main dwelling. The courtyard on the east [9] housed various hydraulic equipment, including buried conduits and a distribution box, necessary for water supply to the pool and the bath wing. Back (north) of the main house was a large area 140 meters wide [10] and of unknown extension to the north which may have been an orchard or a park.
The pars rustica was organized on either side of a vast court [11], of which the perspective was blocked by the succession of buildings on the west. In effect, the desire for symmetry expressed in the garden with the pool was somewhat thwarted by this alignment of the pre-existing annexes. A gateway [12] in the middle of the low wall which separates this area from the garden with the pool allowed access to this space [11], which was very much off the axis of the main dwelling. In the interior of the courtyard [11], the only structures found were the remains of a hexagonal foundation [13] around a quadrangular trench. This combination has been interpreted as a funeral enclosure, possibly that of owner who gave the villa its luxurious character. On either side of [11], the annexes were about ten meters back from the fencing walls.
These observations suggest that this large court [11] was not used for agricultural purposes but is rather to be interpreted as a park. In the second half of the third century, the estate declined and became a quarry for building materials. Later, some parts of the ruins were reoccupied until the middle of the fifth century, as indicated by hasty repairs made with salvaged pieces or light materials.
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  J.-D. Laffite, A. Bressoud, M. Mondy, A. Lefèbvre, M. Feller, I. Dechanez-Clerc, J.-J. Bigot, É. Rouger, LIÉHON (Moselle) « Larry » - Aéroport Metz-Nancy Lorraine, rapport de fouille préventive 2003, INRAP GEN/ SRA DRAC Lorraine, Metz, 2005, 9 vol., 1378 p., 207 figures, 61 plates. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108927
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Richebourg (Yvelines) villa de</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/richebourg_yvelines__villa_de/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/richebourg_yvelines__villa_de/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location AUTRICUM (Chartres, France)
AUTRICUM (Pleiades)
Garden Richebourg (Yvelines) villa de
Keywords  portico trellises stylobate amphorae pergola apse cistern triclinium  Garden Description Though the site has an area of 12 or 13 hectares, only one hectare has been excavated, the residential and agricultural part. Two groups of buildings frame a large garden on a slightly trapezoidal, walled area. To the north was the residence; to the south, the utility buildings, including a silo; while to the east, within its own walls, was the farmyard also with several buildings.
The pars urbana at the north end opened towards the south on a large space [1] developed as a garden. The southern façade was a portico stretching between rooms extending forward from either end of the main house. Along this façade [2], excavations have shown a band of gravel on a masonry base bordered by posts. Perhaps these posts supported a trellis along this façade. Against the stylobate of the portico, several bases of amphorae were discovered, doubtless as pots for plants that perhaps climbed on the trellis. A fragment of a white marble disk could be, according to Y. Barat, the only remains of an oscillum that once hung in the gallery.
The garden was divided into quadrants by two perpendicular roads, once paved with stone, though the stones were long ago carried off. The east-west road divides the garden into two equal parts; it starts in the west from a square entrance porch outside the wall not shown on the plan, then passes through a simple door pierced in the wall and framed by two vertical wooden braces. The other road [4] crosses the garden on the central axis of the residential part in the north, connecting the entry of its southern gallery to the utility building at the southern end of the garden. Symmetrically placed postholes on either side of these two roads indicate perhaps the presence of a pergola or bower. A stone basin was found at the intersection of these two roads. Along the west enclosing wall, other postholes with wedging material may indicate two other pergolas.
These roads mark off four plots of garden land. Dark brown layers indicate that they once received regular manuring and additions of wood ash, fragments of ceramic, shells of oysters and mussels, and pulverized mortar. The plan of the plots is marked out by an orthogonal network of horticultural pots, installed at intervals of 4 meters in each direction. Of the 217 of these pots found, more than 100 were in place. Aside from several bottoms of amphorae, the pots were of the classic flowerpot type, a truncated cone, and they all had a hole and in the bottom and three in the side, near the bottom. A single example had four of these lateral holes. There were five different types all with a top diameter of 8 to 12 centimeters and 9 to 13 centimeters high.
The distribution of each size pot has been carefully analyzed. Barat reports that two of the types were used in a consistent way. Type C, dated at the end of Antonine or beginning of the Severine period, was used only in the northern half of the garden. Type E, dated from the Claudian period, was found only along the post holes of the presumed pergola and would have been for climbing plants such as roses or ivy. (Only these two types could be dated with relative certainty.) In several cases, Barat felt that a grouping of two or three types of pots might simply indicate planting at different times in the same place.
On its northern side, the villa had another façade gallery [6], perhaps an ambulation, opening onto the fields. It was almost 44 meters long and has Tuscan and Corinthian columns. To the west, it was terminated by an apse; and to the east, by a cistern. Baths [7] were installed in the east wing. Next to the house, south of the baths, were several flagstones covered by a layer of garden soil, perhaps marking a flowerbed [8] over a drainage bed composed of fragments of tiles. To the south, six pits [9], 20 to 40 centimeters in diameter and 20 centimeters deep, not in the pattern of the other pots, were filled with an ochre-colored silt. Finally, north of the baths, protected by the extension of the gallery of the north façade, was found a group of five little negative casts of stumps, still with traces of the roots.
Near the southwest corner of the villa, a stone masonry slab [5] of irregular plan but generally U shaped is considered a possible open-air triclinium. It was later damaged by the erection of a building held up by posts.
Pollen analyses have yielded some results, although the pollens were damaged and oxidized by the dry environment. Samples of garden soil were both from the pots and from outside them. Several of the species identified, such as plantain, argue for a mown lawn. The tree species indicate the presence of conifers – cedars, larches and spruces (cedrus, larix, picea). An oleaceae (determined by D. Marguerie) poses problems of interpretation. Was it a lilac or an olive? In either case, it is an imported species. The lilac would come from the northeast of the Balkans; the olive, from the Mediterranean. Though the lilac might seem more probable on the basis of current plantings, it is noteworthy that Pliny reports that the olive was acclimated in central Gaul (H.N. V 1-2, XVII, 47-48). The genus Prunus appeared several times, thus confirming the results of charcoal analysis (anthracology) but without determination of the species – wild cherry or domestic cherry. Ivy is also present, perhaps to cover the pergolas.
Maps None Available
Plans   Plan 1: Fig 4 - Plan of the Athenian Gardens of Richebourg   Images   Plan 1: Bird&amp;#39;s Eye Perspective of the Garden   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Y. Barat, La villa gallo-romaine de Richebourg (Yvelines) in Revue Archéologique du Centre de la France, 38, 1999, p. 117-67, plans p. 122, jardin p.140. (worldcat) Y Barat, D. Morize, Les pots d’horticulture dans le monde antique et les jardins de la villa de Richebourg (Yvelines), in SFECAG, Actes du colloque de Fribourg, 1999, p. 213-36.  Y. Barat, La recherche archéologique des jardins antiques in Les nouvelles de l’archéologie 83-84, 2001, p. 56-62, not. P. 58-59.  G. Coulon, J.C. Golvin, Voyage en Gaule romaine, Actes sud Errance, Arles-Paris, 2002, p.121-3, restitution p. 122-3. (worldcat) Y. Barat and D. Morize, L’archéologie des jardins antiques: le cas de la pars urbana de la villa de Richebourg (Yvelines) in Actualité de la Recherche en Histoire et Archéologie agraires, Annales Littéraires de L’Université de Franche-Comté, 764, Besançon, 2003. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108778
TGN ID 6003548
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roman Villa</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/sainte-marguerite-sur-mer_seine-maritime_roman_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/sainte-marguerite-sur-mer_seine-maritime_roman_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location Sainte-Marguerite-sur-Mer (Seine-Maritime, France)
Sainte-Marguerite-sur-Mer (Pleiades)
Garden Sainte-Marguerite-sur-Mer (Seine-Maritime) Roman Villa
Keywords  mosaics porticos [hypocausts] (http://vocab.getty.edu/page/aat/300004277) [exedrae] (http://vocab.getty.edu/page/aat/300081589) [triclinia] (http://vocab.getty.edu/page/aat/300004359)  Garden Description Following the fortuitous discovery of mosaics in 1820, the site of a large Roman villa was excavated from 1821 to 1830 by M. Solicoffre, then from 1840 to 1848 by P. J. Féret, and again in 1876 by Abbé Loth. The ruins were then abandoned, and our knowledge of them comes entirely from the very uneven documentation of these early explorations. From our perspective, however, what is noteworthy about this literature is not its inadequacy by modern standards but the considerable interest it shows in plants and gardens.
The residential part shows a certain degree of luxury with painted plaster, marble plates, stuccos, and numerous heated rooms. The pars urbana was quadrilateral and was unearthed on more than 60 by 45 meters. In the center was a court [A] of about 25 meters square that was perhaps developed as a garden. In 1843, it was noted that this court was “not yet excavated.” It is not clear whether or not it ever was. Around it were arranged a series of rooms. One large room [HH] (12 x 5 m) with a semicircular apse opened off the southeast corner of the court and must have been a reception room. The central space of the court was apparently bordered on the north, west, and south sides by porticos of unequal width. The bases of the columns and two shafts were found. To the east was found a large area (22.5 x 4.5 m) entirely covered in mosaic. To the north of the villa was a rectangular space [O] that could have been a courtyard or garden. It was bounded on the north by a gallery nearly 25 meters long and heated by hypocausts for its entire length. Semicircular apses extended from the east end and from the north side. Further constructions not excavated extended to the northeast.
Eighty meters to the west, below the villa and parallel to its west side was a belvedere-promenade. This structure (3.1 x 47.6 m) extended in a north-south direction with apses at each end. On the east side was a large room (11.49 x 5.92 m) terminated by an apse on the east and opening onto the promenade and the view to the west. The levels marked on the map of the site imply that this room was 1.48 meters above the promenade, but such a difference is hard to believe. According to Féret, the promenade was paved with mosaic; according to W. Martin, with brick. The semicircular part of the room was ornamented with a “delicious mosaic” of fruits and grapes. The wall of this apse survived up to a height of 10 to 15 centimeters and preserved the traces of a beautiful mosaic (now lost) “in enamel cubes,” that is, smalti. About 1.4 meters west of the apse, in the centerline of this room, was found a masonry mass (1.71 x 1.86 m) considered by some as the base for a statue and by others as the support for a masonry table. Féret called this room an excedra; W. Martin interpreted it as a summer triclinium enjoying a great view of the sea.
The excavators also note at about 55 meters northeast of the promenade a small, square structure that could have been a little temple or shrine. They mention also two springs, one of which had a square basin and was still in use in 1876 by the inhabitants. The waters of the spring on the plateau were channeled by pipes of elm, some of which were discovered: “the trunk of an elm, 1.80 meters long, with its bark still on and hollowed out in the middle by a drill, carried water to feed the baths.” It was found in place along with several others and was then deposited in the museum of antiquities in Rouen.
Maps None Available
Plans   Detailed Plan of Villa at Sainte-Marguerite-sur-Mer.     Plan drawings of the Villa, Temple, and Promenade at Sainte-Marguerite-sur-Mer.   Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  P.J. Féret, Lettre adressée à M. de Caumont sur les fouilles pratiquées à Sainte-Marguerite sur Mer près Dieppe in Bulletin Monumental 9, 1843, p. 92-97.  Ch.W. Martin, Note sur les fouilles exécutées en 1876 sur l’emplacement de la station romaine de Ste-Marguerite-sur-Mer (Seine inférieure), in Bulletin de la Société des Antiquaires de Normandie, 1861, p. 319-326. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/1026569500) abbé J. Loth, Fouilles de Ste-Marguerite-sur-Mer, in Bulletin de la Commission des antiquités de la Seine-Inférieure, Rouen, 1870, p. 68-75. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/812701053) &amp;lt;! &amp;ndash; In the process of being finalized: J.P. Darmon, Recueil &amp;ldquo;Erin Mckay&amp;rdquo; emckay2@towson.eduise II, 5???, 1994 (ou 5 ???), n°:894-902, p.111-114; ???, in CAG Seine-maritime; 76, 20???, p. 497-500 (with detailed bibliography). &amp;ndash;&amp;gt;  Pleiades ID 109153
TGN ID 6003548
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/echternach-villa-rural/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/echternach-villa-rural/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location ECHTERNACH (Luxembourg)
ECHTERNACH (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa
Keywords  mosiacs courtyard peristyle  Garden Description This villa of a farm near Echternach was of the winged corridor type with sumptuous interior marble paneling, mosaics and wall paintings (Fig. 1). Originally constructed in the 60s of the first century AD, the villa was enlarged until it covered an area of 8928 square meters in the third century.
The protruding wings of the house on either side of the main entrance on the north framed a large, open courtyard, 29 x 74 meters in size, possibly a garden (G on plan). In the middle of this courtyard was a masonry pool of grand proportions (14.50 x 60 meters). In the middle of this stone-paved pool was a square base which once supported a statue, a sculptural group or perhaps a crater. The pool was retained as a decorative element throughout all the alterations of the estate until the destruction of the farm in the late 4th or early fifth century The southern peristyle courtyard (16.50 x 17 meters) within the house itself was initially designed as part of the bath complex in this wing, and in this courtyard was a swimming pool or natatio. Soon after the building of the house, the pool was filled in and the courtyard transformed into a garden (G on plan).
There was a garden from the very beginning in the western peristyle courtyard, as witnessed by the presence of garden soil (G on plan). This garden was later abandoned in the early second century.
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  J. Metzler, J. Zimmer and L. Bakker, Ausgrabungen in Echternach, Luxembourg, 1981; P. Van Ossel, Établissements ruraux de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquité tardive dans le nord de la Gaule, Paris, 1992, pp. 350-353, figs. 145-146. (worldcat)](http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/905778589)  Pleiades ID 108955
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa de Châtillon-sur-Seiche</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/noyal_-_ch%C3%A2tillon-sur-seiche_ille-et-vilaine/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/noyal_-_ch%C3%A2tillon-sur-seiche_ille-et-vilaine/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location NOYAL-CHATILLION-SUR-SEICHE (Ille-et-Vilaine, France)
NOYAL-CHATILLION-SUR-SEICHE (Pleiades)
Garden Villa de Châtillon-sur-Seiche
Keywords  barn courtyard trench fanum fountain hypocausts forecourt  Garden Description Six kilometers south of Rennes, this village with medieval churches and pleasant promenades along the banks of the Seiche must once have been the site of castellum from which the name Châtillon derives. The fort was probably on a mound a few hundred meters southwest of the ancient farm and villa described here.
The evolution of this agricultural site can be followed from the period immediately following the Roman conquest up to its destruction at the end of the fourth century. The site lies 0.9 kilometers east of the center of the cloverleaf intersection of N 137 with D 34 in the Guyomerais area on the west side of Noyal-Châtillon-sur-Seiche. Rue des Potiers cuts through the site, with the pars urbana on the north and the smaller pars rustica on the south. The Rue de Condate bounds the area on the east. Known since 1904, the four-hectare site was excavated by Alain Provost between 1984 and 1988 prior to development of a residential subdivision.
From a period immediately following the Roman occupation (from 20 BC to about 40 AD) date a stone enclosure for animals, some agricultural walls, and remnants of a simple barn.
A modest farmhouse (Phase 1) was built about A.D 30. To the south extended a courtyard (65 x 70 m), delimited by a trench, which may have had a garden. Outbuildings included a forge, a workshop, and three small homes with fireplaces.
About AD 80, the farmhouse was razed to make room for the first villa (Phase 2).Built of small stones, this villa consisted of five rooms in a line extending 26.5 meters along the north side of a gallery. A wall replaced the trench delimiting the courtyard. Outbuildings included a barn, a mill, and a chalk oven, in addition to the forge and homes.
Then, somewhere around 180, residential structures were attached to the outside of the wall on the east side of the courtyard (Phase 3). They may have been the residence of the villicus. A little to the south and also outside the courtyard was built a square fanum, a type of temple thought to be of Celtic origin and consisting of a tower in a courtyard surrounded by a gallery.
In the first half of the third century, the complex reached it apogee (Phase 4) with an enclosed courtyard of some 3000 square meters with a fountain in the north-south axis of the main reception room of the north wing.
It was possible to excavate only the eastern half and (on the south side of Rue des Potiers) the whole of the wall which closed the south side of the courtyard. At its southwest corner, this wall turned north at exactly the point required to fit a conceptual restoration of the west side as symmetric to the east with the fountain on the axis of symmetry. Along three sides of the courtyard (excluding the south) ran galleries with wooden supports on the courtyard side and a line of rooms on the outside. On the east side, one room was heated by hypocausts and one was a wine cellar. Since an access road was found on the east, the entrance to the courtyard was presumably on the east side of the forecourt on the south, in an area destroyed in the construction of Rue des Potiers.
The villa showed a certain level of refinement in decor. The fountain, lined with marble with decorative moulding, was formed by two masonry squares, one within the other. A central pedestal probably supported a water jet and possibly a statue. A few fragments of marble statuary were found, including the abdomen and buttocks of what may have been a cupid; but precise original locations could not be determined. Though there is no evidence of mosaics, wall painting with imitations of marble and porphyry was employed, as were some high-quality building materials such as slate and schist. Numerous fragments of bronze plumbing were found, along with collars for attaching metal pipes to wooden tubes and sections of pipe to carry away the waste water.
At the end of the third century, the pars urbana was abandonned, then partially re-occupied around 320 – 330 in the age of Constantine. Final total abandonment came at the end of the fourth century.
Was there a garden? Within the courtyard, there is no direct evidence of planting, but neither is there evidence of a hard surface that would preclude a garden, except that between the north gallery and the fountain there seems to have been a passage way. Outside the courtyard, northeast of the supposed house of the villicus, there were parallel trenches interpreted by the excavator as a garden zone (F on the Phase 4 plan).
A study of pollens and sediments below the levels of the Gallo-Roman villa in a paleosol dated to the late first century BC or early first century AD has revealed the environment of the farm at that time. It shows a soil already worked and gardened by man and the presence of pollens of cereals. The countryside, already totally or partially cleared combined various trees – pine, hazel, oak, holly and linden – with ferns and herbaceous plants, especially grasses and plantains characteristic of prairies and grasslands. A comparison with the quantities of pollens found in the soils of the villa in the second and third centuries shows relative stability of the percentages, as shown in figure 5. While interesting, these findings describe the environment rather than the gardens themselves.
Maps   A Map of Land Development Over Time.   Plans   Plans of Land Development Over Time.   Images   The Fountain Bassin.     Reconstructed cut of the Fountain Bassin.   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Alain Provost, “La villa gallo-romaine de Chatillon-sur-Seiche,” in the catalog of the exposition Nos ancêtres les Riedones, Musée de Bretagne- Eco-musée du pays de Rennes, Rennes, 20 juin, 31 déc. 1990, p. 10-31 (worldcat) Gilles Leroux, Alain Provost, CAG- Ille-et-vilaine (35), p. 270-274. [(worldcat)] (http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/463616145)  Pleiades ID 69488
TGN ID 6003548
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vaise - House with the Xenia</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/vaise-house_with_the_xenia/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/vaise-house_with_the_xenia/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location LUGDUNUM (Lyon, France)
LUGDUNUM (Pleiades)
Garden House with Pilasters (Clos du Verbe Incarné)
Keywords  domus porticoes courtyard drain  Garden Description Xenia were gifts of game, fish, poultry, fruits or vegetables given by a host to a guest to be cooked to the guest’s liking. Here, the name comes from the discovery of a pinax (a painted ceramic tablet) showing xenia. This house was discovered during excavation of the southern sector of the Saint-Pierre land management zone (ZAC) in a suburban quarter of Lyon. The building –one hesitates whether to call it a suburban villa or a domus–extends over 630 square meters. There are traces of occupation of the site in Augustan times, but the house (29 x 24 m) was built in the reign of Tiberius. It is organized in two perpendicular wings around a courtyard with porticos in a U. The galleries are 3.5 meters wide. In this first phase, nine rooms were placed around the court.
The limit of the court on the west is not certain [phase II, 1]. As a hypothesis, an original court of 17.74 meters by 16.40 meters –nearly square but with an extra, sixth, span on the west –has been proposed. The columns, with a maximum diameter of 37 centimeters, were made of semi-circular bricks cemented and covered with white plaster. They rested on limestone bases roughly squared off. A little later, around the end of the reign of Claudius, the house underwent several changes. Room [10] was built, which enlarged the eastern wing. A new room [3] was created, important enough in the eyes of the proprietor to sacrifice part of one of the porticos to fit it in. In the same period, the spaces between the columns were partly closed, while the courtyard was connected to a water supply network. The paintings were freshened up, and the house doubtless had a second floor. In this last phase, however, the house did not last long. It was destroyed at the beginning of the reign of Vespasian, and the site then remained vacant at least until the middle of the fourth century and probably into the fifth. In this final, Claudian phase, the courtyard represented more than 57 percent of the area. It enjoyed running water, which was not present in the houses of the Verbe incarnéquarter in Lugdunumat the same period. A wooden pipe, of which only the negative imprint can be seen, crossed the courtyard and porticos obliquely. A drain from room [5] was connected to it. The basin of a fountain that has disappeared was placed on the axis of room [9]; it was definitely there in the second phase and possibly in the first, though that has not been demonstrated.
The ground of the central part of the courtyard was topsoil and earth coming from under the porticos. Three samples have been studied palynolocially. The results leave no doubt that a garden grew in the center. We quote the abstract of the publication. “The pollen content is relatively poor, and the counts have been made for each sample separately. The spectrum of pollens includes a rather wide diversity of herbaceous plants of which certain families can include ornamental plants such as the tubuliflorous composites and the Caryophyllaceae (pink family). Ruderal plants, that is, those that grow in sites much transformed by man such as clearings or waste places near habitations, predominate: Chenopodiaceae (such as spinach, beets and their relatives –Tr.), gramineous plants, and the following genera: nettles, arnois (artemesia, tarragon –Tr.), and plantain (Plantago lanceolata). This last is often associated with the cultivation of cereals. There were also species of ferns. Walnuts (Juglans) and grapes (Vitis) may have been cultivated around the site. Finally, pine (Pinus) is relatively well represented, but the very high rate of pollenization of the pine and its capacity for dispersion of its pollens often lead to an over-representation of these species. Thus, this courtyard could have been cultivated as an ornamental garden.” (E. Delaval et al., p. 89).
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  E. Delaval, C. Bellon, J. Chastel, E. Plassot, L. Tranoy, Vaise, un quartier de Lyon antique, Document d’archéologie en Rhône-Alpes n° 5, Lyon, 1995. E. Plassot, Le quartier Saint-Pierre, la maison aux xenia, p. 71-129. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 167717
TGN ID 6003548
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 04 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Ram (La Maison au Bélier)</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/house-of-the-ram-la-maison-au-b%C3%A9lier/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/house-of-the-ram-la-maison-au-b%C3%A9lier/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location DUROCORTORUM (Reims, France)
DUROCORTORUM (Pleiades)
Sublocation Description Durocortorum was mentioned by Caesar as the center of the Remi, a Celtic tribe that sided with the Romans against the Belgians. It then became a federated city, nominally independent. Under Augustus, it became the capital of Gallia Belgica. Many vestiges indicate that it was densely settled and unusually extensive. A network of water supply and sewers has been found; an aqueduct brought water from 40 kilometers. The cardo and decumanus are still identifiable today by vestiges of four gates with arches, the northern one still standing; they cardo and decumanus intersect at the present Place Royale. Today, the city is known for its magnificent Gothic cathedral and its fine champagnes.
Garden House of the Ram (La Maison au Bélier)
Keywords  porticos drain corridor  Garden Description BEL 2.3.1: Reims, House of the Ram Excavated in 1992-93 by Agnès Balmelle, this vast house probably covered about 2000 square meters. The date of construction is rather uncertain; it could be as early as the end of the first century or as late as the second half of the second (Fig. 1) The excavations have revealed a portico (A) (20 x 3 m) opening onto an open space which may have been a garden. It was bordered on the southwest by drain which no doubt collected rainwater from the roof and led it away to the northwest. A well (E) was in the north gallery or corridor (B).
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  A. Balmelle, Reims, Le site de la villa des Capucins (site n°51 454 129) : D.F.S. de sauvegarde urgent, S.R.A. Champagne-Ardenne, 1995  A. Balmelle, R. Neiss, Les maisons de l’élite à Durocortorum, in Archéologie urbaine à Reims, Bulletin de la société archéologique champenoise, t. 96, 2003, 4, p. 82. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108945
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House on rue de la Fraternité</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/house-on-rue-de-la-fraternit%C3%A9/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/house-on-rue-de-la-fraternit%C3%A9/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location NEMETACUM (Arras, France)
NEMETACUM (Pleiades)
Garden House on rue de la Fraternité
Keywords  mosiacs peristyles  Garden Description Excavated in 1875-79 in the eastern suburbs of the city by A. Ternick, this large house has been uncovered in a roughly elliptical area with axes of 40 and 20 meters. The chronology is uncertain. It was perhaps destroyed by a violent fire (of which there are traces elsewhere in the city) in the second century and not reconstructed. Some walls were decoratively painted; most floors were concrete, but there is some evidence of mosaics. The floor of room [5] (just below room [1] in the plan) had a large slab of black marble in the center in frame with smaller slabs in the corners. The southwest corner of a peristyle and 12 meters along the west side and 10 meters along the south side have been excavated. The galleries had concrete floors and slender Tuscan columns 20 centimeters in diameter and 1.2 meters apart. The walls were painted red. In the center of the peristyle court was a masonry construction considered as an “impluvium” at the time of excavation, but it was quite possibly a pool. If it were a pool, then the area was almost surely in a garden. The house had another interior open court and possible garden [17] of about 6 x 7 meters near a well [25].
Maps    Arras (Pas de Calais), France. Excavations on the House on rue de la Fraternité. 1875-1879.   Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Alain Jacques, Georges Jelski, “Arras antique, bilan et perspective” in Les villes de la Gaule Belgique au Haut-Empire, Actes du colloque tenu à Saint-Riquier (somme) le 22-23-24 octobre 1982, Revue achéologique de Picardie, p. 124-5. (worldcat) Delmaire et al., Le Nord-Pas- de-Calais, 62/1, CAG, p. 145-147, fig. 46, plan p. 145; H. Stern I, 1 p. 101-102.   Pleiades ID 109194
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House on rue de la Fraternité</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/house_on_rue_de_la_fraternit%C3%A9/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/house_on_rue_de_la_fraternit%C3%A9/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location NEMETACUM (Arras, France)
NEMETACUM (Pleiades)
Garden House on rue de la Fraternité
Keywords  mosiacs peristyles  Garden Description Excavated in 1875-79 in the eastern suburbs of the city by A. Ternick, this large house has been uncovered in a roughly elliptical area with axes of 40 and 20 meters. The chronology is uncertain. It was perhaps destroyed by a violent fire (of which there are traces elsewhere in the city) in the second century and not reconstructed. Some walls were decoratively painted; most floors were concrete, but there is some evidence of mosaics. The floor of room [5] (just below room [1] in the plan) had a large slab of black marble in the center in frame with smaller slabs in the corners. The southwest corner of a peristyle and 12 meters along the west side and 10 meters along the south side have been excavated. The galleries had concrete floors and slender Tuscan columns 20 centimeters in diameter and 1.2 meters apart. The walls were painted red. In the center of the peristyle court was a masonry construction considered as an “impluvium” at the time of excavation, but it was quite possibly a pool. If it were a pool, then the area was almost surely in a garden. The house had another interior open court and possible garden [17] of about 6 x 7 meters near a well [25].
Maps    Arras (Pas de Calais), France. Excavations on the House on rue de la Fraternité. 1875-1879.   Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Alain Jacques, Georges Jelski, “Arras antique, bilan et perspective” in Les villes de la Gaule Belgique au Haut-Empire, Actes du colloque tenu à Saint-Riquier (somme) le 22-23-24 octobre 1982, Revue achéologique de Picardie, p. 124-5. (worldcat) Delmaire et al., Le Nord-Pas- de-Calais, 62/1, CAG, p. 145-147, fig. 46, plan p. 145; H. Stern I, 1 p. 101-102.   Pleiades ID 109194
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/rural-villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/rural-villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location BAD DURKHEIM-UNGSTEIN (Germany)
BAD DURKHEIM-UNGSTEIN (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa
Keywords  villa rustica corridor courtyard  Garden Description The stone structures of this villa rustica, dating to the early second century, replaced earlier timber buildings. With the addition of an annex on the east in the early fourth century, the facade of the house acquired a length of 104 meters. The farm was occupied until the early fifth century.
The main residence is a villa of the winged corridor type (BEL 13.1.1). Two protruding wings on either wide of the entrance on the south framed an open courtyard which may have been planted (G on plan). Behind the house at the north were two more wings framing a second open courtyard (G on plan). This area, possibly a garden, was bordered on the north by a low wall.
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  H. Cüppers, ed., Die Römer in Rheinland-Pfalz, Stuttgart, 1990, pp. 317-319, figs. 156, 199. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108784
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The House aux Fleurons (boulevard de la Paix)</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/the-house-aux-fleurons-boulevard-de-la-paix/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/the-house-aux-fleurons-boulevard-de-la-paix/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location DUROCORTORUM (Reims, France)
DUROCORTORUM (Pleiades)
Sublocation Description Durocortorum was mentioned by Caesar as the center of the Remi, a Celtic tribe that sided with the Romans against the Belgians. It then became a federated city, nominally independent. Under Augustus, it became the capital of Gallia Belgica. Many vestiges indicate that it was densely settled and unusually extensive. A network of water supply and sewers has been found; an aqueduct brought water from 40 kilometers. The cardo and decumanus are still identifiable today by vestiges of four gates with arches, the northern one still standing; they cardo and decumanus intersect at the present Place Royale. Today, the city is known for its magnificent Gothic cathedral and its fine champagnes.
Garden The House aux Fleurons (boulevard de la Paix)
Keywords  porticos trench  Garden Description BEL 2.2.1: Reims, House aux Flerurons Along the north side runs a secondary street following the orientation of the town in Augustan times. Along this street, in the northern part of the house, a series of rooms with mosaics were found. On the south side, the space A (about 30 x 14 m) was probably a garden. The central part, surrounded on three sides by porticos, had two wide trenches (a) cut into the chalk and filled with clay, a strong indication of a garden. The trenches seem to be connected on the south side, and the south wall seems to be the limit of the parcel.
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Ch. Loriquet, La mosaïque des Promenades et autres trouvées à Reims, Reims, 1862 (worldcat) D.R.A.H..A., La Bourse du Travail à Reims, Bulletin de la société archéologique champenoise, n°4, 1977, p. 77-79  R. Neiss, La structure urbaine de Reims antique et son évolution du Ier au IIIe siècle après J.-C. Les villes de la Gaule Belgique au Haut-Empire, in: Actes du colloque tenu à Saint-Riquier (Somme). Revue archéologique de Picardie, n°3-4, 1984, p. 171-191, (worldcat) A. Balmelle, R. Neiss, Les maisons de l’élite à Durocortorum, in Archéologie urbaine à Reims, Bulletin de la société archéologique champenoise, t. 96, 2003, 4, p. 74. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108945
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The House aux Fleurons (boulevard de la Paix)</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/the_house_aux_fleurons_boulevard_de_la_paix/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/the_house_aux_fleurons_boulevard_de_la_paix/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location DUROCORTORUM (Reims, France)
DUROCORTORUM (Pleiades)
Garden The House aux Fleurons (boulevard de la Paix)
Keywords  porticos trench  Garden Description BEL 2.2.1: Reims, House aux Flerurons Along the north side runs a secondary street following the orientation of the town in Augustan times. Along this street, in the northern part of the house, a series of rooms with mosaics were found. On the south side, the space A (about 30 x 14 m) was probably a garden. The central part, surrounded on three sides by porticos, had two wide trenches (a) cut into the chalk and filled with clay, a strong indication of a garden. The trenches seem to be connected on the south side, and the south wall seems to be the limit of the parcel.
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Ch. Loriquet, La mosaïque des Promenades et autres trouvées à Reims, Reims, 1862 (worldcat) D.R.A.H..A., La Bourse du Travail à Reims, Bulletin de la société archéologique champenoise, n°4, 1977, p. 77-79  R. Neiss, La structure urbaine de Reims antique et son évolution du Ier au IIIe siècle après J.-C. Les villes de la Gaule Belgique au Haut-Empire, in: Actes du colloque tenu à Saint-Riquier (Somme). Revue archéologique de Picardie, n°3-4, 1984, p. 171-191, (worldcat) A. Balmelle, R. Neiss, Les maisons de l’élite à Durocortorum, in Archéologie urbaine à Reims, Bulletin de la société archéologique champenoise, t. 96, 2003, 4, p. 74. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108945
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urban House East of Forum</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/urban-house-east-of-forum/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/urban-house-east-of-forum/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location COLONIA AUGUSTA TREVERORUM (Trier, Germany)
COLONIA AUGUSTA TREVERORUM (Pleiades)
Garden Urban House East of Forum
Keywords  insulae atriums peristyles  Garden Description In only one of the excavated houses of the second and third century in two insulae east of the forum beneath the imperial baths can gardens be shown to have existed. This house was demolished when the imperial baths were erected in the last decade of the third century. It seems to have occupied an entire insula measuring 55 x 100 meters. (Fig. 1). An atrium (A on plan) was built in the west wing of the building in the first half of the second century. The atrium was later transformed into a garden with planting beds and a pool. Around the middle of the third century this garden was abandoned. The house also boasted a large peristyle courtyard on the east which may have been planted (G on plan), but for a garden there is no direct archaeological evidence.
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  W. Reusch, &amp;ldquo;Wandmalereien und Mosaikboden eines Peristylhauses im Bereich der Trierer Kaiserthermen,&amp;rdquo; Trierer Zeitschrift 29, 1966:187-235. (worldcat) W. Reusch, &amp;ldquo;Die Ausgrabungen im Westteil der Trierer Kaiserthermen&amp;rdquo;, Bericht der Römisch-Germanischen Kommission 51-52,1970-71:252-270, 281, Beilage 30. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 113319
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa Borg</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/villa-borg/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/villa-borg/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location BORG (Germany)
BORG (Pleiades)
Garden Villa Borg
Keywords  porticoes basins courtyard  Garden Description The villa of Borg is situated in a forest between the villages Borg and Oberleuken, community of Perl (Landkreis Merzig-Wadern), in the border-region Germany - Luxembourg - France. The huge villa complex is situated in a densely occupied Roman settlement region on the fertile plateaus between the river valleys of Saar and Mosel. Pars urbana and pars rustica covered an area of about 7.5 hectare. The villa was built in the direct vicinity of the Roman road from Metz to Trier (Augusta Treverorum), which was part of the far-distance connection between Marseille and Cologne.
Recent archaeological excavations have shown traces of an earlier rural settlement below the foundations of the villa. This first occupation can be dated to late Celtic times or directly to the beginning of Roman occupation. In the second quarter of the 1st century A.D. it was followed by a possibly two-angled timber-framed building of 17.80 x 10.40 m, which is interpreted as proto-villa. The construction of the later stone-buildings took place around 50 A.D. The main period of the villa lasted from the end of the 1st to the late 3rd century A.D. From the middle of the 4th century A.D. (Plan, Fig 1)onwards only some parts of the villa were still occupied. It was completely abandoned by the end of the 4th century A.D.
Since 1987, the eastern part of the site, the pars urbana, was completely excavated. The main building, a porticus villa, type Bollendorf, was completely reconstructed, exactly on top of the Roman foundations. The pars rustica in the western part, covering an area of 400 x 150 m, is not yet excavated. Geophysical measurements gave evidence of two parallel rows of at least 14 small buildings; possible used for storage and handicraft activities.
Unfortunately only a few architectural elements, like the two water basins (Fig 2), gave hints to the Roman garden architecture. The huge water basin of 10 x 30 m and the two-angled central porticus building of the villa were enclosing a yard, which was most probably laid out as a representative Roman garden in Mediterranean style. A few remaining fragments of stone sculptures point to a representative garden architecture. Additionally, archaeobotanical investigations gave evidence of agricultural activities connected with the villa. A waste pit excavated in the inner yard of the pars urbana revealed carbonised waste of processing spelt and einkorn, probably grown as maslin. Further cultivated crops were emmer, naked wheat, hulled barley and the pulses lentil, pea and Celtic bean. Evidence of fruit tree cultivation is scarce. Only pear and a fragment of an undetermined cultivated Prunoideae fruitstone were recorded.
In the year 2000, the reconstructed main building of the villa with its bath, now occupying a small museum, was completed by the reconstruction of a representative Roman garden. This garden is situated between the reconstructed central building and the huge Roman water basin. In the following it was completed by a vegetable garden, a rose garden and a small vineyard, presenting Roman horticulture to the public. The reconstruction was part of the European Union’s Interreg-II project &amp;ldquo;gardens without borders&amp;rdquo;. Concerning the poor local evidence from the recent excavations the reconstruction was mainly based on the better evidence of Roman gardens from villas in Italy and France.
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  J. Brück, &amp;ldquo;Die villa von Borg&amp;rdquo;, in: Der Kreis Merzig-Wadern und die Mosel zwischen Nennig und Metz. Führer zu archäologischen Denkmälern in Deutschland 24 (Stuttgart 1992) 112-119. (worldcat) R. Gleser &amp;amp; A. Miron, Romanisierungsforschung im Saarland. Archäologische Informationen 18, 1995, 213-215  A. Miron (Hrsg.), Das Badegebäude der römischen Villa von Borg (Merzig 1997). (worldcat) J. Wiethold, &amp;ldquo;Archäobotanische Aspekte der &amp;laquo;Romanisierung&amp;raquo; in Südwestdeutschland: Bemerkungen zur Unkrautflora römerzeitlicher Dinkeläcker&amp;rdquo;, in: A. Müller-Karpe, H. Brandt, H. Jöns, D. Krauße &amp;amp; A. Wigg (eds.), Studien zur Archäologie der Kelten und Römer in Mittel- und Westeuropa. Alfred Haffner zum 60 Geburtstag gewidmet. Internationale Archäologie - Studia Honoraria 4 (Rahden/Westfalen 1998) 531-551. (worldcat) M. Frey, Die römische villa von Borg. Ein reiches Landgut mit vorrömischer Tradition&amp;quot;, in: A. Haffner &amp;amp; S. Schnurbein (eds.), Kelten, Germanen und Römer im Mittelgebirgsraum zwischen Luxemburg und Thüringen. Akten des Internationalen Kolloquiums zum DFG-Schwerpunktprogramm &amp;ldquo;Romanisierung&amp;rdquo; in Trier vom 28. bis 30. September 1998. Kolloquien zur Vor- und Frühgeschichte 5 (Bonn 2000) 41-50. (worldcat) J. Wiethold, &amp;ldquo;Kontinuität und Wandel in der landwirtschaftlichen Produktion und Nahrungsmittelversorgung zwischen Spätlatènezeit und gallo-römischer Epoche. Archäobotanische Analysen in der Großvillenanlage von Borg, Krs. Merzig-Wadern&amp;rdquo;, in: A. Haffner &amp;amp; S. Schnurbein (eds.), Kelten, Germanen und Römer im Mittelgebirgsraum zwischen Luxemburg und Thüringen. Akten des Internationalen Kolloquiums zum DFG-Schwerpunktprogramm &amp;ldquo;Romanisierung&amp;rdquo; in Trier vom 28. bis 30. September 1998. Kolloquien zur Vor- und Frühgeschichte 5 (Bonn 2000) 147-159. (worldcat) B. Birkenhagen, Die Römische Villa Borg. Ein Begleiter durch die Anlage (Merzig 2004).(worldcat)  Pleiades ID 272861914
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>*Domus* of the Place Epars</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/domus_of_the_place_des_epars/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Aug 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/domus_of_the_place_des_epars/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location AUTRICUM (Chartres, France)
AUTRICUM (Pleiades)
Garden Domus of the Place Epars
Keywords  domus hypocaust  Garden Description A large reception room of 73 square meters in the northwest corner was heated by a hypocaust under the floor. In this room was a grand composition depicting a procession of people. Next to this room was a square room that looked out down the long axis of the garden that filled the 247 square meter rectangular (19 x 13 m) rectangle of open area. The Corinthian colonnade of the garden was found collapsed towards the outside. Elegant Corinthian capitals of limestone and fragments of column bases of attic type with traces of tinted whitewash and red accents were found during the excavations.
Maps None Available
Plans   LUG_Fig. 1: Chartres, Domus of the Place des Epars, from CAG.   Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  :A. Ollagnier, D. Joly, L’Eure-et-Loir, CAG p. 137-139, plan p. 138 (with bibliography of previous works). (worldcat)   Pleiades ID 108778
TGN ID 6003548
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House with Pilasters (Clos du Verbe Incarné)</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/house-with-pilasters-clos-du-verbe-incarn%C3%A9/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Aug 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/house-with-pilasters-clos-du-verbe-incarn%C3%A9/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location LUGDUNUM (Lyon, France)
LUGDUNUM (Pleiades)
Garden House with Pilasters (Clos du Verbe Incarné)
Keywords  insula / insulae atrium Domus  Garden Description The insula VII of the Clos du Verbe Incarné, excavated from 1977 to 1987, lies on the western slope of a little dip (71 x 34 m) in the upper town, about 160 meters northwest of the center of the top of the theater. In this insula, begun between 40 and 20 BC, one can follow the evolution of this quarter up to the end of the third century. To the north, the insula was bordered by the street called du Capitol and to the west by the street called de Cybèle. The subdivision of the insula was put in place from 15–10 BC. The house occupied 400 square meters, and was organized on an italic plan around a traditional atrium followed by a tablinum[1]. The house of seven or eight rooms did not have a peristyle but did, no doubt, include a hortus[2] (15 x 5 m) at the back of the lot.
The house was originally constructed of adobe on a floor and gutter of granite masonry. Later, in Tibero-Claudian times, a wooden section was added, which facilitated the creation of an upper story on the western part, which also included on the ground level some isolated shops occupying 100 square meters. The neighbor to the north was another small, 315-square-meter house, the Domus with the Mosaic Emblema, which was organized around a four-column atrium, but had no garden. In fact, the House with Pilasters was the only one in the insula to have, without doubt, a little green space. In the southern part of the insula, there were three combinations of house and shop, and another small, 310-square-meter house called the Domus with Lararium.
LUG 1. 1. House with Pilasters. On the rectangle surrounding the word &amp;ldquo;Garden?&amp;rdquo; in the upper left corner is the &amp;ldquo;House with Pilasters.&amp;rdquo; Source, Maison 1996, p.134.
Plans   LUG 1. 1. House with Pilasters. On the rectangle surrounding the word &amp;#34;Garden?&amp;#34; in the upper left corner is the &amp;#34;House with Pilasters.&amp;#34; Source, Maison 1996, p.134.   Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  E. Delaval, “Un îlot d’habitations romaines à Lyon (Ier siècle av.-IIIe siècle ap.J.C.),Clos du Verbe Incarné,colline de Fourvière,” Actes du Ier Congrès Méditerranéen d’ethnologie historique, Lisbonne 4-8 nov. 1991,in Mediterraneo, 4, 1994, p.203-229. E. Delaval,“Espace urbain et habitat privé à Lyon,un îlot de la ville haute au cœur d’une opération d’urbanisme au milieu du Ier siècle,” in Maison 1996, t.I,p. 128-37, planp.134.  Pleiades ID 167717
TGN ID 6002234
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 08 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
