<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gallia on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/categories/gallia/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Gallia on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/categories/gallia/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Vaise - House with the Xenia</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/vaise-house_with_the_xenia/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/vaise-house_with_the_xenia/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location LUGDUNUM (Lyon, France)
LUGDUNUM (Pleiades)
Garden House with Pilasters (Clos du Verbe Incarné)
Keywords  domus porticoes courtyard drain  Garden Description Xenia were gifts of game, fish, poultry, fruits or vegetables given by a host to a guest to be cooked to the guest’s liking. Here, the name comes from the discovery of a pinax (a painted ceramic tablet) showing xenia. This house was discovered during excavation of the southern sector of the Saint-Pierre land management zone (ZAC) in a suburban quarter of Lyon. The building –one hesitates whether to call it a suburban villa or a domus–extends over 630 square meters. There are traces of occupation of the site in Augustan times, but the house (29 x 24 m) was built in the reign of Tiberius. It is organized in two perpendicular wings around a courtyard with porticos in a U. The galleries are 3.5 meters wide. In this first phase, nine rooms were placed around the court.
The limit of the court on the west is not certain [phase II, 1]. As a hypothesis, an original court of 17.74 meters by 16.40 meters –nearly square but with an extra, sixth, span on the west –has been proposed. The columns, with a maximum diameter of 37 centimeters, were made of semi-circular bricks cemented and covered with white plaster. They rested on limestone bases roughly squared off. A little later, around the end of the reign of Claudius, the house underwent several changes. Room [10] was built, which enlarged the eastern wing. A new room [3] was created, important enough in the eyes of the proprietor to sacrifice part of one of the porticos to fit it in. In the same period, the spaces between the columns were partly closed, while the courtyard was connected to a water supply network. The paintings were freshened up, and the house doubtless had a second floor. In this last phase, however, the house did not last long. It was destroyed at the beginning of the reign of Vespasian, and the site then remained vacant at least until the middle of the fourth century and probably into the fifth. In this final, Claudian phase, the courtyard represented more than 57 percent of the area. It enjoyed running water, which was not present in the houses of the Verbe incarnéquarter in Lugdunumat the same period. A wooden pipe, of which only the negative imprint can be seen, crossed the courtyard and porticos obliquely. A drain from room [5] was connected to it. The basin of a fountain that has disappeared was placed on the axis of room [9]; it was definitely there in the second phase and possibly in the first, though that has not been demonstrated.
The ground of the central part of the courtyard was topsoil and earth coming from under the porticos. Three samples have been studied palynolocially. The results leave no doubt that a garden grew in the center. We quote the abstract of the publication. “The pollen content is relatively poor, and the counts have been made for each sample separately. The spectrum of pollens includes a rather wide diversity of herbaceous plants of which certain families can include ornamental plants such as the tubuliflorous composites and the Caryophyllaceae (pink family). Ruderal plants, that is, those that grow in sites much transformed by man such as clearings or waste places near habitations, predominate: Chenopodiaceae (such as spinach, beets and their relatives –Tr.), gramineous plants, and the following genera: nettles, arnois (artemesia, tarragon –Tr.), and plantain (Plantago lanceolata). This last is often associated with the cultivation of cereals. There were also species of ferns. Walnuts (Juglans) and grapes (Vitis) may have been cultivated around the site. Finally, pine (Pinus) is relatively well represented, but the very high rate of pollenization of the pine and its capacity for dispersion of its pollens often lead to an over-representation of these species. Thus, this courtyard could have been cultivated as an ornamental garden.” (E. Delaval et al., p. 89).
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  E. Delaval, C. Bellon, J. Chastel, E. Plassot, L. Tranoy, Vaise, un quartier de Lyon antique, Document d’archéologie en Rhône-Alpes n° 5, Lyon, 1995. E. Plassot, Le quartier Saint-Pierre, la maison aux xenia, p. 71-129. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 167717
TGN ID 6003548
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 04 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House on rue de la Fraternité</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/house_on_rue_de_la_fraternite%CC%81/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/house_on_rue_de_la_fraternite%CC%81/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location NEMETACUM (Arras, France)
NEMETACUM (Pleiades)
Garden House on rue de la Fraternité
Keywords  mosiacs peristyles  Garden Description Excavated in 1875-79 in the eastern suburbs of the city by A. Ternick, this large house has been uncovered in a roughly elliptical area with axes of 40 and 20 meters. The chronology is uncertain. It was perhaps destroyed by a violent fire (of which there are traces elsewhere in the city) in the second century and not reconstructed. Some walls were decoratively painted; most floors were concrete, but there is some evidence of mosaics. The floor of room [5] (just below room [1] in the plan) had a large slab of black marble in the center in frame with smaller slabs in the corners. The southwest corner of a peristyle and 12 meters along the west side and 10 meters along the south side have been excavated. The galleries had concrete floors and slender Tuscan columns 20 centimeters in diameter and 1.2 meters apart. The walls were painted red. In the center of the peristyle court was a masonry construction considered as an “impluvium” at the time of excavation, but it was quite possibly a pool. If it were a pool, then the area was almost surely in a garden. The house had another interior open court and possible garden [17] of about 6 x 7 meters near a well [25].
Maps    Arras (Pas de Calais), France. Excavations on the House on rue de la Fraternité. 1875-1879.   Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Alain Jacques, Georges Jelski, “Arras antique, bilan et perspective” in Les villes de la Gaule Belgique au Haut-Empire, Actes du colloque tenu à Saint-Riquier (somme) le 22-23-24 octobre 1982, Revue achéologique de Picardie, p. 124-5. (worldcat) Delmaire et al., Le Nord-Pas- de-Calais, 62/1, CAG, p. 145-147, fig. 46, plan p. 145; H. Stern I, 1 p. 101-102.   Pleiades ID 109194
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The House aux Fleurons (boulevard de la Paix)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/the_house_aux_fleurons_boulevard_de_la_paix/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_belgica/the_house_aux_fleurons_boulevard_de_la_paix/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location DUROCORTORUM (Reims, France)
DUROCORTORUM (Pleiades)
Garden The House aux Fleurons (boulevard de la Paix)
Keywords  porticos trench  Garden Description BEL 2.2.1: Reims, House aux Flerurons Along the north side runs a secondary street following the orientation of the town in Augustan times. Along this street, in the northern part of the house, a series of rooms with mosaics were found. On the south side, the space A (about 30 x 14 m) was probably a garden. The central part, surrounded on three sides by porticos, had two wide trenches (a) cut into the chalk and filled with clay, a strong indication of a garden. The trenches seem to be connected on the south side, and the south wall seems to be the limit of the parcel.
Maps None Available
Plans None Available
Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Ch. Loriquet, La mosaïque des Promenades et autres trouvées à Reims, Reims, 1862 (worldcat) D.R.A.H..A., La Bourse du Travail à Reims, Bulletin de la société archéologique champenoise, n°4, 1977, p. 77-79  R. Neiss, La structure urbaine de Reims antique et son évolution du Ier au IIIe siècle après J.-C. Les villes de la Gaule Belgique au Haut-Empire, in: Actes du colloque tenu à Saint-Riquier (Somme). Revue archéologique de Picardie, n°3-4, 1984, p. 171-191, (worldcat) A. Balmelle, R. Neiss, Les maisons de l’élite à Durocortorum, in Archéologie urbaine à Reims, Bulletin de la société archéologique champenoise, t. 96, 2003, 4, p. 74. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108945
TGN ID 6000727
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House on the Place des Halles (La maison des Halles)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/house_on_the_place_des_halles_la_maison_des_halles/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/house_on_the_place_des_halles_la_maison_des_halles/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location &amp;ndash; missing in Pleiades &amp;ndash; VINDINUM a.k.a. Subdinnum (Le Mans, France)
VINDINUM a.k.a. Subdinnum (Pleiades)
&amp;lt;## Sublocation&amp;ndash;&amp;gt;
Sublocation Description On the left bank of the Sarthe, where it is joined by the Isaac creek, the Roman town was the successor to a Celtic oppidum. A wall of the late empire enclosed nine hectares.
Garden House on the Place des Halles (La maison des Halles)
Keywords  domus courtyard  Garden Description LUG 6.1.1: Le Mans. House on the Place des Halles. From CAG.
This domus was on the Place des Halles, the former site of the covered market place. It was excavated in 1987-88 south of the principal street. In a part of the ancient city inhabited since the first century, the house occupied a surface (33 x 54 m) of 1782 square meters. Two-story wings of the house surround on three sides a courtyard [1] that may have been a garden. The residential wing, to the south, of careful construction, had four principal rooms with floors of smooth concrete. The existence of a second court farther south, on the other façade of the residential wing has been supposed, but its nature is unknown.
Maps Plans   Restored section of the entire domus by P. André   Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Service Régional de l’Archéologie des Pays de la Loire, La Sarthe, 72, CAG p. 318-319, plan p. 318. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 109236
TGN ID 6003548
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 21 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House on the rue de la Harpe ( *Domus* rue de la Harpe)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/house_on_the_rue_de_la_harpe_domus_rue_de_la_harpe/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/house_on_the_rue_de_la_harpe_domus_rue_de_la_harpe/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location MEDIOLANUM AULERCORUM (Evreux, France)
MEDIOLANUM AULERCORUM (Pleiades)
Garden House on the Place des Halles (La maison des Halles)
Keywords  Domus peristyles porticos fountain courtyards  Garden Description Excavations of a 1400 square meter site in 1989 at 45 rue de la Harpe partially uncovered five habitations of the southern quarter of the city. They were occupied between the first and third century until a final destruction around 275 – 280. Among them, one had a peristyle [1] of which three porticos are know; it was quite likely planted. The same house had another paved court with a fountain [2]. Further south, the corner of another courtyard with porticos (4 x 3 columns) was found.
Maps None Available
Plans   Reconstruction of the four house spaces that make up House on the Rue de la Harpe.   Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  D. CLIQUET, L’Eure, 27, CAG p.136-137, restitution p.136. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 109153
TGN ID 6002234
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 21 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>*Domus* of the Place Epars</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/domus_of_the_place_des_epars/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/domus_of_the_place_des_epars/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location AUTRICUM (Chartres, France)
AUTRICUM (Pleiades)
Garden Domus of the Place Epars
Keywords  domus hypocaust  Garden Description A large reception room of 73 square meters in the northwest corner was heated by a hypocaust under the floor. In this room was a grand composition depicting a procession of people. Next to this room was a square room that looked out down the long axis of the garden that filled the 247 square meter rectangular (19 x 13 m) rectangle of open area. The Corinthian colonnade of the garden was found collapsed towards the outside. Elegant Corinthian capitals of limestone and fragments of column bases of attic type with traces of tinted whitewash and red accents were found during the excavations.
Maps None Available
Plans   LUG_Fig. 1: Chartres, Domus of the Place des Epars, from CAG.   Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  :A. Ollagnier, D. Joly, L’Eure-et-Loir, CAG p. 137-139, plan p. 138 (with bibliography of previous works). (worldcat)   Pleiades ID 167717
TGN ID 6003548
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 16 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Masks (Maison aux Masques)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/house_of_the_masks_maison_aux_masques/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/house_of_the_masks_maison_aux_masques/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location LUGDUNUM (Lyon, France)
LUGDUNUM (Pleiades)
Garden House of the Masks (Maison aux Masques)
Keywords  peristyle opus stigninumboth porticoes stylobate plynth pilasters  Garden Description The two known wings of the house were organized around a peristyle (8x 12 m), probably in a U, though the west wall has not been found but has been drawn on the accompanying plan by extension of wall further south. Two of the three galleries were open. The open area of the peristyle court was ornamented by a rectangular pool (5.4 x 2.6 m) covered with opus signinumboth inside and outside; it had a drain in the northeast corner. The surface of the water in the pool would have been above the level of pounded earth floor of the courtyard. Porticoes 2.8 meters wide around three sides of the courtyard also had pounded earth floors; the stylobate was blocks of limestone while the columns were of circular brick covered with plaster painted red in the lower part, white in the upper, and touched with green highlights. The porticoes were terminated at the west end by engaged columns. The painted plaster is preserved in place in the southwest corner of the peristyle. A red plinth sets off tuffs of green foliage; above are black panels bordered with decorative strings. At a later phase, a wall was built between the last two columns of the of the portico; in the space thus created were found bases for shelves. Near the peristyle were found little theatrical masks in terra cotta which had served as oscilla. An ostrich egg, an exotic import, was perhaps also hung in the peristyle. Onto the south portico opened a reception room [B 20] (8.6 x 6.2 m) rhythmically divided by four pilasters and two columns. Onto the east portico opened an even larger room [B 12] (10.5 x 6.5 m). Both reception rooms had concrete floors with limestone accents. There were also two small courtyards &amp;ndash;one in the south wing, one in the east &amp;ndash;both indicated on the plan.
Maps Not Available
Plans Not Available
Images   perspective drawing of porticoes   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  A. Desbat, Les fouilles de la rue des Farges à Lyon, Groupe lyonnais de recherche en archéologie gallo-romaine, Lyon, 1984, p. 45-49 (worldcat) A. Desbat, Jadis, rue des Farges, archéologie d’un quartier de Lyon antique, exposition au Musée de la Civilisation Gallo-Romaine de Lyon, 1985. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 167717
TGN ID 6003548
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 16 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Richebourg (Yvelines) villa de</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/richebourg_yvelines_villa_de/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/richebourg_yvelines_villa_de/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location AUTRICUM (Chartres, France)
AUTRICUM (Pleiades)
Garden Richebourg (Yvelines) villa de
Keywords  portico trellises stylobate amphorae pergola apse cistern triclinium  Garden Description Though the site has an area of 12 or 13 hectares, only one hectare has been excavated, the residential and agricultural part. Two groups of buildings frame a large garden on a slightly trapezoidal, walled area. To the north was the residence; to the south, the utility buildings, including a silo; while to the east, within its own walls, was the farmyard also with several buildings.
The pars urbana at the north end opened towards the south on a large space [1] developed as a garden. The southern façade was a portico stretching between rooms extending forward from either end of the main house. Along this façade [2], excavations have shown a band of gravel on a masonry base bordered by posts. Perhaps these posts supported a trellis along this façade. Against the stylobate of the portico, several bases of amphorae were discovered, doubtless as pots for plants that perhaps climbed on the trellis. A fragment of a white marble disk could be, according to Y. Barat, the only remains of an oscillum that once hung in the gallery.
The garden was divided into quadrants by two perpendicular roads, once paved with stone, though the stones were long ago carried off. The east-west road divides the garden into two equal parts; it starts in the west from a square entrance porch outside the wall not shown on the plan, then passes through a simple door pierced in the wall and framed by two vertical wooden braces. The other road [4] crosses the garden on the central axis of the residential part in the north, connecting the entry of its southern gallery to the utility building at the southern end of the garden. Symmetrically placed postholes on either side of these two roads indicate perhaps the presence of a pergola or bower. A stone basin was found at the intersection of these two roads. Along the west enclosing wall, other postholes with wedging material may indicate two other pergolas.
These roads mark off four plots of garden land. Dark brown layers indicate that they once received regular manuring and additions of wood ash, fragments of ceramic, shells of oysters and mussels, and pulverized mortar. The plan of the plots is marked out by an orthogonal network of horticultural pots, installed at intervals of 4 meters in each direction. Of the 217 of these pots found, more than 100 were in place. Aside from several bottoms of amphorae, the pots were of the classic flowerpot type, a truncated cone, and they all had a hole and in the bottom and three in the side, near the bottom. A single example had four of these lateral holes. There were five different types all with a top diameter of 8 to 12 centimeters and 9 to 13 centimeters high.
The distribution of each size pot has been carefully analyzed. Barat reports that two of the types were used in a consistent way. Type C, dated at the end of Antonine or beginning of the Severine period, was used only in the northern half of the garden. Type E, dated from the Claudian period, was found only along the post holes of the presumed pergola and would have been for climbing plants such as roses or ivy. (Only these two types could be dated with relative certainty.) In several cases, Barat felt that a grouping of two or three types of pots might simply indicate planting at different times in the same place.
On its northern side, the villa had another façade gallery [6], perhaps an ambulation, opening onto the fields. It was almost 44 meters long and has Tuscan and Corinthian columns. To the west, it was terminated by an apse; and to the east, by a cistern. Baths [7] were installed in the east wing. Next to the house, south of the baths, were several flagstones covered by a layer of garden soil, perhaps marking a flowerbed [8] over a drainage bed composed of fragments of tiles. To the south, six pits [9], 20 to 40 centimeters in diameter and 20 centimeters deep, not in the pattern of the other pots, were filled with an ochre-colored silt. Finally, north of the baths, protected by the extension of the gallery of the north façade, was found a group of five little negative casts of stumps, still with traces of the roots.
Near the southwest corner of the villa, a stone masonry slab [5] of irregular plan but generally U shaped is considered a possible open-air triclinium. It was later damaged by the erection of a building held up by posts.
Pollen analyses have yielded some results, although the pollens were damaged and oxidized by the dry environment. Samples of garden soil were both from the pots and from outside them. Several of the species identified, such as plantain, argue for a mown lawn. The tree species indicate the presence of conifers – cedars, larches and spruces (cedrus, larix, picea). An oleaceae (determined by D. Marguerie) poses problems of interpretation. Was it a lilac or an olive? In either case, it is an imported species. The lilac would come from the northeast of the Balkans; the olive, from the Mediterranean. Though the lilac might seem more probable on the basis of current plantings, it is noteworthy that Pliny reports that the olive was acclimated in central Gaul (H.N. V 1-2, XVII, 47-48). The genus Prunus appeared several times, thus confirming the results of charcoal analysis (anthracology) but without determination of the species – wild cherry or domestic cherry. Ivy is also present, perhaps to cover the pergolas.
Maps None Available
Plans   Plan 1: Fig 4 - Plan of the Athenian Gardens of Richebourg   Images   Plan 1: Bird&amp;#39;s Eye Perspective of the Garden   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Y. Barat, La villa gallo-romaine de Richebourg (Yvelines) in Revue Archéologique du Centre de la France, 38, 1999, p. 117-67, plans p. 122, jardin p.140. (worldcat) Y Barat, D. Morize, Les pots d’horticulture dans le monde antique et les jardins de la villa de Richebourg (Yvelines), in SFECAG, Actes du colloque de Fribourg, 1999, p. 213-36.  Y. Barat, La recherche archéologique des jardins antiques in Les nouvelles de l’archéologie 83-84, 2001, p. 56-62, not. P. 58-59.  G. Coulon, J.C. Golvin, Voyage en Gaule romaine, Actes sud Errance, Arles-Paris, 2002, p.121-3, restitution p. 122-3. (worldcat) Y. Barat and D. Morize, L’archéologie des jardins antiques: le cas de la pars urbana de la villa de Richebourg (Yvelines) in Actualité de la Recherche en Histoire et Archéologie agraires, Annales Littéraires de L’Université de Franche-Comté, 764, Besançon, 2003. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 167717
TGN ID 6002234
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 16 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House with Pilasters (Clos du Verbe Incarné)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/house-with-pilasters-clos-du-verbe-incarne%CC%81/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_lugdunensis/house-with-pilasters-clos-du-verbe-incarne%CC%81/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia
Location LUGDUNUM (Lyon, France)
LUGDUNUM (Pleiades)
Garden House with Pilasters (Clos du Verbe Incarné)
Keywords  insula / insulae atrium Domus  Garden Description The insula VII of the Clos du Verbe Incarné, excavated from 1977 to 1987, lies on the western slope of a little dip (71 x 34 m) in the upper town, about 160 meters northwest of the center of the top of the theater. In this insula, begun between 40 and 20 BC, one can follow the evolution of this quarter up to the end of the third century. To the north, the insula was bordered by the street called du Capitol and to the west by the street called de Cybèle. The subdivision of the insula was put in place from 15–10 BC. The house occupied 400 square meters, and was organized on an italic plan around a traditional atrium followed by a tablinum[1]. The house of seven or eight rooms did not have a peristyle but did, no doubt, include a hortus[2] (15 x 5 m) at the back of the lot.
The house was originally constructed of adobe on a floor and gutter of granite masonry. Later, in Tibero-Claudian times, a wooden section was added, which facilitated the creation of an upper story on the western part, which also included on the ground level some isolated shops occupying 100 square meters. The neighbor to the north was another small, 315-square-meter house, the Domus with the Mosaic Emblema, which was organized around a four-column atrium, but had no garden. In fact, the House with Pilasters was the only one in the insula to have, without doubt, a little green space. In the southern part of the insula, there were three combinations of house and shop, and another small, 310-square-meter house called the Domus with Lararium.
LUG 1. 1. House with Pilasters. On the rectangle surrounding the word &amp;ldquo;Garden?&amp;rdquo; in the upper left corner is the &amp;ldquo;House with Pilasters.&amp;rdquo; Source, Maison 1996, p.134.
Plans   LUG 1. 1. House with Pilasters. On the rectangle surrounding the word &amp;#34;Garden?&amp;#34; in the upper left corner is the &amp;#34;House with Pilasters.&amp;#34; Source, Maison 1996, p.134.   Images None Available
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  E. Delaval, “Un îlot d’habitations romaines à Lyon (Ier siècle av.-IIIe siècle ap.J.C.),Clos du Verbe Incarné,colline de Fourvière,” Actes du Ier Congrès Méditerranéen d’ethnologie historique, Lisbonne 4-8 nov. 1991,in Mediterraneo, 4, 1994, p.203-229. E. Delaval,“Espace urbain et habitat privé à Lyon,un îlot de la ville haute au cœur d’une opération d’urbanisme au milieu du Ier siècle,” in Maison 1996, t.I,p. 128-37, planp.134.  Pleiades ID 167717
TGN ID 6002234
Contributor AUTHOR_ID (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 15 November 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa at the Pont d’Oly, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/jurancon_pyr%C3%A9n%C3%A9es-atlantiques/gallia_villa-at-the-pont-doly_yji/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 12:39:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/jurancon_pyr%C3%A9n%C3%A9es-atlantiques/gallia_villa-at-the-pont-doly_yji/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania
Province Description&amp;ndash;&amp;gt; A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location JURANCON
(Pleiades)
House Villa at the Pont d’Oly
House Description This luxurious villa of late antiquity is most remarkable for having been built on either side of a sizable stream, the Néez, which rises in the Pyrenees and flows into to the Gave on its left bank. This unique feature, however, proved the villa’s undoing, for the Néez changed its course and swept away a large part of the residential sector of the villa on its right (east) bank. The site has been known since 1770 and was excavated and mapped in the nineteenth century. A large area on the left bank was uncovered between 1850 and 1853 by a young English tourist, S. Baring Gould. Because of work on the bed of the Néez, there were salvage excavations on the right bank site in 1989-90 by G. Fabre and R. Monturet, but the results remain largely unpublished.
Garden Courtyard Garden
Keywords  archaeological garden porticos luxurious villa pavilions baths  Garden Description Each building covered about 2000 square meters with an elongated rectangular plan, and the two faced one another across the stream. The parallel long axes of the two buildings run to the north-northeast, but in this description we will take this direction as north. Each building had a portico façade parallel to stream. In the better preserved residential building on the west bank, this portico was about 30 meters long, had six columns, and was closed off at the north and south by roughly square pavilions. The scant remains of the building on the right (east) bank are consistent with the idea that each façade would have seemed to reflect the other. From the rear of the east bank building one looked out to the east onto a large semicircular courtyard. The courtyard was enclosed by a gallery running in a semicircle drawn with a radius of about ten meters and its center in the middle of the back wall of the building. Nothing is known of what was in the courtyard – indeed, half of it and the central portion of this house were completely carried away by the Néez. It would, however, have been a natural place for a garden beautifully visible from the central room of the house. Beyond this semicircle, further to the east, there was a vast rectangular space organized in a U [XIII – XIV]. Again, nothing is known of what was in its open area but a garden is certainly a possibility. The baths, the best known part of the structure, were connected to the house on the west bank.
Plans   Jurancon, Pont d&amp;#39;Oly. Plan of the building on the left bank of the neez by Laffolye in 1870. cl. Photographic archives of historical monuments     Plan supposes of the whole villa by R. Mounturet, after the 1989-91 excavations   Dates Unspecified
Excavation Dates 19th Century
Bibliography  Ch. Le Cœur, Notice sur les mosaïques de Jurançon (Basses-Pyrénées), Bull. du Comité de la Langue, de l’Histoire et des Arts de la France, 1853-54, n°2, p. 378-386 (worldcat) Gallia informations 1, 1991, p. 105-106 (worldcat) G. Fabre, Bilan scientifique, Aquitaine, 1991, p. 110 G. Fabre, Carte archéologique de la Gaule, (64) Pyrénées-Atlantiques, 1994, p. 213-214 worldcat Catherine Balmelle, Les demeures aristocratiques d&amp;rsquo;Aquitaine, societe et culture de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquite tardive dans le sou-ouest de la Gaule, Ausonius, supple. d&amp;rsquo;Aquitania 10, Bordeaux 2001, p. 354-357, plan p. 452. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 249927
TGN ID []()
Contributor Clopper Almon (https://www.econ.umd.edu/facultyprofile/almon/clopper)
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa de Bapteste, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/moncrabeau_lot-et-garonne/gallia_villa_de_bapteste_yji/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 12:39:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/moncrabeau_lot-et-garonne/gallia_villa_de_bapteste_yji/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania
Province Description&amp;ndash;&amp;gt; A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location MONCRABEAU
(Pleiades)
House Villa de Bapteste
House Description The excavations of A. Faugères du Bourg and H. Teulières between 1871 and 1873 revealed a luxurious villa with nearly fifty rooms, twenty-five of them with mosaics and covered with marble. Immediately after the excavation it was reburied and, except for two rooms under roofs, returned to agricultural use. This use accounts for its present poor state of conservation. Sample checks between after 1990 led to urgent salvage operations by Ph. Jacques in 1995. He was able to determine five phase successive phases of construction.
Garden Peristyle Garden
Keywords  archaeological garden luxurious villa mosaic cour d’honneur porticos vestibules gutters (building drainage components) tegulae colonnade aqueduct footbridge socle  Garden Description The first phase was a villa of the second half of the first century with a façade gallery with two wings extending behind the front. It went through two more phases in the second century and was then completely rebuilt (phase 4) in the fourth century around a vast peristyle. A series of embellishments in late antiquity (phase 5) included creation of a cour d’honneur [Q] on the southeast and the addition on the north corner of an octagonal room extending to the northwest and continuing into a tri-lobed room thought to be a reception room by some, though others think it was related to baths. The cour d’honneur [Q] with porticoes in a U had three entrances, one on the axis and two others on the sides. Nothing is known of how the inside of the court was arranged. Off to the south went a gallery which connected the villa to a separate group of buildings, possibly baths. On entering from the cour d’honneur, and passing through the vestibule in the form of two rooms, one after another, one entered a very large, almost square peristyle more than forty meters on a side. It was bordered by a gutter of tegulae to catch the drip from the roofs. The nineteenth century excavations found “a stuccoed pool in the form of a bath tub” with its lead pipe feed still in place. It may have served as an ornament of the peristyle court, but we do not know exactly where it was.
Along the northeast side of the villa ran a portico (50 x 5 m) entirely covered with mosaics. At either end there was a large reception room; and in the center, a passageway to the peristyle. The gallery with its colonnade was thus a belvedere for enjoying a panorama over the countryside. Along this façade ran a trench to carry off rainwater. In the words of the early excavator, “an aqueduct follows the façade and the little sewers where the water from the roof ran off are still in place. Two little footbridges of brick [U] cross them and doubtless brought the dwelling into communication with the gardens.”
The reception room [M] at the northwest extremity of the gallery had in its first third a pool lined with marble (1 x 0.2 m) connected to the gutter that runs along the northeast wing. Two wells of careful and identical form with a polygonal socle are noted [S]. The first, 1.3 meters in diameter, was 8 meters in front of the northeast façade; the other, also outside the house was near the southeast façade. In the first plan published, the first of these was shown on the axis of the passage between the gallery and the peristyle. A channel connects it with the one channel along the front of the house.
Plans   Watercolor by H. Teulieres 1872-1874 (lithograph, A. Blakchet fonds)   Dates second half of the first century CE
Excavation Dates 1871 to 1873
Bibliography  Faugère du Bourg, “Mémoire sur les fouilles de Bapteste” in Actes du Congrès archéologiques de France, Agen et Toulouse, 1874, p. 38-56 (worldcat) E. Morvillez, Forme et évolution des salles de réception des grandes demeures tardives du bassin méditerranéen occidental (IVème-Vième siècle), 1993, t. 1, p. 117-22 worldcat B. Fages, Carte archéologique de la Gaule, Lot-et-Garonne (47), Paris 1995, p.246-49 worldcat Catherine Balmelle, Les demeures aristocratiques d&amp;rsquo;Aquitaine, societe et culture de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquite tardive dans le sou-ouest de la Gaule, Ausonius, supple. d&amp;rsquo;Aquitania 10, Bordeaux 2001, p. 104, 129, 147-148, 371-74, 446. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 249930
TGN ID []()
Contributor Clopper Almon (https://www.econ.umd.edu/facultyprofile/almon/clopper)
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa de l&#39;Arribèra deus Gleisiars, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/lalonquette_pyr%C3%A9n%C3%A9es-atlantiques/gallia_villa_de_larribe%CC%80ra_deus_gleisiars__yji/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 12:39:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/lalonquette_pyr%C3%A9n%C3%A9es-atlantiques/gallia_villa_de_larribe%CC%80ra_deus_gleisiars__yji/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania
Province Description&amp;ndash;&amp;gt; A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location LALONQUETTE
(Pleiades)
House Villa de l&amp;rsquo;Arribèra deus Gleisiars 
House Description The villa was first noted in 1843, then partially explored at the end of nineteenth century, and then extensively excavated by J. Lauffray from 1959 to 1970 but only partly published. Specific researches have been conducted since 1988. Four principal phases of occupation have been revealed between the early empire and the end of antiquity.
Garden ?
Keywords  basins (vessels) terra cotta apse belvedere courtyard mosaic pool [masonry](not sure which one) esplanade  Garden Description In the first phase built in the late first or early second century, there were, to judge from published plans, agricultural buildings raying out from an open courtyard with a circular pool. These structures were not turned towards the Gabas (F. Réchin, 1995).
The villa built later in the second century, the second phase, faced the Gabas to the east. Back of a monumental vestibule with a semicircular portico curving towards the Gabas [XVII] the rooms and the baths were arranged around an irregular peristyle [II] that may have had a garden in the center. The little pool is now almost in the center. Several reception rooms open onto the porticoes, among them a room with a semicircular apse [XII] and the room [XXII] which opens through a semicircular portico towards the Gabas.
The villa of late antiquity is the best known and provides the third and fourth phases. In the fourth century, perhaps in the time of Constantine, the previous constructions were leveled and a new villa built keeping the same orientation and the same placement of the peristyle but using a different construction technique. In front of the villa, there extended to the south a large rectangular court closed by a wall across the south end. It may well have been planted as a garden. The form of the formal vestibule is modified. The peristyle (25 x 21 m) is regularized with four identical porticoes with terra cotta columns.
The open area (17 x 12.6 m) was undoubtedly planted. It was bordered by gutter of terra cotta to catch the water from the roofs. In the center, a little structure with a roof supported by four pillars covered the circular pool, still preserved from the first house. The reception rooms were transformed. Where the former room with a semicircular apse [XII] had been, a new, heated room was constructed with a polygonal apse. The east wing is entirely different. Room [XXII] lost its portico with an apse on the outside and was instead given an alcove to the south. A façade overlooking the river was formed by a gallery (25 x 4.8 m with apses at either end) running north-south, parallel to the river. A series of large rectangular rooms opened onto the peristyle on their west side and onto this gallery to their east sides. The gallery was originally connected to a passageway descending in a hairpin turn towards the shore. This belvedere structure suggests that the area between the house and the river would have been carefully planted and tended.In a fourth and final phase, from the end of the fourth or early fifth century, following a fire in the baths and neighboring rooms, the villa was restored and transformed. The courtyard in front of the villa on the south was kept, though nothing is known of its organization. The galleries of the peristyle were repaved with mosaics. The central pool and its cover seem to have been eliminated. Numerous rooms were added, others were re-decorated, and others lost their heating. The apses at either end of the belvedere overlooking the river were surrounded on the outside by masonry masses, but the colonnade was eliminated and a gently sloping esplanade offered a view of the Gabas.
Dates First phase: late first or early second century; second phase: second century; third and fourth phases: late antiquity.
Excavation Dates 1959-1970
Bibliography  Gallia, XIX, 1961,p. 396-398; XXI, 1963, p. 535-536; XXVII, 1969, p. 376-379; XXIX, 1971, p. 362-364 (worldcat) J. Lauffray J. J. Schreyeck, N. Dupré, “Les établissements et les villas gallo-romaines de Lalonquette (Pyrénées-Atlantiques)” in Gallia 31.1, 1973, p. 123-155 (worldcat) E. Morvillez, Forme et évolution des salles de réception des grandes demeures tardives du bassin méditerranéen occidental (IVème-Vième siècle), 1993, t. 1, p. 134-142 worldcat F. Réchin, Bilan scientifique de la région Aquitaine (Service Régional de l’Archéologie), 1994, 112-113, 1995, p. 103-104 (worldcat) R. Compatangelo, R. Plana Mallart, Bilan scientifique de la région Aquitaine (Service Régional de l’Archéologie), 1997, p. 113-114 ; (worldcat) Catherine Balmelle, Les demeures aristocratiques d&amp;rsquo;Aquitaine, societe et culture de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquite tardive dans le sou-ouest de la Gaule, Ausonius, supple. d&amp;rsquo;Aquitania 10, Bordeaux 2001, p. 99-103, 128-129, 131-133, 359-362, 445. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 249924
TGN ID []()
Contributor Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa of Géou, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/labastide-darmagnac_landes/gallia_villa_of_ge%CC%81ou_yji/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 12:39:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/labastide-darmagnac_landes/gallia_villa_of_ge%CC%81ou_yji/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania
Province Description&amp;ndash;&amp;gt; A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location LABASTIDE-D’ARMAGNAC
(Pleiades)
House Villa of Géou
House Description Situated two kilometers southeast of the town, at a place called Géou, this villa sits on a little plateau overlooking the Douze. It has been known since the middle of the nineteenth century and was excavated between 1970 and 1978.
Garden Courtyard
Keywords  archaeological garden mosaic peristyles (Roman courtyards) pool [masonry](not sure which one)  Garden Description From the first phase of occupation in the early empire there remain only the foundations of a villa rustica. In late antiquity, the villa was totally remodeled. In the new phase, it had an ample, slightly trapezoidal peristyle (44 x 34 m) with a large (7.4 m diameter) pool. This courtyard was presumably planted as a garden. The floors of the porticoes of the peristyle bore polychrome mosaics. Along the southeast and southwest sides of the peristyle stretched the rooms for daily life. The reception room (7.5 x 8.75 m) opened off the middle of the southeast portico. Because the peristyle was trapezoidal – leaning to the right as seen from the reception room – the pool had to be off center to the left in the courtyard to be fully enjoyed from this room. Two symmetric, rectangular masonry masses extend outward from the wall of pool.
Plans   Labastide-d&amp;#39;Armagnac. Plan of Villa of Géou （cat. N.22)   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates 1970-1978
Bibliography  .-P. Bost et al., “La villa gallo-romaine de Géou à Labastide-d’Armagnac (Landes)” Bull.de la société de Borda (Dax), 1984, p. 651-703 (with an unfolding plan by R. Monturet) (worldcat) B. Boyrie-Fénié, Carte archéologique de la Gaule, Les Landes(40), 1994, p. 96-99, n°131 worldcat Catherine Balmelle, Les demeures aristocratiques d&amp;rsquo;Aquitaine, societe et culture de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquite tardive dans le sou-ouest de la Gaule, Ausonius, supple. d&amp;rsquo;Aquitania 10, Bordeaux 2001, p.357-359, plan p. 449. For the pool see, Gallia J. Coupry, 19, 1961, p. 392, 21, 1963, p. 529-30 ; 29 ; 1971 p. 356 ; 33, 1975, p. 483, 35, 1977, p. 465 ; 37, 1979, p. 514. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 249913
TGN ID []()
Contributor Clopper Almon (https://www.econ.umd.edu/facultyprofile/almon/clopper)
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa of Lassalles, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/montmaurin_haute-garonne/gallia_villa_of_lassalles_yji/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 12:39:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/montmaurin_haute-garonne/gallia_villa_of_lassalles_yji/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania
Province Description&amp;ndash;&amp;gt; A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location Montmaurin
(Pleiades)
House Villa of Lassalles
House Descriptions The site was noted in 1864 and was the subject of archaeological research by Abbot Couret between 1879 and 1882. The first systematic excavations began in 1947 and continued under the direction of Georges Fouet until 1960. The very complete publication, based on the state of knowledge at the time, made this villa one of the “celebrities” of Gaul and indeed of the western empire.
The villa of late antiquity was built on earlier structures going back to the middle of the first century. The plan of this early phase proposed by Fouet was made on the basis of probes and remains very hypothetical; it cannot be analyzed with any certainty. Gardens were quite possibly part of this vast pars urbana of the early empire, especially given its size and connection with agricultural structures.
According to Fouet, after a period of abandon between 285 and 325, there followed two phases of work, the first in the time of Constantine and the second around the middle of the fourth century. This second phase, following a fire, saw some transformations in the villa and the creation of the rooms at the northeastern end. The last major phase of construction was thus superimposed on preceding buildings while keeping their orientation and a large part of their lines and proportions. The agricultural buildings, however, do not seem to have been used in the late period. Note that, in this chronology proposed by Fouet, the villa reached its final phase around the year 350.
And then, with the progress of archaeological science, this chronology came to be much discussed. By the mid 1990’s, it was generally agreed that the history of the site had to be revisited and that only by a careful re-evaluation of the old excavations and by the establishment of a precise plan of archaeological work could a whole series of questions be answered about a residence often cited for comparison,but in the end, it itself is not sufficiently well known. The general result of this work has been to recognize that the date given by Fouet for the second phase of the villa as “about 350” is considerably too early; an early fifth century date would be more plausible.
Garden Forecourt garden; courtyard
Keywords  archaeological garden pavilion forecourt peristyles (Roman courtyards) stylobate porticos paleosol glass paste planter pilaster trellis revetment water ladder pergola fountains vestibules garden ornaments statues statuettes (free-standing sculpture)  Garden Description The villa’s main axis runs southwest to northeast; but to avoid complex directions, we will rotate the compass rose and refer to northeast as “east”, the northwest as “north” and so on. In these terms, the main axis of the villa runs from west to east. The domain of the presently visible villa extends over 18 hectares, the area defined by the walls along the north and west and by the river on the south. The monumental façade along the west side runs 117 meters, while from the front gate on the west side to the tip of the final aspe on the east is 126 meters, for a squared-off “footprint” of nearly 15,000 square meters for the main structure. The main part of the villa of late antiquity was organized with a quite symmetrically around the west-to-east axis. On arriving from the west, we would have encountered first the long wall of the west façade. The entry was flanked by two rooms [139 and 140] that were then extended by a gallery to the left and right out to two pavilions [64 and 67] which marked the ends of the great semicircular forecourt to be met on entering. As we stepped inside the central entrance, the semicircle of porticoes reaching towards us would have seemed to be the architectural extension of the welcoming arms of the host coming to greet us. The radius of the inner circle was about 28 meters; and of the outer, about 32 meters. On the inside, the porticoes had marble columns which rested on a low wall. A central walkway stretched ahead, but there can be little doubt that gardens filled both halves of this forecourt, for Fouet carefully noted, “a thick, rich paleosol bordered the porticoes and extended into the two halves of the courtyard up to the central passage.”
To the left of the passage was a little temple of the fanum type (11.5 x 7.5 m). The central altar was a hexagon, while the wall around it was a hexagon elongated towards the south. Two phases of the southern half of the wall have been noted, one more elongated than the other. The excavations yielded numerous offerings, of which six were votive altars, two with dedications, one to Jupiter and the other to Tutela. Fouet dated the construction of the temple to after 350, or in his terms, after the construction of the forecourt.
On crossing the courtyard, we would come to a step up and two large square pillars marking the entrance to the residence proper. Behind the pillars was the porch [62] flanked on either side by heated rooms [55] and [56].
Continuing through the large square room [61], we would have finally reached the grand central peristyle [90] (33 x 30 m) with porticoes about 2.85 meters wide around all four sides. The columns were no doubt marble and were placed on a low wall. Its height is not known precisely. As for the portico of the semicircular court, the site presently shows only a simple stylobate. Around the porticoes were the rooms for daily life, of which a number were heated.
The open part of the courtyard (26 x 23 m) showed no evidence of an ornamental pool. Fouet noted a central east-west passageway about four meters wide which connected the two pairs of large masonry pillars (.9 x 1.1 m in section) in the center of the east and west sides. Originally, they must have supported structures whose height accented the main axis of circulation in the house. Was there a garden in this courtyard? Fouet reported that there had been three different pourings of mortar, but never on the whole surface of the courtyard. Moreover, he demonstrated zones of planting around the border of the peristyle. “In them, a thick paleosol of rich, dark earth replaced the last cementing, and the previous layers of mortar had remained only in places.”
Continuing on ahead, we would have come into a second courtyard (11.5 x 12.1 m), room [27]. The organization of this courtyard poses several questions of interpretation, some of them bearing directly on the question of whether there were plantings here. In particular, the six rectangular structures along the north and south walls [5, 6, 7 and 28, 29, 30] are puzzling. They look a bit like small pools, and indeed they are lined on the inside with rose mortar that may be hydraulic and are covered on the outside with marble. One problem with the pool interpretation, however, is that no means of bringing in water or draining it away was found. The discovery of a quantity of oyster shells in one of them led to the implausible hypothesis that they were for keeping live shellfish. Three other clues to their purpose are: (1) they have been restored with walls that are too thick, (2) the walls of the courtyard were pierced with windows above the structures and otherwise covered with marble plaques except between these structures, and there, in old excavations, the Abbot Couret noted a large quantity of mosaic tessera of glass paste – numerous cubes of light blue, of dark blue, and even some with a gold backing, and (3) in one of the structures was found, reutilized in a burial, a beautiful marble statue of a woman, a Victory or Venus-Victory according to Stirling. Fouet proposed that the structures were holders for planters. One would thus have had marble-paneled walls setting off the colors of the flowers or shrubs in the planters in front of them and, between the planters, mosaics of predominantly blue tones with gold accents. Statues may also have stood between the planters.
According to Fouet, the central area of the courtyard, originally was paved with marble, but then in a final phase “the marble paving was pulled out to make place for lots of dark, rich soil.” So the courtyard became, or became again, a garden.
Today, if we want to continue eastward in the house, we can easily do so by going up the steps at [12] or [14]. But these steps were built by Fouet, and it is not certain that there were any originally here. So we will do well to go back to the large peristyle and use either the corridor [97, 4] on the south or [37, 22] on the north. As noted above, these would have been illuminated by the windows over the planters. Off of these corridors open apse-like semicircular porticoes [11 and 26] with gardens in their central areas [10 and 24]. The outer walls of these porticoes were reinforced by fourteen pilasters placed close together, so we can be reasonably sure that there were no grand bays looking out on gardens beyond. Rather, the gardens in these apses seem intended to embellish the way to the highest reception space.
Continuing on further east and up more steps we reach that space, the reception area [16, 17, 18]. This space was flanked by two rooms to the north and two to the south. Given its elevated position, it must have played a major role. Fouet thought that [17] (5.1 x.6.55 m) was an open space, covered with a trellis, to be enjoyed in the summer. The floor was covered with four large slabs of white marble with blue-gray veins; all four slabs were sawn from the same block to create a pattern with two axes of symmetry. To either side, up one step, opened an elegant room with marble threshold, floor, and walls, with pilasters and roof sloped towards the central room. Two gutters made of imbrix tile still visible ran along the thresholds of [16] and [18] to carry rainwater to the space [19]. Fouet noted the possible presence of fountains in the northeast and southeast corners of room [17]; their presence cannot be verified today. The state of the ruins does not allow a clear opinion to be formed on the function of this unusual space nor on the question of whether [17] was, in fact, open.
In the space [19] at the tip of the axis of the villa, Fouet saw a little garden, but this interpretation is open to question. The level of the walls of [19] is about 2.9 meters below that of [17], and the apse has been much restored and shows several phases. It is possible that this room belonged to a previous phase of the villa and was not part of the final structure. (See Morvillez, 2001, p. 37-38).
Despite the very axial character of the villa, the visitor never had a perspective of the whole. Rather, distinct spaces unfolded as one moved through the house. Very “mineralized” spaces with sumptuous marble revetments alternated with zones of luxuriant plantings. The baths run off to the north from the northwest corner of the rooms around the rectangular peristyle. They are connected to the main house by a courtyard with porticoes and a semicircular apse at the west end. Fouet called the area “the nymphaeum”; but in a recent careful restudy of this wing, A. Bouet (1997) argues that this name was inappropriate. The porticoes had marble columns resting on a low wall. The eastern end of the open space [115] was paved with marble. The western end, [114], was a pool 90 centimeters deep. Finally, a little garden filled the center of the circular apse at the western end. There was perhaps a central fountain. Fouet thought there might have been a fountain with a water ladder in the northern portico at the opening towards room [132]. Bouet (pp. 220-221, Fig. 5) contends that this suggestion also should be forgotten. There are, however, small semi-circles cut out of the edges of the steps which Fouet interpreted as a water ladder. They fit well with the water-ladder interpretation and otherwise make little sense.
Further east, on the axis of this courtyard, was a room with an apse [117] preceded by a vestibule with two columns. This little room was carefully paneled with marble and decorated above the plinths with paintings. There was perhaps originally a fountain in the apse. According to Fouet, at a certain time, the marble paving of the courtyard was pulled up and soil brought in to make a level garden in the whole of the space [113, 114, and 115]. It contained, no doubt, one or possibly two marble sculptured groups related to the myth of Adonis, for scattered fragments were found in the excavation (Stirling, 1994 and 1996, pp. 220-222; Demeures, pp. 233-236.). On his plan, Fouet indicates “exterior gardens” accessible by the corridor [120] which runs along the north of the room with apse [117]. He conjectured in [142] a portico with Tuscan capitals that sheltered a fountain of which only the drain has been found. In his view, the whole formed a pergola (4 x 12 m) open to the gardens to enjoy cool air from the north in the summer.
Plans   The Late Empire villa: general plan (after Fouet, Montmaurin, fig.23)   Images   Model of Villa of Lassalles, view from entrance     Model of Villa of Lassalles, view of rooms   Dates Late antiquity
Excavation Dates 1947-1960
Bibliography  Abbé Couret, Histoire de Montmaurin in Revue de Comminges, 1903, p. 41-55, 77-94, 129-148 (worldcat) G. Fouet, Labrousse M., Découvertes archéologiques en Nebouzan (Haute-Garonne) de 1945 à 1948 in Gallia VII, 1949, I, p. 40-49. (worldcat) G. Fouet, La villa gallo-romaine de Montmaurin in Bulletin archéologique, 1953, p. 268. (worldcat) G. Fouet, La villa gallo-romaine de Montmaurin, XXème supplément à Gallia Paris 1969 (réédité en 1983). (worldcat) J.M. Pailler, Montmaurin, a Garden Villa in Ancient Roman villa Gardens, Dumbarton Oaks Colloquium on the History of Ancient Landscape Architecture, 10, 1984, Washington, 1986, p. 205-221. (worldcat) E.Morvillez, Forme et évolution des salles de réception des grandes demeures tardives du bassin méditerranéen occidental (IVème-Vième siècle), 1993, t. 1, p. 160-166 worldcat L.M. Stirling, Mythological Statuary in Late Antiquity : A case Study of villa Decoration in Southwest Gaul,Ph.D.dissertation, University of Michigan, 1994, p. 23-25, 162-185 (worldcat) L.M. Stirling, Decoration in Late Antique Aquitania, in Aquitania 14, 1994, p. 209-230. (worldcat) A. Bouet, Les thermes de la villa de Montmaurin, Haute Garonne et la pratique balnéaire et sportive dans l’Antiquité tardive, in Aquitania XV, 1997-98, p. 213-244. (worldcat) E. Morvillez, Nouvelles recherches sur l&amp;rsquo;architecture de la villa de Montmaurin : les informations apportées par les carnets de fouilles de G. Fouet. in Mémoires de la Société Archéologique du Midi de la France, LIX, 1999, p. 29-39 Catherine Balmelle, Les demeures aristocratiques d&amp;rsquo;Aquitaine, societe et culture de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquite tardive dans le sou-ouest de la Gaule, Ausonius, supple. d&amp;rsquo;Aquitania 10, Bordeaux 2001, p. 379-385, 447. (worldcat) E. Morvillez, Sur les appartements de réception des hôtes dans l&amp;rsquo;architecture domestique tardive : modes orientales, modes occidentales in Autour de Libanios, culture et société dans l&amp;rsquo;Antiquité tardive, Table ronde organisée par B. Cabouret et E. Morvillez - Université d&amp;rsquo;Avignon, in Pallas 60, 2002, p.231-245. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 249996
TGN ID 7637949
Contributor Clopper Almon (https://www.econ.umd.edu/facultyprofile/almon/clopper)
Publication date 07 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa Lamarque, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/castelculier_lot-et-garonne/gallia_villa-lamarque-_yji/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2020 12:39:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/castelculier_lot-et-garonne/gallia_villa-lamarque-_yji/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania
Province Description&amp;ndash;&amp;gt; A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location CASTELCULIER
(Pleiades)
House Villa Lamarque
House Description The villa was noted in 1859 but forgotten until a farmer turned up first one and then another marble statue in the 1980’s. Soon afterwards, the prospect of a suburban subdivision over the site led to aerial exploration which, thanks to the fact that the barley growing over the walls turned yellow earlier than the rest of the field, yielded a rather precise plan of the whole villa, shown below. Urgent salvage excavations were undertaken between 1987 and 1998. Materials found are at the Centre de Recherche Archéologique d’Aiguillon, and detailed publication of this vast villa is awaited.
The restoration in the archaeological park covers just the area of the baths and is based on a late empire phase. Particularly noteworthy is the circular caldarium [14]; pieces of the mosaic that covered its dome have been found with fragments of fine gold and images of grapes and grape vines.
Garden Peristyle Garden; Courtyard Garden
Keywords  archaeological garden statues baths natationes peristyles (Roman courtyards) gutters (building drainage components) fountains porticos  Garden Description The baths have been carefully studied by phases, with no less than eight identified. The chronology covers the period from the early empire to the sixth century when the villa was abandoned. The first villa was built at the end of the first century. It was in the form of an L around a large rectangular pool or perhaps natatio with a surrounding gallery. The residential part was to the west. Then around the end of the second or beginning of the third century, the principal peristyle was built with rooms for daily life around it. The peristyle has been only partially excavated and may have contained a garden. An apparently very preliminary, undated report found in the Castelculier library mentioned that the “west” corner of the courtyard had been located and that there the courtyard was paved with concrete to within 20 cm of the walls, where there was a gutter to catch the drip from the peristyle roof. The concrete is obviously not favorable to the hypothesis that the area was a garden. However, the report goes on to note that over the concrete was a 15 cm thick layer dense with rocks, pieces of dressed limestone, and ceramic fragments from late antiquity. This layer might perhaps indicate that planters and statuary would have given the paved part of the courtyard the appearance of a garden. Also, a garden in the center remains a possibility.
In late antiquity, the residence occupied 1.5 hectares and included two vast courtyards. In the one to the south, a peristyle formed the heart of the residence; the monumental entrance of the villa has been identified in its east wing. The precise organization of the two spaces, however, is not known. The northern courtyard, partially excavated, with an entrance porch, brought together the agricultural buildings. A semicircular portico, with a central space that may have been planted, connected the south peristyle to the monumental baths with rooms characteristic of late antiquity. These rooms were several times remodeled.
Plans   Castelculier, Villa de Lamarque. Plan of the excavations (1995) by Ph. Jacques (after Fages 1995 [CAG, 47], 186, fig. 123)     Castelculier, Lamarque. Restored plan of state 1 and state 2 (after Fages 1995 [CAG, 47], 187, fig. 124)   Dates End of 1st Century CE
Excavation Dates 1987-1998
Bibliography  N/A, Gallia informations: préhistorie et historie, 1987-88 n° 1 p. 139-142, 1991, n° 1 p. 89-91. (worldcat) Ph. Jacques, Bilan scientifique, Aquitaine, 1994, p. 88-89 ; 1998 ; 100-103, 1998 (worldcat) Br. Fages, Carte archéologique de la Gaule, (47) Le Lot-et-Garonne, 1995, p. 184-195 (worldcat) Catherine Balmelle, Les demeures aristocratiques d&amp;rsquo;Aquitaine, societe et culture de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquite tardive dans le sou-ouest de la Gaule, Ausonius, supple. d&amp;rsquo;Aquitania 10, Bordeaux 2001, p. 89, 348-351, plan p. 448.. (worldcat) Francis Stephanus and Phillippe Jacques, an undated report on the salvage excavations, found in the library in Castelculier.  Pleiades ID 981505 249936
TGN ID []()
Contributor Clopper Almon (https://www.econ.umd.edu/facultyprofile/almon/clopper)
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa de Plassac, Gallia</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/blacciacum_plassacgironde/gallia_villa-de-plassac_yji/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 12:39:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/blacciacum_plassacgironde/gallia_villa-de-plassac_yji/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania
Province Description&amp;ndash;&amp;gt; A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location Blacciacum
(Pleiades)
House Villa de Plassac
House Description The village of Plassac lies 4 kilometers south of Blaye and about 30 kilometers north of Bordeau on the right (east) bank of the Gironde estuary. The Gallo-Roman villa stood on the slope of Montuzet at the place called Clos du Chardonnet, near the estuary of the Gironde. The present parish church of St. Pierre-aux-liens occupies part of the site, which covered more than 5000 square meters. Discovered in the 19th century in the course of expansion of the church, the villa has been the object of successive campaigns of excavation by G. Emard between 1963 and 1974 and probes by J.-P. Bost in the 1970’s.
Garden Peristyle Garden
Keywords  archaeological garden triclinium (room) belvedere opus sectile peristyles (Roman courtyards) ornamental pool apse  Garden Description Three villas followed one another on the same site between the reign of Tiberius and the fifth or early sixth century. The Julio-Claudian villa was built facing the Gironde around the year 30. The Julio-Claudian villa was built facing the Gironde around the year 30. Excavations have brought to light on the river side a grand reception room, combining no doubt a triclinium with a belvedere over the river with the unusual feature of an inward-bowing excedra in a flattened arc 38 meters across on the river side. On either side of this room, to north and south, were structures on two levels. This first villa lasted until at least sometime around A.D. 100. It was then demolished, and the lower levels were filled in to make a terrace that gave a firm footing for the new structure. A new grand room was built, still facing the river but this time further forward and resting on a straight wall on the river side. The room had very thick walls which would seem to indicate an upper floor. Even from the lower room one could enjoy a magnificent panorama over the Gironde to the front and the gardens and buildings to the rear. It was luxuriously ornamented with an opus sectile. There was perhaps a portico on the façade overlooking the river. Directly behind the belvedere room was a courtyard bordered by porticos in a U shape. The northern arm of this U was a double portico, which formed the south side of an interior peristyle which was interpreted as a garden by the excavators. Thus was formed a vast esplanade, a rectangle elongated in the east-west direction and divided in its center by the east-west running double portico.
The northern side of the villa was an external gallery, paralleled on the inside by an ornamental pool 51 meters long, of which one of the long sides has been brought to light. In this reception wing, rooms alternate with courts open to the sky. In the center, a vast room centered on the pool made a passage to the central peristyle. It is flanked in an original manner by two smaller, lateral rooms, placed in two, small, symmetric courts, both covered with marble plaques, both on the walls and on the floor, so that they do not seem to have been used as gardens.
In the east wing, the apartments were organized symmetrically on either side of a central room, flanked by two little rectangular courts planted as gardens. A drain made of tegulae runs around these two spaces. It is pours into the interconnected open channels which run along the porticos of the peristyles of the villa. Some have interpreted this system as ornamental, but one may lean rather towards the interpretation as drains leading the rain water of the roofs to the river. This central room allowed one to pass from the central peristyle to the next to the north, still incompletely excavated, but perhaps also planted as a garden.
The villa saw prosperous days from the time of Trajan to that of Constantine. It then disappeared, a victim doubtless of its age, to be reborn in a third phase. For this period, a labyrinth of late walls makes it difficult to read the logic of the whole. Around 400-430, the eastern wing, the best known, took on its present form, including a bath sector and a series of reception rooms, one of which had a vast polygonal apse on the outside. They all open onto a gallery of the peristyle, of which half is known. The northern wing lost its character of a reception area. It was modified several times and seems to have become a granary or service areas such as a kitchen or stable. Further north, what must have been the park of the second and third centuries was occupied by workshops and then by a late necropolis. The long ornamental pool was filled in during this third phase. The south wing disappeared perhaps in late antiquity, while the buildings of the fourth century are known by probes under the presbytery of the present church.
Plans   state of the excavations in 1974. Plan by R. Monturet, IRAA. Pau (according to GALLIA 1975, 469. fig.15).   Dates 30 CE
Excavation Dates 1963-1974
Bibliography  N/A, Carte archéologique de la Gaule, Gironde, pp. 101-107, plan fig. 48-49, synthèse et bibliographie par J.-P. Bost., Académie des Inscriptions et Belles Lettres. (worldcat) C. Balmelle, Les demeures aristocratiques d’Aquitaine, société et culture de l’Antiquité tardive dans le sud-ouest de la Gaule, p. 393-395, n°40, fig. 303, Ausonius, suppl. d’Aquitiania 10 , Bordeaux 2001. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 138227
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa la Hillère, Gallia</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/montmaurin_haute-garonne/gallia_villa_la_hille%CC%80re_yji/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 12:39:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/montmaurin_haute-garonne/gallia_villa_la_hille%CC%80re_yji/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania
Province Description&amp;ndash;&amp;gt; A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location Montmaurin (Haute-Garonne)
(Pleiades)
House Villa la Hillère
House Description The villa of 1500 square meters has been known since 1865 and was excavated between 1963 and 1965 by G. Fouet. Prompted by the spring, a medieval chapel on the foundations of one of the rooms, and the adjacent cemetery, he had interpreted the site as a water sanctuary. It has been more recently been recognized as a residence, but opinions vary. It is a rare example of fourth century construction on virgin land.
Garden Courtyard
Keywords  archaeological garden courtyard reception room mosaic water court shrubbery  Garden Description It has two distinct buildings. The main, more southern one has a courtyard [P] (31 x 8 m) with three galleries in a U open towards the river. It was once thought there had been a pool in the middle of the U, but it could not be attested by recent investigators. A large, reception room [M] (9.8 m square) with mosaic floor was entirely open toward the river thirty meters ahead, thus strongly suggesting that the area in front of it had been, if not a garden, at least pleasantly landscaped. About ten meters back of the bottom of the U and roughly in line with its northern arm was the the spring, which was surrounded by a hexagonal pool. The more northern building begins fourteen meters northeast of the center of the pool, and its main front wall points directly at the spring. Water from the spring was channeled off to the northeast between the two buildings and to the south-southwest. The area around the spring thus formed a sort of “water court” framed on two sides by the buildings. The main entrance to the southern building was from this court. It would seem safe to speculate that this well-watered area was nicely landscaped, perhaps with trees and shrubbery.
Dates 4th Century
Excavation Dates 1963 to 1965
Bibliography  G. Fouet, Gallia, 20, 83-126. (worldcat) Catherine Balmelle, Les demeures aristocratiques d&amp;rsquo;Aquitaine, societe et culture de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquite tardive dans le sou-ouest de la Gaule, Ausonius, supple. d&amp;rsquo;Aquitania 10, Bordeaux 2001, p. 384-385, plan p. 384. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 246506
TGN ID []()
Contributor Clopper Almon (https://www.econ.umd.edu/facultyprofile/almon/clopper)
Publication date 07 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>