<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 12:58:55 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Test</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/garden/test/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 12:58:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/garden/test/</guid>
      <description>Province Province Description Location Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Keywords Garden Description Maps Plans Images Dates Bibliography Periodo ID Pleiades ID TGN ID Contributor ORCID Publication date Related articles </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Darenth Rural Villa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/garden/darenth-rural-villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 12:08:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/garden/darenth-rural-villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Location Darenth
Garden Rural Villa
Keywords piscinae
villae rusticae
waterspouts
Garden Description Excavations at this site of a Roman villa in Kent uncovered a large rectangular masonry pool in the courtyard, which was enclosed by buildings on the north, west, and east (Fig. 1). The villa buildings took up an area of 150 x 225 meters in total, including the courtyard with a width of 26.5 meters. Occupation at the site began after A.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chester Tomb Painting</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/garden/chester-tomb-painting/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 08:58:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/garden/chester-tomb-painting/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Location Chester
Garden Tomb Painting
Keywords funerary buildings tombs
Garden Description Toynbee’s suggestion that a military tombstone from Chester depicting a row of three gabled buildings with stylized trees or shrubs planted in front of the two at the sides perhaps represents a tomb garden with tomb and flanking funerary buildings, though plausible, cannot in itself be taken to show that tomb gardens existed in Roman Britain; it would, however, suggest that the concept of planting at tombs was regarded as conventionally Roman and appropriate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chedworth Rural Villa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/garden/chedworth-rural-villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 08:19:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/garden/chedworth-rural-villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Location Chedworth
Garden Rural Villa
Keywords balnea
mosaics (visual works)
sherds
villae rusticae
Garden Description This Roman villa in Gloucestershire was partially excavated in the late 19th century, but only the built features and their mosaic floors appear to have been of interest to the Victorian diggers. Excavations in the courtyard conducted between 2000 and 2002 revealed that earlier excavators had not disturbed the courtyard.
Parts of the villa may date to the early 3rd century A.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bancroft Rural Villa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/garden/bancroft-rural-villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2020 18:04:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/garden/bancroft-rural-villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Location Bancroft
Garden Rural Villa
Keywords balnea
gazebos
piscinae
villae rusticae
Garden Description Excavations between 1983 and 1986 at this site in Buckinghamshire revealed a Roman villa of the winged corridor type, which was built in the late 3rd century and rebuilt and enlarged in the mid-4th century (Fig.1).
From the two projecting wings of the house at the northeast and southeast two walls ran eastward, forming an enclosed courtyard 35.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Britannia</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/province/britannia/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2020 12:53:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/province/britannia/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description After Caesar’s campaigns in Britain in 55 and 54 BC, the southern part of the island lay within Rome’s sphere of influence. It was not until the Claudian invasion in 43 AD, however, that Britain was annexed as a Roman province, although the ‘conquest’ of Britain in the west and north continued and proceeded slowly in the decades thereafter. Apart from a brief interlude in the mid-2nd century, when the northern border of the province was fixed at the Antonine Wall in Scotland, from the 120&amp;rsquo;s the northern frontier of the island lay on Hadrian’s Wall stretching from the west to the east coast.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bancroft *Rural Villa*</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/garden/camulodunum-suburban-gardens/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2020 16:47:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/garden/camulodunum-suburban-gardens/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Location Camulodunum
Location Description Camulodunum began as an Iron Age settlement defended by dykes, a combination of V-shaped ditch and rampart created by the upcast earth. It extended from the Roman river on the south to the Colne on the north, a distance of some four kilometers. Within this larger area, a legionary fort was built after the Claudian conquest of Britain in AD 43. On the site of the fort, a veteran colony was planted in about AD 49 and given the name Colonia Victricensis, City of Victory.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>