<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ausgusta_raurica/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 10:02:05 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ausgusta_raurica/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>House in Insula 30 in Augusta Raurica</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ausgusta_raurica/augusta_raurica_house_in_insula_30/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 10:02:05 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ausgusta_raurica/augusta_raurica_house_in_insula_30/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Province Description Location Augusta Raurica
Augusta Raurica (Pleiades)
Location Description The town on the Rhine River possessed colonial status since the late 1st century BC. The street grid, as well as many public and residential buildings, are well known from excavations.
Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden House in Insula 30 in Augusta Raurica
Keywords barrier walls
colonnades
corridors
insulae
peristyles (Roman courtyards)
triclinia
vestibules
water wells
Garden Description Insula 30, east of the central baths, was taken up by a single house built around 200 AD. This replaced several earlier structures on the site. The insula, including the street colonnades, had an overall area of ca. 48 x 60 meters.
The house had a peristyle courtyard of rectangular shape which was surrounded on three sides by a low wall supporting stone columns. The courtyard was unpaved and almost certainly planted (G in Fig. 1). Entering the house from the east, one passed through a vestibule before arriving in the peristyle corridor around the courtyard. The courtyard wall, enclosing an area 14 x 23.50 meters in size, was fronted by a water channel. There was a well in the north. From the triclinium to the west of the courtyard, one had a view directly into the courtyard.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of a house in Insula 30 with a garden courtyard (G). Plan adapted from Laur-Belart 1988, fig. 126. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Insula: 200 A.D.
Bibliography  R. Laur-Belart, Führer durch Augusta Raurica, 5th Ed., Basel, 1988, pp. 134-136, fig. 126. (worldcat) M. Carroll, Romans, Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 55, fig. 20. (worldcat)  Periodo ID Pleiades ID 177494
TGN ID 7017586
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 14 July 2020
Related articles </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House in Insula 1 and 2 in Augusta Raurica</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ausgusta_raurica/augusta_raurica_house_in_insula_1_and_2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 17:34:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/ausgusta_raurica/augusta_raurica_house_in_insula_1_and_2/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Province Description Location Augusta Raurica
Augusta Raurica (Pleiades)
Location Description The town on the Rhine River possessed colonial status since the late 1st century BC. The street grid, as well as many public and residential buildings, are well known from excavations.
Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden House in Insula 1 and 2 in Augusta Raurica
Keywords archaeological garden
barrier walls
insulae
peristyles (Roman courtyards)
porticoes
terrace gardens
Garden Description This house, built on sloping terrain on the northern edge of the city around AD 150, was enlarged twenty years later to incorporate at least two certain gardens (Fig. 1). It bordered north and south on streets and was flanked on the east and west by other houses. In this last phase after ca. 170, the house covered an area of about 2000 square meters. In the center of the building was an irregular peristyle courtyard, at the north end of which was a private bath complex.
East of the house was a long rectangular area open to the sky and divided into plots by a wall. In the northernmost plot a layer of humic soil 20-40 centimeters thick was excavated that the excavators interpret as evidence for a garden (G on plan).
The northern part of the house facing the street included an open terrace which may have been built up on demolished walls of the earlier house. Humus-rich soil in the terrace area may indicate that it was planted (G in Fig. 1). Immediately south of the terrace was a portico that offered a splendid view of the valley.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Augusta Raurica., House in insula 1 and 2. Adapted from Hufschidt.(Rights statement)   Images Dates House: AD 150 - ca. 170
Bibliography  P.-A. Schwarz, „Die Nordmauer und die Überreste der Innenbebauung der spätrömischen Befestigung auf Kastelen in Augusta Rauricorum. Vorbericht über die Grabung 1991.51,“ Jahresberichte aus Augst und Kaiseraugst 13, 1992: 47-76. (worldcat) T. Hufschmid, Kastelen 3. Die jüngeren Steinbauten in den Insulae 1 und 2 von Augusta Raurica. Forschungen in Augst 23, Augst, 1996. (worldcat)  Periodo ID Pleiades ID 177494
TGN ID 7017586
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 14 July 2020
Related articles </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>