<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_viii/house_5/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2020 19:11:52 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_viii/house_5/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Indian Statuette (I.viii.5)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_viii/house_5/house_of_the_indian_statuette/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2020 19:11:52 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_viii/house_5/house_of_the_indian_statuette/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula VIII
House House 5
Garden House of the Indian Statuette (I.viii.5)
Keywords  archaeological garden chests (case furniture) columns (architectural elements) gutters (building drainage components) peristyles (columnades) porticoes statues statuettes (free-standing sculpture)  Garden Description A portico enclosed this garden (a) on the north, east and south sides, and the portico on the west had been closed to create rooms. These enclosed columns can be observed incorporated into the wall but only one of the other columns remains standing. The garden was surrounded by a gutter. A small Indian statuette (0.25 m. high) was found in the adjacent shop and it is believed to have been stored in a wooden chest in one of the rooms off the portico with other domestic items. It had tumbled into the shop when the southwest corner of the peristyle collapsed.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula viii, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 11, p.42; I.viii-ix: plan in Eschebach (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date Bibliography  Della Corte, Case, p. 334. Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 42. (worldcat) Maiuri, “Statuetta eburnea d’art indiana a Pompei,” LeArti (1938), pp. 111-115. Idem, “Navalia pompeiana,” RendNap, n.s., 33 (1959): 22.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 08 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>