<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>kitchen gardens on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/tags/kitchen-gardens/</link>
    <description>Recent content in kitchen gardens on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:57:12 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/tags/kitchen-gardens/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Rustic villa at Rheinbach-Flerzheim</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/rheinbach-flerzheim/rheinbach-flerzheim/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:57:12 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/rheinbach-flerzheim/rheinbach-flerzheim/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Province Description Location Rheinbach-Flerzheim
Garden Rustic villa at Rheinbach-Flerzheim
Keywords  villae rusticae hedges bathhouses (water recreation structures) kitchen gardens piscinae  Garden Description There was no division between the residential and service parts of this modest farm. The house, with its bath (A and B on plan), and the outbuildings were built of stone at the beginning of the 2nd century (Plan 1). The winged corridor type house of this villa rustica was 37 m. long and 20 m. wide, and it had a bath attached to the back.
Enclosing the farm complex was a hedge or row of trees, the planting trenches of which were uncovered in excavations (gray wavy border on plan). Based on the palaeobotanical evidence of carbonised plant remains and pollen, a kitchen garden near the house and fruit trees on the property have been reconstructed. In front of the entrance to the main residence at the south were the remains of a small pool lined with clay. This has been taken as evidence for an ornamental garden surrounding the pool. On a farm of this modest size and simplicity, however, an ornamental garden seems rather unlikely. The farm was occupied until the mid-5th century.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the farmyard with its house (A) and bath (B) enclosed by a hedge (grey line). The open circles are wells. Adapted from Carroll 2001, fig. 38. (Rights statement).   Images Dates Second century CE to mid-fifth century CE
Bibliography  M. Gechter, &amp;ldquo;Der römische Gutshof von Rheinbach-Flerzheim,&amp;rdquo; in Spurensicherung. Archäologische Denkmalpflege in der Euregio Maas-Rhein, Mainz, 1992, pp. 249-54, 452-60. worldcat M. Carroll, Romans, Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 79, fig. 38. worldcat  Pleiades ID 981524
TGN ID 7192890
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 25 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Niederzier Hambach 69</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/niederzier-hambach/niederzier-hambach69/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:55:45 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/niederzier-hambach/niederzier-hambach69/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Province Description Location Niederzier-Hambach
Niederzier-Hambach (Pleiades)
Location Description In the Hambacher Forst region, which lies approximately 30-35 km. west of the former capital city Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium (mod. Cologne), a number of modest villae rusticae have been excavated.
Garden Niederzier Hambach 69
Keywords  villae rusticae fences (site elements) ditches hedges kitchen gardens orchards water wells cherry (plant)  Garden Description This villa rustica was situated west of Cologne in the same region as Hambach 59. It was built in the late 1st century A.D. and inhabited until the 4th century (Plan 1). The farm had a calculated overall area, including the cultivated land, of 50 hectares. The farm compound itself was one hectare in size. The modest house (A on plan) stood just inside the western border of the complex. Elsewhere on the property were various stables, barns, a pond and several wells.
To the east of the house was an area marked off by a narrow ditch (B on plan). This was probably a bedding trench for a protective hedge around a vegetable garden (G on plan). Palaeobotanical material, all of it carbonized, from deposits in wells and pits provide information on the field crops. Considerable amounts of charred chaff in a well in the eastern part of the farmyard suggest that a threshing area for the grain grown on the farm may have been situated near the well. The botanical remains indicate that spelt wheat was the main crop, followed by barley. The farmyard has hedge borders, the planting trenches for which were excavated. Within this area, fruit trees, oaks and alders as well as elderberry bushes possibly were planted.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the farm house (A) and the farmyard enclosed by a hedge (grey line). A vegetable garden (G) may have lain within another hedge (B). Adapted from Gaitzsch 1986, fig. 5. (Rights statement).   Dates Late first century CE until the fourth century CE.
Bibliography  K.-H. Knörzer, &amp;ldquo;Veränderungen der Unkrautvegetation auf rheinischen Bauernhöfen seit der Römerzeit,&amp;rdquo; Bonner Jahrbuch 184, 1984: 491-503. worldcat W. Gaitzsch, &amp;ldquo;Grundformen römischer Landsiedlungen im Westen der CCAA,&amp;rdquo; Bonner Jahrbuch 186, 1986: 397-427, fig. 5. worldcat  Pleiades ID 109210
TGN ID 7128518
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 24 July 2020
Related articles Niederzier-Hambach 59.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Houses of Insula 7 in Colonia Ulpia Traiana</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/colonia_ulpia_xanten/colonia_xanten_insula7/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/colonia_ulpia_xanten/colonia_xanten_insula7/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Xanten
Xanten (Pleiades)
Sublocation Industrial quarter
Sublocation Description This insula southeast of the forum is commonly referred to as an industrial quarter (Plan 1). It was divided into several long, narrow plots on which were houses, shops and workshops.
Garden The houses of Insula 7 in Colonia Ulpia Traiana (Xanten)
Keywords  insulae kitchen gardens courtyards  Garden Description Between the buildings were open areas, some paved and equipped with ovens and pottery kilns, wells and latrines, others unpaved. Some of the small courtyards have been reconstructed by the excavators as kitchen gardens and shrine gardens (Image 1). Organic material from a well in this insula included the remains of peas, beans, lentils, apples, pears and herbs. These fruits and vegetables may have grown in kitchen gardens in the insula, but they may, on the other hand, have been brought into the city from nearby farms.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the houses in *Insula* 7 with paved (stippled) and unpaved courtyards. The black dots are wells. Adapted from Precht and Rüger 1991. Rights statement.   Images   Image 1. Model of the houses in *Insula* 7 with courtyard garden. Photo courtesy of M. Carroll.   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  H.G. Horn, ed., Die Römer in Nordrhein-Westfalen, Stuttgart, 1987, pp. 634-636, fig. 542 (incorrectly labeled as Insula 26). worldcat G. Precht and C.B. Rüger, Archaologischer Stadtplan. Colonia Ulpia Traiana, Cologne, 1991. worldcat  Pleiades ID 108896
TGN ID 7208125
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
