<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/arabia_petraea/havarra/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/arabia_petraea/havarra/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Shrine Complex in Insula E125</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/arabia_petraea/havarra/havarra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/arabia_petraea/havarra/havarra/</guid>
      <description>Province Arabia Petraea
Location Auara
Auara (Pleiades)
Garden Shrine Complex in Insula E125
Keywords  aqueducts basins (vessels) insulae naoi (chambers) planters (containers) shrines (structures) temene  Garden Description A few decades after a Nabataean shrine at Hawara (Roman Havarra) had been severely damaged during the Roman conquest of Arabia Petraea, the site’s inhabitants built another shrine at the same location. The Roman period shrine occupied the southeast corner of a multi-unit insula (E125), but could only be accessed from outside the complex. This shrine consisted of a square naos (containing the cult statue and votive offerings) enclosed in a rectangular open-air temenos (Figs. 1-2). Upon entering the temenos, worshippers walked to the naos along a 20 m long paved processional way that was flanked by two long raised planters. An aqueduct-fed basin next to the door of the naos appears to have supplied the shrine with so much fresh water that it must have been intended not just for ritual cleansing, but for supplying the planters as well. Given the relatively shallow depth of the planters, and that no root balls or pots were found within, they probably contained shrubs and/or flowers rather than trees. Although the architect clearly tried to make the planters symmetrical in size, shape, and location, their design (and that of the whole Roman shrine) was constrained by the reuse of some Nabataean walls as foundations.
Maps Plans   Plan of Shrine Complex in Insula E125.   Images   Perspective reconstruction of Shrine Complex in Insula E125 with the low naos and notched peak behind.   Dates first century CE, mid‐second to third century CE
Bibliography  Oleson, John Peter, M. Barbara Reeves, Gregory S. Baker, Erik de Bruijn, Yvonne Gerber, M. Nikolic, and Andrew N. Sherwood. 2008. “Preliminary Report on Excavations at Al-Humayma, Ancient Hawara, 2004 and 2005.” Annual of the Department of Antiquities of Jordan 52: 309–42. (Stable URL). Reeves, M. Barbara. 2019. “A Nabataean and Roman Shrine with Civic and Military Gods at Humayma, Jordan.” Arabian Archaeology &amp;amp; Epigraphy 30 (1): 134–55. (DOI).  Pleiades ID 746716 (Auara)
TGN ID 7007646 (Ḥawwārah)
Contributor M. Barbara Reeves
Publication date 3 Dec 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>