<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/orbe/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2020 13:44:42 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/orbe/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Orbe</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/orbe/orbe_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2020 13:44:42 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/orbe/orbe_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Orbe
Orbe (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Orbe
Keywords archaeological garden \
 corridors terrace gardens villae rusticae  Garden Description This large palatial house belonged to a villa rustica revealed by excavation and aerial photography. The enclosed farmyard is calculated to have been approximately 420 x 650 meters in size. The house itself, built in the mid-1st century AD and in use until the 4th century, was 200 meters long (Fig. 1). This winged corridor house had two large open courtyards between the protruding wings at the front. These were very likely gardens (G in Fig. 1). Twenty-five meters in front of the house at the east was a long terrace wall 400 meters long running north-south. There may have been gardens or a park (G in Fig. 1) between the house and this terrace wall.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the rural villa (A) with two large courtyard gardens (G) and a possible walled garden (G) to the east of the main house. The dotted lines are structures known only from aerial photography. Adapted from Drack and Fellmann 1988, fig. 423. (Rights Statement)   Dates House: mid-1st century CE - 4th century
Bibliography  D. Weidmann, &amp;ldquo;L&#39;établissement romain d&amp;rsquo;Orbe/Boscéaz,&amp;rdquo; Archäologie der Schweiz 2, 1978: 84-86. (worldcat) W. Drack and R. Fellmann, Die Römer in der Schweiz, Stuttgart, 1988, pp. 463-465, figs. 422-423. (worldcat) R. Fellmann, La Suisse gallo-romaine. Cinq siècles d’histoire, Lausanne, 1992, pp. 152-153, fig. 112. (worldcat) Th. Luginbühl, J. Monnier, Y. Dubois, Vie de palais et travail d’esclave. La villa romaine d’Orbe-Boscéaz. Document du Musée cantonal d’archéologie et d’histoire, Lausanne, 2001, pp. 34-36, 53-55, figs. 28-29, 40, 49-51. [(worldcat)](Vie de palais et travail d’esclave. La villa romaine d’Orbe-Boscéaz)  Pleiades ID 177598
TGN ID 7007438
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 17 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>