<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>puteal on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/tags/puteal/</link>
    <description>Recent content in puteal on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/tags/puteal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Casa dei Cervi</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/italia/tiffany_fong2/casa_dei_cervi/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/italia/tiffany_fong2/casa_dei_cervi/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Insula IV
House 21
Garden Casa dei Cervi
Keywords  [triclinium] [oecus] [portico] [trapezophron] [puteal] [pergola]   Garden Description 545.IV.21 A. Of all the houses that overlooked the Bay on the south edge of the city, this house excavated in 1929-1932 was the most elegant. The triclinium(b) on the north was on an axis through the spacious garden with the large oecus(c) on the south, dividing the garden (a) into two large rectangular beds. The garden was enclosed on the west, north and east by a corridor with windows replacing an earlier portico. Statues that had been displaced by the mud flow to the center of the garden would have stood on either side of the passageway. This collection was the most valuable found in Herculaneum and reflects the patrician culture of this house. These pieces included two groups of stags attacked by hounds (Herculaneum inv. nos. 519, 524), a satyr with a wineskin (Herculaneum inv. no. 520), and a drunken Hercules (Herculaneum inv. no. 525). The satyr pouring from a wineskin is a variation of the well-known bronze found in the House of the Centenary of Pompeii and was a fountain statuette, but Maiuri believed that it had not been installed at the time of the eruption. Other items found in the center of the garden were a trapezophron, a cup and a marble puteal. There were four small marble bases in the south half of the garden set in the soil which probably once held marble herms that were removed by the Bourbons. The terrace yielded a statuette of the boy Eros (Herculaneum inv. no. 2077) and the pieces of another similar statuette. A gutter around the edge of the garden carried roof water to the cistern and the puteal over the cistern opening in the west end of the north gutter was deeply worn by ropes. A view of the sea could be enjoyed from a vantage point in the triclinium on the north across the garden and through the grand oecus which would have served as a triclinium in the summer. Beyond the oecus was a pergola and Jashemski noted that four original terra-cotta pots found by the pergola pillars were the most decorative she had seen. These would have been planted with a display for the pergola
546-547.IV.21. B. and C. On either side of the pergola was a small garden (d)and (e) with an elegant room on the far side with a window to look out to the garden and a second window looking to the sea. The statuettes of Eros may have originally been placed in these rooms, swept away by the mud flow from the eruption.
Plans   Plan of Casa A Graticcio   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1929-1932
Bibliography  Maiuri, Herculaneum, pp. 62-64 Maiuri, Ercolano, pp. 302, 321-323 and fig. 240 (plan) on p. 303. Maiuri, “Fanciullo erote da Ercolano, Le Arti (1943), pp. 175-179 Maiuri, Herculaneum,p. 64 Maiuri, Ercolano, pp. 320, 323.  -
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa del Bicentenario</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/italia/tiffany_fong2/casa_del_bicentenario/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/italia/tiffany_fong2/casa_del_bicentenario/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Insula V
House 15-16
Garden Casa del Bicentenario
Keywords  [portico] [tablinium] [dolium] [puteal]   Garden Description 551.V.15-16. Two hundred years after the first excavation efforts started at Herculaneum in 1738, this house was excavated and the restoration finished, thereby receiving its name. A passageway with windows bordered the garden (a) on the west and a portico with seven columns joined by a low wall stood on the east and north of this garden measuring 9.90 x 4.90 meters. A wide water channel encircled the garden on three sides and there were two entrances, one opposite the tablinium on the north and the other at the southeast corner of the garden. The neck of a large dolium formed the mouth of a well with a heavy masonry puteal located in the center of the garden
Plans   Plan of Casa A Graticcio   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1738
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 371 Maiuri, Herculaneum,p. 48; Maiuri, Ercolano, pp.51, 233 and fig. 174 (plan) on p. 222  -
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa del Mobilio Carbonizzato</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/italia/tiffany_fong2/casa_del_mobilio_carbonizzato/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/italia/tiffany_fong2/casa_del_mobilio_carbonizzato/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Insula V
House 5
Garden Casa del Mobilio Carbonizzato
Keywords  fauces aedicula opus signinum aedicula lararium [lararium]  Garden Description 549.V.5. Visible from the fauces, this little courtyard (a) had an elaborate aedicula shrine which was excavated in 1932-1933. A low double wall with a gutter bordered the courtyard on the west and north sides with a cistern opening located in the center of the west edge of garden. Four small flower beds on the sides and a circular bed in the center had raised borders to retain the water for the plants within, and the remainder of the courtyard was paved in opus signinum. Jashemski commented that the garden had been restored with eleven such small planting beds. The east wall had traces of an animal painting on a blue background by the aedicula lararium. A deer was painted on the right side and several more indistinct animal forms were noted over the lararium. At the south end of this wall there were traces of leaves and a lattice fence suggesting a garden painting may have been located here.
Plans   Plan of Casa dell’Ara Laterizia     Plan of Casa dell’Ara Laterizia   Images   Illustration of Casa dell’Ara Laterizia     Illustration of Casa dell’Ara Laterizia   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date 1932-1933
Bibliography  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 370-371 Maiuri, Herculaneum,p. 44 Maiuri, Ercolano, pp.260-261 and fig. 203 (plan) on p. 256.  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa del Telaio</title>
      <link>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/italia/tiffany_fong2/casa_del_telaio/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:00:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://roman-gardens.github.io/gre/province/italia/tiffany_fong2/casa_del_telaio/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Insula V
House 4/3
Garden Casa del Telaio
Keywords  textrina portico puteal  Garden Description 548.V.4/3. There was a courtyard (a) in the center of this house which was apparently attached to a textrina. The courtyard was surrounded by a portico with seven supporting brick columns. These were connected by a low wall and a second wall on the inside was slightly lower and formed a gutter. A terra-cotta puteal was located by the entrance on the north over the cistern opening. Maiuri concluded there was enough soil present here to indicate this had been a garden.
Plans   Plan of Casa dell’Ara Laterizia     Plan of Casa dell’Ara Laterizia   Images   Illustration of Casa dell’Ara Laterizia     Illustration of Casa dell’Ara Laterizia   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates unspecified
Excavation Date unspecified
Bibliography  Maiuri, Ercolano, p. 430 and fig. 370 (plan) on p. 427  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski worldcat
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
