<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>hedges on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/hedges/</link>
    <description>Recent content in hedges on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:58:07 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/hedges/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Rural villa at Voerendaal</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/voerendaal/voerendaal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:58:07 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/voerendaal/voerendaal/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Province Description Location Voerendaal
Voerendaal (Pleiades)
Garden Rural villa at Voerendaal
Keywords  villae rusticae porticoes piscinae hedges courtyards  Garden Description The stone-built structures of this villa rustica near the Meuse river, the largest excavated thus far in the Netherlands, were erected in the early 2nd century and repeatedly enlarged until the abandonment of the farm around 300 A.D. (Plan 1). The total area of the farm, including the cultivated land, is calculated to have been ca. 150 hectares. The main residence (A on plan) lay in the northern half of the complex which measured 167 x 214 m. (3.5 hectares) in size. The porticoed facade in its final state was 190 m. long.
In front of the house to the south was a large area (17 x 37 m.), enclosed by a stone wall on two sides and villa porticoes on the other sides. This has been interpreted as a formal garden (G on plan) with low plantings, hedges and a pool (P on plan; Image 1 [NO IMAGE INCLUDED]). The main road leading from the gate in the south to the house in the north cut through this enclosed area. The excavators postulate a vegetable garden behind the house for easy, daily access. The boundaries of the farm complex were planted with a row of trees or a hedge, the planting pits of which had survived. The many carbonized grains of wheat and chaff found in and around a large building in the northeastern part of the courtyard enclosure suggest that wheat grown in the fields of the farm was processed here. The main crop at Voerendaal was spelt; very little emmer or bread wheat was present in the organic remains.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the rural villa with a possible walled garden (G) and its pool (P) south of the house (A). Hedges (rows of dots) enclosed the farmyard. Adapted from Willems 1992, Fig. 307. (Rights statement).   Images Dates Early second century CE to ca. 300 CE
Bibliography  W.J.H. Willems, &amp;ldquo;Die kaiserzeitliche Villa von Voerendaal&amp;rdquo;, in Spurensicherung. Archäologische Denkmalpflege in der Euregio Maas-Rhein, Mainz, 1992, pp. 526-534, figs. 307-308. worldcat P. Van Ossel, Établissements ruraux de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquité tardive dans le nord de la Gaule, Paris, 1992, pp. 363-365, fig. 155. worldcat  Pleiades ID 109442
TGN ID 7272601
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rustic villa at Rheinbach-Flerzheim</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/rheinbach-flerzheim/rheinbach-flerzheim/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:57:12 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/rheinbach-flerzheim/rheinbach-flerzheim/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Province Description Location Rheinbach-Flerzheim
Garden Rustic villa at Rheinbach-Flerzheim
Keywords  villae rusticae hedges bathhouses (water recreation structures) kitchen gardens piscinae  Garden Description There was no division between the residential and service parts of this modest farm. The house, with its bath (A and B on plan), and the outbuildings were built of stone at the beginning of the 2nd century (Plan 1). The winged corridor type house of this villa rustica was 37 m. long and 20 m. wide, and it had a bath attached to the back.
Enclosing the farm complex was a hedge or row of trees, the planting trenches of which were uncovered in excavations (gray wavy border on plan). Based on the palaeobotanical evidence of carbonised plant remains and pollen, a kitchen garden near the house and fruit trees on the property have been reconstructed. In front of the entrance to the main residence at the south were the remains of a small pool lined with clay. This has been taken as evidence for an ornamental garden surrounding the pool. On a farm of this modest size and simplicity, however, an ornamental garden seems rather unlikely. The farm was occupied until the mid-5th century.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the farmyard with its house (A) and bath (B) enclosed by a hedge (grey line). The open circles are wells. Adapted from Carroll 2001, fig. 38. (Rights statement).   Images Dates Second century CE to mid-fifth century CE
Bibliography  M. Gechter, &amp;ldquo;Der römische Gutshof von Rheinbach-Flerzheim,&amp;rdquo; in Spurensicherung. Archäologische Denkmalpflege in der Euregio Maas-Rhein, Mainz, 1992, pp. 249-54, 452-60. worldcat M. Carroll, Romans, Celts and Germans. The German Provinces of Rome, Stroud, 2001, p. 79, fig. 38. worldcat  Pleiades ID 981524
TGN ID 7192890
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 25 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Niederzier Hambach 59</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/niederzier-hambach/niederzier-hambach59/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:55:45 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/niederzier-hambach/niederzier-hambach59/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Province Description Location Niederzier-Hambach
Niederzier-Hambach (Pleiades)
Location Description In the Hambacher Forst region, which lies approximately 30-35 km. west of the former capital city Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium (mod. Cologne), a number of modest villae rusticae have been excavated.
Garden Niederzier Hambach 59
Keywords  villae rusticae ditches fences (site elements) hedges water wells orchards cherry (plant)  Garden Description This farm, known as Hambach 59, was built in the late 1st century A.D. and inhabited until its destruction in the 4th century (Plan 1). The farmhouse, 19.50 x 26 m. in size (A on plan), occupied a position in the northern part of the complex, and looked out on the rest of the farm to the south where various outbuildings and stables stood. There was no division between the residential part and the service area of the farm.
The farmyard was enclosed by a hedge (dotted lines on plan) and took up an area of approximately 1.5 hectares. Outside of the enclosed farmyard to the north were four large plots, presumably for orchards and cultivated fields, which were marked off by ditches or fences (outlined in black on plan). Two of these plots were approximately one hectare in size. The reconstruction of the vegetation on the farm is based on the palaeobotanical analysis of deposits from the four wells in front of the house. The material includes charred fruits and seeds as well as unburnt plant remains and pollen. Cherry pits are evidence for sweet cherry trees. Oak pollen, as well as the water-logged remains of the buds and bud scales of the oak tree, suggest that a shady oak may have grown near one of the wells in the courtyard. Walnut pollen was found in such large quantities in the wells, that one can safely assume the presence of walnut trees near the house. The same applies for lime trees attested by their pollen in the sediments. The remains of coriander and linseed in the wells suggest that these plants may have grown in the vegetable garden in the immediate vicinity of the house. The hedge surrounding the farm compound may have consisted of a combination of hazelnut, elderberry, raspberry and brambleberry, which were all present as pollen, shells, and seeds in the sediments. Box is attested by the pollen in the wells, but it is uncertain where this plant grew on the site.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the farm with hedges (dotted lines) and fences (solid lines) enclosing orchards, fields and the farmyard with its house (A). Plan adapted from Gaitzsch 1990, fig. on p. 238. (Rights statement).   Images Dates Late first century CE until the fourth century CE.
Bibliography  W. Gaitzsch, &amp;ldquo;Der römische Gutshof im &amp;lsquo;Gewährhau’ bei Niederzier,&amp;rdquo; in H. Hellenkemper, H. Koschik and B. Trier, eds., Archäologie in Nordrhein-Westfalen, Cologne, 1990, pp. 235-41. worldcat K.-H. Knörzer and J. Meurers-Balke, &amp;ldquo;Die Wirtschafts- und Nutzflächen eines römischen Gutshofes,&amp;rdquo; in H. Hellenkemper, H. Koschick and B.Trier, eds., Archäologie in Nordrhein-Westfalen, pp. 242-46. worldcat W. Gaitzsch, &amp;ldquo;Antikes Landleben im Modell einer villa rustica,&amp;rdquo; Archäologie im Rheinland 1990, Cologne, 1991, pp. 46-49.  Pleiades ID 109210
TGN ID 7128518
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 24 July 2020
Related articles Niederzier-Hambach 69.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Niederzier Hambach 69</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/niederzier-hambach/niederzier-hambach69/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:55:45 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/niederzier-hambach/niederzier-hambach69/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Province Description Location Niederzier-Hambach
Niederzier-Hambach (Pleiades)
Location Description In the Hambacher Forst region, which lies approximately 30-35 km. west of the former capital city Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium (mod. Cologne), a number of modest villae rusticae have been excavated.
Garden Niederzier Hambach 69
Keywords  villae rusticae fences (site elements) ditches hedges kitchen gardens orchards water wells cherry (plant)  Garden Description This villa rustica was situated west of Cologne in the same region as Hambach 59. It was built in the late 1st century A.D. and inhabited until the 4th century (Plan 1). The farm had a calculated overall area, including the cultivated land, of 50 hectares. The farm compound itself was one hectare in size. The modest house (A on plan) stood just inside the western border of the complex. Elsewhere on the property were various stables, barns, a pond and several wells.
To the east of the house was an area marked off by a narrow ditch (B on plan). This was probably a bedding trench for a protective hedge around a vegetable garden (G on plan). Palaeobotanical material, all of it carbonized, from deposits in wells and pits provide information on the field crops. Considerable amounts of charred chaff in a well in the eastern part of the farmyard suggest that a threshing area for the grain grown on the farm may have been situated near the well. The botanical remains indicate that spelt wheat was the main crop, followed by barley. The farmyard has hedge borders, the planting trenches for which were excavated. Within this area, fruit trees, oaks and alders as well as elderberry bushes possibly were planted.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the farm house (A) and the farmyard enclosed by a hedge (grey line). A vegetable garden (G) may have lain within another hedge (B). Adapted from Gaitzsch 1986, fig. 5. (Rights statement).   Dates Late first century CE until the fourth century CE.
Bibliography  K.-H. Knörzer, &amp;ldquo;Veränderungen der Unkrautvegetation auf rheinischen Bauernhöfen seit der Römerzeit,&amp;rdquo; Bonner Jahrbuch 184, 1984: 491-503. worldcat W. Gaitzsch, &amp;ldquo;Grundformen römischer Landsiedlungen im Westen der CCAA,&amp;rdquo; Bonner Jahrbuch 186, 1986: 397-427, fig. 5. worldcat  Pleiades ID 109210
TGN ID 7128518
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 24 July 2020
Related articles Niederzier-Hambach 59.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
