<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>tombs on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/tombs/</link>
    <description>Recent content in tombs on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/tombs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Funerary Chamber of Manlia Felicitas</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_appia/funerary_chamber_of_manlia_felicitas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_appia/funerary_chamber_of_manlia_felicitas/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location VIA APPIA Funerary Chamber of Manlia Felicitas
Sublocation Via Appia
Sublocation Description An early Roman road (via publica) originating at Rome and terminating at Brundisium, the Via Appia was begun in the fourth century B.C. by the censor Appius Claudius Caecus. The Latin author Statius described the Via Appia as &amp;ldquo;queen of the long roads&amp;rdquo;.
Garden Funerary Chamber of Manlia Felicitas
Keywords  villa tombs funerary buildings  Garden Description In 1937 a French student, Louis Vignon, searching for new catacombs around the third mile of the Via Appia near the tomb of Caecilia Metella, discovered a subterranean funerary chamber accessible via a descending stair that ended at a landing which opened perpendicularly into the middle of one of its walls. Each of the other three walls contained an arcosolium decorated with frescoes depicting animal and vegetal life against a background of herbs and flowers beneath hanging garlands punctuated by aquatic fowl, doves, and the heads of youths; beneath the frescoes the lower walls were paneled in polychrome marble. The figured scenes—at the back, opposite the entrance, a pair of peacocks flanking a niche; to the left a pair of Cupids draping a gazelle in a long ribbon; to the right a pair of gazelles on either side of a twisted tree—belong to a stock of Hellenistic motifs evocative of the gardens of the blessed popular at Rome during the Julio-Claudian period and, especially, the reign of Augustus, to which Wuillemier thought the monument belonged. When Vignon returned to the site thirteen years later, the underground chamber could not be located, but at the edge of the site, near an ancient aedicula fronting the Via Appia, he found a marble funerary inscription in a pile of broken stones evidently recovered from a second subterranean room beneath the aedicula. Underground galleries extending off the subterranean room and from the intersection at the entrance to the tomb chamber seemed to Vignon to join the two structures to each other in a large subterranean complex (Fig. XXX). The inscription (AE 1952, 35)—an epitaph to a freedwoman Manlia Felicitas set up by her fellow freedman and husband of thirty-five years, P. Manlius Epigonus, her daughter Manlia Flora, and her daughter’s husband L. Calpurnius Servatus—declares that the “twenty-fourth part” (pars semunciaria) (either of the entire estate or of an acre, about 40 meters square) “in these gardens of the Manlii” (in his hortis Manlianis) entrusted by Manlia Salvilla (evidently the patroness of Epigonus and Felicitas) to Epigonus for him to hand over to Felicitas, Felicitas had wanted to belong to their daughter Flora. It is uncertain whether “these Manlian gardens” refer to a tomb garden proper or to a suburban estate (horti): both are well attested in conjunction with suburban tombs (see vol. 1, 208). Reference to a “twenty-fourth part”, the (indirect) involvement of the patroness Salvilla, and the early imperial fashion of styling suburban estates as “gardens” named after their owners (regularly expressed in adjectival form) here favor the latter. Whether the inscription, which in form and formula appears not later than the second century, can be put into any direct relation with the subterranean chamber with arcosoli, a tomb type more characteristic of the fourth century, remains doubtful. But the discovery of both on the same property perhaps suggests a continuous use of the site as a funerary space for two centuries.
Dates 130CE
Bibliography   J. Bodel, Roman Tomb Gardens, Cambridge University Press, 2018, p. 208-209. link
  P. Wuilleumier , Sur la Voie Appienne: Les horti Manliani, Comptes rendus des séances de l&amp;rsquo;Académie des Inscriptions et Belles-Lettres,1951, 34-41; Archaiologike Ephemeris, 1952, 35; Quilici 1977: 39 (horti Manliani) worldcat
  G.-L. Gregori , Horti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, Bullettino della Commissione Archeologica Comunale di Roma BCom 92 (1987-88) [1989]: 180 n. 35, 185. worldcat
  Pleiades ID 990721366
Contributor John Bodel
Publication date 01 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monumental Tomb Garden Complex</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_labicana/monumental_tomb_garden_complex/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_labicana/monumental_tomb_garden_complex/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Via Labicana Monumental Tomb Garden Complex
Sublocation Via Labicana
Sublocation Description An ancient Roman road connecting Rome and Labicum.
Garden Monumental Tomb Garden Complex
Keywords  courtyards ditches epitaphs funerary buildings sepulchral monuments tombs  Garden Description Two conjoining fragments of a cut marble slab found in the cemetery of Centocelle at the third mile of the Via Labicana, now in the Palazzo Ducale in Urbino, show part of a plan (not drawn to scale) of a large rectangular funerary garden (546 x 524.5 Roman feet, almost exactly 10 iugera, about 5.8 acres, in area) bounded on at least two sides by a private road that branched off near the end of a longer side to intersect a public thoroughfare 1,783 Roman feet (about 1/3rd of a Roman mile) long, beside which several rectangular tomb plots, some marked with border cippi at the (rear?) corners, are marked off in a reed bed. To judge from the stippling on the stone (incompletely marked on the most frequently reproduced drawing of the plan), a second reed bed occupying a triangular plot between the shorter length of private road and a ditch on the opposite side (a subsecivum) extended perpendicularly from the short side of the triangle at the hypotenuse in a narrow band equal in width to that of the reed bed beside the public road and the private road around the perimeter of the enclosure (see the photograph in Luni, fig. 6). De Rossi believed, on no firm evidence, that the property bounded by the public road and reed bed extending off the top of the plan was productive agricultural land attached to the tomb; if so, the territory was perhaps circumscribed by a band of reedbeds and private roads of uniform width bordering the property. But since we know neither the purpose nor the original extent of the plan, the significance of the undifferentiated area outside the enclosed tomb garden remains a matter of speculation: the only features labeled on the plan are the public road, the ditch, and the stippled reedbeds.
The enclosed tomb garden, accessible only by an entranceway at the upper left corner (according to the orientation of the plan) and by a narrow door next to an aedicular structure outside the enclosure in the lower left of the plan, is characterized by a strict formality of design. The garden proper consists of eight rectangular plots marked with stippling, possibly flower beds or lawns, regularly disposed amid perfectly aligned single or triple rows of equidistant circular dots, probably representing trees. A double row of dots separated from the others along the upper perimeter perhaps represents a pergola or elevated walkway. The lower third of the enclosure is dominated by a large tower-tomb monument (perhaps 15 meters square at the base) apparently similar in form to a mausoleum near S. Maria Capua Vetere sketched by Pirro Ligorio and known as “La Conocchia” (“The Distaff”). The tower-tomb sits in the center of a rectangular courtyard bordered by a single row of trees (interrupted by the rear wall of the tomb) that form an ambulatory around the perimeter. The longest side of the courtyard, along the bottom of the plan, gave access to connecting service rooms aligned perpendicularly behind the shorter sides of the courtyard and, in the lower left, a rectangular aedicular building outside the entrance, possibly a funerary shrine or perhaps the custodian’s quarters.
The plan has been dated as early as the Augustan age (by Huelsen, who favored De Rossi’s fanciful attribution of the tomb complex to “Turia”, fragments of whose well known epitaph were found, similarly cut for reuse in covering loculi, in the same cemetery of Centocelle [cf. CIL 6.37053 with 1527, 31670]), but the scale of the complex and the design of the monument seem more compatible with a date later in the first or second century.
The Centocelle plan provides uniquely valuable, if ambiguous, evidence for the arrangement of the planting and the disposition of the monument within a Roman tomb garden (our other surviving plan of a tomb-garden complex [see Claudia Peloris] focuses on the internal articulation of the buildings), but it can hardly be considered typical: not only is the central monument of a form and type not found elsewhere in the region of Rome (the only known parallel is at Capua), but the size of the plot dwarfs all others known in central Italy and is second in area only to the thirty-five iugera (almost twenty acres) of farm land dedicated by a Roman knight at Parma to supporting his funerary celebrations (see C. Praeconius P.f. Ventilius Magnus). If the round dots do indeed represent trees and the stippled areas flower beds, the size of the area laid out primarily, it seems, for amenity (even if the trees bore fruit and the flowers produced garlands and perfume) is far larger than that of other attested funerary gardens in Italy that served primarily a decorative purpose. Productive funerary gardens of comparable and smaller area that we can identify elsewhere in Rome and Italy were normally equipped with work buildings (aedificia) and retail outlets (bars and shops, tabernae) (see vol. 2, XXX). The spaces on the plan flanking the courtyard and identified as storerooms could well have housed farming and gardening tools, but the footprint of the structure in the lower left corner seems ill-suited to the design of a tavern. More probably a collective monument (perhaps of a funerary collegium) than a familial tomb, the complex raises more questions than it resolves about the characteristic form and function of the Roman tomb garden (see no. XXX, funerary collegium of the Cocceii).
Dates The plan was dated as early as the Augustan age, the scale and design seem more later in the frist or second century.
Bibliography   J. Bodel, Roman Tomb Gardens, Cambridge University Press, 2018, pp. 222-224. link
  Ch. Hülsen, Piante iconografiche incise in marmo, BMDAI(R) 5 (1890): 46-63 worldcat
  H. von Hesberg, Römische Grundrissplane auf Marmor, in Bauplanung und Bautheorie der Antike (Berlin 1984) 121-24;worldcat
  M. Luni, Iscrizioni pubbliche ed iscrizioni relative ad edifici, in 1756-1986. Il Museo Archeologico di Urbino I (Urbino 1986) 167 figs. 6-7. worldcat
  R. Volpe,Cento anni a Centocelle: dal volo di Wilbur Wright ai recenti scavi, in Atti del Convegno Nazionale di Archeologia Aerea “100 anni di Archeologia Aerea in Italia&amp;rdquo; (Roma 15-17 aprile 2009), Archeologia Aerea 4-5, 2010-2011, pp.41-46. Fig. 3 worldcat
  Pleiades ID 811119037
Contributor John Bodel
Publication date 01 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Temple Tomb Garden of Q. Haterius Tychicus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_labicana/temple_tomb_garden_of_q._haterius_tychicus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_labicana/temple_tomb_garden_of_q._haterius_tychicus/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Via Labicana Temple Tomb Garden of Q. Haterius Tychicus
Sublocation Via Labicana
Sublocation Description An ancient Roman road connecting Rome and Labicum.
Garden Temple Tomb Garden of Q. Haterius Tychicus
Keywords  funerary buildings sepulchral monuments tombs villa garden pavilions  Garden Description One of the well-known reliefs from the tomb monument of the Haterii found in 1848 at a villa site after the fourth mile of the Via Labicana and depicting the temple tomb they adorned seems to represent schematically a garden and ornamental pavilion (diaeta) enclosed by a perimeter wall or fence in front of the tomb (Fig. XXX). The property evidently belonged to a building contractor, probably the redemptor Q. Haterius Tychicus (CIL 6.607, perhaps a freedman of Q. Haterius Antoninus, the consul of 53 CE), who participated in several prominent public building projects during the Flavian era and who erected his monument (to judge from the style of the relief decoration) during the Trajanic period. The tomb itself, built on an inset tufa base c. 3.5 meters square, partly out of peperino blocks, partly in reticulate work, and partly with brickwork, is almost wholly destroyed. In 1970, about ten meters from the tomb, new excavations at the site unearthed a dedication to Silvanus set up by two Q. Haterii (AE 1982, 78), probably at the boundary of the funerary garden represented in the relief by the enclosed pavilion. In the same garden was found the so-called urn of the Haterii, in all likelihood an elaborately sculpted fountain base.
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  G.-L. Gregori, Horti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, Bullettino della Commissione Archeologica Comunale di Roma worldcat  -F. Sinn and K. S. Freyberger, Vatikansiche Museen: Museo Gregorio Profano ex Lateranense: Dir Grabdenkmäler 2: Die Ausstatung des Hateriusgrabes, (Mainz 1996) 45-51, no. 5 (pl. 7, figs. 8-10). worldcat
Pleiades ID 229438406
Contributor John Bodel
Publication date 01 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of a Funerary Collegium</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_labicana/tomb_garden_of_a_funerary_collegium/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_labicana/tomb_garden_of_a_funerary_collegium/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Via Labicana Tomb Garden of a Funerary Collegium
Sublocation Via Labicana
Sublocation Description An ancient Roman road connecting Rome and Labicum.
Garden Tomb Garden of a Funerary Collegium
Keywords  crematories funerary buildings tombs  Garden Description A marble slab found at the cemetery of Centocelle and now preserved in the National Museum in Stockholm records the establishment in 16 CE of a funerary garden and various appurtenances by two senior officials of a funerary collegium and the clearing of an area beyond a perimeter wall for the construction of new crematories (ustrinae). The long commemorative text, our most detailed verbal record of the appointments of a Roman funerary garden, is worth quoting in full:
T. T. Coccei Gaa and Patiens, quaestors (of the funerary collegium) for the third time, according to the will of the decurions set up the square dining table in the pavilion (or, less probably, dining room), the sideboard and base, the sundial, the fountain basin with supports, the marble well, the stucco-work above the wall of the middle path with the tiled roof, the little travertine column beneath the sundial, the projecting eaves in front of the portico, the scales and weights. And, thanks to the kindness and generosity of their patron Titus, they undertook the clearing of a place behind the further perimeter wall and the transferring of the crematories from the furthest fence to there and the construction of a path there and a doorway. And the same men with public money decorated those places which their patron Titus had granted to the decurions with the seeds of vines and fruits and flowers and all sorts of greenery, in the consulship of Sisenna Taurus and L. Scribonius Libo.
T. T. Coccei Gaa et / Patiens quaest(ores) III ((tertio)) / mensam quadratam in trichil(a), / abacum cum basi, horologium, / labrum cum fulmentis, marmor /5 putiale, crustas supra parietem / itineris medi cum tegulis, columel/lam sub horologio Tiburtina(m?) 7 (sic) / protectum ante porticum, truti/nam et pondera d(e) d(ecurionum) s(ententia) posuerunt; / et locum post maceriam ulteriorem /10 emendum ustrinasque de consaepto / ultimo in eum locum traiciendas et / iter ad eum locum ianuamque bene/ficio et liberalitate T. patroni faci/enda curauerunt; /15 idemque uitium pomorumq(ue) et florum / uiridiumque omnium generum / seminibus ea loca quae T. p(atronus) decuri/onibus suis adtribuerat ex pecu/nia publica adornauerunt, /20 Sisenna Tauro L Scribonio Libone co(n)s(ulibus). /
The inscription concludes with eight hexameters urging readers to recognize in the expense incurred the just observance of piety and, for peace of mind, to follow the example of those who created and tended for the garden during their lifetimes so as to be remembered and cared for by others after their deaths (CLE 371). It is tempting to set the tomb complex of the funerary collegium described in this text in relation to the marble plan of a large tomb garden found also found in the Centocello cemetery and now in Urbino (no. XXX), but the references to ustrinae accessed by a path and gate, “the wall of a middle path with a tiled roof”, and projecting eaves in front of a portico are difficult to reconcile with the markings on the marble plan. If the two records do concern the same cemetery complex, the plan does not seem to depict the part of it described in the inscription of the collegium.
Dates 16 CE
Bibliography   B. E. Thomasson and M. Pavese,A Survey of Greek and Latin Inscriptions on Stone in Swedish Collections, (Stockholm 1997) XXX worldcat
  G.-L. Gregori, Horti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, Bullettino della Commissione Archeologica Comunale di Roma worldcat
  L. Chioffi, Epigrafia e insediamenti: Il caso del suburbio di Roma, in La forma della città e del territorio (Atlante Tematico di Topografia Antica V Supplemento), edited by S. Quilici Gigli (Rome, 1999) 53 n. 9.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 229438405
Contributor John Bodel
Publication date 01 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Anonymous</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_labicana/tomb_garden_of_anonymous/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_labicana/tomb_garden_of_anonymous/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Via Labicana Tomb Garden of Anonymous
Sublocation Via Labicana
Sublocation Description An ancient Roman road connecting Rome and Labicum.
Garden Tomb Garden of Anonymous
Keywords  epitaphs sepulchral monuments tombs  Garden Description A fragmentary marble slab found beside the Via Labicana near the cemetery of Centocelle and recording the end of an epitaph addressed in part to an Aurelius identifies a cepotaphium in the formulaic clause prohibiting misuse or alienation of the tomb property.
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  G.-L. Gregori, Horti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, Bullettino della Commissione Archeologica Comunale di Roma worldcat  Pleiades ID 60995119
Contributor John Bodel
Publication date 01 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Aur(elius) Inachus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_appia/tomb_garden_of_aurelius-inachus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_appia/tomb_garden_of_aurelius-inachus/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location VIA APPIA Tomb Garden of Aur(elius) Inachus
Sublocation Via Appia
Sublocation Description An early Roman road (via publica) originating at Rome and terminating at Brundisium, the Via Appia was begun in the fourth century B.C. by the censor Appius Claudius Caecus. The Latin author Statius described the Via Appia as &amp;ldquo;queen of the long roads&amp;rdquo;.
Garden Tomb Garden of Aur(elius) Inachus
Keywords  tombs  Garden Description An inscription found beside the Via Appia near the tomb of Cecelia Metella in 1851 identifies a cepotaphium belonging to Aur(elius) Inachus, a freedman of one of the Antonine emperors (probably Commodus), who served as assistant to the messengers at the office of the emperor’s private accounts, and to Aurelia Macariane, Aurelia Rodogune, and their freedmen and freedwomen and descendants (CIL 6.8505 cf. p. 3459). The womens’ names are unusual: “R(h)odogune” is recorded only once elsewhere at Rome; “Macariane” (the not uncommon “Macaria” plus a suffix modeled on “Rodogune”?) appears to be otherwise unattested. The absence of a praenomen from Inachus’s name and the abbreviation of his gentilicium point to a date in the first half of the third century.
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography   J. Bodel, Roman Tomb Gardens, Cambridge University Press, 2018, p. 236. link
  G.-L. Gregori , SHorti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, Bullettino della Commissione Archeologica Comunale di Roma” worldcat
  Pleiades ID 811119037
Contributor J Bodel  Publication date 01 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of C. Nonius Minyas</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_ardeatina/tomb_garden_of_c._nonius_minyas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_ardeatina/tomb_garden_of_c._nonius_minyas/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location VIA ARDEATINA Tomb Garden of C. Nonius Minyas
Sublocation Via Ardeatina
Sublocation Description The Via Ardeatina connected Rome and Ardea.
Garden Tomb Garden of C. Nonius Minyas
Keywords  funerary buildings tombs  Garden Description An epitaph the late first or second century found near the intersection of the Via Ardeatina and the ancient road corresponding to the modern Via delle Sette Chiese identifies an estate or farm of Merops or Merope (horti or fundus Meropianus), perhaps the imperial freedman Ti. Claudius Merops, who served as procurator for the regions of Rome some time in the Julio-Claudian era (CIL 6.4018), and near it a large walled funerary garden (280 Roman feet wide and 360 feet deep, about two acres in area) with service building built by C. Nonius Minyas, who provided access to it through the larger entry gate to the fundus Meropianus. Among funerary gardens of known dimensions in Italy, Minyas’s ranks in the top quartile (see vol. 1 “Tomb Gardens” fig. 8).
Dates late first or second century
Bibliography   CIL 6.23090 (pp. 3529, 3917); ILS 8345; J. Bodel, Roman Tomb Gardens, Cambridge University Press, 2018, pp. 225, 236. link
  A. Carandini , SHortensia: orti e frutteti intorno a Roma, in Misurare la terra: centuriazione e coloni nel mondo romano. città, agricoltura, commercio: materiali da Roma e suburbia (Rome, 1985) 69; L. Avetta, in S. Panciera, ed., La collezione epigrafica dei Musei Capitolini (Tituli 6) (Rome 1987), 281 (Tav. XLIV, fig. 4), cf. 334 no. 334 worldcat
  G.-L. Gregori, Horti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, Bullettino della Commissione Archeologica Comunale di Roma worldcat
  G.Tomasetti, Iscrizione della via Ardeatina, Bulletino dell’instituto di Corrispondenza archeologica 8.9 (1875), pp.205-206.worldcat
  Pleiades ID 195817642
Contributor John Bodel
Publication date 01 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Claudia Semne</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_appia/tomb_garden_of_claudia_semne/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_appia/tomb_garden_of_claudia_semne/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location VIA APPIA Tomb Garden of Claudia Semne
Sublocation Via Appia
Sublocation Description An early Roman road (via publica) originating at Rome and terminating at Brundisium, the Via Appia was begun in the fourth century B.C. by the censor Appius Claudius Caecus. The Latin author Statius described the Via Appia as &amp;ldquo;queen of the long roads&amp;rdquo;.
Garden Tomb Garden of Claudia Semne
Keywords  aediculae funerary buildings pavilions tombs vineyard  Garden Description Four inscriptions unearthed in 1792 between the second and third mile of the Via Appia near S. Sebastiano identify the tomb garden complex of Claudia Semne, wife of M. Ulpius Crotonensis, a freedman of the emperor Trajan (CIL 6.15592-155495; ILS 8063c). According to the principal text (CIL 6.15593), the rectangular tomb monument (c. 3.1 x 3.8 m.) was surrounded by an enclosed garden (hortus) in which were “pavilions (tricliae), a little vineyard (viniola), a well (puteum), and shrines (aediculae) in which statues of Claudia in the likeness of the gods (in formam deorum)” were housed. Within the tomb were two inscribed funerary altars, one dedicated to Fortuna, Spes, Venus, and the memory of Claudia Semne (CIL 6.15594), the other to the couple’s freeborn son (CIL 6.15595), who died at the age of eighteen; and, probably, a statuette of Claudia Semne with the attributes of Spes and three busts of Semne and her son, which were found nearby. The tomb itself was richly decorated by Crotonensis with reliefs and portrait statuary associating wife and son with their divine counterparts, Venus and a young hunter (perhaps Meleager or Adonis). A pair of statuettes of the son wearing a toga and holding a book roll and box probably flanked the entrance to the tomb. In this paradeigmatic context of private deification, the garden was perhaps meant to evoke a Hellenistic funerary paradeisos and its associations with the divine afterlife, but pavilions, wells, and vineyards were standard appurtenances of the Roman funerary garden as well. The style of the sculptural decoration points to a date around 130 CE.
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography   Bignamini, Ilaria, and Amanda Claridge， The Tomb of Claudia Semne and Excavations in Eighteenth-Century Rome. Papers of the British School at Rome 66 (1998): 215-44. Accessed December 1, 2020. link
  G.-L. Gregori , SHorti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, Bullettino della Commissione Archeologica Comunale di Roma” worldcat
  H. Wrede,Das Mausoleum des Claudia Semne und die bürgerliche Plastik der Kaiserzeit,MDAI(R) 78 (1971): 125-66;worldcat
  J. Bodel, Roman Tomb Gardens, Cambridge University Press, 2018, p. 208-209. link
  Pleiades ID 537932155
Contributor John Bodel
Publication date 01 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of M. Aurel(ius) Alexander</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_ardeatina/tomb_garden_of_m._aurelius_alexander/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_ardeatina/tomb_garden_of_m._aurelius_alexander/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location VIA ARDEATINA Tomb Garden of M. Aurel(ius) Alexander
Sublocation Via Ardeatina
Sublocation Description The Via Ardeatina connected Rome and Ardea.
Garden Tomb Garden of M. Aurel(ius) Alexander
Keywords  aediculae funerary buildings tombs domus  Garden Description An epitaph of the late second or early third century found in 1715 between the first and second mile of the Via Ardeatina near the church of S. Balbina records that a senior centurion and Roman knight, M. Aurelius Alexander detached from his house (domus, rather than horti, the expanding urban environment having now encompassed this suburban zone) a cepotaphium made for himself and his wife, Aurelia Antiochiana, their freedmen and descendents. A final injunction aiming to prevent alienation of the property by any means idly threatened transgressors with a fine of 100,000 sesterces (!), to be paid in to the sacred treasury.
Dates late second or early third century
Bibliography   J. Bodel, Roman Tomb Gardens, Cambridge University Press, 2018, p. 236. link
  G.-L. Gregori , SHorti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, Bullettino della Commissione Archeologica Comunale di Roma worldcat
  Pleiades ID 390400921
Contributor John Bodel
Publication date 01 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Terentia</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_aurelia/tomb_garden_of_terentia/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_aurelia/tomb_garden_of_terentia/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Via Aurelia Tomb Garden of C. Nonius Minyas
Sublocation Via Aurelia
Sublocation Description An ancient Roman road begun ca. 241 B.C. by the censor C. Aurelius Cotta.
Garden Tomb Garden of Terentia
Keywords  epitaphs tombs  Garden Description A fragmentary (and probably reused) epitaph, probably of the first or second century CE, found in the catacombs of Calepodio beside the Via Aurelia identifies a cepota[phium] of Terentia.
Bibliography   J. Bodel, Roman Tomb Gardens, Cambridge University Press, 2018, pp. 225, 237. link
  G.-L. Gregori, Horti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, Bullettino della Commissione Archeologica Comunale di Roma worldcat
  Pleiades ID 283772837
Contributor John Bodel
Publication date 01 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Memorial Tomb Garden of Ortorius Heleis and Ortoria Eutychis</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_latina/memorial_tomb_garden_of_ortorius_heleis_and_ortoria_eutychis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_latina/memorial_tomb_garden_of_ortorius_heleis_and_ortoria_eutychis/</guid>
      <description>Province italia
Location via latina
via latina (Pleiades)
Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Memorial Tomb Garden of Ortorius Heleis and Ortoria Eutychis
Keywords  tombs  Garden Description An inscribed marble plaque found in the early 1930s covering a drain near Ponte Lungo in the region of the Via Tuscolana south of Rome records the epitaph of a Greek-speaking couple, Ortorios Heleis and Ortoria Eutychis, evidently devotees of the cult of Isis, who some time during the second or early third century built for their ten-year old son Markos Ortorios Eleutheros “an eternal bridal chamber” (aionion nymphona) and “for themselves, in expectation of their death, and for their freedmen and their descendants, a memorial tomb garden” ([mne]meion kepotaphon). The inscription, which includes a prayer to Osiris to grant the boy cool water in the afterlife, dwells on the son’s untimely death and his parents bereavement.
Maps Plans Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  J. M. C. Toynbee, Death and Burial in the Roman World, Print book : English : Hopkins pb. ed., 96 and n. 312. worldcat G.-L. Gregori, Horti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, Article : Italian, BCom 92 (1987-88) [1989] 180 n. 37. worldcat  Pleiades ID 93042695
TGN ID 6006328
Contributor Pier Giorgio Monti (ORCID: 0000-0001-7719-0920)
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of (Cl)oelia Tyche and (C)loelia Faustina</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/unknown_provenance/tomb_garden_of_cloelia_tyche_and_cloelia_faustina/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/unknown_provenance/tomb_garden_of_cloelia_tyche_and_cloelia_faustina/</guid>
      <description>Province italia
Location Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Tomb Garden of (Cl)oelia Tyche and (C)loelia Faustina
Keywords  tombs epitaphs  Garden Description The lower right portion of a marble slab found in the vicinity of the Via del Mare outside Rome records an epitaph of the late first or second century dedicated to a mother, [Cl]oelia Tyche, and sister, [C]loelia Faustina, and their freedmen and freedwomen, and declaring that the property, which comprised “a tomb monument and building and garden enclosed by a wall” (hoc monimentum et aedificium et hortum, ita uti maceria clusum est), would not pass to the heir.
Maps Plans Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  G. Vergantini, La collezione epigrafica dei Musei Capitolini: Inediti – revisioni –contributi al riordino, (Tituli 6), edited by S. Panciera (Rome 1987) 152-53 n. 72, Tav. XXXIX, 4. worldcat G.-L. Gregori, Horti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, BCom 92 (1987-88) [1989] 176 n. 4. worldcat  Pleiades ID TGN ID Contributor Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Anonymous</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/unknown_provenance/tomb_garden_of_anonymous/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/unknown_provenance/tomb_garden_of_anonymous/</guid>
      <description>Province italia
Location Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Tomb Garden of Attia Quintilla
Keywords  tombs epitaphs  Garden Description A fragmentary opisthographic slab of unknown urban provenance, now in the Lapidario Profano ex Lateranense of the Vatican Museums, records an anonymous epitaph dedicating to the dedicator and his household a tomb garden (cepotafi[um]) and tomb monument with a building.
Maps Plans Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  G.-L. Gregori, Horti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, BCom 92 (1987-88) [1989] 177 n. 10. worldcat  Pleiades ID TGN ID Contributor Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Anonymous</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_praenestina/tomb_garden_of_anonymous/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_praenestina/tomb_garden_of_anonymous/</guid>
      <description>Province italia
Location via latina
via latina (Pleiades)
Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Tomb Garden of Anonymous
Keywords  tombs  Garden Description A funerary plaque (evidently complete) discovered in 1861 beside the Via Praenestina near Tor Sapienza records the dimensions of a tomb plot “with a garden enclosed by a wall” eighty-one and a half feet in frontage, forty-three and a half feet in depth (c. 320 square meters).
Maps Plans Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  G.-L. Gregori, Horti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, Article : Italian, BCom 92 (1987-88) [1989][1989] 178 n. 20. worldcat  Pleiades ID 93042695
TGN ID 6006328
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Attia Quintilla</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/unknown_provenance/tomb_garden_of_attia_quintilla/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/unknown_provenance/tomb_garden_of_attia_quintilla/</guid>
      <description>Province italia
Location Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Tomb Garden of Attia Quintilla
Keywords  tombs epitaphs  Garden Description A handsome marble funerary altar of unknown but presumably urban provenance, now in the Louvre, decorated on the front with Erotes holding garlands and on the sides with storks and other birds records the epitaph of Attia T. f. Quintilla set up by her father, Attius Phlegon, her mother Attia Quinta (probably both ex-slaves), and her brother Attius T. f. Quintianus. Along with the monument, which can be dated to the first or early second century, Quintilla’s parents and brother also dedicated to her and to their descendants and the freedmen and freedwomen of their household “a field or garden (agrum sive hortum) with a building, enclosed by a wall”.The building, a substantial structure of some thirteen rooms, seems to comprise, on the ground floor, a series of three work rooms opening off a central corridor that leads directly through the house from front to back, a two-room suite separately accessible from the front porch (perhaps the residence of the gardner and overseer of the tomb), and a stairway to the upper floor. The upper floor presents a more seigneural aspect: in addition to two large rooms and a pair of small functional rooms corresponding to those on the first floor, the residential space includes a narrow rectangular room or balcony over the entranceway and a two-room suite and a separate room built out above the rear service court and overlooking the garden. A broad passageway eleven feet wide along the side of the building seems to allow for a wagon to be backed into position for loading directly from the garden. The dimensions of the rooms inscribed along most of the interior walls indicate that the three building plans are not drawn to the same scale, and it is not clear how the two structures were situated in relation to each other. The configuration of the aedificium and garden suggests the arrangements of a working kitchen garden with related workspaces on the ground floor and a residential and dining area on the upper floor, perhaps for the use of family members celebrating communal meals at the tomb site during the annual Parentalia and other festivals of the dead. The cepotaphium dedicated by C. Cominius Abascantus at Puteoli in 148 CE provided for the town magistrates and officers of the Augustales to dine annually at the site in a dining room above his tomb (no. XXX).
Maps Plans Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  W. Altmann, Die römischen Grabaltäre der Kaiserzeit, (Berlin 1905) 168 no. 214; S. worldcat S. Ducroix, Catalogue analytique des inscriptions latines sur pierre conservées au Musée du Louvre, (Paris 1975) 96 no. 314. worldcat D. Boschung, Antike Grabaltäre aus den Nekropolen Roms, (Acta Bernensia X) (Bern 1987) 107 no. 329, Taf. worldcat G.-L. Gregori, Horti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, BCom 92 (1987-88) [1989] 177 n. 9. worldcat  Pleiades ID TGN ID Contributor Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of C. Hostius Pamphilus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/unknown_provenance/tomb_garden_of_c._hostius_pamphilus/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/unknown_provenance/tomb_garden_of_c._hostius_pamphilus/</guid>
      <description>Province italia
Location Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Tomb Garden of C. Hostius Pamphilus
Keywords  tombs epitaphs  Garden Description A travertine slab of unknown urban provenance, now in the Mus-ei Capitolini, records an epitaph of the mid first century BCE of a freedman doctor, C. Hostius C.l. Pamphilus, who bought a tomb (thirteen by twenty-four feet in area) for himself and his wife Nelpia M. l. Hymnis, and for their freedmen and their descendants. A crude verse (almost a septenarius) following the dedication declares “this is our eternal home, this our farm, these our gardens (horti), this our monument”. It is unclear whether horti here refers to a tomb garden or, perhaps more probably, to a suburban estate, as normally in contemporary fashionable usage. The ambivalence of the term in any case draws a link, conceptual as well as topographical, between productive rural property (fundus) and a burial monument conceived of as a home for the deceased. If horti refers to a tomb garden proper, it would be among the earliest attested in the environs of Rome.
Maps Plans Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  M. Mattei, Testimonianze epigrafiche e attestazioni letterarie relative all’area degli Horti Lamiani, in Le tranquille dimore degli dei, edited by M. Cima and E. La Rocca (Venice 1986) 153-54 fig. 103. worldcat G.-L. Gregori, Horti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, BCom 92 (1987-88) [1989] 178 n. 21, 179 fig. 2; J. worldcat Bodel, Monumental Villas and Villa Monuments, JRA 10 (1997) 26. worldcat  Pleiades ID TGN ID Contributor Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Claudia Peloris</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/unknown_provenance/tomb_garden_of_claudia_peloris/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/unknown_provenance/tomb_garden_of_claudia_peloris/</guid>
      <description>Province italia
Location Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Tomb Garden of Claudia Peloris
Keywords  tombs epitaphs  Garden Description A marble plaque now in the archaeological museum of Perugia but probably of urban origin records the epitaph of a freedwoman of Octavia, the daughter of the deified emperor Claudius, Claudia Peloris, and her husband, also an imperial freedman and procurator of the Augusti, Ti. Claudius Eutychus, who left to her sisters and freedwomen and their descendants charge of a building (aedificium) and tomb monument (monumentum). An inscribed plan at the center of the plaque depicting different sections of a building and tomb complex (evidently the ones specified in the text) shows, at the right, a walled tomb enclosure, with the monument built into the rear wall and a corridor leading off the left side of the forecourt to a stair descending perpendicularly to an undergound burial chamber below; at the left, the ground floor of a two storey building (the set of rooms depicted at the top of the plan represents the second floor) with a roughly rectangular walled garden (70 X 76 X 65 X 65 Roman feet, some 410 square meters), opening off the rear (Fig. XXX). The building, a substantial structure of some thirteen rooms, seems to comprise, on the ground floor, a series of three work rooms opening off a central corridor that leads directly through the house from front to back, a two-room suite separately accessible from the front porch (perhaps the residence of the gardner and overseer of the tomb), and a stairway to the upper floor. The upper floor presents a more seigneural aspect: in addition to two large rooms and a pair of small functional rooms corresponding to those on the first floor, the residential space includes a narrow rectangular room or balcony over the entranceway and a two-room suite and a separate room built out above the rear service court and overlooking the garden. A broad passageway eleven feet wide along the side of the building seems to allow for a wagon to be backed into position for loading directly from the garden. The dimensions of the rooms inscribed along most of the interior walls indicate that the three building plans are not drawn to the same scale, and it is not clear how the two structures were situated in relation to each other. The configuration of the aedificium and garden suggests the arrangements of a working kitchen garden with related workspaces on the ground floor and a residential and dining area on the upper floor, perhaps for the use of family members celebrating communal meals at the tomb site during the annual Parentalia and other festivals of the dead. The cepotaphium dedicated by C. Cominius Abascantus at Puteoli in 148 CE provided for the town magistrates and officers of the Augustales to dine annually at the site in a dining room above his tomb (no. XXX).
Maps Plans Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Ch. Hülsen, Piante iconografiche incise in marmo, MDAI(R) 5 (1890) 46-52 and Tav. III; H. von Hesberg. worldcat H. von Hesberg, Römische Grundrissplane auf Marmor, in Bauplanung und Bautheorie der Antike (Berlin 1983) 124-26. worldcat G.-L. Gregori, Horti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, BCom 92 (1987-88) [1989] 181 fig. 3, 184. worldcat  Pleiades ID TGN ID Contributor Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of M. Aurelius Syntomus and Aurelia Marciane</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_praenestina/tomb_garden_of_m.aurelius_syntomus_and_aurelia_marciane/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_praenestina/tomb_garden_of_m.aurelius_syntomus_and_aurelia_marciane/</guid>
      <description>Province italia
Location via praenestina
via praenestina (Pleiades)
Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Tomb Garden of M. Aurelius Syntomus and Aurelia Marciane
Keywords  tombs  Garden Description A marble slab found in 1745 near a circular tomb monument beside the Via Praenestina at the first mile from the Porta Maggiore records “a building with tomb garden (cepotaphium) and monument (memoria)” built up from the ground by M. Aurelius Syntomus and his wife Aurelia Marciane for themselves, their son and daughter, and their freedmen and descendants, probably some time in the late second or third century.
Maps Plans Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  G.-L. Gregori, Horti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, Article : Italian, BCom 92 (1987-88) [1989] 176 n. 7. worldcat  Pleiades ID 108896
TGN ID 7208125
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of P. Sullius Zoticus and Sullia Nice</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/unknown_provenance/tomb_garden_of_p._sullius_zoticus_and_sullia_nice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/unknown_provenance/tomb_garden_of_p._sullius_zoticus_and_sullia_nice/</guid>
      <description>Province italia
Location Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Tomb Garden of (Cl)oelia Tyche and (C)loelia Faustina
Keywords  tombs epitaphs  Garden Description A marble slab of unknown urban provenance broken at the bottom and long lost records an epitaph of the first or second century erected by P. Sullius Zoticus and his wife Sullia Nice to themselves, their children, their freedmen and freedwomen and their descendants; to “another wife” of Zoticus, Iulia Tatiane; and (it seems) to a Sullius Istefanus. The epitaph concludes with provision for a fine to be paid to the treasury of the pontiffs and the Vestal Virgins by any who attempt to alienate the tomb and surrounding property, which comprised “a garden with cistern enclosed by a surrounding wall” (in conti[nenti] / hortulu(m) maceria clus[um] / at cisterna(m) perten[dentem]).
Maps Plans Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  G.-L. Gregori, Horti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, BCom 92 (1987-88) [1989] 177 n. 11. worldcat  Pleiades ID TGN ID Contributor Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Q(uintius) Medicus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_tiburtina/tomb_garden_of_quintius_medicus/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/tomb_garden_near_rome/via_tiburtina/tomb_garden_of_quintius_medicus/</guid>
      <description>Province italia
Location via tiburtina
via tiburtina (Pleiades)
Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Tomb Garden of Q(uintius) Medicus
Keywords  tombs  Garden Description An opisthographic marble slab found reused for a Christian tomb (ICUR 8842) in the catacombs of S. Cyriaca on the Via Tiburtina records the epitaph of an imperial freedman, Q(uintius) Medicus, who some time during the first or second century built a tomb garden (cepotafiu(m)) for himself and granted possession of it to his daughter, Quinta Vitalis.
Maps Plans Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  G.-L. Gregori, Horti sepulchrales e cepotaphia nelle iscrizioni urbane, Article : Italian, BCom 92 (1987-88) [1989] 182 n. 48. worldcat  Pleiades ID 272213281
TGN ID Contributor Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Iul(ia) Victorin(a) in Scarbantia</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/scarbantia/scarbantia_tomb_garden_of_iulia_victorina/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 10:08:21 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/scarbantia/scarbantia_tomb_garden_of_iulia_victorina/</guid>
      <description>Province Pannonia
Location Scarbantia
Scarbantia (Pleiades)
Garden Tomb Garden of Iul(ia) Victorin(a) in Scarbantia
Keywords  epitaphs literary garden stelae tombs viridarium  Garden Description A limestone funerary stele of probably third century date unearthed in 1973 near Scarbantia at Winder am See (Burgenland) and now in the Burgenländische Landesmuseum at Eisenstadt records an epitaph set up by Septimius Alcides, a veteran of the legio XIII Gemina Iulia, for his wife, Iul(ia) Victorin(a), dead at thirty, for whom he built at his own expense a funerary pleasure garden (viridarium).
Maps Dates 3rd century
Bibliography  AE 1973, 433. Epigraphische Datenbank Heidelberg HD011378.  Pleiades ID 197501
TGN ID 4008442
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 22 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Fl(avius) Dalmatius in Savaria</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/savaria/savaria_tomb_garden_of_flavius_dalmatius/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 09:49:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/savaria/savaria_tomb_garden_of_flavius_dalmatius/</guid>
      <description>Province Pannonia
Location Savaria
Savaria (Pleiades)
Garden Tomb Garden of Fl(avius) Dalmatius in Savaria
Keywords  epitaphs inscription literary garden tombs  Garden Description A limestone slab found near the monastery of St. Martin in Szombathely (Savaria), Hungary, in 1845 and subsequently transferred to the National Museum in Budapest records the epitaph of a high ranking equestrian official (vir perfectissimus), Fl(avius) Dalmatius, and his wife Aur(elia) Iulia, who some time during the third or fourth century built a tomb on their villa estate and composed for it a verse inscription in which Dalmatius hopes for commemoration from a future owner of the property: “Whoever will be master of this house and garden after me, gather the nearby roses for me, put out the white lilies which the green garden will grow for me: these are the gifts of the blessed” (Quisquis {h}e(ris) post me d(o)m(inus) Laris huius et (h)orti, / vicinas mihi carpe rosas, mihi lilia pone / [ca]ndeda{s} q(uae) viridis dabit (h)ortulus: ista (sc. munera) beat(or)um). A freedman Volussius and freedwoman Sabatia saw to the erection of the inscription and monument. On the basis of the final platitude, with its reference to “the blessed” (beati), Diehl considered Dalmatius and his wife to be Christians. For Adamik, on the other hand, commemoration with flowers, a practice condemned by Christian writers as idolatrous, points to a pagan context. The phrasing of the hexameters reveals familiarity also with Roman literary conventions of funerary commemoration (cf. Martial 1.61.3, quiquis eris nostri post me regnator agelli&amp;hellip;).Whatever the religious beliefs of Dalmatius and his wife, the equipping of their tomb with a funerary garden to support commemorative celebrations at the site is fully in keeping with the literary pretensions of their epitaph in representing the couple as fully assimilated and sophisticated Romans.
Maps Dates 3rd or 4th century
Bibliography  CIL 3.4185. CLE 578. ILCV 296. A. Mócsy and T. Szentléleky, Die römischen Steindenkmäler von Savaria. Amsterdam, 1971, p. 117, no. 161, photo 143. (worldcat) T. Adamik,Archaeologiai Ertesítö 110, 1983:3-9 = AE 1984:722.  Pleiades ID 197498
TGN ID 4008442
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 22 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Ti. Claudios Lykos</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/macedonia/thessaloniki/thessaloniki_tomb_garden_of_tib_claudios_lykos/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 09:07:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/macedonia/thessaloniki/thessaloniki_tomb_garden_of_tib_claudios_lykos/</guid>
      <description>Province Macedonia
Location Thessaloniki
Thessaloniki (Pleiades)
Garden Tomb Garden of Ti. Claudios Lykos
Keywords  tombs sarcophagi epitaphs  Garden Description A limestone sarcophagus found at Thessaloniki and first reported in 1962 preserves an epitaph set up in 147 A.D. by Ti. Claudios Lykos, a local town counselor (bouleutÆw), for himself, his loving wife Meinoukia (Minucia) Theoprepes, and his two daughters Roda and Theoprepes. As Robert correctly observed (Bull. Épigr. 1963:134), the garbled inscription—a product, it seems, of two drafts of the text being confused by the carver—nonetheless makes clear that Lykos had built a tomb garden complex, which he calls a ≤r“on, comprising “a field, house, garden, and, burial place” (égrÒw, oﬁk€a, k∞pow, tÒpow), in which were situated various sarcophagi (lhnÒi) and statues (éndriãntew) and which he attempted to prevent from future alienation. Two other inscriptions found in the same complex identify Lykos as granting, in one case, a cinerary urn (kaÊstra), in the other, in 167 A.D., a burial place (tÒpow) to others for their monuments. A secondary inscription on the cover of Lykos’s sarcophagus attests its reuse later in the third century. Robert and Kubińska considered the “house” (oﬁk€a) to be that of a gardener appointed to oversee the garden complex, but the traditional formulaic pairing of field and house, garden and tomb attested elsewhere (at the tomb gardens of C. Hostius Pamphilus at Rome [cross-ref, XXX] and of C. [Ma?]rcius C. l. Cleon at Bari [cross-ref XXX]) suggests that it is Lykos’s own house that is meant and, perhaps, that the tomb garden is located on its property. For the conventional “tomb” (tãfow, sepulchrum, monumentum) Lykos substitutes “burial place” (tÒpow, Latin locus, as in l(ocus) d(atus) d(ecreto) d(ecurionum), a formula for awarding honorific burials with which Lykos the decurion was assuredly familiar), but his conformity to the traditional conceptual juxtapositions is apparent. To judge from the presence of statues and more than one sarcophagus, and from the granting of burial space to others, Lykos’s funerary garden was a substantial complex.
Maps Images Dates 147 CE, 167 CE
Bibliography : IG X 2,1.608; J. Kubińska, Les monuments funéraires dans les inscriptions grecques de l’Asie Mineure. Warsaw, 1968, p. 146; P. Petsas, “AgrÒw, oﬁk€a, k∞pow, tÒpow,” in J. H. Dell, ed. Macedonian Studies in Honor of Charles F. Edson. Thessaloniki, 1981, pp. 295-98; Bull. Épigr. 1963, 134; 1984, 252.
Pleiades ID 491741
TGN ID 7011182
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 16 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cemetery Garden of Metrodorus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/dalmatia/salona/salona_cemetery_garden_of_metrodorus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 10:10:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/dalmatia/salona/salona_cemetery_garden_of_metrodorus/</guid>
      <description>Province Dalmatia
Location Salona
Salona (Pleiades)
Sublocation Garden Cemetery Garden of Metrodorus
Keywords  tombs epitaphs sarcophagi (coffins)  Garden Description A sarcophagus found at Salona in 1824, transported to the museum in Split, and subsequently lost bore an inscription recording the donation by Aur(elius) Aprilianus to Aur(elius) Amurus and Aur(elia) Quinta of a sarcophagus “which is in the garden of Metrodorus” and specifying that it was put into position while they were still alive (Aur(elius) Aprilianus se vivo donavet arcam Aur(elio) Amuro et Aur(eliae) Quinte que est in orto Metrodori. Vivi sibi posuerunt…). The find spot of the sarcophagus is not known, but Wilkes plausibly associates the garden of Metrodorus with a walled cemetery a hundred meters outside the city gate on the north side of the road leading west from town, which comprises a number of individual familial plots marked out by dividing walls within an area enclosed by a massive masonry perimeter built of blocks more than four meters long. The garden of Metrodorus was perhaps home also to the monument of Iulia Mutiana erected “among the sarcophagi in the middle in the garden, near the road, overlooking the old (?) courtyard (or seed bed)” (see the preceding entry): the two inscriptions belong broadly to the same period (the latter second or third century) and might well be contemporary with each other.
Maps Plans Images Dates Late second or third century (CE)
Bibliography  CIL 3.2207 M. Abramic´, VAHD 52, 1935-49:1-18 J. J. Wilkes, Dalmatia. London, 1969, pp. 360-61, fig. 16.  Pleiades ID 197488
TGN ID 7017320
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 15 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden with Monument of Julia Mutiana</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/dalmatia/salona/salona_tomb_garden_with_monument_of_julia_mutiana/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 17:06:21 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/dalmatia/salona/salona_tomb_garden_with_monument_of_julia_mutiana/</guid>
      <description>Province Dalmatia
Location Salona
Salona (Pleiades)
Sublocation Garden Tomb Garden and Pool of Cingius Iustinus
Keywords  tombs epitaphs  Garden Description An inscription reported among those of Salona records an epitaph set up by Iulia Mutiana for herself and her husband Aur(elius) Pateas in a place granted her by A. Aelius Marullinus “among the sarcophagi in the middle in the garden, near the road, overlooking the old (?) courtyard (or seed bed)” (inter arcas in medio in horto at viam prospicientem in areolam vet(erem ?)). The specification of a location within the garden, the mention of (other) sarcophagi, and the concession of Marullinus suggest that the cemetery was extensive and perhaps public. The term areola used to describe the area overlooked by Mutiana’s monument generally means “courtyard” in architectural contexts (e.g. CIL 6.9077), “garden plot” or “seed bed” in agricultural ones (e.g. Columella 5.12.3, 10.362, 11.2.75). It is difficult to know which sense is to be preferred here. Whatever its character, Mommsen questioned the description of the areola as “old” (vet(erem)) and proposed an alternative reading “behind” (ret(ro)), unnecessarily, it seems. Nomenclature and circumstance (inhumation burial) point to a date in the second half of the second or the third century.
Maps Plans Images Dates Second half of the second or the third century (CE)
Bibliography  CIL 3.2397.  Pleiades ID 197488
TGN ID 7017320
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 14 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden and Pool of Cingius Iustinus</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/dalmatia/salona/salona_tomb_garden_and_pool_of_cingius_iustinus/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 16:52:02 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/dalmatia/salona/salona_tomb_garden_and_pool_of_cingius_iustinus/</guid>
      <description>Province Dalmatia
Location Salona
Salona (Pleiades)
Sublocation Garden Tomb Garden and Pool of Cingius Iustinus
Keywords  piscinae tombs epitaphs  Garden Description A rock cut inscription at Salonae marks the spot where some time in the late second or third century Cingius Iustinus made a fishpond or pool (piscina) in the garden of his wife Aelia Licinia for her and for himself (fecit piscinam in horto Aeliae Liciniae coiugi incomparabili et sibi). No tomb is mentioned, but the dedication D(is) M(anibus) identifies the text as an epitaph and thus points to a funerary context.
Maps Plans Images Dates Late second or third century (CE)
Bibliography  CIL 3.2279  Pleiades ID 197488
TGN ID 7017320
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 14 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Anonymous Gaul in Andematunnum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/andematunnum/andematunnum_tomb_garden_of_anonymous_gaul/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2020 10:33:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_superior/andematunnum/andematunnum_tomb_garden_of_anonymous_gaul/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania Superior
Location Andematunnum
Andematunnum (Pleiades)
Garden Tomb Garden of Anonymous Gaul in Andematunnum
Keywords  former reservoirs inscription literary garden mausoleums orchards tombs  Garden Description A famous inscription from the territory of the Lingonian Gauls (Langres) known only from a manuscript of the tenth century records the will of a local hunting enthusiast who built for himself a lavish mausoleum (cella memoriae) and equipped it with orchards (pomaria) and a reservoir (lacus) put in the care of two freedmen who are instructed to devote the revenues from them to upkeep of the tomb complex, and three landscape gardeners (topiarii) and their apprentices, each to be supported annually by the testator’s grandson, Sex. Iulius Aquila, and his heirs. The will goes on to provide for annual banquets at the tomb site, to be funded by Aquila and his heirs (not explicitly from proceeds of the orchards), and to ensure that any deviations from the testator’s prescriptions be undertaken only in order that the complex be better adorned, better planted, and better perfected (nisi..ut melius colantur et conserantur perficianturque).
Maps Images Dates unspecified
Bibliography  CIL 13.5708. EDCS-19800561 ILS 8379. FIRA III 49. J.-J. Hatt, La tombe gallo-romaine (Paris 1951) 65-84. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 177441
TGN ID 6002235
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 13 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Garden of Ael(ius) Iul(ius) Iulianus, Decurion in Romula</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/dacia_traiana/romula/romula_tomb_garden_of_aelius_iulius_iulianus_decurion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 07:56:03 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/dacia_traiana/romula/romula_tomb_garden_of_aelius_iulius_iulianus_decurion/</guid>
      <description>Province Dacia Traiana
Province Description Location Romula
Romula (Pleiades)
Garden Tomb Garden of Ael(ius) Iul(ius) Iulianus, Decurion in Romula
Keywords  epitaphs inscription literary garden tombs  Garden Description A slab unearthed near Resça (Romula), Romania, in 1954 records a verse epitaph set up by Valeria Gemellina for her husband Ael(ius) Iul(ius) Iulianus, a decurion of the colony of Romula, some time probably in the later second or third century. In it she describes in pastoral terms well suited to the hexameter the setting of the “eternal home” (i.e. the tomb) she built for him (hanc Iuliano domum flendo fabricavi perennem): “See how Gemellina, along with her children, out of respect for her worthy husband built a resting place for him amidst the vines and shrubbery and the lush grass, where deep shade from an overhanging branch supplies the greenery” (ecce Gemellina pietate ducta marito / struxindolens digno sedem cum liberis una / inter pampinea virgulta et gramina laeta / umbra super rami virides ubi densa ministrat).
Maps Images Dates Later second century/third century
Excavation Dates 1954
Bibliography  AE 1957, 334.  Pleiades ID 981518
TGN ID 8712318
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 12 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tomb Painting in Chester</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/chester/chester_tomb_painting/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 08:58:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/chester/chester_tomb_painting/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Chester
Garden Tomb Painting in Chester
Keywords  funerary buildings tombs  Garden Description Toynbee’s suggestion that a military tombstone from Chester depicting a row of three gabled buildings with stylized trees or shrubs planted in front of the two at the sides perhaps represents a tomb garden with tomb and flanking funerary buildings, though plausible, cannot in itself be taken to show that tomb gardens existed in Roman Britain; it would, however, suggest that the concept of planting at tombs was regarded as conventionally Roman and appropriate.
Maps Dates unspecified
Bibliography  R. P. Wright and I. A. Richmond, Catalogue of the Inscribed and Sculptured Stones in the Grosvenor Museum, Chester (1955) 40 no. 92, pl. 26. (world cat) J. M. C. Toynbee, Death and Burial in the Roman World (London 1971) 100. (world cat)  Pleiades ID 89144
89144
TGN ID 7026064
Contributor John Bodel (ORCID: 0000-0003-1820-6368)
Publication date 08 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>