<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/moncrabeau_lot-et-garonne/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 12:39:10 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/moncrabeau_lot-et-garonne/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa de Bapteste, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/moncrabeau_lot-et-garonne/gallia_villa_de_bapteste_yji/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 12:39:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p2_yuhanji/moncrabeau_lot-et-garonne/gallia_villa_de_bapteste_yji/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania
Province Description&amp;ndash;&amp;gt; A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location MONCRABEAU
(Pleiades)
House Villa de Bapteste
House Description The excavations of A. Faugères du Bourg and H. Teulières between 1871 and 1873 revealed a luxurious villa with nearly fifty rooms, twenty-five of them with mosaics and covered with marble. Immediately after the excavation it was reburied and, except for two rooms under roofs, returned to agricultural use. This use accounts for its present poor state of conservation. Sample checks between after 1990 led to urgent salvage operations by Ph. Jacques in 1995. He was able to determine five phase successive phases of construction.
Garden Peristyle Garden
Keywords  archaeological garden luxurious villa mosaic cour d’honneur porticos vestibules gutters (building drainage components) tegulae colonnade aqueduct footbridge socle  Garden Description The first phase was a villa of the second half of the first century with a façade gallery with two wings extending behind the front. It went through two more phases in the second century and was then completely rebuilt (phase 4) in the fourth century around a vast peristyle. A series of embellishments in late antiquity (phase 5) included creation of a cour d’honneur [Q] on the southeast and the addition on the north corner of an octagonal room extending to the northwest and continuing into a tri-lobed room thought to be a reception room by some, though others think it was related to baths. The cour d’honneur [Q] with porticoes in a U had three entrances, one on the axis and two others on the sides. Nothing is known of how the inside of the court was arranged. Off to the south went a gallery which connected the villa to a separate group of buildings, possibly baths. On entering from the cour d’honneur, and passing through the vestibule in the form of two rooms, one after another, one entered a very large, almost square peristyle more than forty meters on a side. It was bordered by a gutter of tegulae to catch the drip from the roofs. The nineteenth century excavations found “a stuccoed pool in the form of a bath tub” with its lead pipe feed still in place. It may have served as an ornament of the peristyle court, but we do not know exactly where it was.
Along the northeast side of the villa ran a portico (50 x 5 m) entirely covered with mosaics. At either end there was a large reception room; and in the center, a passageway to the peristyle. The gallery with its colonnade was thus a belvedere for enjoying a panorama over the countryside. Along this façade ran a trench to carry off rainwater. In the words of the early excavator, “an aqueduct follows the façade and the little sewers where the water from the roof ran off are still in place. Two little footbridges of brick [U] cross them and doubtless brought the dwelling into communication with the gardens.”
The reception room [M] at the northwest extremity of the gallery had in its first third a pool lined with marble (1 x 0.2 m) connected to the gutter that runs along the northeast wing. Two wells of careful and identical form with a polygonal socle are noted [S]. The first, 1.3 meters in diameter, was 8 meters in front of the northeast façade; the other, also outside the house was near the southeast façade. In the first plan published, the first of these was shown on the axis of the passage between the gallery and the peristyle. A channel connects it with the one channel along the front of the house.
Plans   Watercolor by H. Teulieres 1872-1874 (lithograph, A. Blakchet fonds)   Dates second half of the first century CE
Excavation Dates 1871 to 1873
Bibliography  Faugère du Bourg, “Mémoire sur les fouilles de Bapteste” in Actes du Congrès archéologiques de France, Agen et Toulouse, 1874, p. 38-56 (worldcat) E. Morvillez, Forme et évolution des salles de réception des grandes demeures tardives du bassin méditerranéen occidental (IVème-Vième siècle), 1993, t. 1, p. 117-22 worldcat B. Fages, Carte archéologique de la Gaule, Lot-et-Garonne (47), Paris 1995, p.246-49 worldcat Catherine Balmelle, Les demeures aristocratiques d&amp;rsquo;Aquitaine, societe et culture de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquite tardive dans le sou-ouest de la Gaule, Ausonius, supple. d&amp;rsquo;Aquitania 10, Bordeaux 2001, p. 104, 129, 147-148, 371-74, 446. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 249930
TGN ID []()
Contributor Clopper Almon (https://www.econ.umd.edu/facultyprofile/almon/clopper)
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>