<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>atriums on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/atriums/</link>
    <description>Recent content in atriums on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 00:10:10 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/atriums/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Casa della Gemma (Insula or. I.1)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/insula_or._i/house_1/casa_della_gemma/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 00:10:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/herculaneum/insula_or._i/house_1/casa_della_gemma/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Italia (Pleiades)
Location Herculaneum
Herculaneum (Pleiades)
Location Description An ancient Roman town of Campania destroyed by the eruption of Mt. Vesuvius in A.D.79. Named as a UNESCO World Heritage Site in 1997.
Insula Insula Orientalis I
House House 1
Garden Casa della Gemma (A)
Keywords  vaults cisterns atriums sundial  Garden Description A. This garden (a) is built partially into the edge of the hill and partially on vaults. A square opening enclosed by a high wall in the center of the garden supplies light to the floor below, shared by both the Casa della Gemma with windows on three sides and the Casa del Rilievo di Telefo next door with windows on one side. The garden was perhaps jointly owned, although neither had an entrance into the area. Three sides of the garden had large raised gutters 0.74 m. wide; 0.70 m. high which collected roof water and conveyed it to a cistern in the atrium of Casa della Gemma. A sundial is located in this garden.
Plans   Plan of the new excavations of Herculaneum (Maiuri, Herculaneum)     Herculaneum - insula orientalis I. 1-3   Images   Herculaneum - insula orientalis I. 1-2 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)     Herculaneum - insula orientalis I. 1-3 (Stanley Jashemski, Jashemski Archives, University of Maryland)   Pleiades ID 432873
TGN ID 7031897
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Maiuri, Herculaneum, p.65 (worldcat) Maiuri, Ercolano, p. 341 and fig. 266 (plan) on p. 337 (worldcat) Gibbs, p. 295, no. 3074G  Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 20 October 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Eisenstadt</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/eisenstadt/eisenstadt_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 09:31:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/eisenstadt/eisenstadt_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Pannonia
Location Eisenstadt
Eisenstadt (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Eisenstadt
Keywords  altars (religious fixtures) archaeological garden atriums peristyles (Roman courtyards) podiums (building divisions) porticoes villae rusticae  Garden Description The residence of this villa rustica was entered on the southeast by a portico (Fig. 1). After passing through a room interpreted as the atrium, one arrived in the open courtyard which had a peristyle on three sides (G on plan). On the northern edge of the courtyard was a podium (P on plan) near which votive altars to Diana and Silvanus were found, both gods of the woods and suitable subjects for a garden. This corner of the courtyard, thus, seems to have had religious character. In the middle of the courtyard was a square foundation, measuring 1.80 x 1.80 m., possibly the remains of a base for some kind of figure. The villa rustica was established in the early 2nd century and occupied probably until the 4th century.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the rural villa with a peristyle courtyard (G) and a podium (P) for sculpture. Adapted from Thomas 1964, fig. 73. (Rights statement.)   Dates Early 2nd century - 4th century
Bibliography  E.B. Thomas, Römische Villen in Pannonien, Budapest, 1964, pp. 137-151, fig. 73. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 197425
TGN ID 7003056
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Legionary Houses at Castra Vetera (Germania Inferior)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/castra_vetera/ger_inf_castra_vetera/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:57:44 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/castra_vetera/ger_inf_castra_vetera/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Province Description Location Castra Vetera
Castra Vetera (Pleiades)
Garden Legionary houses at Castra Vetera (Germania inferior)
Keywords  castra praetoriums atriums peristyles (Roman courtyards) tablina pedestals Pliny the Younger  Garden Description In the Neronian fort of the 5th and 15th legions near the civilian settlement of Colonia Ulpia Traiana were two vast buildings on either side of the headquarters building (principia). These were the residences, or praetoria, of the two legionary commanders. The western palatial complex was 76-77 m. in width and 97 m. in length (over 7400 sq. m.) (Plan 1). It was entered from the east through a vestibule and an atrium. The villa had several peristyle courtyards, including one long peristyle courtyard with apsidal ends which has been interpreted as a garden (G on plan). Between the atrium and the apsidal courtyard was a large room, possibly a tablinum or a dining room. This courtyard measured 18.80 x 83 m. and had an open area 10.80 m. wide, surrounded on all sides by a covered columned walkway, 3.50 m. in width.
The partially excavated eastern villa was 78.50 m. wide and 109 m. in length. It too had several peristyle courtyards and one long courtyard 19 x 74.60 m. in size. The open area between the covered walkways was 5.80 m. wide. In front of each of the columns surrounding the courtyard were buttress-like foundations which the excavator interpreted as possible bases for statues. The excavator referred to the long courtyards in these houses as &amp;ldquo;hippodrome gardens&amp;rdquo;, and compared them to known stadium or hippodrome gardens at Pliny&amp;rsquo;s Tuscan villa, on the Palatine in Rome (Domus Augustana) and at Hadrian&amp;rsquo;s villa at Tivoli. The comparison is unacceptable, however, since both ends of the courtyards in the legionary camp are apsidal, unlike a stadium or hippodrome which has one straight end. The long garden courtyards at Xanten may have had more in common with the long, apsidal gardens referred to by Pliny as gestatio in modum circi (Epist. 5.6.17). It can be considered reasonably certain that the courtyards in both legionary villas were not foreseen for races or athletic activities, but for gardens as an ideal place for promenades.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the western *praetorium* in the double legionary base with its long apsidal garden (G). Adapted from Lehner 1930, fig. 39. (Rights statement).   Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  H. Lehner, Vetera. Die Ergebnisse der Ausgrabungen des Bonner Provinzialmuseums bis 1929. Römisch-Germanische Forschungen 4, Berlin, 1930, pp. 52-60, figs. 38-41. worldcat  Pleiades ID 108867
TGN ID 7004944
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 25 July 2020
Related articles The Houses of Insula 7 in Colonia Ulpia Traiana</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Atrium House</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_atrium/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 07:38:05 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_atrium/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Garden Atrium House (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords  urban villas villae urbanae atrium houses atriums tablina colonnades peristyles (Roman courtyards) apsed pools piscinae  Garden Description West of the House of Dionysos stood the so-called &amp;ldquo;atrium house&amp;rdquo; which covered an area of 1400 sq. m. (Plan 1). It was built around the middle of the 1st century A.D.
Entering from the colonnaded street at the west, one passed through a room reconstructed as an atrium, continuing along a corridor around the tablinum, and arrived at a peristyle courtyard with a semicircular pool. This courtyard, approximately 10 x 13 m. in size, was almost certainly a garden (Plan 1, G). A ground level gutter ran around the edge of the unpaved courtyard. This part of the house remained unchanged until the destruction of the building in the 4th century.
Maps Plans   Plan 1: Plan of the so-called &amp;#39;atrium house&amp;#39; with an apsidal pool (P) in its garden courtyard (G). Adapted from Precht 1971, fig. 2. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Middle of the first century CE until the fourth century CE
Bibliography  G. Precht, &amp;ldquo;Die Ausgrabungen um den Kölner Dom. Vorbericht über die Untersuchungen,&amp;rdquo; Kölner Jahrbuch 12, 1971:55-56, fig. 2, pl. 7.2. (worldcat) H. Hellenkemper, &amp;ldquo;Architektur als Beitrag zur Geschichte der CCAA,&amp;rdquo; in H. Temporini, ed., Aufstieg und Niedergang der Römischen Welt II.4, Berlin, 1974, p. 810, figs. 20-21. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108751
TGN ID 7004446
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 09 July 2020
Related articles House of Dionysos (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>