<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>atriums on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/atriums/</link>
    <description>Recent content in atriums on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 10:02:09 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/atriums/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Caupona; Officina Libraria (I.ii.24)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_24/caupona_officina_libraria_i.ii.24/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 10:02:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_24/caupona_officina_libraria_i.ii.24/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 24
Garden Caupona; Officina Libraria (I.ii.24)
Keywords  aedicula lararium archaeological garden atriums cauponae flowerpots podiums (building divisions) porticoes tables (support furniture) triclinia  Garden Description The garden (a) east of the atrium had a portico extending along the south and part of the west sides. A low wall (0.52 m. high) connected the columns and an entrance to the garden was located on the west. In 1873 the caupona was excavated. The garden contained a masonry triclinium (l.medius, 3.85 m.; l.summus and l.imus, 3.20 m.) with a table. The badly damaged triclinium revealed the amphoras used in its construction. A low podium along the north wall was thought by Fiorelli to have held flower pots. Mau reported a drainage channel at the corner of the triclinium formed by the l.meduis and the l.summus, although it is no longer evident. The base of an aedicula lararium remains against the east wall opposite the north end of the east couch.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation dates 1873
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 23, no. 17. Fiorelli, Descr., p. 47. (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), col. 60. Jashemski, Gardens, 1:179. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 25. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), p. 245. Ibid., (1874), pp. 253-256, 262-263. Mau-Kelsey, p. 404. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 77. Soprano, pp. 292-293, no. 1. Viola, “Scavi” p. 13. (worldcat) Warscher, “Codex.” photo no. 32.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 27 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.ii.17 B</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_17/i.ii.17_b/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2020 15:01:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_17/i.ii.17_b/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 17
Garden I.ii.17 B
Keywords  archaeological garden atriums mural paintings (visual works) peristyles (columnades) pillars porticoes statues statuettes (free-standing sculpture) tablina  Garden Description The peristyle garden to the east of the atrium was excavated in 1873. It had a portico on the north and west supported by two pillars, one at the northwest corner and the other in the middle of the north side. A gutter sloped towards the southeast corner as it went around the east, north, and west edges of the garden. A shrine-like structure was built against the east wall with the marble veneered façade above the level of the floor of the niche. The niche contained a marble statuette of Venus, her left arm supported by a statuette (1.04 m. high; Mus Naz. inv. no. 109 608; Ruesch no. 1325). The wall behind the statue was painted to represent blue drapery and the ceiling had a shell-like fluting. Two small marble statuettes of toads (Mus. Nac. inv. no. 109 609, 109 610) found in the garden and probably the one of two doves (Mus. Naz. inv. no. 120 407) found in the tablinum decorated the flowerbeds. There was also a marble head of a man identified as Agrippa, found cemented in a cup (total height 0.285 m.; Mus. Nac. inv. no. 109 611; Reusch no. 1081). The marble statuette of Hercules wrapped in a lion skin (0.70 m. high; Mus. Nac. inv. no. 109 677) found in the atrium was probably a garden decoration. The large room on the north had a fine view of the garden and the east and south walls of the garden were decorated with garden paintings. These were separated by narrow panels with a painting of a candelabrum, according to Mau, and each painting featured a fence with an amphora upon it. Behind this there was a thicket with birds. On either side of the amphora there was an ibis, and a pheasant in the center. Fiorelli mentioned observing animals in the paintings. Jashemski notes that no trace of the paintings remained when she examined the site, and further, she has never seen a pheasant represented in any garden paintings. Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation dates 1873
Bibliography  Boyce, p. 22, no. 10. de Franciscis, Ritratto, p. 25 and figs. 10-11. (worldcat) Döhl, p.1. Dwyer, Pomp. Sculpture, pp. 124, 12. (worldcat) Fiorelli, Descr., p. 44. (worldcat) GiornSc, n.s., 3 (1874-1877), cols. 46-47, 48, 55. Grimal, p. 445, no. 1.  Jashemski, Gardens, 1::124-125. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, pp. 23-24. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 313. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 233-235. Ibid. (1874), pp. 265-266. Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 265-266.  Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. gen.,” p. 76. Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “L’arte,” p. 6 and pl. 14 (Venus). Schefold, WandP, p. 10. (worldcat)  Sogliano, “Pitture,” p. 223, no. 691. (worldcat)  Sogliano, “Scavi,” p. 310. (worldcat) Viola, “Scavi” pp. 12 and 76, no. 1, p.77, nos. 5, 12, p.79, nos. 45, 46. (worldcat) Warscher, “Codex,” photo no. 32.  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 26 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I.ii.6</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_6/i.ii.6/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2020 12:44:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ii/house_6/i.ii.6/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula II
House House 6
Garden I.ii.6
Keywords  archaeological garden atriums graffiti (casual notations) gutters (building drainage components) inscription peristyles (columnades) piscinae porticoes puteal  Garden Description The west portico of the small peristyle garden at the rear of the house was entered through two doors directly from the atrium. The garden was enclosed on four sides by a portico supported by eight stuccoed brick columns. On the foreside, the two first columns on the left had a larger intercolumniation corresponding to the wide opening opposite the atrium. Between these columns stood a terra-cotta puteal covered with white stucco. A gutter around the edges of the garden was shown in the plan. The round pool in the center of the garden no longer exists, and only stumps of the columns remain today. One of the graffiti on the walls of the portico noted that on November 17 Puteolana gave birth to three males and two females (XV K(alendas) NOV(embres) PVTEOLANA PEPERIT MASCL(os) III FEMEL[as] II) (CIL IV.3890). Perhaps they were either piglets or puppies. Pigs were more common in ancient cities than is commonly realized.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ii, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, plan 5, p. 22; Viola, Scavi, pl. 1; Niccolini, Case, vol. 3, “Topo grafia,” pl. 9 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Bibliography  Fiorelli, Descr., p. 39. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, 1: 104-105 (for the graffito). (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 21. (worldcat) Mau, BdI (1874), pp. 199. Niccolini, Case, vol. 2, “Descr. Gen.,” p. 76. Pernice, p. 18. Viola, “Scavi,” p 11. (worldcat) Warscher, “Codex.”  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 24 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Eisenstadt</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/eisenstadt/eisenstadt_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 09:31:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/eisenstadt/eisenstadt_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Pannonia
Location Eisenstadt
Eisenstadt (Pleiades)
Garden Rural Villa in Eisenstadt
Keywords  altars (religious fixtures) archaeological garden atriums peristyles (Roman courtyards) podiums (building divisions) porticoes villae rusticae  Garden Description The residence of this villa rustica was entered on the southeast by a portico (Fig. 1). After passing through a room interpreted as the atrium, one arrived in the open courtyard which had a peristyle on three sides (G on plan). On the northern edge of the courtyard was a podium (P on plan) near which votive altars to Diana and Silvanus were found, both gods of the woods and suitable subjects for a garden. This corner of the courtyard, thus, seems to have had religious character. In the middle of the courtyard was a square foundation, measuring 1.80 x 1.80 m., possibly the remains of a base for some kind of figure. The villa rustica was established in the early 2nd century and occupied probably until the 4th century.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the rural villa with a peristyle courtyard (G) and a podium (P) for sculpture. Adapted from Thomas 1964, fig. 73. (Rights statement.)   Dates Early 2nd century - 4th century
Bibliography  E.B. Thomas, Römische Villen in Pannonien, Budapest, 1964, pp. 137-151, fig. 73. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 197425
TGN ID 7003056
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 22 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Legionary Houses at Castra Vetera (Germania Inferior)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/castra_vetera/ger_inf_castra_vetera/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2020 10:57:44 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/castra_vetera/ger_inf_castra_vetera/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Province Description Location Castra Vetera
Castra Vetera (Pleiades)
Garden Legionary houses at Castra Vetera (Germania inferior)
Keywords  castra praetoriums atriums peristyles (Roman courtyards) tablina pedestals Pliny the Younger  Garden Description In the Neronian fort of the 5th and 15th legions near the civilian settlement of Colonia Ulpia Traiana were two vast buildings on either side of the headquarters building (principia). These were the residences, or praetoria, of the two legionary commanders. The western palatial complex was 76-77 m. in width and 97 m. in length (over 7400 sq. m.) (Plan 1). It was entered from the east through a vestibule and an atrium. The villa had several peristyle courtyards, including one long peristyle courtyard with apsidal ends which has been interpreted as a garden (G on plan). Between the atrium and the apsidal courtyard was a large room, possibly a tablinum or a dining room. This courtyard measured 18.80 x 83 m. and had an open area 10.80 m. wide, surrounded on all sides by a covered columned walkway, 3.50 m. in width.
The partially excavated eastern villa was 78.50 m. wide and 109 m. in length. It too had several peristyle courtyards and one long courtyard 19 x 74.60 m. in size. The open area between the covered walkways was 5.80 m. wide. In front of each of the columns surrounding the courtyard were buttress-like foundations which the excavator interpreted as possible bases for statues. The excavator referred to the long courtyards in these houses as &amp;ldquo;hippodrome gardens&amp;rdquo;, and compared them to known stadium or hippodrome gardens at Pliny&amp;rsquo;s Tuscan villa, on the Palatine in Rome (Domus Augustana) and at Hadrian&amp;rsquo;s villa at Tivoli. The comparison is unacceptable, however, since both ends of the courtyards in the legionary camp are apsidal, unlike a stadium or hippodrome which has one straight end. The long garden courtyards at Xanten may have had more in common with the long, apsidal gardens referred to by Pliny as gestatio in modum circi (Epist. 5.6.17). It can be considered reasonably certain that the courtyards in both legionary villas were not foreseen for races or athletic activities, but for gardens as an ideal place for promenades.
Maps Plans   Plan 1. Plan of the western *praetorium* in the double legionary base with its long apsidal garden (G). Adapted from Lehner 1930, fig. 39. (Rights statement).   Images Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  H. Lehner, Vetera. Die Ergebnisse der Ausgrabungen des Bonner Provinzialmuseums bis 1929. Römisch-Germanische Forschungen 4, Berlin, 1930, pp. 52-60, figs. 38-41. worldcat  Pleiades ID 108867
TGN ID 7004944
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 25 July 2020
Related articles The Houses of Insula 7 in Colonia Ulpia Traiana</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Atrium House</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_atrium/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 07:38:05 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_atrium/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Garden Atrium House (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords  urban villas villae urbanae atrium houses atriums tablina colonnades peristyles (Roman courtyards) apsed pools piscinae  Garden Description West of the House of Dionysos stood the so-called &amp;ldquo;atrium house&amp;rdquo; which covered an area of 1400 sq. m. (Plan 1). It was built around the middle of the 1st century A.D.
Entering from the colonnaded street at the west, one passed through a room reconstructed as an atrium, continuing along a corridor around the tablinum, and arrived at a peristyle courtyard with a semicircular pool. This courtyard, approximately 10 x 13 m. in size, was almost certainly a garden (Plan 1, G). A ground level gutter ran around the edge of the unpaved courtyard. This part of the house remained unchanged until the destruction of the building in the 4th century.
Maps Plans   Plan 1: Plan of the so-called &amp;#39;atrium house&amp;#39; with an apsidal pool (P) in its garden courtyard (G). Adapted from Precht 1971, fig. 2. (Rights statement)   Images Dates Middle of the first century CE until the fourth century CE
Bibliography  G. Precht, &amp;ldquo;Die Ausgrabungen um den Kölner Dom. Vorbericht über die Untersuchungen,&amp;rdquo; Kölner Jahrbuch 12, 1971:55-56, fig. 2, pl. 7.2. (worldcat) H. Hellenkemper, &amp;ldquo;Architektur als Beitrag zur Geschichte der CCAA,&amp;rdquo; in H. Temporini, ed., Aufstieg und Niedergang der Römischen Welt II.4, Berlin, 1974, p. 810, figs. 20-21. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 108751
TGN ID 7004446
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 09 July 2020
Related articles House of Dionysos (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>