<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>atriums on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/atriums/</link>
    <description>Recent content in atriums on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 09:31:35 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/atriums/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Rural Villa in Eisenstadt</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/eisenstadt/eisenstadt_rural_villa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 09:31:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/pannonia/eisenstadt/eisenstadt_rural_villa/</guid>
      <description>Province Pannonia
Province Description Location Eisenstadt
Eisenstadt (Pleiades)
Location Description Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Rural Villa in Eisenstadt
Keywords altars (religious fixtures)
archaeological garden
atriums
peristyles (Roman courtyards)
podiums (building divisions)
porticoes
rural villas
villae rusticae
Garden Description The residence of this villa rustica was entered on the southeast by a portico (Fig. 1). After passing through a room interpreted as the atrium, one arrived in the open courtyard which had a peristyle on three sides (G on plan). On the northern edge of the courtyard was a podium (P on plan) near which votive altars to Diana and Silvanus were found, both gods of the woods and suitable subjects for a garden. This corner of the courtyard, thus, seems to have had religious character. In the middle of the courtyard was a square foundation, measuring 1.80 x 1.80 m., possibly the remains of a base for some kind of figure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Atrium House</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_atrium/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 07:38:05 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/germania_inferior/cologne/colonia_cologne_atrium/</guid>
      <description>Province Germania inferior
Location Cologne
Cologne (Pleiades)
Location Description This large town on the west bank of the Rhine river was the civitas capital of the Ubii in the first half of the 1st century A.D. It was granted the status of colonia by Claudius in 50 and became the provincial capital in 85.
Sublocation Sublocation Description Garden Atrium House (Colonia Claudia Ara Agrippinensium)
Keywords urban villas
villae urbanae
atrium houses
atriums
tablina
colonnades
peristyles (Roman courtyards)
apsed pools
piscinae
Garden Description West of the House of Dionysos stood the so-called &amp;ldquo;atrium house&amp;rdquo; which covered an area of 1400 sq. m. (Plan 1). It was built around the middle of the 1st century A.D.
Entering from the colonnaded street at the west, one passed through a room reconstructed as an atrium, continuing along a corridor around the tablinum, and arrived at a peristyle courtyard with a semicircular pool. This courtyard, approximately 10 x 13 m.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>