<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>villae suburbanae on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/villae-suburbanae/</link>
    <description>Recent content in villae suburbanae on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/villae-suburbanae/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>villa at site 10</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/via_gabina/villa_at_site_10/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/via_gabina/villa_at_site_10/</guid>
      <description>Province italia
Location villa at site 10
villa at site 10 (Pleiades)
Sublocation Via Gabina
Sublocation Description For six and a half weeks each summer from 1976 through 1989 Philip Oliver-Smith and the author (both of Rice University) excavated, often to bedrock, two sites fourteen kilometers east of the center of ancient Rome. The team worked from a surface survey conducted by John Ward Perkins and Anne Kahane in 1964, which traced the path of the via Gabina, a road joining Rome and Gabii and supplanted in the 1st century B.C. by the more up-to-date via Praeneste (today the via Praenestina-Fig.1). This same survey established by the collection of surface material thirty-five occupation sites bordering the via Gabina. From these sites we selected three for further investigation, two of which were fully uncovered to reveal the remains of two suburban villas and a late Roman horreum or giant barn. For recording purposes we kept the site designations of Ward Perkins and Kahane. Therefore the discussion here will refer to the villas at Site 10 and Site 11. In 1976, our first season, two trial trenches located structures at Site 13 (another villa?), but no further digging was done here because of problems involving crop rotation (our work was carried out on the land of a still existing farm), time, and money.
Garden Villa at site 10
Keywords  courtyards corridors domus mosaics (visual works) villae suburbanae  Garden Description This large complex villa structure was founded in the Augustan period and was abandoned in the early 3rd century A.D, with evidence from pottery of continued occupation that time. Not even the peristyle core of the plan could be dated to what we call Period 1 (the early occupation period of the Via Gabina sites). Pottery, roof tile stamps, and construction technique (revetted concrete) all give four phases to the villa remains – Augustan, Julio Claudian, Domitianic, and Hadrianic. Reconstructions have been accomplished for all the phases of Period 2, but what interests us here with our focus on gardens is the last or Hadrianic phase (Phase 2 D – Figs. 4 and 5).
The villa had a western enclosed garden area (Figs. 4 and 5) framed on the east by a Doric loggia at least from the time of Domitian. It was then that the owners created an elaborately decorated triclinium (Fig. 4, “35”) overlooking the garden and affording a view back to Rome (thus setting up the contrast of the serenity of the country with the congestion of the city). This was a major addition to the villa/residence. Phase 2D extended the loggia and gave a greater sense of symmetry to the facade. No pool of any depth was possible because the space of the garden overlaid bedrock-cut chambers for the fermentation of wine. Again, there could be no determination of specific planting; not even flotation material was helpful. It was in this western garden area that a huge horreum/barn was constructed in the late 4th or early 5th century C.E.
2.B.	The peristyle garden of Phase 2D (Figs. 4, “B” and 5) dates from the Augustan core of construction (Phase 2A). Overlooking the peristyle center through a wide double doorway was an oecus or reception/dining room (Fig. 4, “2”) with an emblema (59cm x 59cm) at the center of its mosaic floor. The emblema (now on permanent exhibition in the Palazzo Massimo alle Terme di Museo Nazionale Romano) portrays “The Rape of Hylas” (Fig. 6). This depiction was found in situ and oriented to be seen to best advantage from the couch of the padrone or distinguished guest at the back of the room. The location of the couch was indicated in the design of the black and white mosaic surrounding the emblema – unfortunately the Museo Nazionale’s restoration has reversed this relationship by turning the emblema so it would be read in proper perspective from the door of the oecus and not the couch). From bedrock cuts (Fig. 4, “b”) and a nearby well, it would seem the pool and grotto into which Hylas was abducted was emulated in the open area of the peristyle garden. Hence a view from the principal couch first of the graphic depiction of the rape and then a simulation of the place it occurred. The iconography involved in this sequence and subject relates to the agricultural function of the villa itself and its bucolic character. Because the emblema consists of a single tile containing the tiny tesserae (therefore portable) and can be dated to the beginning of the 1st century B.C., it may well be that the emblema was also an embellishment of the Period 1 villa.
These two sites represent a rare glimpse of the transformation of suburban Rome over more than twelve centuries of occupation.
Maps Plans   fig04_recon_phase2d   Images   fig05_recon_phase2d.     The Rape of Hylas.   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  J.B. Ward Perkins and A. Kahane, ed., The Via Gabina, Papers of the British School at Rome, 40 (1972), 91-126. worldcat W. Widrig, Two Sites on the Ancient Via Gabina, British Museum Occasional Paper 24 (1980), 119-141. worldcat W. Widrig, Land Use at the Via Gabina Villas, Ancient Roman Villa Gardens (Dumbarton Oaks, 1987), 225-260. worldcat  Pleiades ID 622606468
TGN ID 7208125
Contributor Walter M Widrig (https://www.worldcat.org/wcidentities/lccn-n2009061717)
Publication date 22 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>villa at site 11</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/via_gabina/villa_at_site_11/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/via_gabina/villa_at_site_11/</guid>
      <description>Province italia
Location villa at site 11
villa at site 11 (Pleiades)
Sublocation Via Gabina
Sublocation Description For six and a half weeks each summer from 1976 through 1989 Philip Oliver-Smith and the author (both of Rice University) excavated, often to bedrock, two sites fourteen kilometers east of the center of ancient Rome. The team worked from a surface survey conducted by John Ward Perkins and Anne Kahane in 1964, which traced the path of the via Gabina, a road joining Rome and Gabii and supplanted in the 1st century B.C. by the more up-to-date via Praeneste (today the via Praenestina-Fig.1). This same survey established by the collection of surface material thirty-five occupation sites bordering the via Gabina. From these sites we selected three for further investigation, two of which were fully uncovered to reveal the remains of two suburban villas and a late Roman horreum or giant barn. For recording purposes we kept the site designations of Ward Perkins and Kahane. Therefore the discussion here will refer to the villas at Site 10 and Site 11. In 1976, our first season, two trial trenches located structures at Site 13 (another villa?), but no further digging was done here because of problems involving crop rotation (our work was carried out on the land of a still existing farm), time, and money.
Garden Villa at site 11
Keywords  barns atrium houses courtyards villae suburbanae  Garden Description This villa at Site 11 was a simple “U” plan farmhouse initiated at the beginning of the 3rd century B.C. (Period 1). In the Augustan Age this farmhouse was transformed into a more luxurious atrium type villa/residence (Period 2 – Figs. 2 and 3). During the reign of Trajan a bath suite was added as well as an outside plunge pool in what seems to have been a western enclosed garden (hortus) from as early as Period 1. Because of the proximity of bedrock and the fact the slight earth cover had been ploughed for centuries, any evidence of what might have been planted in the garden had long since been destroyed. We know, however, that there must have been surrounding olive groves from the press facilities of the villa, also dating from the time of Trajan. All was abandoned in the second or third decade of the 3rd century of the Christian Era.
Maps Plans   Plan at the Villa at site 11.   Images   fig03_the axon of the Villa at site 11.   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  J.B. Ward Perkins and A. Kahane, ed., The Via Gabina, Papers of the British School at Rome, 40 (1972), 91-126. worldcat W. Widrig, Two Sites on the Ancient Via Gabina, British Museum Occasional Paper 24 (1980), 119-141. worldcat W. Widrig, Land Use at the Via Gabina Villas, Ancient Roman Villa Gardens (Dumbarton Oaks, 1987), 225-260. worldcat  Pleiades ID 622606468
TGN ID 7208125
Contributor Walter M Widrig (https://www.worldcat.org/wcidentities/lccn-n2009061717)
Publication date 22 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Suburban Gardens in Camulodunum</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/camulodunum/camulodunum_suburban_gardens/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2020 16:47:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/britannia/camulodunum/camulodunum_suburban_gardens/</guid>
      <description>Province Britannia
Province Description Location Camulodunum
Camulodunum (Pleiades)
Location Description Camulodunum began as an Iron Age settlement defended by dykes, a combination of V-shaped ditch and rampart created by the upcast earth. It extended from the Roman river on the south to the Colne on the north, a distance of some four kilometers. Within this larger area, a legionary fort was built after the Claudian conquest of Britain in AD 43. On the site of the fort, a veteran colony was planted in about AD 49 and given the name Colonia Victricensis, City of Victory. It became the first provincial capital, later superseded by Londinium (London). Outside its walls was a V-shaped defensive ditch.
Garden Suburban Gardens in Camulodunum
Keywords  archaeological garden ditches villae suburbanae  Garden Description Outside the walls of the city, utilitarian gardens were planted, possibly in the 3rd century, in allotments along the road leading to the Balkerne Gate. Upon the widening of the defensive ditch at the foot of the walls around AD 275, a thick dump of soil was deposited on these garden allotments, preserving a short stretch of mounded cultivation beds laid out in rows. The excavators have suggested that the beds might have been formed for growing vines or plants such as asparagus. It is uncertain whether the gardens were attached to suburban dwellings at this time, but by about 300 practically all suburban houses in this area had been demolished without replacement.
Maps Images Images not available
Fig. 1: Area outside the Balkerne gate before widening of the town ditch. Details of the beds in the middle of the section of are gardens in the foreground are based on excavation. From Crummy, City of Victory, p. 42. (Rights statement)
Dates 3rd century - about 300
Bibliography  P. Crummy, Excavations at Lion Walk, Balkerne Lane and Middleborough, Colchester, Essex. Colchester Archaeological Report 3, Colchester, 1984, fig. 106. (worldcat) P. Crummy, City of Victory, Colchester, 1997, pp. 114-115, figs. on pp. 100, 116-117. (worldcat)  Periodo ID Pleiades ID 79393
TGN ID 7011866
Contributor Maureen Carroll (ORCID: 0000-0001-9958-8032)
Publication date 06 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
