<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ix/house_1/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 14:57:51 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ix/house_1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Beautiful Impluvium; Casa del Bell Impluvio (I.ix.1)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ix/house_1/house_of_the_beautiful_impluvium/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 14:57:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_ix/house_1/house_of_the_beautiful_impluvium/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula IX
House House 1
Garden House of the Beautiful Impluvium; Casa del Bell Impluvio (I.ix.1)
Keywords  archaeological garden atriums cubicula (domestic spaces) fountains impluvia inscription mural paintings (visual works) pergolas peristyles (columnades) porticoes predellas  Garden Description According to Eschebach’s plan, there was a portico at the rear of this house that enclosed this peristyle garden (a) on four sides. A small section of the foundation wall remains on the south end of the east side. The cubiculum (b) to the east of the atrium has a garden representation on the west half of the black predella on the south wall. It was poorly preserved but the left section shows a garden with a lattice fence and a pergola. Faint images remain of a similar pergola on the right side. The center of the painting, (which is 0.09 x 0.84 m.) has an open area with a crater perhaps serving as a fountain in a pergola. Two additional pergolas stand to either side. Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula ix, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 12, p. 44 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Date Bibliography  CIL IV. 10274, 10333 (for amphoras found in the garden March 3, 1952). de Vos, p.135 in Bastet.  Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, pp. 44; 395. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 09 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>