<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/xue_xia/neapolis/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 10:39:31 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/xue_xia/neapolis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>House of the Nymphs (Maison des Nymphes)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/xue_xia/neapolis/house_of_the_nymphs/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/xue_xia/neapolis/house_of_the_nymphs/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa Proconsularis Africa proconsularis (Pleiades)
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location Neapolis
Neapolis (Pleiades)
Location Description The city of Neapolis that bears a Greek name meaning the “new city,” is located on the south coast of Cap Bon at 60 km from Carthage. The municipal history of the city is not well known. Scholars disagree as to the foundation date of the colony some think it became colonia Iulia with Cesar and others think that it was elevated to the rank of colony by Augustus.
Garden House of the Nymphs (Maison des Nymphes)
Keywords  peristyles (columnades) peristyles (Roman courtyards) mosaics (visual works) oeci triclinia amphorae (storage vessels)  Garden Description This large house (1500m2) laid-out around a peristyle-garden is known for its mosaic pavements figuring Homeric scenes. The peristyle is entered from the S. The N wing had a vast oecus-triclinium bordered on both sides by two apartments that each had two rooms and a passage to a pseudo-atrium (Plan view, Fig.1).
The peristyle was trapezoidal in shape (8.29 x 9 x 16. 15 m) and was bordered by 12 columns. Four porticos, 5m wide, enclosed the garden. The semicircular pool facing the oecus-triclinium, that projected into the garden was paved with a mosaic depicting a mask of Ocean among fishes and had an inscription “NYMFARUM DOMUS” quoting a passage from Virgil’s Aeneid. According to the excavator, J.-P. Darmon, a row of broken amphoras that had served as planting pots were found along the central axis of the garden facing the oecus and the basin (Fig.2)
Maps Plans   Fig.1: Plan of the House of the Nymphs. (Rights statement)   Images   Fig.2: Photographic view of the garden. (Rights statement)   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  J.P. Darmon, Nymfarum domus, Les pavements de la maison des Nymphes à Néapolis (Nabeul, Tunisie) et leur lecture, Leiden, 1980, p. 9, pp. 85-6 et p. 146. (worldcat) A.-A. Malek, &amp;ldquo;Entre jardin et mosaïque &amp;ldquo;: La verticalité et le merveilleux dans la vie quotidienne, in La Maison Gréco-romaine IX, Collection de l&amp;rsquo;Ecole Française de Rome n°352, Rome, 2005, p. 1335-1346. (worldcat) Bullo, S. and F. Ghedini, Amplissimae atque ornatissimae domus: l&amp;rsquo;edilizia residenziale nelle citta della Tunisia roman, Rome: Edizioni Quasar, 2003, p. 179-182. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 315093
TGN ID 1094981
Contributor Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Salsamenta (Usine de salaison)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/xue_xia/neapolis/house_of_the_salsamenta/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 10:39:31 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/africa_proconsularis/xue_xia/neapolis/house_of_the_salsamenta/</guid>
      <description>Province Africa Proconsularis Africa proconsularis (Pleiades)
Province Description The history of Roman Africa begins in 146 BC with the destruction of Carthage and the establishment of the province of Africa in the most fertile part of the Carthaginian Empire. The new province covered about 5000 square miles (17,172 square kilometers) of the northern part of modern Tunisia. A praetor governed the area from his headquarters at Utica. The Romans inherited a thriving agriculture developed by the Carthaginians. The climate was hospitable. Wheat and barley were the most important cereals; wine and olive oil were also produced and there were various fruit trees.
Location Neapolis
Neapolis (Pleiades)
Location Description The city of Neapolis that bears a Greek name meaning the “new city”, is located on the south coast of Cap Bon at 60 km from Carthage. The municipal history of the city is not well known. Scholars disagree as to the foundation date of the colony some think it became colonia Iulia with Cesar and others think that it was elevated to the rank of colony by Augustus.
Garden House of the Salsamenta (Usine de salaison)
Keywords  peristyles (columnades) peristyles (Roman courtyards) basins (vessels)  Garden Description A fish-curing factory located to the SE of the Nymfarum domus was renovated between the IInd and the IIIrd centuries. Among the changes made was the design of a small house organized around a small peristyle garden (4 x 4 m.) (XXII) and bound by a low wall that curved to make a semi-circular basin (Plan view, Fig.1; ).
During the second half of the IVth century, with the abandonment of the industrial unit, the residential area was enlarged and a second semi-circular basin was added in the garden.
Maps Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the House of the Salsamenta. (Rights statement)   Images   Fig. 2: Rendering of the House of the Salsamenta. (Rights statement)     Fig. 3: Photos of the House of the Salsamenta site. (Rights statement)     Fig. 3: Photos of the House of the Salsamenta site. (Rights statement)     Fig. 4: Photos of the House of the Salsamenta site. (Rights statement)     Fig. 5: Photos of the House of the Salsamenta site. (Rights statement)   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  L. Slim, M. Bonifay, P. Trousset and al., “L’usine de salaison de Néapolis (Nabeul). Premiers résultats des fouilles 1995-1998”, Africa XVII, 1999, pp. 159-161, fig. 6, 7. (worldcat) Bullo, S. and F. Ghedini, Amplissimae atque ornatissimae domus: l&amp;rsquo;edilizia residenziale nelle citta della Tunisia roman, Rome: Edizioni Quasar, 2003, p. 183-184. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 315093
TGN ID 1094981
Contributor Amina-Aïcha Malek (ORCID: 0000-0002-1628-615X) Blanc-Bijon, Véronique (WorldCat Identities: lccn-nb99006585)
Publication date 11 July 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
