<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>porticos on Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/porticos/</link>
    <description>Recent content in porticos on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 11:20:32 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/tags/porticos/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Large Vestibule</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-of-the-large-vestibule_y.sun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 11:20:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p1_yunyan_sun/augustoritum__-_limoges/gallia-aquitania_house-of-the-large-vestibule_y.sun/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia Aquitania Aquitania (Pleiades)
Location AUGUSTORITUM - Limoges
Augustoritum (Pleiades)
Location Description The earliest traces of settlement in this area are at the oppidum of Villejoubert 25 kilometers east of the city. The Roman settlement of Limoges proper dates from about 15-10 B.C. and was named Augustoritum (Augustus’s ford) in honor of the emperor. It covered some 65 to 100 hectares and was laid out in a regular rectangular grid. The ancient wall dates from the end of the third century. The town took water from several sources, including the aqueduct of Aigoulène; there were drains for waste water disposal. There were several public fountains and baths, a theater, an arena, and temples. The city declined in the fourth century. Its Roman name was replaced by the Celtic name of the local people; and its regular street pattern, almost totally lost.
Garden House of the Large Vestibule
Keywords  porticos vestibule  Garden Description This house was discovered in the quarter of the multimedia library, northwest of the forum. It was part of insula VII-5, covered an area of 1600 square meters, and underwent two successive stages. In its first stage, it had a mural chimney which gave the house its name. Four wings for living surrounded a 200 square-meter interior court with a gallery [1], which was crossed by an underground stream. It was destroyed about A.D. 70-80 to make place for the House of the Large Vestibule, its second stage. The new house was generally over the level of the old. A large, 600 square meter garden [1], surrounded on four sides by porticos, formed the center of the house. To the north, in the central axis of the house is the 249 square meter vestibule which gives its name to the house. Two cubbyholes opening onto the northern portico fill the corners on either side of the vestibule.
Dates The first stage was destroyed about A.D. 70-80 to make place for the House of the Large Vestibule, its second stage.
Bibliography  J.P. Loustaud. Limoges antique, Travaux d’Archéologie Limousine, supplément 5, 2000, 2000, p. 205-208, plan p. 206 (with bibliography of earlier works). (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 138203
TGN ID 7030318 7008410
Contributor AUTHOR_ID
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>