<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/sorde-labbaye__landes/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:07:01 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/sorde-labbaye__landes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Barat-de-Vin, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/sorde-labbaye__landes/gallia_aquitania_barat-de-vin_j.zhou/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:07:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/sorde-labbaye__landes/gallia_aquitania_barat-de-vin_j.zhou/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_Aquitania Gallia_Aquitania (Pleiades)
Province Description A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location Sorde-L&amp;rsquo;Abbaye, Landes
Sorde-L&amp;rsquo;Abbaye, Landes (Pleiades)
House Barat-de-Vin
House Description Two kilometers east of Sorde-l’Abbaye, beside the ancient road from Dax to Pamplona sat this structure on a terrace above the former bed of the Gave. The ruins have been known since the second half of the nineteenth century. They were partially excavated by J. Lauffray between 1957 and 1966. He considered the structure a villa. Later, Boyrie–Fénié and Bost (1994) conjectured that it was a wayside inn. Balmelle is inclined, on the basis of architecture and décor, to the villa interpretation.
Garden Keywords  garden pavilions columns (architectural elements)  Garden Description There are two structures separated by thirty meters or more. It is thought that they may have been connected by a peristyle not yet found. The more southern, lower structure is remarkable for the height of the remaining walls, in some places more than three meters. The southeast wing of this structure includes a large gallery [XI] (41 x 5 m) that ran parallel to the stream. It had large bays separated by columns of green marble. This unit made a sort of belvedere which connected the baths on the northwest to a large pavilion at the southeast extremity. Both the pavilion and the baths belong to a phase of construction in the fourth century. There is a spring between the stream and the baths, which may account for their location. Two possible locations for gardens may be conjectured: (1) between the gallery and the stream, and (2) in a possible peristyle between the upper (eastern) and lower (southern) known structures.
Plans Dates Unspecified
Excavation Dates 1957CE-1966CE
Bibliography  J. Lauffray, Notes sur les fouilles gallo-romaines de Sorde-L’Abbaye, 1965 (no page numbers) B. Boyrie-Fénié, CAG, 40, 1994, p. 154-155, n°306. (worldcat) Catherine Balmelle, Les demeures aristocratiques d&amp;rsquo;Aquitaine, societe et culture de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquite tardive dans le sou-ouest de la Gaule, Ausonius, supple. d&amp;rsquo;Aquitania 10, Bordeaux 2001, p. 417-419. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 249908
TGN ID Contributor Clopper Almon
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Villa of Sorde-l’Abbaye, Europa</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/sorde-labbaye__landes/gallia_aquitania_villa_of_sorde-labbaye_j.zhou/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 12:07:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/gallia_aquitania/gallia_aquitania_p3_jianingzhou/sorde-labbaye__landes/gallia_aquitania_villa_of_sorde-labbaye_j.zhou/</guid>
      <description>Province Gallia_Aquitania Gallia_Aquitania (Pleiades)
Province Description A Roman province formed in 27 B.C. by Augustus. According to Strabo, it incorporated the territories of the Aquitani and 14 other peoples whose territories were located between the Garumna and Liger rivers.
Location Sorde-L&amp;rsquo;Abbaye, Landes
Sorde-L&amp;rsquo;Abbaye, Landes (Pleiades)
House Villa of Sorde-l’Abbaye
House Description This villa covering 2000 square meters is in the center of the town, only a few meters from the bank of the Gave d’Oloron and inside the enclosure of the Abbey of Saint John, begun in 975. The abbey follows the orientation of the villa and covers part of it. The villa was noted in 1873 and excavated between 1957 and 1966 by J. Lauffray. At least three phases of work and embellishment have been detected.
Garden Keywords  mosaics (visual works) columns (architectural elements)  Garden Description It has two peristyles of very different sizes. The larger (30 x 22.5 m ), to the northwest, is trapezoidal in shape; the sides running in the north-south direction are parallel, but the other two are not. It had marble columns. One of the galleries (20.8 x 4.3 m) had a mosaic floor with stars formed by two squares and other geometric and figured motifs. They are tentatively dated at the end of the fourth or early years of the fifth century. The second, smaller peristyle in the southern part of the house (about 15 x 14 m on the outside and 8.5 x 7.2 m on the inside) was surrounded by galleries 2.3 meters wide. At an even later period, it connected the baths – along the south side near the river &amp;ndash; to the main body of the house. The geometric mosaic decoration are very late – sixth and even perhaps seventh century. Though without pools or other direct evidence, both peristyles are possible locations for gardens. Remarkably, the site was occupied, seemingly without interruption, until the beginning of the Middle Ages.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of the Villa of Sorde-l’Abbaye after the excavations of 1958-1966 (n° 172&amp;amp;180.     Fig. 2: Plan of the Villa of Sorde-l’Abbaye (cat. n° 59).   Dates 1873CE
Excavation Dates 1957CE-1966CE
Bibliography  J. Lauffray, Sorde-L’Abbaye, ville romaine et médiévale d’après les recherches récentes, Les Amis de Sorde et du Pays d’Orthe, 1962, p. 24-31 (worldcat) B. Boyrie-Fénié, CAG, 40, 1994, p.125-134, n°282. (worldcat) Catherine Balmelle, Les demeures aristocratiques d&amp;rsquo;Aquitaine, societe et culture de l&amp;rsquo;Antiquite tardive dans le sou-ouest de la Gaule, Ausonius, supple. d&amp;rsquo;Aquitania 10, Bordeaux 2001, p. 414-417, plan p. 415 and 448. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 981505 249908
TGN ID Contributor Clopper Almon
Publication date </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>