<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/region_ii_2/insula_iii/house4_6/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/region_ii_2/insula_iii/house4_6/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Large Garden in House 4-6 in Pompeii Region II (II.iii.4-6)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/region_ii_2/insula_iii/house4_6/ii.iii.4-6b/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/region_ii_2/insula_iii/house4_6/ii.iii.4-6b/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region II
House House 4-6 in Pompeii Region II
Garden Large Garden in House 4-6 in Pompeii Region II (II.iii.4-6)
Keywords  villa courtyards  Garden Description B. The small garden to the rear of house 4 had an entrance into this large open area (b) which had been planted at the time of the eruption. There was a second entrance (6) from the side street. At the time of excavation a cistern was noted in the southwest corner, a basin along the south wall just before the jog, and the presence of seven root cavities. Jashemski found a few other scattered root cavities later, but too much damage had occurred from new growth to determine the original planting plan. At the east end of the north wall a door opened to a small sacellum with an aedicula lararium on a small podium on the rear wall and a small masonry. Fig.16, 17.18.59
Plans   garden paintings detail 1.   Dates Unspecified
Bibliography   Jashemski, Wilhelmina F, and Stanley A. Jashemski, The Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the Villas Destroyed by Vesuvius. New Rochelle, NY: Caratzas, 1993. Print. pp. 84-85 worldcat
  Orr, David G.Roman Domestic Religion: A Study of the Roman Household Deities and Their Shrines at Pompeii and Herculaneum, Ann Arbor, Mich: UMI, 1999. Print.pp. 399-400;worldcat
  Pleiades ID 998787235
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 2 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Small Garden House 4-6 in Pompeii Region II (II.iii.4-6). </title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/region_ii_2/insula_iii/house4_6/ii.iii.4-6a/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 10:54:29 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_ii/region_ii_2/insula_iii/house4_6/ii.iii.4-6a/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region II
House House 4-6 in Pompeii Region II
Garden Small Garden House 4-6 in Pompeii Region II
Keywords  statuettes (free-standing sculpture) tufa villa  Garden Description A. A small garden (a) at the rear of this connected house and caupona may have originally contained the two small statuettes found at this site in 1953. The two pieces were a headless ithyphallic tufa statuette (0.33 m. high with base; Pompeii inv. no. 10017) and a marble statuette of Venus (0.51 m. high without base; Pompeii inv. no. 9926) with much of the red color preserved in the drapery. The Inventory Books list this house as II.vi.4.
Dates Unspecified
Bibliography  Jashemski, Wilhelmina F, and Stanley A. Jashemski, The Gardens of Pompeii: Herculaneum and the Villas Destroyed by Vesuvius. New Rochelle, NY: Caratzas, 1993. Print. pp. 84 worldcat  Pleiades ID 998787235
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 2 December 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>