<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gardens of the Roman Empire</title>
    <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_v/houses_3&#43;16/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Gardens of the Roman Empire</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2020 19:32:26 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_v/houses_3+16/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>I.v.3/16 B</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_v/houses_3&#43;16/i.v.3&#43;16/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2020 19:32:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_v/houses_3&#43;16/i.v.3&#43;16/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula V
House House 3/16
Garden I.v.3/16 B
Keywords  archaeological garden columns (architectural elements) cryptoportici fulcrum human remains loggias pillars pilasters stairs tables (support furniture) triclinia vegetable gardens  Garden Description B. At the rear of the house, a large enclosed garden (b) had been increased in size by reducing the wings of the cryptoporticus. The last owner had built a spacious loggia (5 x 20 m.) above the north wing of the cryptoporticus overlooking the garden. A high wall joined the five pillars and the roof supporting pilaster and formed windows into the garden. At the west end of the loggia was a masonry triclinium with side couches, each having a fulcrum (foot), (l. medius 4.41m.; l.summus and l. imus 4.68 m.; dia. of table 0.55m.). A large area was left open for tables or dancers, suggesting to Spinoza that this could have been a public gathering place. There were low seats in front of the side couches and extended along the terrace walls that may have been intended for children according to Soprano. A kitchen was located on the north side of the loggia. Six steps from the southeast corner of the loggia led up into the garden which had been raised to the level of the windows in the cryptoporticus. Della Corte thought that this garden had been used to raise many cabbages and leeks. The remains of eleven victims of the volcanic eruption were found in the garden.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula v, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 8, p. 33; Viola, *Scavi*, pl. 1; Niccolini, *Case*, vol. 3, “*Topografia*,” pl. 10 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates Bibliography  Della Corte, Case, p. 228. (worldcat) Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 34. (worldcat) Maruri, NSc (1933), pp. 256, 258-259, 272 and pl. 5 (plan). Salza Prina Ricotti, “Cucine,” 268-271. Soprano, pp. 294-295, no. 4 and fig. 30. Spinazzola, NSc (1914), pp. 256, 259-262, 287, 365-368. Spinazzola, Scavi nuovi, pp.121-122, 442, 444-445, 451, 453. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 06 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House of the Cryptoporticus; Casa Del Crirtoportico; Casa Omerica; House of T. Lucretius Carus (I.v.3/16)</title>
      <link>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_v/houses_3&#43;16/house_of_the_cryptoporticus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2020 19:15:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://christiancasey.github.io/gre/province/italia/pompeii/region_i/insula_v/houses_3&#43;16/house_of_the_cryptoporticus/</guid>
      <description>Province Italia
Location Pompeii
Pompeii (Pleiades)
Sublocation Region I
Insula Insula V
House House 3/16
Garden House of the Cryptoporticus; Casa Del Crirtoportico; Casa Omerica; House of T. Lucretius Carus (I.v.3/16)
Keywords  archaeological garden atriums busts (sculpture) columns (architectural elements) cryptoportici lararia loggias mural paintings (visual works) peristyles (columnades) pillars porticoes stairs  Garden Description A. A passageway from the atrium led to a modest peristyle garden (a) visible through a window in the rear wall. A low wall enclosed the garden on the north and east sides along with five brick columns covered with white stucco and a pillar supporting the roof of the portico. A large, well preserved wall painting survived on the west wall of the north portico as well as a niche lararium decorated with a painted bust of Mercury. From the garden a flight of stairs led down to an elegant cryptoporticus (underground portico) illuminated by light from the adjacent garden through high windows. A solarium terrace, or loggia, overlooking the large garden (b) could be reached by another flight of stairs form the east portico.
Plans   Fig. 1: Plan of Pompeii with Region I highlighted, plan in Jashemski, Gardens, p.21 (Rights Statement).     Fig. 2: Plan of Region I, insula v, plan in Jashemski, *Gardens*, plan 8, p. 33; Viola, *Scavi*, pl. 1; Niccolini, *Case*, vol. 3, “*Topografia*,” pl. 10 (Rights Statement).   Dates unspecified
Excavation Dates Bibliography  Boyce, p. 25, no. 36. Della Corte, NSc (1914), pp. 74-75. Jashemski, Gardens, vol.II, p. 34. (worldcat) Spinazzola, NSc (1914), pp. 259-263. Spinazzola, Scavi nuovi, p.441 and fig. 493 (plan) on p. 433. (worldcat)  Pleiades ID 433032
TGN ID 7004658
Contributor Wilhelmina Jashemski (https://lib.guides.umd.edu/c.php?g=326514&amp;amp;p=2193250)
Publication date 05 August 2020</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>